The Princess on the Pea

Once upon a time there was a prince. He wanted a princess, but she had to be a real princess. So he traveled all over the world to find one, but wherever he went there was something wrong. There were plenty of princesses, but he wasn’t quite sure if they were real princesses. There was always something that wasn’t quite right. Then he went back home and was so sad because he dearly wanted to have a real princess.

One evening there was a terrible storm. Lightning flashed and thunder roared, the rain poured down, it was simply dreadful! Then there was a knock at the town gate, and the old king went to open it.

There was a princess standing outside. But good Lord how she looked because of the rain and terrible weather! Water was streaming from her hair and her clothes, running in the toes of her shoes and out of the heels. Then she said that she was a real princess.

‘Well, we’ll see about that,’ thought the old queen, but she didn’t say a word. She went into the bedroom, took off all the bedclothes, and placed a pea at the bottom of the bed. Then she took twenty mattresses and put them on top of the pea, and another twenty eiderdown quilts on top of the mattresses.

That’s where the princess was to sleep that night.

The next morning they asked her how she had slept.

‘Oh, dreadfully!’ said the princess. ‘I hardly closed my eyes all night. Lord knows what there was in my bed. I was lying on something hard, and I’m black and blue all over! It’s simply dreadful!’

Then they could see that she was a real princess, since she had felt the pea through those twenty mattresses and those twenty eiderdown quilts. No one else could have such tender skin except for a real princess.

And so the prince took her as his wife, because now he knew that he had a real princess. And the pea was placed in the Royal Curiosity Cabinet, where it can still be seen today, as long as no one has taken it.

Now you see, that was a real story!

The Steadfast T in Soldier

Once upon a time there were twenty- five tin soldiers. They were brothers, because they were all born from an old tin spoon. Rifles they held at their shoulders, and their faces looked straight ahead. Red and blue, and oh so lovely were their uniforms. When the lid was removed from the box in which they lay, the very first words they heard in the world were, ‘Tin soldiers!’ That’s what a little boy cried, clapping his hands. They had been given to him because it was his birthday, and now he lined them up on the table. Each soldier looked exactly like the next, except for one who was slightly different. He had only one leg because he was the last to be cast, and there wasn’t enough tin left. Yet he stood just as firmly on one leg as the others did on two, and he’s the one who turned out to be remarkable.

On the table where they stood were many other toys, but the one that was most striking was a charming castle made of paper. Through the tiny windows you could see right into the halls. Outside stood small trees around a little mirror that was meant to look like a lake. Swans made of wax were swimming around on it, reflected in the mirror. The whole thing was so charming, and yet the most charming of all was a little maiden who stood in the open doorway to the castle. She had also been cut out of paper, but she was wearing a skirt of the sheerest tulle and a tiny narrow blue ribbon over her shoulder like a sash. In the middle sat a gleaming spangle as big as her face. The little maiden was stretching out both arms, because she was a dancer, and she was also lifting one leg so high in the air that the tin soldier couldn’t see it at all, and he thought that she had only one leg, just like him.

‘Now there’s a wife for me!’ he thought. ‘But she looks rather refined, and she lives in a castle. I have only a box, and it has to hold twenty- five of us. That’s no place for her! Still, I have to see about making her acquaintance.’ And then he stretched out full- length behind a snuff box that stood on the table. From there he could get a good look at the elegant little lady, who continued to stand on one leg without losing her balance.

Later that evening all the other tin soldiers were put back in their box, and the people of the house went to bed. Then the toys began to play. They gave tea parties, fought battles, and danced. The tin soldiers rattled in their box because they wanted to play too, but they couldn’t open the lid. The nutcracker turned somersaults, and the slate pencil scribbled all over the slate. There was such a commotion that the canary woke up and started chattering too, and in verse, of all things. The only two who didn’t budge were the tin soldier and the little dancer. She held herself erect on her toes, with her arms held out. He was just as steadfast on one leg, and his eyes didn’t leave her for a second.

Then the clock struck twelve, and Bam! the lid of the snuff box flew open, but there was no tobacco inside – no, there was a little black troll. What a wily trick that was.

‘Tin soldier!’ said the troll. ‘Keep your eyes to yourself!’

But the tin soldier pretended not to hear him.

‘Well, just wait till morning,’ said the troll.

When morning came and the children got up, the tin soldier was moved over to the windowsill, and whether it was the troll or a gust of wind, all of a sudden the window flew open and the soldier plummeted headfirst from the fourth floor. What a terrifying speed, with his leg turned upward! He landed on his cap, with his bayonet stuck between the cobblestones.

The servant girl and the little boy went downstairs at once to look for him, but even though they nearly stepped on him, they couldn’t see him. If the tin soldier had shouted‘Here I am!’ they probably would have found him, but he didn’t think it was proper to yell when he was in uniform.

Then it started to rain. One drop came down faster than the other; it turned into a regular downpour. When it was over, two street urchins came along.

‘Hey, look!’ said one of them. ‘There’s a tin soldier lying here. Let’s send him out for a sail.’

And so they made a boat out of newspaper, set the tin soldier in the middle of it, and he sailed off down the gutter. The two boys ran alongside, clapping their hands. God save us, what waves there were in that gutter, and what a current! Well, it’s true that there had just been a downpour. The paper boat pitched up and down, and at times it would spin so fast that the tin soldier swayed. But he remained steadfast, his expression unflinching, standing erect with his rifle at his shoulder.

All of a sudden the boat washed in under a plank that lay over the gutter. It grew just as dark as inside his box.

‘I wonder where I’ll end up now,’ he thought. ‘Yes, well, this is all the troll’s fault. Oh, if only the little maiden were sitting here in the boat, then I wouldn’t care if it was twice as dark!’

At that moment a big water rat appeared. It lived under the gutter plank.

‘Have you got a travel pass?’ asked the rat. ‘Let’s see your travel pass!’

But the tin soldier didn’t say a word, holding his rifle even tighter. The boat raced along, with the rat right behind. Oh, how it gnashed its teeth, shouting to sticks and pieces of straw:

‘Stop him! Stop him! He didn’t pay the toll! He didn’t show his travel pass!’

But the current grew stronger and stronger. The tin soldier could already glimpse daylight up ahead where the plank ended, but he also heard a roaring sound that would scare even a brave man. Just imagine: Where the plank ended, the gutter plunged right into a huge canal. For him it would be just as dangerous as for us to sail over an enormous waterfall.

He was already so close that he couldn’t stop. The boat rushed forward; the poor tin soldier held himself as upright as he could. No one was going to say that he so much as blinked an eye. The boat spun around three or four times and filled with water up to the rim. It was going to sink. The tin soldier was standing in water up to his neck, and the boat sank deeper and deeper, the paper began dissolving faster and faster. Then the water was over the soldier’s head. That’s when he thought about the charming little dancer, whom he would never see again. And in his ears the soldier heard:

‘Flee, warrior, flee!

Death is after you!’

Then the paper fell apart, and the tin soldier plunged right through. But at that very instant he was swallowed by a big fish.

Oh, how dark it was inside! It was even worse than under the gutter plank, and it was much more cramped. But the tin soldier was steadfast and stretched out full- length with his rifle at his shoulder.

The fish thrashed about, making the most terrifying movements. Finally it grew quite still, and what looked like a bolt of lightning flashed through it. The light shone so bright, and someone cried loudly, ‘Tin soldier!’ The fish had been caught, brought to market, sold, and then ended up in a kitchen where the servant girl slit it open with a big knife. Putting two fingers around his waist, she plucked out the soldier and carried him into the parlor where everyone wanted to see the remarkable man who had traveled inside the belly of a fish. But the tin soldier was not the least bit proud of himself. They set him on the table and there . . . Oh, what strange things can happen in the world! The tin soldier was in the very same parlor where he had been before. He saw the very same children and the toys on the table and the lovely castle with the charming little dancer. She was still standing on one leg with the other lifted high in the air. She too was steadfast. The tin soldier was touched, he was just about to weep tears of tin, but that wouldn’t be proper. He looked at her and she looked at him, but neither said a word.

At that moment one of the little boys picked up the soldier and tossed him right into the stove, giving no explanation at all. The troll in the box was most certainly to blame.

The tin soldier stood there, brightly lit, and felt a terrible heat, but whether it was from the actual fire or from love, he didn’t know. The paint had worn right off him, but whether this had happened on his journey or from sorrow, no one could say. He looked at the little maiden, she looked at him, and he felt himself melting. But he still stood there, steadfast, with his rifle at his shoulder. Then a door opened, the wind seized hold of the dancer, and she flew like a sylph right into the stove to the tin soldier, burst into flame, and was gone. Then the tin soldier melted into a lump, and the next day, when the servant girl took out the ashes, she found him in the shape of a little tin heart. But all that was left of the dancer was the spangle, and that had been burned black as coal.

The N ightingale

In China, as you probably know, the Emperor is Chinese, and everyone around him is Chinese too. This story happened many years ago, but that’s precisely why it’s worth hearing, before it’s forgotten. The Emperor’s palace was the most magnificent in the world, made entirely of fine porcelain, so costly but so fragile, so delicate to the touch that you had to be extremely careful. In the garden you could see the most wondrous flowers. Tied to the most splendid of them were silver bells that jingled, and you couldn’t walk past without noticing the flowers. Yes, everything was quite artful in the Emperor’s garden, which stretched so far that even the gardener didn’t know where it ended. If you kept on walking you would come to the loveliest forest with tall trees and deep lakes. The forest went right down to the sea, which was deep and blue. Great ships could sail right under the branches. And among the branches lived a nightingale who sang so blissfully that even the poor fisherman, who had many other things to tend to, would lie still and listen whenever he heard the nightingale as he pulled in his fishing nets at night. ‘Dear Lord, how beautiful she sounds!’ he said.

But then he had to go back to his work and forget about the bird. Yet the next night when she sang again and the fisherman appeared, he would say the same thing, ‘Dear Lord, how beautiful she sounds!’

Travelers came from countries all over the world to admire the Emperor’s city and the palace and the garden. But if they happened to hear the nightingale, they all said, ‘That’s the best thing of all!’

The travelers would talk about everything when they went back home, and the learned men wrote many books about the city, the palace, and the garden, but they didn’t forget the nightingale; she was esteemed above all else. Those who could write poetry wrote the loveliest poems, every single one about the nightingale in the forest by the deep sea.

These books circulated around the world, and one day some of them even reached the Emperor. He sat on his golden chair, reading and reading, as he kept nodding his head, because it pleased him to hear the magnificent descriptions of the city, the palace, and the garden. ‘Yet the nightingale is the best of all!’ he read in the book.

‘What’s this?’ said the Emperor. ‘The nightingale? I know nothing about it! Is there such a bird in my empire, let alone in my own garden? I’ve never heard of her. To think I had to learn about her from a book!’

And then he called for his Lord Chamberlain, who was so refined that if anyone lower in rank dared speak to him or ask him about something, his only reply was ‘P!’ And that means nothing at all.

‘Supposedly there is a truly extraordinary bird here called the nightingale,’ said the Emperor. ‘They say that she’s the best thing in all my vast domain. Why hasn’t anyone told me about her?’

‘I’ve never heard her mentioned before,’ said the Lord Chamberlain. ‘She has never been presented at court.’

‘I want her to come here tonight and sing for me,’ said the Emperor. ‘The whole world knows what I have, but I do not.’

‘I’ve never heard her mentioned before,’ said the Lord Chamberlain. ‘I’ll search for her, I’ll find her!’

But where was she to be found? The Lord Chamberlain ran up and down all the stairs, through the halls and corridors. Not a single person he met had ever heard mention of the nightingale. So the Lord Chamberlain ran back to the Emperor and said that she must be a fable concocted by those who write books. ‘Your Imperial Majesty should not believe what people write. It’s all fabrication and what’s called black magic.’

‘But the book I was reading was sent to me by the mighty Emperor of Japan,’ said the Emperor, ‘so it must be true. I want to hear the nightingale. She must be here tonight! I bestow on her my highest favor! And if she doesn’t come, then all the members of the court will be punched in the stomach after they’ve eaten their supper.’

‘ Xing- pei! ’ said the Lord Chamberlain, and once again he ran up and down all the stairs, through all the halls and corridors. And half the court ran along with him, because they didn’t want to be punched in the stomach. Everyone was asking about the remarkable nightingale that was known to the whole world but to no one at court.

Finally they came upon a poor little girl in the kitchen, and she said, ‘Oh Lord, the nightingale! I know her well. Yes, how she can sing! Every evening I’m allowed to take home a few scraps from the table for my poor sick mother. She lives down near the shore, and when I walk back feeling tired, I take a rest in the forest, and then I hear the nightingale singing. It makes my eyes fill with tears. It’s as if my mother were kissing me.’

‘Little kitchen maid,’ said the Lord Chamberlain, ‘I shall arrange a permanent post for you in the kitchen and permission to watch the Emperor eat if you can lead us to the nightingale. She has been summoned here tonight.’

And so they all set off for the forest, to the place where the nightingale usually sang. Half the court went along. As they were walking, a cow began to moo.

‘Oh!’ said the royal squires. ‘Now we’ve found her. What remarkable power for such a small creature! We’re quite certain we’ve heard her before.’

‘No, those are the cows mooing,’ said the little kitchen maid. ‘We’re still quite far from the place.’

Now the frogs began croaking in the bog.

‘Lovely!’ said the Chinese Court Chaplain. ‘Now I can hear her. It sounds just like little church bells.’

‘No, those are the frogs,’ said the little kitchen maid. ‘But I think we’ll hear her soon.’

Then the nightingale began to sing.

‘There she is,’ said the little girl. ‘Listen! Listen! And there she sits!’ And then she pointed at a little gray bird up in the branches.

‘Is it possible?’ said the Lord Chamberlain. ‘That’s not at all how I imagined her. How plain she looks! She must have lost her color from seeing so many refined people all around.’

‘Little nightingale!’ cried the little kitchen maid in a loud voice. ‘Our Most Gracious Emperor would like so much for you to sing for him.’

‘With the greatest pleasure,’ said the nightingale and sang so it was sheer delight.

‘It sounds just like glass bells,’ said the Lord Chamberlain.‘And look at her little throat – she’s singing with all her might. It’s strange that we’ve never heard this bird before. She will be a huge success at court.’

‘Shall I sing some more for the Emperor?’ asked the nightingale, who thought the Emperor was among them.

‘My splendid little nightingale,’ said the Lord Chamberlain, ‘I have the great pleasure of summoning you to a royal celebration this evening, where you will enchant His Exalted Imperial Grace with your charming song.’

‘My song sounds best out in nature,’ said the nightingale, but she willingly went along with them when she heard that this was the Emperor’s wish.

At the palace everything had been properly cleaned and polished. The walls and floors, which were made of porcelain, gleamed with thousands of golden lamps. The loveliest flowers, the ones with bells attached, had been placed in the corridors; there was a draft and a great commotion, making all the bells ring. You couldn’t hear yourself think.

In the middle of the great hall, where the Emperor was seated, a golden perch had been placed, and that was where the nightingale was to sit. The entire court was present, and the little kitchen maid had been given permission to stand behind the door, since she now held the title of Real Kitchen Maid. Everyone was dressed in his very finest, and everyone was looking at the little gray bird, to whom the Emperor nodded.

And the nightingale sang so wondrously that tears filled the Emperor’s eyes. Tears rolled down his cheeks, and then the nightingale sang even more beautifully; the song went straight to the heart. The Emperor was so happy that he said the nightingale must wear his golden slipper around her neck. But the nightingale thanked him and said that she had already received reward enough.

‘I’ve seen tears in the Emperor’s eyes. For me that is the richest treasure. An emperor’s tears have a wondrous power. God knows, that is reward enough.’ And then she sang again in her sweet, blessed voice.

‘This is the most lovable coquetry we’ve ever known,’ said the women all around, and then they put water in their mouths in order to cluck whenever anyone spoke to them. They thought they too could be nightingales. Even the lackeys and chambermaids announced that they were satisfied, and that is saying a great deal because they’re the most difficult of all to please. Yes, the nightingale certainly was a success!

Now she would stay at court, and have her own cage, as well as the freedom to promenade twice a day and once at night. Twelve servants were sent along, each of them holding tight to a silk ribbon attached to her leg. There wasn’t the least bit of pleasure in those excursions.

The whole city was talking about the extraordinary bird. If two people met, one of them would say to the other‘Night!’ and the other would say ‘Gale!’ and then they would sigh, fully understanding each other. Why, eleven grocers’ children were named after her, but not one of them could even carry a tune.

One day a big package arrived for the Emperor. On the outside it said: ‘Nightingale.’

‘Here we have a new book about our famous bird,’ said the Emperor. But it wasn’t a book. A little work of art lay inside the box, a mechanical nightingale that was supposed to look like the live one, although it was completely encrusted with diamonds, rubies, and sapphires. As soon as they wound up the mechanical bird it sang one of the tunes that the real bird sang, and its tail moved up and down, glittering with silver and gold. Around its neck hung a little ribbon, and on it were the words: ‘The Emperor of Japan’s nightingale is paltry compared to the Emperor of China’s.’

‘It’s lovely!’ they all said, and the person who had brought the mechanical bird was at once given the title of Supreme Imperial Nightingale Bringer.

‘Let’s have them sing together. What a duet that will be!’

And then they had to sing together, but it was not a success, because the real nightingale sang in her own way, while the mechanical bird ran on cylinders. ‘There’s nothing wrong with that,’ said the Music Master. ‘It keeps perfect time and is obviously a follower of my own methods.’ Then the mechanical bird had to sing alone. It brought just as much joy as the real bird, and on top of that it was much more charming in appearance. It glittered like bracelets and brooches.

Thirty- three times it sang the very same tune, and yet it never grew tired. Everyone could have listened to it all over again, but the Emperor felt that the live nightingale should also sing a little. But where was she? No one had noticed that she had flown out the open window, off to her green forests.

‘Well, what sort of behavior is that?’ said the Emperor. And all the members of court began scolding, saying that the nightingale was a most ungrateful creature. ‘Yet we have the best bird of all,’ they said, and then the mechanical bird had to sing some more, and that was the thirty- fourth time they heard the same tune. But they didn’t yet know it by heart, because it was so complicated, and the Music Master lavished great praise on the bird. Yes, he assured them that it was better than the real nightingale, not only in terms of its attire and the scores of lovely diamonds, but also internally.

‘For you see, ladies and gentlemen, and above all Your Imperial Highness! You can never count on what will come out of the real nightingale, but with the mechanical bird everything is certain. This is how it will sound, and no other way. You can explain it, you can open it up and demonstrate the human reasoning, how the cylinders are arranged, how they operate, and how one turns the other.’

‘Those are my thoughts exactly,’ they all said. And the Music Master was granted permission, on the following Sunday, to display the bird to the people. They too should hear it sing, said the Emperor. And they heard it and were as pleased as if they had drunk themselves giddy on tea; that was so typically Chinese. And everyone said ‘Oh!’ and held up in the air the finger that we call ‘ pot- licker’ and then they nodded. But the poor fishermen who had heard the real nightingale said, ‘It sounds nice enough, and it does look quite like it, but something is missing, we don’t know what.’

The real nightingale was banished from the realm.

The mechanical bird had its place on a silk pillow close to the Emperor’s bed. All the gifts it had been given, gold and precious stones, were spread around it, and in title it had risen to Supreme Imperial Nightstand Singer. In rank it was number one on the left, because the Emperor considered the side of the heart to be the most noble, and even in an Emperor the heart is on the left. The Music Master wrote twenty- five volumes about the mechanical bird, books that were so learned and so lengthy, and written in the most difficult of Chinese words, that everyone said they had read and understood them, because otherwise they would have seemed stupid and then they would have been punched in the stomach.

A whole year passed in this fashion. The Emperor, the court, and all the other Chinese people knew by heart every little cluck of the mechanical bird’s song, but that was precisely why they liked it above all else. They could sing it themselves, and they did. The street urchins sang ‘ Xi- xi- xi! Cluck- cluck- cluck!’ And the Emperor sang it too. Oh yes, it was certainly lovely!

But one evening when the mechanical bird was singing its best and the Emperor was lying in bed and listening, it went‘Clunk!’ inside. Something burst. ‘Buzzzzzz!’ all the gears spun around, and then the music stopped.

The Emperor sprang out of bed at once and called for his royal physician, but what good could he do? Then they summoned the watchmaker. After much discussion and a great deal of study, he managed to get the bird working fairly well, but he said that it would have to be played sparingly because the cylinder pegs were worn out. It would be impossible to replace them with new ones so that the music would play properly. That was a terrible shame! Only once a year did they dare let the mechanical bird sang, and even that was almost too often. But then the Music Master gave a little speech using big words and said that it was just as good as new, and so it was just as good as new.

Five years passed, and the whole land suffered a great sadness, because everyone was truly very fond of their Emperor. Now they said he was ill and about to die. A new emperor had already been chosen, and the people stood outside on the street and asked the Lord Chamberlain how things were going with their Emperor.

‘P!’ he said and shook his head.

Cold and pale, the Emperor lay in his big, magnificent bed. The entire court thought he was dead, and all of them had run off to greet the new Emperor. The valets had run outside to talk about it, and the palace maids were holding a big coffee party. All around in the halls and corridors cloth had been laid down so that no one’s footsteps could be heard. That’s why it was so quiet, so quiet. But the Emperor was not yet dead. Rigid and pale, he lay in the magnificent bed with the long velvet curtains and the heavy gold tassels. High above, a window stood open, and the moon was shining on the Emperor and the mechanical bird.

The poor Emperor could hardly breathe; it felt as if something were sitting on his chest. He opened his eyes and saw that it was Death sitting on his chest. He had put on the gold crown and was holding in one hand the Emperor’s gold sword, and in the other his magnificent banner. All around in the folds of the great velvet bed curtains peculiar heads were sticking out, some of them quite horrid, others so blessedly gentle. They were all of the Emperor’s good and bad deeds, looking at him, now that Death was sitting on his heart.

‘Do you remember this?’ one after the other whispered.‘Do you remember this?’ And then they told him so many things that the sweat poured from his brow.

‘I never knew that!’ said the Emperor. ‘Music, music, the great Chinese drum!’ he shouted. ‘So I won’t have to listen to everything they’re saying.’

But they kept on, and Death nodded, as the Chinese do, at everything that was said.

‘Music, music!’ screamed the Emperor. ‘You blessed little golden bird! Sing now, sing! I’ve given you gold and precious things. I myself have hung my golden slipper around your neck. So sing now, sing!’

But the bird stood silent. There was no one to wind it up, and otherwise it couldn’t sing. But Death kept on looking at the Emperor with his big, empty eye sockets, and it was so quiet, so horribly quiet.

At that moment, close to the window, the loveliest song was heard. It was the live little nightingale, who was sitting on a branch outside. She had heard about the Emperor’s distress, and that’s why she had come, to offer solace and hope. And as she sang, the figures grew more and more pale, the blood began to flow faster and faster through the Emperor’s weak limbs, and Death himself listened and said, ‘Keep singing, little nightingale! Keep singing!’

‘Yes, if you give me the magnificent gold sword! Yes, if you give me the opulent banner! If you give me the Emperor’s crown!’

And Death returned each treasure for a song, and the nightingale still kept singing. She sang of the silent churchyard where the white roses grow, where the fragrant elder tree stands, and where the fresh grass is watered by the tears of the bereaved. Then Death had such a longing for his own garden that he floated out like a cold white fog, out the window.

‘Thank you, thank you!’ said the Emperor. ‘You heavenly little bird, of course I recognize you! You’re the one I chased from my realm. And yet you have sung the evil visions away from my bed and driven Death from my heart. How shall I reward you?’

‘You have already rewarded me,’ said the nightingale. ‘I won tears from your eyes the first time I sang. I will never forget that about you. They are the jewels that make a singer’s heart glad. But sleep now and grow strong and healthy. I will sing for you.’

And she sang. The Emperor fell into a sweet slumber, so gentle and refreshing was his sleep.

The sun was shining through the windows when he awoke, strong and healthy. None of his servants had yet returned, because they all thought he was dead. But the nightingale was still sitting there, singing.

‘You must stay with me forever,’ said the Emperor. ‘You shall only sing when you want to, and I will smash the mechanical bird into a thousand pieces.’

‘Don’t do that,’ said the nightingale. ‘It has done the best it could. Keep it as you always have. I can’t live in the palace, but let me come whenever I wish. Then in the evening I will sit on the branch by your window and sing for you, to make you both joyous and pensive. I will sing about those who are happy and those who suffer. I will sing about the evil and the good that is kept hidden from you. The little songbird flies far and wide, to the poor fisherman, to the farmer’s rooftop, to everyone who is far from you and your court. I love your heart more than your crown, and yet the crown has a scent of something sacred about it. I will come, I will sing for you. But one thing you must promise me.’

‘Anything!’ said the Emperor, standing there in his imperial robes, which he had donned himself, and holding the sword that was heavy with gold pressed to his heart.

‘One thing I ask of you. Tell no one that you have a little bird who tells you everything, and things will go even better.’

And then the nightingale flew off.

The servants came in to tend to their dead Emperor. Oh yes, there they stood. And the Emperor said, ‘Good morning!’

The Red Shoes

There was a little girl who was so delicate and charming, but in the summer she always had to go barefoot because she was poor. In the winter she wore big wooden clogs that made her little ankles turn quite red, and that was awful.

In the middle of the village lived old Mother Shoemaker. She sat and sewed as best she could, using old strips of red cloth to make a little pair of shoes. Quite clumsy they were, but well- intended, and the little girl was to have them. The little girl’s name was Karen.

On the very day that her mother was buried, Karen was given the red shoes, and she wore them for the first time. Now, it’s true that they weren’t the proper shoes for mourning, but she didn’t have any others, and so she wore them on her bare feet, walking behind the humble coffin made of straw.

All at once a grand old carriage appeared, and inside sat a grand old woman. She looked at the little girl and felt sorry for her. Then she said to the pastor, ‘Listen here, give me that little girl and I will be kind to her!’

Karen thought she said this because of her red shoes, but the old woman said they were awful, and they were burned, while Karen was dressed in nice, clean clothes. She had to learn to read and sew, and people said that she was charming, but the mirror said, ‘You are much more than charming, you’re lovely!’

Then the queen happened to travel through the land, and she brought along her little daughter, who was a princess. People came flocking to the palace, and Karen was there too. The little princess stood in a window for all to see dressed in fine white clothes. She wore neither a train nor a golden crown, but she had lovely, red kidskin shoes. Of course they were much prettier than the ones that Mother Shoemaker had sewn for little Karen. But nothing in the world could compare with red shoes!

Then Karen was old enough to be confirmed. She was given new clothes and she was also to have new shoes. The rich shoemaker in town measured her little foot. This was at home in his own parlor, where big glass cupboards stood filled with elegant shoes and shiny boots. Everything looked charming, but the old woman didn’t see well, so it gave her no pleasure. In the midst of all the shoes stood a pair of red ones just like the ones the princess had worn. How beautiful they were! The shoemaker said they had been sewn for the child of a count, but they didn’t fit properly.

‘They must be made of the finest leather,’ said the old woman. ‘How they shine!’

‘Yes, how they shine!’ said Karen. And they fit, so they were bought. But the old woman didn’t know that they were red, because she would never have allowed Karen to be confirmed wearing red shoes, and yet she did.

Everyone looked at her feet. When she walked up the church aisle toward the chancel doorway, she thought even the old paintings on the crypts, those portraits of pastors and their wives wearing stiff collars and long black gowns, had fixed their eyes on her red shoes. And that was all she could think of when the pastor placed his hand on her head and spoke of the holy baptism, of the pact with God, and the fact that she should now be a good Christian. The organ played so solemnly, the children sang so beautifully, and the old cantor sang too, but Karen thought only of her red shoes.

By that afternoon the old woman had heard from everyone that the shoes were red, and she said how dreadful that was. It wasn’t the least bit proper. From that day on, whenever Karen went to church, she would always wear black shoes, even if they were old.

The following Sunday was her first communion, and Karen looked at the black shoes, she looked at the red ones –and then she looked at the red ones again and put them on.

It was lovely sunny weather. Karen and the old woman walked along the path through the grain fields where it was rather dusty.

At the church door stood an old soldier with a crutch and a long, odd- looking beard that was more red than white; in fact, it was red. He bowed all the way to the ground and asked the old woman whether he might wipe off her shoes. Karen stretched out her little foot too. ‘Oh look, what lovely dancing shoes!’ said the soldier. ‘Stay on tight when you dance!’ Then he slapped his hand on the soles.

The old woman gave the soldier a little skilling and then went with Karen into the church.

Everyone inside looked at Karen’s red shoes; all the paintings looked at them too. And when Karen knelt before the altar and put the golden chalice to her lips, she thought only of the red shoes. They seemed to be swimming around in the chalice before her, and she forgot to sing the hymn, she forgot to say the Lord’s Prayer.

Then everyone left the church, and the old woman climbed into her carriage. As Karen lifted her foot to climb in after her, the old soldier who was standing close by said, ‘Oh look, what lovely dancing shoes!’ And Karen couldn’t help herself, she had to take a few dance steps. As soon as she started, her feet kept on dancing. It was as if the shoes had taken control. She danced around the corner of the church, she couldn’t stop herself. The coachman had to run after and grab her, and he lifted her into the carriage, but her feet kept on dancing and she kicked hard at the kind old woman. Finally they managed to take off the shoes, and her feet stopped moving.

At home the shoes were put in a cupboard, but Karen couldn’t help looking at them.

Then the old woman fell ill, and they said she wouldn’t live long. She needed someone to nurse and tend her, and who should do it but Karen? But over in town there was to be a great ball, and Karen was invited. She looked at the old woman, who didn’t have long to live, after all. She looked at the red shoes, and she didn’t think there was any sin in that. She put on the red shoes. Why shouldn’t she? And then she went to the ball and began to dance.

But when she wanted to turn right, the shoes danced to the left, and when she wanted to move up the floor, the shoes danced down the floor, down the stairs, along the street, and out the town gate. Dance she did, and dance she must, right out into the dark forest.

Then she saw a light overhead among the trees, and she thought it must be the moon, because it had a face, but it was the old soldier with the red beard. He sat there nodding and said, ‘Oh look, what lovely dancing shoes!’

Then Karen was horrified and tried to take off the red shoes, but they wouldn’t come off. She tore off her stockings, but the shoes had grown onto her feet; dance she did and dance she must, over field and meadow, in rain and in sunshine, night and day, but nighttime was the most terrible of all.

She danced into the open churchyard, but the dead weren’t dancing. They had better things to do than dance. She wanted to sit down on the pauper’s grave where bitter tansy grew, but for her there was no peace or rest. And when she danced toward the open church door, she saw an angel there in long white robes, with wings that reached from his shoulders to the ground. His face was stern and solemn, and in his hand he held a sword, gleaming and wide.

‘Dance you shall!’ he said. ‘Dance in your red shoes until you turn pale and cold! Until your skin shrivels up like a mummy’s! Dance from door to door. And wherever proud and vain children live, you will knock so they hear and fear you! Dance you shall, dance–!’

‘Have mercy!’ cried Karen. But she didn’t hear what the angel replied, because her shoes carried her through the gate, out to the field, across the road, and along the path, and always she had to keep dancing.

Early one morning she danced past a door she knew quite well. Inside a hymn could be heard, and they carried out a coffin that was adorned with flowers. Then she knew that the old woman was dead, and she felt as if she had now been forsaken by everyone and cursed by the angel of God.

Dance she did, and dance she must, dance into the dark night. Her shoes carried her over thickets and stumps, her feet were worn bloody. She danced across the heath to a lonely little house. She knew that this was where the executioner lived. She tapped her finger on the windowpane and said, ‘Come out! Come out! I can’t come inside, because I’m dancing!’

And the executioner said, ‘Don’t you know who I am? I chop off the heads of evil people, and I can feel my ax is trembling!’

‘Don’t chop off my head,’ said Karen. ‘Because then I won’t be able to repent my sin. But chop off my feet with the red shoes!’

Then she confessed to her sin, and the executioner chopped off her feet with the red shoes. But the shoes kept dancing with the little feet across the fields and into the deep forest.

And he carved wooden feet and crutches for her, taught her a hymn that sinners always sing, and she kissed the hand that had wielded the ax and set out across the heath.

‘Now I’ve suffered enough for those red shoes,’ she said.‘Now I’m going to church so they can see me.’ And she walked as fast as she could toward the church door, but when she got there, the red shoes were dancing in front of her. She was horrified and turned away.

All week long she was sad and wept many bitter tears, but when Sunday came, she said, ‘All right! Now I’ve suffered and struggled enough! I should think that I’m just as good as many of those people sitting so proudly inside the church.’Then she set off quite boldly, but she got no farther than to the gate when she saw the red shoes dancing in front of her. She was horrified and turned away, repenting her sin with all her heart.

She went over to the parsonage and asked if she might be taken into service there. She would work hard and do everything she could. She had no wish for wages; all she asked for was a roof over her head and permission to stay with good people. The pastor’s wife felt sorry for her and gave her a position. And she was hardworking and thoughtful. Quietly she would sit and listen when the pastor read aloud from the Bible in the evening. All the children were very fond of her, but whenever they spoke of adornments and finery and being as lovely as a queen, she would shake her head.

The next Sunday they all went to church and they asked if she would like to come along, but with tears in her eyes she looked sadly at her crutches. Then the others went to hear God’s Word while she went alone into her tiny room. It was only big enough for a bed and a chair. There she sat with her hymnbook. As she began reading with a pious heart, the wind carried the tones of the organ from the church to her. She raised her tear- stained face and said, ‘Oh, help me, God!’

Then the sun shone so bright, and right in front of her stood the angel of God in the white robes, the one she had seen that night at the church door. He was no longer holding a sharp sword but a lovely green bough that was covered with roses. He touched it to the ceiling, which raised up high, and at the spot he had touched shone a golden star. He touched the walls and they moved outward. She saw the organ that was playing; she saw the old paintings of the pastors and their wives. The congregation was sitting in the carved pews and singing from their hymnals.

The church itself had come home to the poor girl in the tiny, cramped room, or perhaps she had gone to the church. She was sitting in a pew with the others from the parsonage. When they finished the hymn and looked up, they nodded and said, ‘It was right for you to come, Karen.’

‘It was God’s mercy,’ she said.

The organ soared, and the children’s voices in the choir sounded gentle and lovely. The bright, warm sunshine streamed through the window, reaching the church pew where Karen sat. Her heart was so filled with sunlight, with peace and joy, that it burst. Her soul flew on the sunlight to God, and no one asked about the red shoes.

被偷的白象

一

下面这个稀奇的故事是我在火车上偶然相识的一个人讲给我听的。他是一位年过七十的老先生，他那和善而斯文的面貌和真挚而诚实的态度使他嘴里说出来的每一桩事情都给人以无可置疑的真实的印象。他说：

你知道暹罗的皇家白象在那个国家是多么受人尊敬的吧。你也知道，它是国王御用的。只有国王才能养它，而且它实际上甚至比国王多少还要高出几分，因为它不仅受人尊敬，而且还受人崇拜。好吧，五年前，大不列颠和暹罗两国之间发生国界纠纷的时候，没过多久，事实就证明了错误在暹罗方面。因此一切赔偿手续被迅速执行，英国代表说他很满意，过去的嫌隙也应该忘记才行。这使暹罗国王大为安心，于是一方面为了表示感激，一方面也许是为了要消除英国对他可能还存在着的一点儿残余的不满情绪，他愿意给英国女王送一份礼物——照东方人的想法，这是与敌方和解的唯一妥当的方法。这份礼物不但应该是高贵的，而且必须是超乎一切的高贵才行。那么，还有什么礼物能比一只白象更适当呢？当时我在印度担任着一种特殊的文官职位，因此被认为特别配得上给女皇陛下献礼的荣幸任务。暹罗政府特地给我备了一只船，还配备了侍从、随员和伺候象的人。经过相当长的时间，我到了纽约港，就把我那受皇家重托的礼物安顿在泽西城，叫它住在很讲究的地方。为了恢复这只牲口的健康，然后继续航行，我们不得不停留一些时候。

过了两个星期，一切安然无事——然后我的灾祸就开始了。白象被偷了！深夜有人把我叫醒，通知我这个可怕的不幸事件。我一时简直因恐惧和焦急而发狂，我真不知如何是好。然后我渐渐平静下来，恢复了神志。我不久就想出了办法——因为事实上一个有头脑的人所能采取的有且只有一个办法。那时候虽然已经是深夜，我还是赶到纽约，找到一位警察引我到侦缉总队去。幸好我到的正是时候，侦缉队的头目、有名的督察长布朗特正准备动身回家。他是个中等身材、体格结实的人，当他深思的时候，他惯爱皱起眉头、凝神地用手指头敲着额部，这会马上给你一个印象，使你深信自己站在一个不平凡的人物面前。一看他那样子，就使我有了信心、有了希望。我向他申述了我的来意。这桩事情丝毫也不使他惊慌，看样子，他还是铁一般的镇定，并没有引起他多大的反应，就好像我告诉他的事情是有人偷了我的狗一般。他挥手叫我坐下，沉着地说道：

“请让我想一会儿吧。”

他一面这么说，一面在他的办公桌前面坐下，用手托着头。好几个书记正在办公室的另一头工作，往后的六七分钟里，我所听到的声音就只有他们的笔在纸上划出的响声。同时，督察长坐在那儿，凝神沉思。最后，他抬起头来，他的面孔那种坚定的轮廓表现出一种胸有成竹的神气，这向我说明他的脑子里已经想出了主意，计划已经拟订了。他说（声音低沉而且给人深刻的印象）：

“这不是个普通案件。一切步骤都要小心周到，每一步都要站稳脚跟，然后再放胆走下一步。一定要保守秘密才行——深深的、绝对的秘密。无论对什么人都不要谈起这件事，连对报馆记者也不要提。他们这批人归我来对付吧，我会只叫他们得到一点儿符合我的目的、故意告诉他们的消息。”他按了按铃，一个年轻人走过来。“阿拉里克，叫记者们暂时不要走。”那个小伙子出去了。“现在我们再继续来谈正经事吧——要有条有理地谈。干我这一行，要是不用严格和周密的方法，什么事也办不好。”

他拿起笔和纸来：“那么——象的名字？”

“哈森·本·阿里·本·赛林·阿布达拉·穆罕默德·摩伊赛·阿汉莫尔·杰姆赛杰吉布荷伊·都里普·苏丹·爱布·布德普尔。”

“好的。教名是什么？”

“大壮。”

“好的。出生的地方呢？”

“暹罗首都。”

“父母还在吗？”

“不——死了。”

“除了他而外，他们还生过别的孩子吗？”

“没有——他是独生子。”

“好的。在这一项底下，有这几点就够了。现在请你描述一下这只象的样子，千万不要遗漏细节，无论多么不重要的——这就是说，照你的看法认为不重要的。对于我们这一行的人，根本就没有什么不重要的细节，这种事情根本就不存在。”

于是我一边描述，他一边记录。我说完的时候，他说：

“好吧，你听着。要是我有弄错的地方，请你更正。”

他照下面这样念：

“身高十九英尺[1]，身长从额顶到尾根二十六英尺，鼻长十六英尺，尾长六英尺，全长，包括鼻子和尾巴，四十八英尺，牙长九英尺，耳朵大小与这些尺寸相称。脚印好像一只桶子立在雪里印上的痕迹。象的颜色，灰白。每只耳朵上有一个装饰珠宝的洞，像碟子那么大。特别喜欢给旁观的人喷水，并且爱拿鼻子作弄

人，不仅是那些和他相识的，连完全陌生的人也是一样。右后腿略跛，左腋下因从前生过疮，有一个小疤。被偷时背上有一个包括十五个座位的乘厢，披着一张普通地毯大小的金丝缎鞍毯。”

他写的没有错误。督察长按了按铃，把这份说明书交给阿拉里克，吩咐他说——

“把这张东西马上印五万份，寄到全州各地的侦缉队和当铺去。”阿拉里克出去了。

“哈——说了半天，总算还不错。另外我还得要一张这个东西的相片才行。”我给了他一张。他很认真地把它仔细看了一阵，说道：

“只好将就吧，反正找不到更好的。可是他把鼻子卷起来，塞在嘴里，这未免太不凑巧，一定要使人产生误会，因为他平常当然不会把鼻子卷成这个样子。”他又按了按铃。

“阿拉里克，把这张相片拿去印五万份，明天早上先办这件事，和那张说明书一同寄出。”

阿拉里克出去执行他的命令。督察长说——

“当然非悬赏不可了。那么，数目怎么样？”

“你看多少合适呢？”

“第一步，我认为——唔，先来个两万五千块钱吧。这桩事情很复杂、很难办，不知有多少逃避的路子和隐藏的机会哩。这些小偷到处都有朋友和伙伴——”

“哎呀，您知道那些人是谁吗？”

那张习惯于把思想和感情隐藏在心里的谨慎的面孔使我猜不出一点儿影子，他那说得若无其事的回答也是一样：

“那个你不用管。我可能知道，也可能不知道。我们通常都是看犯案的人下手的方法和他所要弄到手的东西的大小，从这里去找到一点儿巧妙的线索，推测他是谁。我们现在要对付的不是一个扒手，也不是一个普通的小偷，这个你可要弄明白。这回被偷的东西不是一个生手随便‘扒’了去的。刚才我说过，办这个案子是要跑许多地方的，小偷们一路往别处跑，还要随时掩盖他们的踪迹，查起来也很费劲，所以照这些情形来看，两万五千块钱也许还太少一点儿，不过我想起头先给这个数目还是可以的。”

于是我们就商定了这个数目，作为初步的悬赏，然后这位先生说道：

“在侦探史里有些案子说明某些犯人是根据他们的胃口方面的特点而破案的。那么，这只象究竟吃什么东西、吃多少分量呢？”凡是可以做线索的事情，这位先生没有不注意的。

“啊，说到他吃的东西嘛——他不管什么都吃。人也吃，《圣经》也吃——人和《圣经》之间的东西，不管什么他都吃。”

“好——真是好得很，可是太笼统了。必须说得仔细些——干我们这一行，最讲究的就是仔细。好吧，先说人。每一顿——再不然你爱说每一天也行——他要吃几个人呢，要是新鲜的话？”

“他不管新鲜不新鲜，每一顿他要吃五个普通的人。”

“好极了！五个人，我把这个记下来。他最爱吃哪些国家的人呢？”

“他对国籍也不大在乎。他特别爱吃熟人，可是对生人也并没有成见。”

“好极了。那么再说《圣经》吧，他每一顿要吃几部《圣经》呢？”

“他可以吃得下整整的一版。”

“这说得不够清楚，你指的是普通的八开本，还是家庭用的插图本呢？”

“我想他对插图是不在乎的。那就是说，我觉得他并不会把插图看得比简单的文本更宝贵。”

“不，你没听明白我的意思。我说的是本子的大小。普通八开本的《圣经》大概是两磅半重，可是带插图的四开大本有十磅到十二磅重。他每顿能吃几本多莱版的《圣经》呢？”

“你要是认识这只象的话，就不会问这些了。人家有多少他就吃多少。”

“好吧，那么照钱数来计算吧，这点我们总得大概弄清楚才行。多莱版每本要一百块钱，俄国皮子包书角的。”

“他大概要五万块钱的才够吃——就算是五百本吧。”

“对，这倒是比较明确一点儿，我把这个记下来。好吧，他爱吃人和《圣经》，这些都说得很不错。另外他还吃什么呢？我要知道详细情形。”

“他会丢开《圣经》去吃砖头，他会丢开砖头去吃瓶子，他会丢开瓶子去吃衣服，他会丢开衣服去吃猫儿，他会丢开猫儿去吃牡蛎，他会丢开牡蛎去吃火腿，他会丢开火腿去吃糖，他会丢开糖去吃馅儿饼，他会丢开馅儿饼去吃洋芋，他会丢开洋芋去吃糠皮，他会丢开糠皮去吃干草，他会丢开干草去吃燕麦，他会丢开燕麦去吃大米，因为他主要是靠这个喂大的。除了欧洲的奶油，无论什么东西他都来者不拒的，就连奶油，他要是尝出了味道，那也会吃的。”

“好极了。平常每顿的食量是……大概要……”

“噢，从四分之一吨到半吨之间，随便多少都行。”

“他爱喝……”

“凡是液体的东西都行。牛奶、水、威士忌、糖浆、蓖麻油、樟脑油、石炭酸[2]——这样说下去是没有用处的。你无论想到什么液体的东西都记下就是了。只要是液体的东西，他什么都喝，只除了欧洲的咖啡。”

“好极了。喝多大分量呢？”

“你就写五至十五桶吧——他口渴的程度一时一样，别的方面，他的胃口是没有变化的。”

“这些事情都非常重要。这对于寻找他应该是可以提供很好的线索。”

他按了按铃。

“阿拉里克，把伯恩斯队长找来吧。”

伯恩斯来了。布朗特督察长给他说明全部案情，一五一十地说得很详细。然后他用爽朗而果断的口吻说（由他的声调可以听出他的办法已经拟订得很清楚，而且也可以知道他是惯于下命令的）：

“伯恩斯队长，派琼斯、戴维斯、哈尔西、贝茨、哈克特他们这几个侦探去追寻这只象吧。”

“是，督察长。”

“派摩西、戴金、墨菲、罗杰斯、塔珀、希金斯和巴塞洛缪他们这几个侦探去追寻小偷。”

“是，督察长。”

“在那只象被偷出去的地方安排一个强有力的卫队——三十个精选的弟兄组成的卫队，还要三十个换班的——叫他们在那儿日夜严格守卫，没有我的书面手令，谁也不许走出去——除了记者。”

“是，督察长。”

“派些便衣侦探到火车上、轮船上和码头仓库那些地方去，还有由泽西城往外面去的大路上，命令他们搜查所有形迹可疑的人。”

“是，督察长。”

“把那只象的照片和附带的说明书拿给这些人，吩咐他们搜查所有的火车和往外开的渡船以及其他的船。”

“是，督察长。”

“象要是找到了，就把他捉住，打电报通知我。”

“是，督察长。”

“要是找出了什么线索，也要马上通知我——不管是这畜生的脚印，还是诸如此类的踪迹。”

“是，督察长。”

“发一道命令，叫港口警察留心巡逻河边一带。”

“是，督察长。”

“赶快派便衣侦探到所有的铁路上去，往北直到加拿大，往西直到俄亥俄，往南直到华盛顿。”

“是，督察长。”

“派一批专家到所有的电报局去，收听所有的电报，叫他们要求电报局把所有的密码电报都译给他们看。”

“是，督察长。”

“这些事情千万要做得极其秘密——注意，要秘密得绝对不走漏消息才行。”

“是，督察长。”

“照通常的时刻准时向我报告。”

“是，督察长。”

“去吧！”

“是，督察长。”

他走了。

布朗特督察长沉思了一会儿，没有作声，同时他眼睛里的那股子火气渐渐冷静下来，终于消失了。然后他向我转过身来，用平静的声音说道：

“我不喜欢吹牛，那不是我的习惯，可是——我们一定能找到那只象。”

我热情地和他握手，向他道谢，而且心里也确实是感谢他。我越看这位先生，就越喜欢他，也越对他这职业当中那些神秘且不可思议的事情感到羡慕和惊讶。然后我们在这天晚上暂时分手了，我回寓所的时候，比到他的办公室的时候心里快活得多了。

二

第二天早上，一切都登在报上，登得非常详细，甚至还增加了新的内容——包括：侦探甲、侦探乙和侦探丙的“推测”，估计这次的盗窃案是怎么干的，盗窃犯是谁，以及他们带着赃物到什么地方去了。一共有十一种推测，把一切可能的估计都包括了，单是这一个事实就表示侦探们是些怎样的别出心裁的思想家。没有哪两种推测是相同的，甚至连大致相似的都没有，唯一相同的只有一个显著的情节，关于这一点，十一个人的见解倒通通是绝对一致的。那就是，虽然我的房子后面被人拆开了墙，而唯一的门又照旧是锁着的，那只象却并不是由那个口子被牵出去的，而是由另外一条出路（还没有发现的）出去的。大家一致认为盗窃犯是故意拆开一个豁口，迷惑侦探们。像我或是任何其他外行，恐怕绝不会想得出这个，可是却一会儿都骗不了侦探们。所以我所认为没有什么奥妙的唯一的一桩事情实际上正是我弄得最迷糊的一桩事情。十一种见解都指出了盗窃嫌疑犯，可是没有两个人说的盗窃犯是相同的，嫌疑犯总数共计三十七人。报纸上的各种记载末尾都提到了一切意见中最重要的一种——布朗特督察长的意见。这种叙述有一部分是像下面这样说的：

督察长知道两个主犯是谁，即“好汉”达菲和“红毛”麦克法登。在这次盗窃事件发生前十天，他就感觉到会有人打算干这桩事，并

且还暗中跟踪这两个有名的坏蛋。可是不幸在事件发生的那天晚上，他们忽然去向不明，还没有来得及找到他们的下落，那家伙已经不见了——也就是那只象。

达菲和麦克法登是干这一行的最大胆的匪徒，督察长有理由相信去年冬天在一个严寒的夜里从侦缉总队把火炉偷出去的就是他们——结果还没有到第二天早上，督察长和在场的每个侦探都归医生照料了，有些人冻坏了脚，有些人冻坏了手指头、耳朵和其他部分。

我看了这段头一半的时候，对于这位奇特的人的了不起的智慧比以前更加惊叹。他不但以明亮的眼光看透目前的一切，就连未来的事情也瞒不住他。我不久就到了他的办公室，并且对他说，我不能不认为他早该把那两个人逮捕起来，预先防止这桩麻烦事和一切损失才对。可是他的回答很简单，而且是无可辩驳的：

“预防罪行发生不是我们的责任范围以内的事，我们的任务是惩治罪行。在罪行发生之前，我们当然不能先行惩治。”

我说我们第一步的秘密被报纸破坏了，不但我们的一切事实，连我们所有的计划和目的通通被泄露了，甚至所有的嫌疑犯的名字也被宣布出来，这些人现在当然就会伪装起来，或是隐藏着不露面。

“随他们去吧。叫他们看看我的本事，知道我要是打定了主意要抓他们的时候，我的手就会落在他们身上，把他们从秘密地方捉到，就像命运之神的手那么准确。至于报纸呢，我们非和他们通声气不可。名誉、声望，经常被大家谈到——这些事就是当侦探的人的命根子。他必须发表他的事实，否则人家还以为他根本不知道什么事实；他也必须发表他的推测，因为无论什么事情也赶不上一个侦探的推测那么稀奇、那么惊人，而且这也最能使人对他敬佩万分；我们还必须发表我们的计划，因为报纸刊物非要这个不可，我们要是不给他们，就不免要得罪他们。我们必须经常让大家知道我们在干些什么，否则他们就会以为我们什么也没干。我们与其让报纸上说些刻薄话，或者更糟糕，说些讽刺话，就不如让它说‘布朗特督察长的聪明和非凡的推测是如此这般’，那要痛快得多。”

“我知道您的话是很有道理的。可是我看了今天早上报纸发表的您的谈话，里面有一段说到您对某一个小小问题不肯吐露您的意见。”

“是呀，我们常来这一手，这是颇有作用的，并且我对那个问题根本还没有一定的主张哩。”

我交了一笔数目相当大的款子给督察长，作为临时开支，接着就是坐下来等待消息。现在我们随时都准备着电报会陆续拍来。我把报纸重新拿来看，又看看我们那份说明的传单，结果发现那二万五千元的悬赏似乎是专给侦探们的。我说我认为这笔奖金应该给任何捉到那只象的人。督察长却说：

“将来找到象的总是侦探们，所以奖金反正会归给应得的人。要是别人找到这只畜生，那也无非是靠着留心侦探们的行动，利用从他们那儿偷来的线索和踪迹才办得到。那么归根结底，奖金也还是应该归侦探们得才对。奖金的正当作用是要鼓励那些贡献他们的时间和专门智慧来干这类事情的人，而不是要把好处拿给那些幸运儿，他们不过是碰巧发现一件悬赏寻找的东西，并不是靠他们的才能和辛苦来赚得这些奖金的。”

不消说，这当然是很有道理的。现在角落上的电报机开始嘚嘚地响起来了，结果收到下面这封急电：

纽约州，花站，上午七时半

已有线索。附近农场上发现连串足迹甚深。向东跟踪两英里[3]，无结果；料象已西去。拟向该方追踪。

达利侦探

“达利是我们队里最得力的侦探之一，”督察长说，“我们不久就可以再接到他的消息。”

第二封电报又来了：

新泽西，巴克镇，上午七时四十分

刚到此地。玻璃工厂夜间被闯入，吞去瓶子八百只。附近唯一多水处在五英里外。必向该地前进。象必渴。所吞系空瓶。

贝克侦探

“这也表示很有希望。”督察长说，“我跟你说过这家伙的胃口可以做很好的线索吧。”

第三封电报是：

长岛，泰勒维尔，上午八时十五分

附近一干草堆夜间失踪。想系食去。已有线索，再前进。

哈伯德侦探

“你看他这么东奔西跑的！”督察长说：“我早就知道这事情够麻烦，可是我们终归还是可以把他抓到。”

纽约州，花站，上午九时

向西跟踪三英里。足迹大而深，不整齐。适遇一农民，据云并非象脚印，乃冬寒地冻时挖出树秧之坑。请示机宜。

达利侦探

“啊哈！偷儿的同党！这事情越来越热闹了。”督察长说。

他口授了下面这封电报给达利：

逮捕此人，逼供同伙。继续跟踪——必要时直抵太平洋岸。

布朗特督察长

其后一封电报是：

宾夕法尼亚州，康尼点，上午八时四十五分

煤气公司营业部夜间被闯入，食去三个月未付款煤气账单。已获线索，续进。

墨菲侦探

“天哪！”督察长说，“他连煤气账单也吃吗？”

“他大概不知道——当然吃啰，可是这不能饱肚子。至少没有别的东西一起吃下去是不行的。”

这时候又来了这封令人兴奋的电报：

纽约州，艾恩维尔，上午九时半

初抵此。全村惊惶万状。象于今晨五时过此村。或谓象已西去，一说东行，一说北行，一说南行——但众人均称彼等未及细察。象触毙一马，已割取小块供线索。此系象鼻击毙者；由打击方式推断，似系自左方袭击。由此马卧地姿势判断，料象已沿柏克莱铁路北去。先行四小时半，拟立即跟踪追捕。

霍斯侦探

我发出了欢呼。督察长还是像一尊雕像似的不动声色。他镇静地按了按铃。

“阿拉里克，请伯恩斯队长到这儿来。”

伯恩斯来了。

“有多少人可以马上派去出勤？”

“九十六个，督察长。”

“立刻派他们往北去，叫他们集中在柏克莱铁路沿线艾恩维尔以北一带。”

“是，督察长。”

“叫他们极其秘密地行动。另外还有别的人下班的时候，马上叫他们准备出勤。”

“是，督察长。”

“去吧!”

“是，督察长。”

马上又来了另外一封电报：

纽约州，赛奇角，十时半

初抵此。八时十五分象过此地。全镇人已逃空，仅留一警察。象显然未向警察袭击，而欲击灯柱。但击中两者。已自警察尸体割肉一块做线索。

斯图曼侦探

“原来象已经转向西边去了，”督察长说，“可是他逃不掉，因为我派出的人已经在那一带地方分布到各处了。”

其后的一封电报说：

格罗佛站，十一时十五分

初抵此。全村人已逃空，仅余老弱病夫。三刻钟前象由此经过。正值反禁酒群众大会召

开，象由窗中伸入其鼻，自蓄水池吸水将大会冲散，有人遭水灌注——旋即死去，数人淹毙。侦探克洛斯与奥少夫纳西曾过此镇，但向南行——故与象相左。周围数英里地区均大为惊恐——居民均由家中逃出。逃往各处，均遇此象，丧命者颇多。

布朗特侦探

我简直要流泪，因为这场灾难太使我难受了。可是督察长只说：

“你看——我们正在一步步把他包围起来。他觉出了我们已经来到，又往东转了。”

可是还有许多叫我们伤脑筋的消息在后面。电报又带来了这个消息：

霍艮港，十二时十九分

初到此。半小时前象行经此地，曾引起极度惊恐与兴奋。象在各街横行——装管工二人路过，一人丧命，一人得解脱，众皆悲恸。

欧弗拉赫第侦探

“这下子他可是让我的弟兄们包围住了，”督察长说，“怎么也逃不掉了。”

分布到新泽西和宾夕法尼亚各地的侦探们又拍来了一连串的电报，他们都在追踪各种线索，其中包括被蹂躏的粮仓、工厂、主日学校的图书馆，大家都怀着很大的希望——实际上这些希望简直成了确有把握的事。督察长说：

“我很想能够和他们通消息，叫他们往北去，可是这办不到。侦探只到电报局去发电报来向我报告；马上他又走了，你简直不知在哪儿找得到他。”

然后又来了这封电报：

康涅狄格州，桥港，十二时十五分

巴南愿出每年四千元代价，获使用此象供张贴流动广告之特权，由目前至侦探寻获此象时为止。拟在象身贴马戏团招贴画。盼即复。

波格斯侦探

“这简直是荒谬绝伦！”我大声地说。

“当然是啰，”督察长说，“巴南先生自以为非常精明，可是他显然还看不透我——我可看透了他。”

于是他给这封急电口授回电：

谢绝巴南所提条件。需七千元，否则作罢。

布朗特督察长

“看吧。不要等多久就会有回电。巴南先生不在家，他在电报局——他在交涉生意的时候有这个习惯。不消三分钟……”

同意。

巴南

电报机嘚嘚嘚的声音打断了督察长的谈话。我对这个非常离奇的插曲还没有来得及发表意见，下面这封急电就把我的心思引到另一个恼人的方面去了：

纽约州，波利维亚，十二时五十分

象由南方抵此，十一时五十分过此向森林

前进。途中驱散出殡行列，送葬者牺牲二人。居民放小炮击象后逃散。侦探伯克与我于十分钟后由北方赶到，但因误认若干地下土坑为象踪，致延误甚久；但终获象踪，追至森林。然后伏地爬行，继续注视象踪，追随至丛林中。伯克先行，不幸象已停步休息；故伯克因低头察看象踪，尚未发觉象在眼前，头已触其后腿。伯克即刻起立，手握象尾欢呼“奖金应归……”但出言未毕，象鼻一击已使此勇士粉身碎骨而死。我向后逃，象转身穷追，直至林边，速度惊人，我本非丧命不可，幸因老天保佑，送葬行列所余数人又与象遭遇，使其转移目标。现闻送葬者无一人生还，但也不算损失过重，剩余送葬用品足以再举办另一丧葬活动。象已再行失踪。

马尔鲁尼侦探

分派到新泽西、宾夕法尼亚、得拉维尔和弗吉尼亚等地的那些苦干和有信心的侦探们都在跟着有希望的新线索追寻，我们除了从他们那里以外，始终没有得到任何消息，直到下午两点过后，才接到这封电报：

巴克斯特中心，二时十五分

象曾到此地，周身贴马戏团广告，驱散一奋兴会，将改过自新者毙伤甚多。居民将象囚于栏中，派人守卫。其后侦探布朗与我来此，即入栏持照片与说明书对此象进行鉴定。各种特征一概相符，仅有一项不得见——即腋下疮疤。布郎为查明起见，匍匐至象体下细察，结果立即丧命——头部被击碎，但碎脑中一无所有。众皆奔逃，象亦匿去，横冲直撞，伤亡多人。象虽逃去，但因炮伤，沿途均留显著之血迹。定能再度寻获。现象已穿越茂林向南前进。

布朗特侦探

这是最后一封电报。晚上起了雾，非常之浓，以至三英尺外的东西都看不见。浓雾整夜没有散。渡船不得不停开，甚至连公共汽车都不能行驶。

三

第二天早晨，报纸上还是像从前一样，登满了侦探们的推测；我们那些惨剧也通通登出来了，另外还登了许多消息，都是报馆从各地电报通讯员方面得来的。篇幅占了一栏又一栏，一直占到一版三分之一的地位，还加上一些显眼的标题，使我看了心里发烦。这些标题一般的情状大致是这样：

白象尚未捕获！

仍在继续前进，到处闯祸！

各处村庄居民惊骇欲狂，逃避一空！

白色恐怖在他前面传播，死亡与

糜烂接踵而至！

侦探尾随其后。粮仓被毁，工厂被劫一空，收成被吃光，公众集会被驱散，酿成惨剧无法形容！侦缉队中三十四位最出色的侦探的推测！督察长布朗特的推测！

“啊哈！”督察长布朗特几乎露出兴奋的神色，说道，“这可真是了不起！这是任何侦探机关从来没有碰到过的好运道。这个案件的名声会传到天涯地角，永垂不朽，我的名字也会跟着传出去的。”

但是我没有什么可高兴的。我觉得所有那些血案似乎都是我干出来的，那只象只不过是我不负责任的代理人罢了。受害的人数增加得多么快呀！有一个地方，他“干涉了一次选举，弄死了五个投重票的违法选民”。在这个举动之后，他又杀害了两个不幸的人，他们名叫奥唐诺休和麦克弗兰尼根，“前一天才来到这全世界被压迫者的家乡来避难，正想要第一次运用美国公民选举投票的光荣权利，恰好遭到这个暹罗煞星的毒手而丧命了”。到另一处，他“发现了一个疯狂的兴风作浪的传教士，正在准备他新一轮的对跳舞、戏剧和其他不能还击的事物所要进行的英勇的攻击，一脚就把他踩死了”。又在另一个地方，他“杀害了一个避雷针经纪人”。遇难的人数越来越多，血腥气越来越重，伤心惨目的事件越来越多。丧命的共达六十人，受伤的二百四十人，一切记载都证明了侦探们的活动和热心，而且结尾都是说“有三十万老百姓和四个侦探看见过这个可怕的畜生，而这四个侦探之中有两个被他弄死了”。

电报机又嘚嘚嘚地响起来，我简直听了就害怕。随即消息就一条条传过来，可是这些消息的性质却使我感到快慰的失望。不久就明白了，象已不知去向。雾使他得以找到一个很好的藏身之所，没有被人发觉。从一些极荒谬的遥远地点打来的电报说是在某时某刻有人在雾里瞥见过一个隐隐约约的庞然大物，那“无疑是象”。这个隐隐约约的庞然大物曾在新港、新泽西、宾夕法尼亚、纽约州内地、布鲁克林，甚至在纽约市区，处处都曾有人瞥见过！但是处处都是这个隐隐约约的庞然大物很快就不见了，丝毫没有留下什么痕迹。强大的侦缉队分派到广大地区的那许多侦探，每人都按时来电报告，个个都有线索，而且都在跟踪，拼命往前穷追。

但是那一天过去了，并无其他结果。

第二天又是一样。

再往后一天还是一样。

报纸上的消息渐成千篇一律，其中的各种事实都是毫无价值的，各种线索都是没有结果的，各种推测几乎都是搜尽枯肠想出来故意使人惊讶、使人高兴、使人眼花缭乱的。

我遵照督察长的建议，把奖金加了一倍。

又过了四个沉闷的日子，然后那些可怜的、干得很起劲的侦探遭到了一次严重的打击——报馆记者们谢绝发表他们的推测，很冷淡地说：“让我们歇一歇吧。”

白象失踪两个星期之后，我遵照督察长的意见，把奖金增加到七万五千元。这个数目是很大的，但是我觉得我宁肯牺牲我的全部私人财产，也不要失掉我的政府对我的信任。现在侦探们倒了霉，报纸上就转过笔锋来攻击他们，对他们加以最令人难堪的讽刺。这使一些卖艺的歌手们想出了一个好主意，他们把自己打扮成侦探，在舞台上用可笑至极的方法追寻那只象。漫画家们画出那些侦探拿着小望远镜在全国各地一处一处地仔细察看，而象却在他们背后从他们口袋里偷苹果吃。他们还把侦探们戴的徽章画成各式各样的可笑的漫画——侦探小说的封底上用金色印着这个徽章，你一定是看到过的——那是一只睁得很大的眼睛，配上“我们永远不睡”这几个字。侦探们到酒店去喝酒的时候，那故意逗笑的掌柜就恢复一句早已作废的话，说道：“您喝杯醒眼酒好吗？”空气中弥漫着浓厚的讽刺气氛。

但是有一个人在这种气氛中始终保持镇定，处之泰然，不动声色，那就是坚定不移的督察长。他那双大胆的眼睛永不表示丧气，他那沉着的信心永不动摇。他老是说：

“让他们去嘲笑吧！谁最后笑就笑得最痛快。”

我对这位先生的敬仰变成了一种崇拜。我经常在他身边。他的办公室对他而言已经成为一个不愉快的地方，现在一天比一天更加厉害了。可是他既然受得了，我当然也要撑持下去——至少是能撑多久就撑多久。所以我经常到他这里来，并且停留很久——我好像是唯一能够忍受得了的外人。大家都不知道我怎么会熬得下去。我每每似乎觉得非开小差不可，可是一到这种时候，我就看看那张沉着而且显然是满不在乎的脸，于是又坚持下去了。

白象失踪以后，大约过了三个星期，有一天早上，我正想要说我不得不息鼓收兵的时候，那位大侦探却提出一个绝妙的拿手办法来，这下子可阻止了我那个念头。

这个办法就是和窃犯们妥协。我虽然和世界上最有机智的天才有过广泛的接触，可是这位先生的思想之丰富实在是我生平从来没有见过的。他说他相信可以出十万元和对方妥协，把那只象找回来。我说我相信可以勉强凑这个数目。可是那些可怜的侦探非常忠心地努力干了一场，怎么办呢？他说：

“按照妥协的办法，他们照例得一半。”

这就打消了我唯一的反对理由，于是督察长写了两封信，内容如下：

亲爱的夫人。——你的丈夫只要和我立即约谈一次，就可以得一笔巨款（而且完全保证不受法律干涉）。

督察长布朗特

他派他信任的信差把这两封信送一封给“好汉”达菲“不知是真是假的妻子”，另一封给“红毛”麦克法登的“不知真假的妻子”。

一小时之内，来了这么两封无礼的回信：

你这老糊涂蛋：“好汉”达菲已经死了两年了。

布里奇特·马奥尼

瞎子督察长，——“红毛”麦克法登早就被绞死了，他已经升天一年半了。除了当侦探

的，随便哪个笨蛋也知道这桩事情。

玛丽·奥胡里根

“早就猜想到这些事情了，”督察长说，“这一证明足见我的直觉真是千真万确。”

一个办法刚刚行不通，他又想出另外一个主意来了。他马上写了一则广告拿到早报上去登，我把它抄了一份：

子——亥戌丑卯酉。二四二辰。未丑寅卯——辰亥三二八成酉丑卯。寅亥申寅，——；二已！寅丑酉。密。

他说只要偷儿还活着，见了这则广告就会到往常约会的地点去。他还说明了这个往常约会的地点是侦探和罪犯之间进行一切谈判的地方。这次的约会定在第二天晚上十二点举行。

在那个时刻来到之前，我们什么事情也不能做，所以我赶快走出这个办公室，而且心里实在因为得到这个喘息的机会而有谢天谢地的感觉。

第二天晚上十一点，我带着十万元现钞，交到督察长手里，过了一会儿他就告辞了，眼睛里流露出那勇往直前的、一向没有消失的信心。一个钟头几乎无法忍受的时光终于熬过去了，然后我听见他那可喜的脚步声，于是我喘着气站起来，一歪一倒地跑过去迎接他，他那双明亮的眼睛里发出多么得意的闪光啊！他说：

“我们妥协了！那些开玩笑的家伙明天就要改变论调了！跟我去！”

他拿着一支点着的蜡烛大步地走进一个绝大的圆顶地窖，那儿经常有六十个侦探在睡觉，这时候还有二十来个在打牌消遣。我紧跟在他后面。他飞快地一直往地窖里老远的、阴暗的那一头走过去。我正在闷得要命、简直要晕倒的时候，他一下子绊倒了，倒在一个大家伙的伸开的肢体上。我听见他一面倒下去，一面欢呼道：

“我们这种高贵的职业果然是名不虚传的。你的象在这儿哪！”

我被人抬到上面那办公室里，他们用石炭酸使我清醒过来了。整个侦缉队都拥了进来，随后那一番欢天喜地的祝贺真是热闹非凡，我从来没有见过那种场面。他们把记者们邀请过来，打开一桶一桶的香槟酒来痛饮祝贺，大家握手、道贺，简直没有个完，兴头十足。当时的英雄人物当然是督察长，他的快乐到了顶点了，而且也是靠他的耐心、品德和勇敢换来的，所以叫我看了很欢喜。虽然我站在那儿，已经成了一个无家可归的穷光蛋，我受托的那个无价之宝也死了，我为本国服务的职位也完蛋了，一切都由于我向来似乎有个致命的老毛病——对于一个重大的托付老是粗心大意地执行。一双双传神的眼睛对督察长表示了深切的敬仰，还有许多侦探的声音悄悄地说：“你瞧瞧人家——实在是这一行的大王——只要给他一点儿线索就行，他就只需要这个，不管什么东西藏起来了，他没有找不着的。”大家分那五万元奖金的时候，真是兴高采烈；分完之后，督察长一面把他那一份塞进腰包，一面发表了一篇简短的谈话。他在这篇谈话里说道：“痛痛快快地享受这笔奖金吧，伙计们，因为这是你们赚来的；并且还不只这个——你们还给侦探这种职业博得了不朽的名声。”

又来了一封电报，内容是：

密歇根，孟禄，上午十时

三星期来，初遇一电报局。随象踪骑马穿过森林，抵此地时已奔波千英里，脚印日见其

重，日见其大，且日益显明。望勿急躁——至多再一星期，定能将象寻获。万无一失。

达利侦探

督察长叫大家给达利三呼喝彩，给“侦缉队里这位能手”欢呼，然后吩咐手下给他打电报去，叫他回来领取他那一份奖金。

被偷的象这场惊人的风波就这样完结了，第二天报纸上又是满篇好听的恭维话，只有一个无聊的例外。这个报纸说：“侦探真是伟大！像一只失踪了的象这么个小小的东西，他找起来也许是慢一点儿——白天他尽管整天寻找，夜里就跟象的尸体睡在一起，一直拖到三个星期，可是他终归还是会把他找着——只要把象错放在那里的人给他说明地点就行了！”

我永远失去了可怜的大壮。炮弹给了他致命伤，他在雾里悄悄地走到那个倒霉的地方；在敌人的包围之中，又经常受到侦缉的危险，他连饿带熬，一直瘦下来，最后死神才给了他安息。

最后的妥协花掉了我十万元，侦探的费用另外花掉四万二千元，我再也没有向我本国政府去申请一个职位，我成了个倾家荡产的人，成了个落魄人间的流浪汉——可是我始终觉得那位先生是全世界空前的大侦探，我对他的敬仰至今还是没有减退，而且一辈子都不会改变。

（张友松 译）

[1] 1英尺≈0.3米。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为译者注。）

[2] 即苯酚。常温下为无色透明针状晶体。此处所指可能是石炭酸水溶液或其它含有石炭酸成分的液体。——编者注

[3] 1英里≈1.6公里。——编者注

一个顺风顺水的坏小子的故事

从前，有个叫吉姆的坏小子——然而，如果你留意一下，就会发现你在主日学校[1]读到的那些书里，几乎所有坏小子都叫詹姆斯。这着实很奇怪，不过，咱们这位主人公确实叫吉姆，千真万确。

吉姆没有一位患病的母亲——一位笃信宗教、痨病缠身、十分乐于从此躺进坟墓长眠不起的母亲，但是，因为对儿子强烈的爱，她最终还是生下了他，心中满是焦虑，害怕自己哪天撒手人寰，她的儿子将被留下独自面对这个残暴而冷酷的世界。在主日学校的那些书里，大多数坏小子都叫詹姆斯，并且有个患病的母亲。她们会对詹姆斯说，“好，我现在躺下啦”，诸如此类的话，然后用甜蜜而哀伤的语调唱歌哄他们入睡，再给他们一个晚安吻。最后，詹姆斯入眠后，母亲则跪在他的床边哀哭。但是，我们这位主人公可不一样。他叫吉姆，母亲没病没灾——没有痨病，也没有任何如此这般的毛病，反之，她身体还挺壮实。而且，她也并不虔诚信教。更甚者，她也没那么担心吉姆。她曾经说，吉姆要是不小心伤到了脖子，那也没什么大不了。晚上睡觉前，她经常打吉姆的屁股，且从来没给过他什么晚安吻；相反，她所谓的“晚安”就是离开前扇吉姆一顿耳光。

有一次，这个坏小子偷了食品柜的钥匙，伸手进去偷吃果酱。为了不让母亲看出来，他还往果酱罐里倒焦油来掩人耳目。不过，他做这些的时候，心里可没有突然间掠过什么糟糕的感觉，也没有一个声音在他耳边说：“我这样忤逆妈妈对吗？这么做是不是太罪恶了？那些偷吃善良母亲果酱的坏孩子后来都怎么样了？”接下来，他也没有一个人孤零零地跪在地上，心中暗暗保证再也不做坏事，继而，捧着一颗轻盈、愉悦的心站起来去找妈妈，跟她道出个中缘由并乞求原谅。不用说，他母亲也没有被感动得双眼满是骄傲的泪水，心怀感激地祝福他。不，那是其他坏小子在书本中的境遇；奇怪的是，咱们这位吉姆的遭遇可谓与众不同。他吃了果酱，还用他一贯粗鄙而应受谴责的方式说“棒呆了！”。然后，他又往里面倒了倒焦油，再次说，“棒呆了！”。接着哈哈大笑，断言道，当他母亲发现这一切，那个老婆子一定会暴跳如雷。然而，当她真的有所察觉，他坚称自己毫不知情，而她则狠狠地抽了他一顿鞭子，弄得自己号啕大哭。关于这个小男孩的一切都如此稀奇——一切都和那些在其他书中司空见惯的坏小子詹姆斯大相径庭。

有一次，他爬到橡子果园的苹果树上去偷苹果。树枝没有折断，他也没有摔着胳膊、被农场主家的神犬咬伤，更没有因此连续几个星期卧病在床，进而在病中忏悔，从此摇身一变，成为一个乖孩子。哦，根本没有！他随心所欲地偷了好多苹果，又安然无恙地返回地面。他连怎么对付那只狗都盘算好了，当它跑过来准备咬他的时候，他举起一块砖头将它砸了个四仰八叉。这实在太奇怪了，其他那些劝人向善的书里（通常封底绘有大理石花纹，插图里满是身穿燕尾服、短马裤，头戴大檐帽的男士，以及长裙的腰线在胳膊以下、没有加束腰的女士），可从来没发生过这种事儿。主日学校的书里从来没有这档子事儿。

有一次，他偷了老师的铅笔刀。一想到被发现就要挨一顿鞭子，吉姆不禁十分害怕，于是，他将铅笔刀塞进了乔治·威尔逊的帽子里——可怜的威尔逊，寡妇威尔逊太太的孩子，道德小标兵，全村公认的好孩子。威尔逊总是很听妈妈的话，从不说谎，勤奋好学，对主日学校简直着了迷。当那把小刀从威尔逊的帽子里掉出来，这个可怜的小男孩一下垂下头，羞红了脸，好像自己真的犯了错。气急败坏的老师认定他就是小偷，就在老师的戒尺马上要打到威尔逊瑟瑟发抖的肩膀上时，他们中间并没有突然出现一位纯属虚构的白发太平绅士[2]，更见不到他拿腔拿调地说：“放了那个高尚的小男孩——那个真正犯错的懦夫就在这里！课间休息的时候，我正好路过校门口，没人注意到我，而我却看到了真正偷东西的人！”没有这样的事情发生，吉姆也没有因此挨一顿揍。自然，那位受人尊敬的绅士也没有在这些哭哭啼啼、感激涕零的师生面前进行什么长篇的说教。他也没有牵起乔治的手说，这样的小男孩值得被夸奖，然后邀请他上门与自己同住，让他帮忙打扫办公室，生生火，跑跑腿，砍砍柴，之后，再让乔治去学法律，平时帮自己的妻子做做家务，再空出些时间去消遣，最后，这个小男孩月入四十美分，幸福无忧。不，故事本该是这样的，但吉姆的版本不是这样的。没有一位爱管闲事的老绅士突然闯入，找吉姆的麻烦，所以，好孩子乔治挨了打，吉姆则在一旁幸灾乐祸。因为，你知道的，吉姆讨厌好孩子。吉姆说：“他看不起那些没种的。”多么粗鄙的语言啊，这个又坏又疏于管教的臭小子。

然而，吉姆身上最让人啧啧称奇的地方就是当他星期日[3]去划船的时候，居然没有溺水；又一个星期天，吉姆去钓鱼，正赶上暴风雨，却没有被闪电击中。怎么会这样？你也许翻了又翻，翻遍了主日学校的书，然而，从现在到下一个圣诞节你也找不到一个相似的故事。哦，不！你能找到的那些星期日去划船的坏小子全都会无一例外地溺水；而他们如果星期日去钓鱼，则一定会遭雷击。那些星期日载着小坏蛋的船都不太好过。而当那些小坏蛋在安息日[4]跑去钓鱼，则十有八九会遭遇暴风雨。咱们这位吉姆是怎么躲过这一切的，对我来说可真是个谜。

这位吉姆的日子过得有如神助——一准儿是这样。什么都伤不到他。有一次，他甚至给兽栏里的大象喂了一块口嚼烟，也没有被大象用鼻子敲得脑袋落地。他在橱柜里翻翻拣拣，找一瓶薄荷露，可从来没有因此把硝酸喝进肚。他偷走了父亲的枪，在安息日那天跑出去打猎，也没有崩掉自己三四根手指。他一时气急，挥拳打向自己妹妹的太阳穴，但她也没有因此整个夏天都病恹恹，接着不幸离世，更没有在弥留之际，留下温柔宽恕的蜜语，让他备受谴责的内心更受打击。不，她挺过来了。故事的最后，他离开了，走到海边，再也没有回来。他发现自己在这个世界上悲伤而孤独，他心爱的人都已经长眠地下，而他孩童时代那藤蔓掩映中的家也已经轰隆隆倒塌，走向破败。啊，不！这些都没有发生。他回来了，醉醺醺的，像个浪人似的，先进了警察局。

他长大了，结婚了，拥有了一个庞大的家庭。一天晚上，他用斧头一个个敲碎了他们的脑袋。后来，他凭着一整套的偷奸耍滑发了家，现在已经成了村子里最可鄙、最恶毒的无赖了。可他广受尊敬，已经是州议会的一员了。

所以，你看到了，主日学校那些书里的可从来没有一个詹姆斯能有咱们这位有如神助的坏蛋吉姆的好运气。

（郭宇萌 译）

[1] 主日学校：英、美等诸国为贫民开办的初等教育机构，通常周日开课。兴起于18世纪末，盛行于19世纪上半期。

[2] 太平绅士是一种源于英国，由政府委任民间人士担任维持社区安宁、防止非法刑罚及处理一些较简单的法律程序的职衔，多半是适用在英美法系的国家或是曾使用英美法系的地区。

[3] 根据当时的习俗，星期日，教徒应该去教堂做礼拜。

[4] 安息日（the Sabbath）被普遍认为是犹太教（Judaism）主要节日之一。Sabbath一词源于阿卡德语，本意为“七”，希伯来语意为“休息”“停止工作”，犹太历每周的第七日（每逢星期五日落到星期六日落）。犹太人谨守安息日为圣日，不许工作。

一个不得善终的好孩子的故事

本文是在几个文友的坚持之下写就的，他们认为，如果我之前写的道德小品《一个顺风顺水的坏小子的故事》值得被印制发售并保存上几个星期，那么，一个合理而不带偏见的姊妹篇理应获得同样的不朽。

——写在前面的话

从前，有个叫雅各布·比利文斯的好孩子。他总是很听父母的话，无论他们的要求多么不可理喻，他总是认真读书，去主日学校的时候从来没有迟到过。他不会逃学，即使冷静下来想想，发现逃学将是他能做到的最有利可图的事儿。从来没有一个小孩能把他约出来玩，他实在太奇怪了。无论谎言多么便利，他也不会撒谎。他只是说撒谎是不对的，而这个理由对他来说就足够了。他太诚实，简直有些可笑了。雅各布这套古怪的行为方式简直超越了世间万物。他不会在星期天玩弹球，不会掏鸟窝，也不会给街头艺人的猴子们几枚辣味糖果；他看上去对一切合情合理的娱乐活动都兴致缺乏。因此，其他几个男孩总是试图推测并理解他，可是他们完全得不出任何令人满意的答案；就像我之前说过的一样，他们只能得出一些模模糊糊的答案——他一定是“有毛病”了。因此，他们将他纳入自己的保护，从不允许任何人伤害他。

这个好孩子读了主日学校所有的书，这些书是他最大的慰藉——这就是全部奥秘所在了。他相信主日学校书里那些优秀的小男孩，并对他们充满信心，希望可以邂逅他们中的一员；但他从来没有真的遇到过。也许，他们全都在他出生前就去世了吧。无论什么时候，只要他读到一个好孩子的故事，马上就会翻到结局去看这个孩子结局如何，因为他想不远万里地去找他，好好端详端详他。但这些都无济于事，那些好孩子全都在故事结尾过世了。你能在书页里看到一张葬礼的图片——所有亲朋好友和主日学校的孩子都来了，他们穿着十分短小的马裤，搭配过大的女帽，站在墓碑前，每个人都拿着一码半长的纸巾哭哭啼啼。他经常这样寻不到结果，从来没有亲眼见过任何一个好孩子，谁让他们在故事最后都死了呢。

雅各布有一个崇高的理想——他希望被写进主日学校的书里。他希望被写进去，再配上一幅画，画面中，他满怀光荣地坚决不肯对自己的母亲撒谎，而她则因为他的“成就”喜极而泣；或者另一幅画，画中，他站在门廊上，给一位可怜兮兮、抚养着六个孩子、无家可归的女乞丐一便士，告诉她想怎么花就怎么花，但是不能挥霍无度，因为挥霍可是一种罪行；抑或另一幅画，画面中，他宽宏大量地拒不告发一个坏小子，而这家伙总是在雅各布从学校出来的路上躲在拐角处等着他，抄起一块板子猛打他的脑袋，一路“嘿！嘿！”地大叫，追着雅各布回家。这就是年轻的雅各布·比利文斯的志向——他渴望被写入主日学校的书里。但是，有时当他想起所有好孩子都死了的时候，心里多多少少有些不舒服。他喜欢活着，你知道的，而那些主日学校书里的好孩子却都死了，这实在是“成为他们”最让人感到不舒服的地方了。他知道，做个好孩子是有损健康的；他知道，想要和书里那些好孩子一样好到不可思议的程度可是比得了痨病还要致命的；他知道，他们之中没有一个人能够活得长久，而一想到如果他真的被写进书里自己也看不到，他就十分痛苦；然而，如果他们在他去世之前就出了书，那这本书可就流行不起来了——没有葬礼画面可不行。如果书里不写上他弥留之际给身边人的箴言，那可算不上一本主日学校藏书。所以，到了最后一刻，他当然只好拿定了主意，竭尽全力，好好活着，尽量坚持，并且在死期将近时准备好自己的遗言。

但是，不知为何，这个好孩子一直诸事不顺，发生在他身上的事儿和其他书里那些好孩子的经历一直大相径庭。那些好孩子一路顺风顺水，而坏小子们都摔断了腿；但是，在他的故事里，一定是哪颗螺母松动了，哪里出了岔子，一切都对不上。他发现吉姆[1]·布莱克在偷苹果，便走到树下，给他讲书里那些坏小子的下场——从邻居家的树上摔下来，伤了胳膊。吉姆也从树上摔了下来，但是，吉姆摔到了他身上，伤到了他的胳膊，自己却毫发无伤。雅各布搞不懂这是怎么回事。书里可从来没发生过这种事。

还有一次，那些坏小子将一位盲人推到泥坑里，雅各布冲上去帮忙，满心以为会得到盲人的祝福。然而，那个盲人根本毫无谢意，而是举起拐杖狠狠打了他的脑瓜子一下，并称下次雅各布要是再敢先推他、再假意帮助他，他就要抓他个现行——这和哪本书里写的都对不上，雅各布把所有书都重新看了一遍。

雅各布一直想要找一只无家可归、饥肠辘辘且饱受折磨的牧羊犬。他想把它带回家，好好喂养，并得到狗狗长久的感激。终于被他找到了一只，雅各布高兴坏了。他把它带回家喂养，不过，正当他想好好摸摸它的时候，那只狗猛地扑向他，咬碎了他身上所有的衣服，只有前裆的布片还稍有保留，让他狠狠出了个大洋相。这可够奇怪的。它和书里的狗是同一种品种，但习性却大相径庭。这个男孩无论做什么都会弄得一团糟。那些书里的孩子屡屡被嘉奖的地方，恰恰成了雅各布最徒劳倒霉的地方。

有一次，他在去主日学校的路上看到一群坏小子出发去划帆船。他吓坏了，要知道，在他受过的教育里那些星期日去开帆船的男孩无一例外都溺水了。所以，他赶紧划着一个小木筏去警告他们，不过，一根原木挡了他的路，他脚下一滑，栽进了水里。很快，有人把他捞出水里，医生帮他把身体里的水挤出来，大吼着将他叫醒了。但他还是感冒了，足足卧床了九个星期。最莫名其妙的就是，那些坏小子倒是一整天都玩得很尽兴，最后活蹦乱跳地回家了，实在不可思议。雅各布·比利文斯说，书里可从来没有发生过这样的事。他完全惊呆了。

痊愈后，雅各布有些心灰意冷。但无论如何，他还是决定继续干下去。他知道，直到目前为止，他的经历还不足以成书。他还没有过上好孩子的生活，如果他可以坚持到最后，那么他希望有一天可以做到最好。如果一切都不尽如人意，他还能靠着临终遗言扳回一城。

看过书，雅各布发现现在是他出海去当船上侍者的时候了。他拜访了一位船长，提出了自己的申请。当船长管他要介绍信的时候，他骄傲地掏出一个小册子，指着上面的话：“致雅各布·比利文斯，来自他慈爱的老师”。但那位船长是个粗鄙野蛮的汉子，他说道，“哦！这算什么！”这根本证明不了雅各布能刷好盘子、使好饮料机。他可不需要雅各布。这简直是雅各布一生中最不可理喻的一件事了。在如何唤起船长的恻隐之心这方面，一本写着老师溢美之词的小册子可从来没有失手过，它们通常能为被推荐者带来各种既光荣又赚钱的职务——他从来没在任何一本书上读到自己这种境遇。他实在无法相信发生在自己身上的事。

这个男孩总是四处碰壁。发生在他身上的事儿从来都和书上对不上。终于有一天，当他正四处寻觅坏孩子想要加以劝诫时，他发现他们都聚在一个老铸铁厂里，正在拿十四五只狗取乐。他们将这群狗拴成长长的一列，正准备往它们的尾巴上紧紧地系上空炸药罐。雅各布心有所动。他坐在一个罐子上，使命将至，他毫不介意沾上油腻。他抓住打头那只狗的脖子，转眼充满责备地望着最调皮的汤姆·琼斯。但就在此时，麦克沃尔特总督盛怒着走进来了。所有坏小子都跑了，雅各布却特意满脸无辜地站起来，并开始了主日学校书里那一套庄重的发言，开头不外乎“哦，先生！”。然而，现实中，无论乖小孩还是坏小子都没能就着“哦，先生！”来一番高谈阔论。总督根本等不及听下面的话。他抓着雅各布的耳朵就将他提起来转了个圈儿，举起手狠狠打了他背后一下，瞬间，雅各布被弹出屋顶，朝着太阳一路高飞，那些狗则像风筝一样跟着他飞。地面上，一点儿总督和老铸铁厂的影子都看不见了。而雅各布·比利文斯呢，他根本没机会留下精心准备的遗言了，除非是说给鸟听。最后，虽然他身体的主要部分算是落在了邻郡树顶上，他身体的其他部分却散落在四个小镇上，所以，人们不得不验了五次尸来看他是不是死了，是怎么死的。从来没有一个男孩被这么惨烈地分尸过。

这个已故的好孩子，事事竭尽全力，却从来得不到书中的待遇。除了他之外，其他男孩照他那么做都兴旺发达了。他的故事实在卓绝，个中缘由也许永远也弄不清了。

（郭宇萌 译）

[1] 可能是对应上一篇文章提到的，所有“坏小子都叫吉姆”的说法。

The Story of the Good Little Boy Who Did Not Prosper

[The following has been written at the insistence of several literary friends, who thought that if the history of ‘The Bad Little Boy Who Didn’t Come to Grief’ (a moral sketch which I published five or six years ago) was worthy of preservation several weeks in print, a fair and unprejudiced companion piece to it would deserve a similar immortality.

editorial MeMoranduM]

Once there was a good little boy by the name of Jacob Blivens. He always obeyed his parents, no matter how absurd and unreasonable their demands were; and he always learned his book, and never was late at Sabbath school. He would not play hookey, even when his sober judgment told him it was the most profitable thing he could do. None of the other boys could ever make that boy out, he acted so strangely. He wouldn’t lie, no matter how convenient it was. He just said it was wrong to lie, and that was sufficient for him. And he was so honest that he was simply ridiculous. The curious ways that that Jacob had surpassed everything. He wouldn’t play marbles on Sunday, he wouldn’t rob birds’ nests, he wouldn’t give hot pennies to organ- grinders’ monkeys; he didn’t seem to take any interest in any kind of rational amusement. So the other boys used to try to reason it out and come to an understanding of him, but they couldn’t arrive at any satisfactory conclusion; as I said before, they could only figure out a sort of vague idea that he was‘afflicted,’ and so they took him under their protection, and never allowed any harm to come to him.

This good little boy read all the Sunday- school books; they were his greatest delight. This was the whole secret of it. He believed in the good little boys they put in the Sunday- school books; he had every confidence in them. He longed to come across one of them alive, once; but he never did. They all died before his time, maybe. Whenever he read about a particularly good one, he turned over quickly to the end to see what became of him, because he wanted to travel thousands of miles and gaze on him; but it wasn’t any use; that good little boy always died in the last chapter, and there was a picture of the funeral, with all his relations and the Sunday- school children standing around the grave in pantaloons that were too short, and bonnets that were too large, and everybody crying into handkerchiefs that had as much as a yard and a half of stuff in them. He was always headed off in this way. He never could see one of those good little boys, on account of his always dying in the last chapter.

Jacob had a noble ambition to be put in a Sunday- school book. He wanted to be put in, with pictures representing him gloriously declining to lie to his mother, and she weeping for joy about it; and pictures representing him standing on the doorstep giving a penny to a poor beggar- woman with six children, and telling her to spend it freely, but not to be extravagant, because extravagance is a sin; and pictures of him magnanimously refusing to tell on the bad boy who always lay in wait for him around the corner, as he came from school, and welted him over the head with a lath, and then chased him home, saying ‘Hi! hi!’ as he proceeded. That was the ambition of young Jacob Blivens. He wished to be put in a Sunday- school book. It made him feel a little uncomfortable sometimes when he reflected that the good little boys always died. He loved to live, you know, and this was the most unpleasant feature about being a Sunday- school- book boy. He knew it was not healthy to be good. He knew it was more fatal than consumption to be so supernaturally good as the boys in the books were; he knew that none of them had ever been able to stand it long, and it pained him to think that if they put him in a book he wouldn’t ever see it, or even if they did get the book out before he died, it wouldn’t be popular without any picture of his funeral in the back part of it. It couldn’t be much of a Sunday- school book that couldn’t tell about the advice he gave to the community when he was dying. So, at last, of course he had to make up his mind to do the best he could under the circumstances – to live right, and hang on as long as he could, and have his dying speech all ready when his time came.

But somehow, nothing ever went right with this good little boy; nothing ever turned out with him the way it turned out with the good little boys in the books. They always had a good time, and the bad boys had the broken legs; but in his case there was a screw loose somewhere, and it all happened just the other way. When he found Jim Blake stealing apples, and went under the tree to read to him about the bad little boy who fell out of a neighbour’s apple tree, and broke his arm, Jim fell out of the tree too, but he fell on him, and broke his arm, and Jim wasn’t hurt at all. Jacob couldn’t understand that. There wasn’t anything in the books like it.

And once, when some bad boys pushed a blind man over in the mud, and Jacob ran to help him up and receive his blessing, the blind man did not give him any blessing at all, but whacked him over the head with his stick and said he would like to catch him shoving him again and then pretending to help him up. This was not in accordance with any of the books. Jacob looked them all over to see.

One thing that Jacob wanted to do was to find a lame dog that hadn’t any place to stay, and was hungry and persecuted, and bring him home and pet him and have that dog’s imperishable gratitude. And at last he found one, and was happy; and he brought him home and fed him, but when he was going to pet him the dog flew at him and tore all the clothes off him except those that were in front, and made a spectacle of him that was astonishing. He examined authorities, but he could not understand the matter. It was of the same breed of dogs that was in the books, but it acted very differently. Whatever this boy did, he got into trouble. The very things the boys in the books got rewarded for turned out to be about the most unprofitable things he could invest in.

Once when he was on his way to Sunday- school he saw some bad boys starting off pleasuring in a sailboat. He was filled with consternation, because he knew from his teaching that boys who went sailing on Sunday invariably got drowned. So he ran out on a raft to warn them, but a log turned with him and slid him into the river. A man got him out pretty soon, and the doctor pumped the water out of him and gave him a fresh start with his bellows, but he caught cold and lay sick abed nine weeks. But the most unaccountable thing about it was that the bad boys in the boat had a good time all day, and then reached home alive and well, in the most surprising manner. Jacob Blivens said there was nothing like these things in the books. He was perfectly dumbfounded.

When he got well he was a little discouraged, but he resolved to keep on trying, anyhow. He knew that so far his experiences wouldn’t do to go in a book, but he hadn’t yet reached the allotted term of life for good little boys, and he hoped to be able to make a record yet, if he could hold on till his time was fully up. If everything else failed, he had his dying speech to fall back on.

He examined his authorities, and found that it was now time for him to go to sea as a cabin boy. He called on a ship captain and made his application, and when the captain asked for his recommendations he proudly drew out a tract and pointed to the words: ‘To Jacob Blivens, from his affectionate teacher.’ But the captain was a coarse, vulgar man, and he said, ‘Oh, that be blowed!’That wasn’t any proof that he knew how to wash dishes or handle a slush- bucket, and he guessed he didn’t want him. This was altogether the most extraordinary thing that ever had happened to Jacob in all his life. A compliment from a teacher, on a tract, had never failed to move the tenderest of emotions of ship captains and open the way to all offices of honour and profit in their gift – it never had in any book that ever he had read. He could hardly believe his senses.

This boy always had a hard time of it. Nothing ever came out according to the authorities with him. At last, one day, when he was around hunting up bad little boys to admonish, he found a lot of them in the old iron foundry fixing up a little joke on fourteen or fifteen dogs, which they had tied together in long procession and were going to ornament with empty nitroglycerine cans made fast to their tails. Jacob’s heart was touched. He sat down on one of those cans – for he never minded grease when duty was before him – and he took hold of the foremost dog by the collar, and turned his reproving eye upon wicked Tom Jones. But just at that moment Alderman McWelter, full of wrath, stepped in. All the bad boys ran away; but Jacob Blivens rose in conscious innocence and began one of those stately little Sunday- school- book speeches which always commence with ‘Oh, Sir!’ in dead opposition to the fact that no boy, good or bad, ever starts a remark with‘Oh, Sir!’ But the Alderman never waited to hear the rest. He took Jacob Blivens by the ear and turned him around, and hit him a whack in the rear with the flat of his hand; and in an instant that good little boy shot out through the roof and soared away toward the sun, with the fragments of those fifteen dogs stringing after him like the tail of a kite. And there wasn’t a sign of that Alderman or that old iron foundry left on the face of the earth; and as for young Jacob Blivens, he never got a chance to make his last dying speech after all his trouble fixing it up, unless he made it to the birds; because, although the bulk of him came down all right in a treetop in an adjoining county, the rest of him was apportioned around among four townships, and so they had to hold five inquests on him to find out whether he was dead or not, and how it occurred. You never saw a boy scattered so.

Thus perished the good little boy who did the best he could, but didn’t come out according to the books. Every boy who ever did as he did prospered, except him. His case is truly remarkable. It will probably never be accounted for.

新兵

他们发现，有些时候，借助某个想法或举动，他可以在时间与距离两种模式中废除空间，一种是思想的，另一种是物理的。

——《路易·朗贝尔的思想史》

1793年11月的一个晚上，卡朗唐镇的重要人士都聚集在戴伊夫人家的客厅，集会每天在这里进行。有些事情，在大城市不会引起一丁点的注意，但是，在小城镇却会牵动所有人的神经。这种常规性的集会在小地方就格外引人注目。两天前，戴伊夫人以身体不适为由，闭门谢客，前一天也没有接待任何人。普普通通的日子里，这两件事情在卡朗唐产生的影响，堪比巴黎所有的剧院关门停演。这样的生活好像是不完整的。然而，在1793年，戴伊夫人的举动无疑会招来最致命的后果。对于贵族来说，即便是很小的冒险举动，都可能变成关乎生存与死亡的问题。这一晚，诺曼底人的脸上挂着强烈的好奇和高度的敏感，为了清楚了解诺曼底人的反应，尤其是戴伊夫人内心的挣扎，有必要解释一下她在卡朗唐扮演的角色。她此刻的危险处境，许多人在革命期间也经历过。此外，读者的怜悯之心也会使这个故事更加有声有色。

戴伊夫人，是个寡妇，在贵族流亡时期离开了宫廷，她已故的丈夫是一位中将，曾获骑士勋章。她在卡朗唐一带拥有大量财产，避难于此，期许躲避恐怖浪潮的影响。基于对小镇的充分了解，她的预期十分准确。革命没有对下诺曼底地区带来大面积的破坏。尽管从前戴伊夫人只是在巡视自己的地产时与当地的贵族有过几面之缘，但是，现在她决计向当地的大资本家和新权威人士敞开家门，努力让他们因能和自己攀上关系而感到沾沾自喜，又不引起仇恨和嫉妒。优雅、和善，骨子带着不可言喻的温柔，她不必奴颜婢膝，也无须求天告地，便可以轻松取悦他人。借助巧妙的策略，她成功赢得了广泛的尊重。机敏的性格使得她在微妙之处也游刃有余，满足不同社会阶级要求的同时，既不伤害倔强的新贵的自尊心，也不冒犯老朋友。

不同于下诺曼底女子的光鲜、丰满的美，三十八岁的她有着纤弱的美，或者说贵族的高雅。外貌俊美、端庄；体态轻盈、纤细。说起话来，苍白的脸色就会变得光彩照人，充满活力。黑色的大眼睛散发着和蔼与亲切，平静与虔诚的眼神又仿佛在昭示，她的人生已经由不得她了。在如花的年纪嫁给了一个年老又多疑的军人。丈夫在风流宫廷中有名无实的地位在她脸上罩上了深沉的忧郁。曾经这张脸上肯定也焕发过迷人的魅力和爱情的活力。她不得不始终压抑女人的天真与任性，尽管依旧感受得到，只是不去想，总之，在她心底埋藏着少女的激情。其实她的魅力源于这种内在的青春。只是，有时候内在的青春会在神情上出卖她，让人觉得是内心欲望的天真表达。她的眼神使人生敬，举止言谈中却总是夹杂着少女对未知的将来的渴望与冲动；很快，再不敏感的男人也会爱上她，尽管如此，迫于她端庄的举止，也只能敬而远之。她的心灵生而高贵，又因经历多番残酷斗争的磨砺，超乎众人，连男人都自叹不如。这般性格势必内含某种强大的激情。戴伊夫人的爱都集中一处——母爱。嫁为人妻，她在对儿子过分的疼爱中找回被生活剥夺的幸福与快乐。她不仅仅以纯洁、无私的母爱去爱他，还带着情人的妩媚，妻子的嫉妒。儿子不在眼前时，她就感到难过。儿子不在家时，她就坐立不安。永远也看不够，她只因儿子活着，也只为他活着。为了让大家体会这种情感的力量，只需要略做一点补充，这孩子不单单是戴伊夫人唯一的儿子，也是她在世上唯一的亲人，她唯一可以寄托人生的忧虑、期望、快乐的人。已故的丈夫戴伊伯爵是家族最后的香火，她也是自己家族最后的继承人。人世利益的盘算和人心灵深处最崇高的渴望相并而行，使得在女人身上本来就很强烈的情感，在伯爵夫人心里越燃越烈。她对儿子百般呵护，养儿的艰辛也使得孩子对她来说更加宝贵；医生不止一次预言，她可能会失去他，但是，她只相信自己的直觉，从不灰心。不管医生怎么说，她还是幸福地陪着儿子闯过童年的难关，看他身体日益强壮，有种不可名状的开心。

多亏她持续不断的照料，孩子日渐长大，长成风度优雅的小伙子。二十岁的时候，就已经是凡尔赛镇最出色的骑兵之一。诚然，不是所有母亲的付出都会得到回报，但是戴伊夫人很幸运，她的儿子非常爱她；他们心灵共通，情同挚友。即便没有血缘关系，他们也一定可以像兄弟一样相互感知，这种友谊在生活中是十分罕见的。十八岁时，这位年轻的伯爵被任命为龙骑兵团少尉，依当时的处境，为了捍卫荣誉，不得不跟随贵族流亡。

戴伊夫人，高贵、富有，作为流亡贵族的母亲，不可能对自己严峻的处境视而不见。除了给儿子保留一笔丰厚的财产，别无他求。她放弃了与他一同流亡的幸福。当读到那些严苛的法条，得知共和派每天都依照它们没收卡朗唐流亡贵族的家产时，她为自己大胆的举动拍手叫好。难道她不是冒着生命危险来守护儿子的财富吗？后来，听说国民议会判决残忍的死刑时，她确认自己唯一的宝贝安好，远离危险、远离断头台，便安心地睡了。她快乐地认为自己做出了最明智的选择，可以同时保全所有的财产。保守着自己心中的秘密，对不幸的年代做出所有必需的妥协，为了不损害女人的尊严和牺牲贵族的信念，她把自己的痛苦包裹在冷酷的神秘中。在卡朗唐等待她的重重困难，她早已了然于心。在这里占居首户，岂不是每天都有被推上断头台的可能？可是，被作为母亲所拥有的勇气支撑，她知道如何平等对待穷人，减轻他们的痛苦，以赢得拥护；她也知道如何保护富人的财产，取悦他们，让自己变得不可或缺。她接待市镇检察官、镇长、地方法院庭长、公诉人，甚至革命法庭的法官。这群人中，前面四位都未婚，百般献殷勤，想要娶她为妻。为了得到她，他们不是恐吓她，自己可以给她带来多少麻烦，就是告诉她，自己可以向她提供怎样的庇护。这位公诉人是卡昂的前任律师，从前负责照管伯爵夫人的财产利益，试图以忠心与慷慨，博得她的爱情。危险的手段！他是所有追求者中，最可怕的一位。他也是唯一对伯爵夫人巨额财产状况了如指掌的人，因为她曾经是他的客户。仗着拥有巨大的权力，可以说是这个地区的生杀大权，他的贪婪与日俱增。这个男人，尚年轻，举止如此高贵优雅，以至于戴伊夫人无法辨清他的为人。然而，无视与诺曼底人明争暗斗的危险，她运用女人天生的才智和狡黠，使情敌之间相互牵制。竭力争取时间，她希望可以安然无损地度过混乱期。当时，国内保皇主义分子每天自信地认为革命结束指日可待，而这一执念断送了他们其中很多人的性命。

尽管困难重重，戴伊夫人还是很巧妙地保持着自身的独立，直到这一天，以一种令人费解的轻率，她毫无顾忌地关上了家门。她的反常举动勾起了大家浓厚、真切的兴趣。当晚来访的客人得知伯爵夫人无法接待他们的时候，表现出强烈的不安。再者，出于当地人特有的、赤裸裸的好奇，他们打探戴伊夫人是遭遇了不幸，遇到了烦心事，还是得了重病。名叫布丽吉特的老管家解答了大家的疑惑。她说，夫人把自己关在房间里，谁也不想见，甚至家仆。生活在修道院似的小镇，人们养成了分析和解释他人行为举止的习惯。自然，在对戴伊夫人略表同情之后，不知道她到底是高兴还是悲伤，每个人都开始搜寻她突然闭门谢客的原因。

“如果她生病了，她应该打发人去找医生，”第一个好奇者揣测道，“但是医生今天一天都在我家下棋。他笑着对我说，现今只有一种病……并且这种病无药可救。”

他小心翼翼地抛出这个笑话。于是，女人、男人，老人和年轻的女孩开始了形形色色的猜测。每个人都觉得自己瞥见了一个秘密，这个秘密充满了大胆的想象。第二天，他们的猜疑持续加重。一如小镇的生活很难掩人耳目，女人们首先察觉到布丽吉特采购的食物比往常要多得多。这一点无可争议。一大早，就有人在集市上看见了老管家，不同往常的是，她买了市场上唯一的野兔。小镇上的人都知道，戴伊夫人不喜欢吃野味。野兔也就成了种种猜疑的出发点。与平常一样，老人们出来散散步，他们察觉伯爵夫人家里可能正在进行某种秘密集会，家仆的谨小慎微和遮遮掩掩可以提供佐证。仆人在花园里拍打地毯，要是在前一天，没有人会注意这件事情，可是现在，这张地毯成了故事的线索，大家都借此发挥。每个人都有自己的版本。第二天，听说戴伊夫人自称身体不适，当晚，卡朗唐所有的大人物聚集在镇长的兄弟家。他是一位已婚的老商人，为人正直，受人敬重，连戴伊夫人都很尊重他。聚会中，这位富有孀妇的追求者们都讲出了自己大大小小的猜测；每个人都想让此次迫使她名誉受损的神秘事件对自己有利。公诉人编了一整出戏，故事的结局是戴伊夫人的儿子连夜赶回了家中。镇长认为是有一位旺代的反抗派教士，逃亡于此，请求庇护。但是，这天是周五，买野兔的事情让镇长觉得很尴尬。地方法院庭长则坚信她收留的是被严密追捕的朱安党人或西部保皇党人的某个头目。其他人觉得她收留的是一个从巴黎监狱逃脱的贵族。总之，大家都怀疑伯爵夫人做出了一个大胆的举动，而这一举动依照当时的法律是重罪，足以把她送上断头台。公诉人小声说，大家最好保守这个秘密，尽力去拯救这个大步迈向深渊的不幸女人。

“如果你们散播这件事，”他补充道，“我就不得不介入，去搜查她的家，这样的话……”他没有把话说完，但是大家都明白他的意思。

伯爵夫人的挚友都十分担心她，以至于第三天的一大早，镇行政长官让他的妻子给她写信，鼓励她当晚像往常一样接待客人。更果断的是老商人，这天早上，他直接去了戴伊夫人家。他决心伸出援手，执意要见她，不过令他感到吃惊的是，当他看到戴伊夫人时，她正忙着在小花园里摘花，准备把它们插在花瓶里。

“她肯定在庇护她的情人。”老商人自言自语道，突然十分同情这个迷人的女人。伯爵夫人反常的神情证实了他的猜疑。老商人被女人天生的献身精神深深打动了，因为男人都会因女人甘心为他们牺牲而感到欣喜。老商人告诉了戴伊夫人镇上关于她的流言，以及她危险的处境。

“因为，”他最后说道，“尽管有些公职人员会欣然宽恕保护神父的英勇行为，但是没有人会同情您，如果他们发现您是为爱献身。”

听了这一席话，戴伊夫人用疑惑又疯狂的眼神盯着老商人，看得他瑟瑟发抖。

“跟我来。”她一边说一边拉着他的手往卧室走。确定只有他们两个人的时候，她从胸口掏出一封脏兮兮、皱巴巴的信。“读。”她使出全身的力气从牙缝里挤出这个字。

她瘫在扶手椅上，像丢了魂。老商人掏出眼镜擦拭时，她抬起头来，第一次用好奇的目光打量着他。她有点变腔，轻声对他说：“我十分信任您。”

“我不是来分担您的罪行了吗？”这位老好人直率地回答道。

她浑身战栗。在这个小镇上，她第一次感到自己的灵魂与另一个灵魂相契合。老商人一下子就明白了伯爵夫人的沮丧与欢乐。她的儿子参加了格朗维勒远征，被捕，这封信是儿子在狱中写给她的。这封信给她带来的可能是喜讯，也可能是噩耗。儿子在信中说，对自己的越狱计划很有把握，这三天，他会乔装打扮回到家中。这封致命的信也预示着，如果他第三天晚上没有出现，等待伯爵夫人的将是撕心裂肺的永别。他恳请母亲给冒生命危险捎信的人一大笔钱。老商人拿着信的手不听使唤地颤抖。

“已经是第三天了！”戴伊夫人吼道，她迅速站起来，抢过信，焦急地在房间里走来走去。

“您之前太不小心了，”老商人说道，“为什么让女管家买那些食物？”

“他回来的时候可能饿得要死，累得要命，还有……”她说不下去了。

“我还是很了解我弟弟的，”老商人接过话来，“我这就去说服他站在您这边。”

在这个事情上，老商人重新找回了自己从前在生意场上的机敏，给戴伊夫人出了很谨慎又很有远见的主意。在商量妥当他们各自该说和该做的事情以后，老商人利用各种巧妙的理由，去走访卡朗唐所有的大人物，通知他们，尽管戴伊夫人身体抱恙，今晚还是会在家中接待他们。机智地与诺曼底人周旋，巧妙地回答了大家对伯爵夫人病情的询问，他成功瞒过了所有关心此神秘事件的人。他的初次走访可谓十分成功。他跟一个患痛风的老妇人说，戴伊夫人急性痛风发作，差点要了她的命。从前发生类似状况的时候，著名的特罗尚医生给她开过一个方子。在胸口上贴一张新鲜的兔皮，卧床静养。幸好及时用了这个神奇的偏方，这两天戴伊夫人才脱离生命危险。目前已经痊愈，今晚可以接待来访的客人。故事取得了惊人的效果。这位卡朗唐的医生是一位秘密保皇党人。他进一步解释了药方的原理，借助自己的声望加强了故事的影响力。尽管如此，种种猜疑已经深深扎根在一些顽固分子和理性主义者的心里，不可能一下完全消除。这天晚上，客人早早来到戴伊夫人家中，其中一些人来窥探她的脸色，另一些是出于友谊，大部分人都被她奇迹般的康复吸引而来。他们看见伯爵夫人坐在客厅的壁炉旁。戴伊夫人家的客厅和卡朗唐人家的装修一样简朴。为了不伤害来访客人的狭隘胸襟，她放弃了从前奢华的生活，房间还都是老样子，甚至接待室的地砖都没打磨。她还留着墙上灰暗的旧挂毯，具有乡村特色的家具，点起了蜡烛。入乡随俗，在吝啬与拮据的生活面前，她没有退缩。但是她知道，她的客人会原谅她的奢华，如果是对他们有益的话。她从来不会忽略任何一个能够取悦客人的细节，比如给他们提供丰盛的晚餐。她甚至假装吝啬去迎合爱算计的人。她佯装在奢华面前做出让步，她懂得优雅地服从。所以，这天晚上七点左右，卡朗唐最优秀也是最糟糕的小集团就已经聚集在戴伊夫人家中，围坐在壁炉旁。在老商人同情、关切的目光的支持下，房间的女主人带着难以想象的勇气，应付着客人琐碎的问题、无聊愚蠢的争论。但是，每当有人敲门，或者听到路上有脚步回声时，她便会问一些关乎小镇利益的问题，以掩盖自己的不安。她引发了大家对苹果酒的热议，在老商人的积极应和下，大家似乎已经忘了去窥探她的神情，觉得她举止得体，落落大方。公诉人和其中一位革命法庭的法官则沉默不语，仔细观察着戴伊夫人面部表情的细微变化，尽管房间里十分嘈杂，他们还是静下心来仔细地听。他们多次提出了使她很尴尬的问题，但是，她都灵活应对了。这是母亲才有的勇气啊！戴伊夫人组织了牌局，大家分别围坐在牌桌前，玩波士顿、翻转棋、惠斯特牌。她自己依旧和几个年轻人攀谈，十分悠然自得，像极了老练的演员。戴伊夫人提议玩罗多游戏，假称只有自己知道游戏用具在哪儿，然后就消失了。

“亲爱的布丽吉特，我快要被闷死了。”她一边喊叫，一边擦着喷涌而出的泪水，泪光闪烁的双眸里充满了躁动、痛苦和焦虑。“他还没有来。”她接着说道，爬上楼梯，看了看卧室，“在这里，我呼吸和生存。再过几分钟，他就会来的，无论如何！因为他还活着，我确定他还活着。我的心这么对我说的。你什么也没听到吗，布丽吉特？老天爷，我愿意用我的余生作为交换，只为知道他在监狱中，还是正走在乡间的路上！我忍不住去想！”

她又一次检查房间是否布置妥当。壁炉里火烧得正旺。百叶窗关得严严实实。家具也擦得锃亮。从床铺的细节也可看出所有的东西都是她和布丽吉特一起准备的。她的期待体现在每一个精心的小细节，房间的花香里，飘荡着甜蜜的温柔和最纯洁的爱。只有母亲可以预知一个士兵的渴望，并完完全全地满足他。可口的菜肴，精心挑选的酒，鞋子，换洗衣物，总之，一个劳累的旅行者归家所需要的一切都准备好了，什么也不缺。一个母亲的爱尽现眼前。

“布丽吉特？”她用让人心碎的嗓音叫了她一声，她正把椅子挪到桌子前，仿佛她的梦想就要成真，又仿佛在加强自己的幻想。

“会的！夫人，他肯定会回来的。他肯定不远了。我保证他肯定活着，正在回来的路上。”布丽吉特回应道，“我在《圣经》里放了一把钥匙，珂丹读《约翰福音》的时候，我把钥匙捧在手上。夫人，您知道吗？钥匙没有转动。”

“这可信吗？”伯爵夫人问道。

“当然了，夫人，很灵验的。我以我的灵魂得救向您担保，他还活着。上帝从不欺人。”

“尽管在这里等待他的是危险，我还是十分想见他。”

“可怜的奥古斯特先生，”布丽吉特哭喊道，“他肯定是靠双脚走回来的。”

“八点的钟已经敲响了！”伯爵夫人惊恐地叫道。

她担心自己在房间里待太久了，她本不应该来的。看着房间里的一切，她相信儿子还活着。她下了楼。在走进客厅之前，她在楼梯的廊柱旁停留了片刻，听听寂静的小城里是否有回声。她对守在门口的布丽吉特的丈夫笑了笑。他因为长时间集中精力听外面的动静，目光显得有些呆滞。她无论看什么，都能看见儿子的影子。她迅速回到客厅，假装一副很开心的样子，和小姑娘们一起玩罗多游戏。玩的过程中，她时不时说自己有点不舒服，就又回到了壁炉旁边的扶手椅上休息。这就是当时戴伊夫人家的活动情况和大家的精神状态。

与此同时，一个身着褐色卡马尼奥拉服的年轻人——那个年代十分典型的着装——正在从巴黎到瑟堡的路上，赶往卡朗唐。刚开始征兵的时候，没有什么规章纪律。当时需求紧急，共和派没有时间给士兵提供装备，在路上碰到穿着平民便服的新兵，也不稀奇。这些年轻人，有人走在队伍的前面，有人拖在队伍的后面，他们前进的步伐主要取决于他们承受劳累的长途跋涉的方式。大家关心的“旅行者”，正走在向瑟堡进发的特遣部队前面。卡朗唐的镇长已经等了他们好几小时，想要给他们分发士兵借宿证。这位年轻人的脚步沉重又坚定，仿佛在宣示，他早已习惯了粗野的军旅生活。尽管皎洁的月光洒满卡朗唐周围丛生的杂草，他早已注意到云层积得很厚，仿佛要下雪了。害怕被暴风围困，他加快了脚步，顾不上劳累。他背上背着一个差不多空了的包，手里拿着黄杨手杖，是从高大的树篱上砍下来的，这种形状的灌木在下诺曼底地区十分常见。孤独的旅行者一走进卡朗唐，就看见沐浴在冷寂的月光中的楼塔。他的脚步声回荡在寂静无人的街上。他不得不向一个还在工作的纺织工打听镇长的住处。镇长家并不远，他很快就走到他家门廊下，申请了士兵借宿证，坐在石椅上等待。但是，他却被叫到镇长跟前，被从头到脚，仔细打量了一番。这个新兵风度翩翩，不像是一般人家的孩子，神情透露出贵族的气质，脸上的智慧也暗示着他曾经接受过良好的教育。

“你叫什么名字？”镇长一边问，一边向他投去耐人寻味的目光。

“于连·朱西厄。”新兵回答道。

“你从哪里来？”他接着问，嘴角露出一丝狐疑的微笑。

“巴黎。”

“你的战友应该离这里还有一段距离吧？”他操着诺曼底人嘲讽的口吻继续问道。

“我比大部队快十二公里。”

“一定有什么特殊的情感吸引你来到卡朗唐吧，新兵？”镇长狡猾地问道。“这样也好，”他摆手止住了将要开口讲话的年轻人，“我知道该把你送到哪里了。拿着，这是你的士兵借宿证明，走吧，公民朱西厄！”

镇长在说“公民”二字时，带着一股嘲讽的意味。借宿证上有戴伊夫人提前安排好的住处。年轻人好奇地看着地址。

“他知道他不用走太远。他出门后，要穿过广场！”年轻人离开时，镇长自己吼道，“他可真是胆大！愿上帝带领他！看来他早就想好了如何应对一切。但是，如果不是我，而是其他人要求看他的证件，他就完蛋了！”

就在这时，卡朗唐九点半的钟声响起。戴伊夫人家前厅的风灯点着了，家仆帮他们的女主人和男主人们穿好鞋子，披上外套或者斗篷。打牌的人算清账目。按照小城当地的风俗，大家一起离开。

“公诉人好像不想离开。”一位夫人说道。他们在广场上相互道别，准备各自归家时，她发现这位重要的人物不在。

事实上，这位可怕的公诉人正和伯爵夫人单独待在一起。她浑身颤抖，期待他赶紧离开。

“女公民，”在漫长、恐怖的沉寂后，他终于开了口，“我在这里是为了看看共和国的法律是如何执行的……”

戴伊夫人打了个寒战。

“您没有什么想对我说的吗？”他问道。

“没有。”她吃惊地答道。

“啊！夫人！”他一边喊一边坐在她旁边，换了另外一种口吻，继续说，“这个节骨眼上，说错一个字，你、我都有可能被送上断头台。我观察您的性格、您的精神状况、您的行为举止很久了，才不会被您今晚演的这出戏欺骗。您在等您的儿子，我确信无疑。”

伯爵夫人摆手否认。尽管她已经面色苍白，为了显示自己的坚定，依旧紧绷着脸上的肌肉。她所有的举动都没有逃脱公诉人犀利的目光。

“那么，就接他回家吧，”这位革命的官员接着说道，“但是他最迟只能在家里待到明天早上七点。明天，天一亮，我就会带着一封起草好的告发信登门……”

她惊愕地看着他，神情足以使老虎心生怜悯。

他又用温柔的口气继续说：“我会用细致的搜查证实这封告发信是无稽之谈。有了我的报告，今后您就可以彻底摆脱大家的猜疑。我会高谈您的爱国情操，您的公民责任感，不会有任何闪失。”

戴伊夫人害怕这是一个陷阱，她一动不动，但是她的脸已经憋得通红，舌头也僵住了。突然传来了敲门声……

“天哪！”这个母亲惊恐地叫道，瘫在了地上，“救救他吧，救救他吧！”

“没有问题，我会救他的！”公诉人充满激情地答道，“就算搭上我们的性命，也要保全他。”

“我要死了！”她叫道。公诉人礼貌地扶她起来。

“夫人，”他摆出演说家的架势说，“我不想您有任何的亏欠，包括您自己。”

“夫人，他……”布丽吉特惊呼，她原本以为只有女主人一个人在家。

看见公诉人的瞬间，兴奋、开心的老仆人愣住了，吓得脸色苍白。

“谁来了，布丽吉特？”他温和、优雅地问道。

“一个新兵，镇长让他暂住这里。”仆人答道，顺手递出了士兵借宿证。

“的确，”公诉人看了证明之后说，“今天会有一个部队抵达卡朗唐！”

他离开了。

伯爵夫人此刻需要百分之百信任她的前任律师，容不得半点怀疑。尽管已经没有站立的力气，她还是迅速爬上楼。打开门，看见儿子，跌进他的怀里：“哦！我的孩子，我的孩子！”她抽泣着叫道，疯狂地亲吻他。

“夫人。”陌生人说道。

“天哪！这不是他！”她向后跌了几步，在新兵面前站定，用惊恐的目光盯着他。

“老天爷，怎么会长得如此相像！”布丽吉特惊叹道。

一瞬间，大家陷入了沉寂。年轻人看着戴伊夫人的神情紧张得发抖。

“先生，”她说，靠着布丽吉特的丈夫，痛苦侵袭了她全身，这第一次打击就足以要了她的命，“抱歉，我不能继续待在这里陪您了，如果您不介意的话，让我的家仆来服侍您。”

她被布丽吉特和她的丈夫扶下楼梯。

“怎么会这样，夫人？”老女仆一边安顿女主人，一边叫道，“这个男人竟然要睡在奥古斯特先生的床上，穿奥古斯特先生的拖鞋，吃我精心为奥古斯特先生准备的馅饼！我要是被推上断头台，我……”

“布丽吉特！”戴伊夫人吼道。

老仆人默不作声。

“闭嘴，你这个话痨，”她的丈夫小声说，“难道你想害死夫人吗？”

就在这时，新兵的房间里传出来一些动静，他准备吃饭了。

“我不能待在这里了，”戴伊夫人喊道，“我要去花房，在那里，夜间更方便听外面的声音。”

她在失去儿子的恐惧和重逢的希望之间挣扎。夜，一片可怕的死寂。当新兵大部队到达卡朗唐，每个人都找到自己的住处时，对于伯爵夫人来说，是可怕的时刻。每个脚步，每个动静都会激起她的希望，但紧跟而来的安静，又会让希望变成泡影。

清晨，伯爵夫人不得不回她自己的房间。布丽吉特留心主人的一举一动，看她没有出来，就走进房间，发现夫人已经死了。

“她肯定听见了新兵穿好衣服后，在奥古斯特先生的房间里走来走去，唱那首该死的《马赛曲》，像在马槽里一样，”布丽吉特哭喊道，“这足以要了她的命！”

导致伯爵夫人死亡的痛苦远比这个要沉重得多，很可能是可怕的幻象。戴伊夫人在卡朗唐逝世的那一刻，她的儿子在莫尔比昂被枪决了。我们可以将这出悲剧纳入所有超越法律空间，关乎同情的观察里。孤独的人们带着好奇收集的资料，有一天会成为一门新兴科学的基础，只是今天，这个天才还没有出现。

1831年2月于巴黎

（陈爽 译）

The Atheist’s Mass

A doctor to whom science owes a fine physiological theory and who, while still young, achieved a place amongst the celebrities of the Paris school of medicine(that centre of enlightenment to which all the doctors of Europe pay homage), Doctor Bianchon, practised surgery for a long time before devoting himself to medicine. His early studies were directed by one of the greatest of French surgeons, by the celebrated Desplein who passed through the world of science like a meteor. Even his enemies admit that he took with him to the grave a method that could not be handed on to others. Like all men of genius he had no heirs; he carried his skill within him and he carried it away with him. A surgeon’s fame is like an actor’s. It exists only so long as he is alive and his talent can no longer be appreciated once he has gone. Actors and surgeons, great singers too, and virtuoso musicians who by their playing increase tenfold the power of music, are all heroes of the moment. Desplein’s life is a proof of the resemblance between the destinies of these transitory geniuses. His name which was so famous yesterday is almost forgotten today. It will remain only in his own field without going beyond it. But extraordinary conditions are surely necessary for the name of a scholar to pass from the domain of Science into the general history of humanity. Did Desplein have that width of knowledge which makes a man the mouthpiece or the representative of an age? Desplein possessed a god- like glance; he understood the patient and his disease by means of a natural or acquired intuition which allowed him to appreciate the diagnosis appropriate to the individual, to decide the precise moment, the hour, the minute at which he should operate, taking into account atmospheric conditions and temperamental peculiarities. To be able to collaborate with Nature in this way, had he then studied the endless combination of beings and elemental substances contained in the atmosphere or provided by the earth for man, who absorbs them and uses them for a particular purpose? Did he use that power of deduction and analogy to which Cuvier owes his genius? However that may be, this man understood the secrets of the flesh; he understood its past as well as its future, by studying the present. But did he contain all science in his person as did Hippocrates, Galen, Aristotle? Did he lead a whole school towards new worlds? No. If it is impossible to refuse to this constant observer of human chemistry the ancient science of Magism, that is to say, the knowledge of the elements in fusion, of the causes of life, of life before life, of what it will be, judging from its antecedents before it exists, all this unfortunately was personal to him. In his life he was isolated by egoism, and today that egoism is the death of his fame. Over his tomb there is no statue proclaiming to the future, in ringing tones, the mysteries which Genius seeks out at its own expense. But perhaps Desplein’s talent was in keeping with his beliefs, and consequently mortal. For him the terrestrial atmosphere was like a generative bag; he saw the earth as if it were an egg in its shell, and unable to know whether the egg or the hen came first, he denied both the fowl and the egg. He believed neither in the animal anterior to man nor in the spirit beyond him. Desplein was not in doubt, he affirmed his opinion. He was like many other scholars in his frank, unmixed atheism. They are the best people in the world but incorrigible atheists, atheists such as religious people don’t believe exist. It was hardly possible for such a man to hold a different opinion, for from his youth he was used to dissecting the living being par excellence, before, during and after life, and to examining all its functions without finding the unique soul that is indispensable to religious theories. Desplein recognized a cerebral centre, a nervous centre and a circulatory centre, of which the first two do duty for each other so well that at the end of his life he was convinced that the sense of hearing was not absolutely necessary to hear, nor the sense of sight absolutely necessary to see, and that the solar plexus could replace them without anyone noticing it. He thus found two souls in man and this fact confirmed his atheism, although it still tells us nothing about God. He died, they say, impenitent to the last, as unfortunately do many fine geniuses. May God forgive them!

This really great man’s life exhibited many pettinesses, to use the expression of his enemies who in their jealousy wanted to diminish his fame, but it would be more appropriate to call them apparent contradictions. Envious or stupid people who do not know the reasons which explain the activities of superior minds immediately take advantage of a few superficial contradictions to make accusations on which they obtain a momentary judgement. If, later on, the plans which have been attacked are crowned with success, when the preparations are correlated with the results, some of the calumnies which were made beforehand remain. Thus, in our own time, Napoleon was condemned by our contemporaries when he spread out the wings of his eagle over England: but we needed the events of 1822 to explain 1804 and the flat- bottomed boats at Boulogne.[1]

Since Desplein’s fame and scientific knowledge were unassailable, his enemies attacked his strange disposition and his character, while in fact he was simply what the English call eccentric. At times he dressed magnificently like the tragedian Crébillon, at times he seemed unusually indifferent to clothes. Sometimes he was to be seen in a carriage, sometimes on foot. He was now sharp- tempered, now kind, apparently hard and stingy, yet capable of offering his fortune to his exiled rulers who honoured him by accepting it for a few days. No man has inspired more contradictory judgements. Although, to obtain the Order of Saint Michael (which doctors are not supposed to solicit), he was capable of dropping a Book of Hours from his pocket at Court, you can be sure that inwardly he laughed at the whole thing. He had a profound contempt for mankind, having studied them from above and from below, having surprised them without pretence, as they performed the most solemn as well as the pettiest acts of life. A great man’s gifts often hang together. If one of these giants has more talent than wit, his wit is still greater than that of a man of whom one says simply, ‘He is witty.’ All genius presupposes moral insight. This insight may be applied to some speciality, but he who sees the flower must see the sun. The doctor who heard a diplomat whose life he had saved ask, ‘How is the Emperor?’, and who replied, ‘The courtier is coming back to life, the man will follow!’ was not only a surgeon or a physician, he was also extremely witty. Thus the close and patient observer of humanity will justify Desplein’s exorbitant pretensions and will realize, as he himself realized, that he was capable of being as great a minister as he was a surgeon.

Among the riddles which Desplein’s life reveals to his contemporaries we have chosen one of the most interesting, because the solution will be found at the end of this tale and will answer some of the foolish accusations which have been made against him.

Of all the pupils whom Desplein had at his hospital, Horace Bianchon was one of those to whom he became most warmly attached. Before doing his internship at the Hôtel Dieu,[2] Horace Bianchon was a medical student, living in a miserable boarding- house in the Latin Quarter, known by the name of La Maison Vauquer.[3] There this poor young man experienced that desperate poverty which is a kind of melting- pot whence great talents emerge pure and incorruptible, just as diamonds can be subjected to any kind of shock without breaking. In the violence of their unleashed passions, they acquire the most unshakeable honesty, and by dint of the constant labour with which they have contained their balked appetites, they become used to the struggles which are the lot of genius. Horace was an upright young man, incapable of double- dealing in affairs of honour, going straight to the point without fuss, as capable of pawning his coat for his friends as of giving them his time and his night’s rest. In short, Horace was one of those friends who are not worried about what they receive in exchange for what they give, certain as they are to receive in their turn more than they will give. Most of his friends had for him that inner respect which is inspired by unostentatious goodness, and several of them were afraid of his strictures. But Horace exercised these virtues without being prudish. He was neither a puritan nor a preacher; he swore quite readily when giving advice, and enjoyed a good meal in gay company when opportunity offered. He was good company, no more squeamish than a soldier, bluff and open, not like a sailor – for the sailor of today is a wily diplomatist – but like a fine young man who has nothing to hide in his life; he walked with his head high and his heart light. In a word, Horace was the Pylades of more than one Orestes, creditors being today the most real shape assumed by the ancient Furies. He wore his poverty with that gaiety which is perhaps one of the greatest elements of courage, and like all those who have nothing, he contracted few debts. Sober as a camel, brisk as a stag, he was unwavering both in his principles and in his behaviour. The happiness of Bianchon’s life began on the day when the famous surgeon obtained evidence of the good qualities and failings which, the one as much as the other, made Doctor Horace Bianchon doubly precious to his friends. When a clinical chief adopts a young man, that young man has, as they say, his foot in the stirrup. Desplein always took Bianchon with him to act as his assistant in well- to- do homes, where some reward would nearly always find its way into the student’s purse, and where little by little the mysteries of Parisian life were revealed to the young provincial. Desplein also kept him in his surgery during consultations and gave him work to do there. Sometimes he would send him to accompany a rich patient to a spa. In short, he was making a practice for him. The result of all this was that after a time the lord of surgery had a devoted slave. These two men, the one at the height of his fame and leader of his profession, enjoying an immense fortune and an immense reputation, the other, a modest Omega, having neither fortune nor fame, became intimate friends. The great Desplein told his assistant everything. He knew if a certain lady had sat down on a chair beside the master, or on the famous surgery couch where Desplein slept. Bianchon knew the mysteries of that temperament, both lion- like and bull- like, which in the end expanded and abnormally developed the great man’s chest and caused his death from enlargement of the heart. The student studied the eccentricities of Desplein’s very busy life, the plans made by his sordid avarice, the hopes of the politician concealed behind the scientist; he foresaw the disappointments in store for the only feeling hidden in that heart which was hardened rather than hard.

One day Bianchon told Desplein that a poor watercarrier from the Saint- Jacques quarter had a horrible illness caused by fatigue and poverty; this poor Auvergnat had eaten only potatoes during the severe winter of 1821. Desplein left all his patients. At the risk of working his horse to death, he rode as fast as he could, followed by Bianchon, to the poor man’s house and himself had him carried to the nursing- home founded by the famous Dubois in the Faubourg Saint- Denis. Desplein attended the man, and when he had cured him, gave him the money to buy a horse and a water- cart. This Auvergnat was remarkable for one original characteristic. One of his friends fell ill; he took him straight away to Desplein and said to his benefactor, ‘I would not have allowed him to go to another doctor.’ Surly as he was, Desplein grasped the water- carrier’s hand and said, ‘Bring them all to me.’And he had the peasant from the Cantal admitted to the Hôtel Dieu, where he took the greatest care of him. Bianchon had already noticed several times that his chief had a predilection for Auvergnats, and especially for water- carriers. But as Desplein had a kind of pride in his treatments at the Hôtel Dieu, his pupil didn’t see anything very strange in that.

One day, as Bianchon was crossing the Place Saint- Sulpice, he noticed his master going into the church about nine o’clock in the morning. Desplein, who at that period of his life never moved a step except by carriage, was on foot and slipping in by the door of the Rue du Petit- Lion, as if he had been going into a house of doubtful reputation. Bianchon’s curiosity was naturally aroused, since he knew his master’s opinions and that he was a‘devyl’ of a Cabanist[4] (devyl with a y, which in Rabelais seems to suggest a superiority in devilry). Slipping into Saint- Sulpice, he was not a little astonished to see the great Desplein, that atheist without pity for the angels, who cannot be subjected to the surgeon’s knife, who cannot have sinus or gastric trouble, that dauntless scoffer, kneeling humbly, and where? . . . in the chapel of the Virgin, where he listened to a Mass, paid for the cost of the service, gave alms for the poor, all as solemnly as if he had been performing an operation.

‘He certainly didn’t come to clear up questions about the Virgin birth,’ said Bianchon in boundless astonishment. ‘If I had seen him holding one of the tassels of the canopy on Corpus Christi day, I would have taken it as a joke; but at this hour, alone, with no one to see him, that certainly gives one food for thought!’

Bianchon did not want to look as if he was spying on the chief surgeon of the Hôtel Dieu and he went away. By chance Desplein invited him to dinner that very day, not at home but at a restaurant.

Between the fruit and the cheese, Bianchon managed skilfully to bring the conversation round to the subject of the Mass, calling it a masquerade and a farce.

‘A farce,’ said Desplein, ‘which has cost Christendom more blood than all Napoleon’s battles and all Broussais’leeches! The Mass is a papal invention which goes no further back than the sixth century and which is based on Hoc est corpus. What torrents of blood had to be spilt to establish Corpus Christi day! By the institution of this Feast the court of Rome intended to proclaim its victory in the matter of the Real Presence, a schism which troubled the Church for three centuries. The wars of the Counts of Toulouse and the Albigensians are the tail- end of this affair. The Vaudois and the Albigensians[5] refused to recognize this innovation.’

In short Desplein enjoyed himself, giving free rein to his atheistic wit, and pouring out a flood of Voltairean jokes, or, to be more precise, a horrible parody of the Citateur.[6]

‘Well,’ Bianchon said to himself, ‘where is the pious man I saw this morning?’

He said nothing; he had doubts whether he really had seen his chief at Saint- Sulpice. Desplein would not have bothered to lie to Bianchon. They both knew each other too well; they had already exchanged ideas on subjects which were just as serious, and they had discussed systems de natura rerum, probing or dissecting them with the knives and the scalpel of incredulity. Three months went by. Bianchon did not follow up the incident, although it remained stamped on his memory. One day in the course of that year, one of the doctors at the Hôtel Dieu took Desplein by the arm, in Bianchon’s presence, as if to ask him a question.

‘What were you going to do at Saint- Sulpice, my dear chief?’ he asked.

‘I went to see a priest who had a diseased knee. Madame la Duchesse d’Angoulême did me the honour of recommending me,’ said Desplein.

The doctor was satisfied with this excuse, but not so Bianchon.

‘Oh! So he goes to see bad knees in church! He was going to hear Mass,’ the student said to himself.

Bianchon determined to keep a watch on Desplein. He recalled the day and the time on which he had surprised him going in to Saint- Sulpice and he determined to go there the following year on the same day and at the same time, to find out if he would surprise him there again. If that happened, the regularity of his worship would justify a scientific investigation, for in such a man there should not be a direct contradiction between thought and deed. The following year, on the day and at the hour in question, Bianchon, who was by this time no longer Desplein’s assistant, saw the surgeon’s carriage stop at the corner of the Rue de Tournon and the Rue du Petit- Lion. From there his friend crept stealthily along by the walls of Saint- Sulpice where he again heard Mass at the altar of the Virgin. It was certainly Desplein, the chief surgeon, the atheist in petto, the pious man on occasion. The plot became more involved. The famous scientist’s persistence complicated everything. When Desplein had left the church, Bianchon went up to the sacristan who came to minister to the chapel, and asked him if the gentleman was a regular attendant.

‘I have been here for twenty years,’ said the sacristan,‘and for all that time Monsieur Desplein has been coming four times a year to hear this Mass; it was he who founded it.’

‘He founded it!’ said Bianchon as he walked away. ‘This is as much a mystery as the Immaculate Conception, which of itself must make a doctor an unbeliever.’

Although Dr Bianchon was a friend of Desplein’s, some time went by before he was in a position to speak to him about this strange circumstance of his life. If they met at a consultation or in society, it was difficult to find that moment of confidence and solitude when, with feet up on the fire- dogs and heads leaning against the backs of their chairs, two men tell each other their secrets. Finally, seven years later, after the 1830 Revolution, when the people stormed the Archbishopric, when, inspired by Republican sentiments, they destroyed the golden crosses which appeared, like flashes of lightning, in this vast sea of houses, when Disbelief and Violence swaggered together through the streets, Bianchon surprised Desplein going into Saint- Sulpice. The doctor followed him in and took a place near him without his friend making the least sign or showing the least surprise. Both of them heard the foundation Mass.

‘Will you tell me, my friend,’ Bianchon said to Desplein when they were outside the church, ‘the reason for this display of piety? I have already caught you three times going to Mass, you! You must tell me the reason for this mysterious activity, and explain to me the flagrant discrepancy between your opinions and your behaviour. You don’t believe in God, yet you go to Mass! My dear chief, you must answer me.’

‘I am like many pious men, men who appear to be profoundly religious but are quite as atheistic as we are, you and I.’

And he let forth a torrent of epigrams about political personalities of whom the best known provides us in this century with a new edition of Molière’s Tartuffe.

‘That’s not what I am talking about,’ said Bianchon. ‘I want to know the reason for what you have just been doing here. Why did you found this Mass?’

‘Well, my dear friend,’ said Desplein, ‘since I am on the brink of the grave, there is no reason why I shouldn’t speak to you about the beginning of my life.’

At this moment Bianchon and the great man happened to be in the Rue des Quatre- Vents, one of the most horrible streets in Paris. Desplein pointed to the sixth storey of one of those houses which are shaped like an obelisk and have a medium- sized door opening on to a passage. At the end of the passage is a spiral staircase lit by apertures called jours de souffrance. The house was a greenish colour; on the ground floor lived a furniture dealer; a different kind of poverty seemed to lodge on each floor. Raising his arm with an emphatic gesture, Desplein said to Bianchon, ‘I lived up there for two years.’

‘I know the place; d’Arthez lived there and I came here almost every day in my youth. At that time we called it the “jar of great men”! Well, what of it?’

‘The Mass that I have just heard is linked to events which took place at the time when I lived in the attic where, so you tell me, d’Arthez lived. It is the one where a line of washing is dangling at the window above a pot of flowers. I had such a difficult time to start with, my dear Bianchon, that I can dispute the palm of the sufferings of Paris with anyone. I have put up with everything, hunger, thirst, lack of money, lack of clothes, of footwear, of linen, everything that is hardest about poverty. I have blown on my numbed fingers in that “jar of great men”which I should like to visit again with you. I worked during one winter, when I could see my own head steaming and a cloud of my own breath rising like horses’breath on a frosty day. I don’t know what enables a man to stand up to such a life. I was alone, without help, without a farthing either to buy books or to pay the expenses of my medical education. I had no friends and my irritable, sensitive, restless temperament did me no good. No one could see that my bad temper was caused by the difficulties and the work of a man who, from his position at the bottom of the social ladder, was striving to reach the top. But I can tell you, you to whom I don’t need to pretend, that I had that basis of good feeling and keen sensitivity which will always be the prerogative of men who, after having been stuck for a long time in the slough of poverty, are strong enough to climb to any kind of summit. I could get nothing from my family or my home beyond the inadequate allowance they made me. In short, at this period of my life, all I had to eat in the mornings was a roll which the baker in the Rue du Petit- Lion sold me more cheaply because it was yesterday’s, or the day before yesterday’s. I crumbled it up into some milk and so my morning meal cost me only two sous. I dined only every other day at a boarding- house where dinner cost sixteen sous. In this way I spent only nine sous a day. You know as well as I do the care I had to take of my clothes and my footwear. I don’t think, later on in life, we are as much distressed by a colleague’s disloyalty as you and I were when we saw the mocking grin of a shoe that was becoming unsewn, or heard the armhole of a frock- coat split. I drank only water; I had the greatest respect for cafés. Zoppi’s seemed to me like a promised land which the Luculli of the Latin Quarter alone had the right to patronize. Sometimes I wondered whether I would ever be able to have a cup of white coffee there, or play a game of dominoes. In short, I transferred to my work the fury which poverty inspired in me. I tried to master scientific knowledge so that I should have an immense personal worth deserving of the place I would reach when I emerged from my obscurity. I consumed more oil than bread; the light which lit up those stubborn vigils cost me more than my food. The struggle was long, hard and unrelieved. I aroused no feelings of friendship in those around me. To make friends, you must mix with young people, have a few sous so that you can go and have a drink with them, go with them everywhere where students go. I had nothing. And no one in Paris realizes that“nothing” is “nothing”. When there was any question of revealing my poverty I experienced that nervous contraction of the throat which makes our patients think that a ball is rising up from the gullet into the larynx. Later on I met people who, born rich and never having lacked for anything, don’t know the problem of this rule of three:“A young man is to crime as a hundred sous piece is to X.”These gilded fools say to me, “Why did you get into debt? Why did you take on such crushing obligations?” They remind me of the princess who, knowing that the people were dying of hunger, asked, “Why don’t they buy cake?”I should very much like to see one of those rich people, who complains that I charge too much for operating on him, alone in Paris, without a penny, without a friend, without credit and forced to work with his two hands to live. What would he do? Where would he satisfy his hunger? Bianchon, if at times you have seen me bitter and hard, it was because I was superimposing my early sufferings on the lack of feeling, the selfishness, of which I had thousands of examples in high places; or I was thinking of the obstacles which hatred, envy, jealousy, and calumny have placed between me and success. In Paris, when certain people see you ready to put your foot in the stirrup, some of them pull you back by the coat- tail, others loosen the buckle of the saddle- girth so that you’ll fall and break your head; this one takes the shoes of your horse, that one steals your whip. The least treacherous is the one you see coming up to shoot you at point- blank range. You have enough talent, my dear fellow, soon to be acquainted with the horrible, unending battle which mediocrity wages against superiority. If one evening you lose twenty- five louis, the next day you will be accused of being a gambler and your best friends will say that the day before you lost twenty- five thousand francs. If you have a headache, you will be called a lunatic. If you have one outburst of temper, they will say you are a social misfit. If, in order to resist this army of pygmies, you muster your superior forces, your best friends will cry out that you want to eat up everything, that you claim to have the right to dominate and lord it over others. In short, your good qualities will become failings, your failings will become vices, and your virtues will be crimes. If you have saved a man, they’ll say you have killed him; if your patient is in circulation again, they will affirm that you have sacrificed the future to the present; if he is not dead, he will die. Hesitate, and you will be lost! Invent anything at all, claim your just due, you will be regarded as a sly character, difficult to deal with, who is standing in the way of the young men. So, my dear fellow, if I don’t believe in God, I believe still less in man. You recognize in me a Desplein very different from the Desplein everyone speaks ill of, don’t you? But let’s not rummage in this muck heap. Well, I used to live in this house; I was busy working to pass my first examination and I hadn’t a sou. I had reached one of those extreme situations where, you know, a man says to himself, “I shall join the army.” I had one last hope. I was expecting from home a trunk full of linen, a present from old aunts of the kind who, knowing nothing of Paris, think of your shirts and imagine that with thirty francs a month their nephew lives on caviar. The trunk arrived while I was at the school; the carriage cost forty francs. The porter, a German cobbler who lived in a garret, had paid the money and was keeping the trunk. I went for a walk in the Rue des Fossés- Saint-Germain- des- Prés and in the Rue de l’ Ecole- de- Médecine, but I could not think up a plan which would deliver my trunk to me without my having to pay the forty francs; naturally I would have paid them after I had sold the linen. My stupidity made me realize that I was gifted for nothing but surgery. My dear fellow, sensitive souls whose gifts are deployed in a lofty sphere are lacking in that spirit of intrigue which is so resourceful in contriving schemes. Their genius lies in chance; they don’t seek for things, they come on them by chance. Well, I returned at nightfall at the same time that my neighbour, a water- carrier named Bourgeat, a man from Saint- Flour, was going home. We knew each other in the way two tenants do who have rooms on the same landing, and who hear each other sleeping, coughing, and dressing, till in the end they get used to one another. My neighbour informed me that the landlord, to whom I owed three quarters’ rent, had turned me out; I would have to clear out the next day. He himself had been given notice because of his calling. I spent the most unhappy night of my life. Where would I find a carrier to remove my poor household affairs and my books? How would I be able to pay the carrier and the porter? Where was I to go? I kept on asking myself these unanswerable questions through my tears, like a madman repeating a refrain. I fell asleep. Poverty has in its favour an exquisite sleep filled with beautiful dreams. The next morning, just as I was eating my bowlful of crumbled bread and milk, Bourgeat came in and said in his bad French, “Monchieur l’étudiant, I’m a poor man, a foundling from the Chain- Flour hospital. I’ve no father or mother and I’m not rich enough to get married. You haven’t many relations either, or much in the way of hard cash. Now listen. I’ve got a hand- cart downstairs which I’ve hired for two chous an hour. It’ll take all our things. If you’re willing, we’ll look for digs together since we’re turned out of here. After all, this place isn’t an earthly paradise.”

‘ “I know that alright, Bourgeat, my good fellow,” I replied. “But I’m in rather a jam. Downstairs I have a trunk containing linen worth a hundred crowns. With that I could pay the landlord and what I owe the porter, but I haven’t got a hundred sous.”

‘ “That doesn’t matter, I’ve got some cash,” Bourgeat replied cheerfully, showing me a filthy old leather purse.“Keep your linen.”

‘Bourgeat paid my three quarters’ rent and his own and settled with the porter. Then he put our furniture and my linen on to his cart and dragged it through the streets, stopping in front of every house which had a “to let” sign hanging out. My job was to go up and see if the place to let would suit us. At midday we were still wandering about the Latin Quarter without having found anything. The price was a great difficulty. Bourgeat suggested that we should have lunch at a wine- shop; we left our cart at the door. Towards evening, I discovered in the Cour de Rohan, Passage du Commerce, two rooms, separated by the stair in the attic at the top of a house. The rent was sixty francs a year each. We were housed at last, my humble friend and I. We had dinner together. Bourgeat, who earned about fifty sous a day, had about a hundred crowns. He was soon going to be able to realize his ambition and buy a water- cart and a horse. When he learned about my situation (for he dragged my secrets out of me with a deep cunning and a good nature the memory of which still touches my heart), he gave up for some time his whole life’s ambition. Bourgeat had been a street- merchant for twenty- two years; he sacrificed his hundred crowns to my future.’

Desplein gripped Bianchon’s arm with emotion.

‘He gave me the money I needed for my exams. My friend, that man realized that I had a mission, that the needs of my intelligence were more important than his own. He took care of me; he called me his child and lent me the money I needed to buy books. Sometimes he would come in very quietly to watch me working. Last but not least, he took care, as a mother might have done, to see that instead of the bad and insufficient food which I had been forced to put up with, I had a healthy and plentiful diet. Bourgeat, who was a man of about forty, had the face of a medieval burgess, a dome- like forehead and a head that a painter might have used as a model for Lycurgus. The poor man’s heart was filled with affections which had no outlet. The only creature that had ever loved him was a poodle which had died a short time before. He talked to me continually about it and asked me if I thought that the Church would be willing to say Masses for the repose of its soul. His dog was, so he said, a true Christian and it had gone to church with him for twelve years, without ever barking there. It had listened to the organ without opening its mouth and squatted beside him with a look that made him think it was praying with him. This man transferred all his affections to me; he accepted me as a lonely and unhappy creature. He became for me the most attentive of mothers, the most tactful of benefactors, in short, the ideal of that virtue which delights in its own work. Whenever I met him in the street, he would glance at me with an understanding look filled with remarkable nobility; then he would pretend to walk as if he was carrying nothing. He seemed happy to see me in good health and well- dressed. In short, it was the devotion of a man of the people, the love of a working- girl transferred to a higher sphere. Bourgeat did my errands; he woke me up at night at the hours I asked him to. He cleaned my lamp and polished our landing. He was as good a servant as he was a father, and tidy as an English girl. He did the housework. Like Philopoemen he used to saw up our wood, doing everything with simplicity and dignity, for he seemed to realize that his objective added nobility to everything he did. When I left this good man to do my residence at the Hôtel Dieu, he felt an indescribable grief at the thought that he could no longer live with me. But he consoled himself with the prospect of saving up the money needed for the expenses of my thesis, and made me promise to come and see him on my days off. Bourgeat was proud of me; he loved me both for my sake and for his own. If you look up my thesis you will see that it was dedicated to him. During the last year of my internship, I had earned enough money to pay back everything I owed to this admirable Auvergnat, by buying him a horse and a water- cart. He was furious when he knew that I had been depriving myself of my money, and nevertheless he was delighted to see his wishes realized. He both laughed and scolded me. He looked at his cart and his horse, wiping a tear from his eyes as he said, “That’s bad! Oh, what a splendid cart! You shouldn’t have done it. The horse is as strong as an Auvergnat.” I have never seen anything more moving than this scene. Bourgeat absolutely insisted on buying me that case of instruments mounted in silver which you have seen in my study, and which is for me the most valuable thing I have there. Although he was thrilled by my first successes, he never let slip the least word or gesture which implied,“That man’s success is due to me.” And yet, without him, poverty would have killed me. The poor man had dug his own grave to help me. He had eaten nothing but bread rubbed with garlic, so that I could have coffee to help me work at night. He fell ill. As you can imagine, I spent the nights at his bedside. I pulled him through the first time, but he had a relapse two years later, and in spite of the most constant care, in spite of the greatest efforts of medical science, his end had come. No king was ever as well cared for as he was. Yes, Bianchon, to snatch that life from death I made supreme efforts. I wanted to make him live long enough for me to show him the results of his work and realize all his hopes for me; I wanted to satisfy the only gratitude which has ever filled my heart and put out a fire which still burns me today.’

After a pause, Desplein, visibly moved, resumed his tale. ‘Bourgeat, my second father, died in my arms leaving me everything he possessed in a will which he had had made by a public letter- writer and dated the year when we went to live in the Cour de Rohan. This man had the simple faith of a charcoal- burner. He loved the Blessed Virgin as he would have loved his wife. Although he was an ardent Catholic, he had never said a word to me about my lack of religion. When his life was in danger, he begged me to do everything possible to enable him to have the help of the Church. I had Mass said for him every day. Often, during the night, he would express fears for his future; he was afraid that he had not lived a sufficiently holy life. Poor man! He worked from morning to night. To whom then would Paradise belong – if there is a Paradise? He received the last rites like the saint he was and his death was worthy of his life. I was the only person to attend his funeral. When I had buried my only benefactor, I tried to think of a way of paying my debt to him. I realized that he had neither family nor friends, wife nor children. But he was a believer, he had a religious conviction. Had I any right to dispute it? He had spoken to me shyly about Masses said for the repose of the dead. He didn’t want to impose this duty upon me, thinking that it would be like asking payment for his services. As soon as I could establish an endowment fund, I gave Saint- Sulpice the necessary amount to have four Masses said there a year. As the only thing I can give to Bourgeat is the satisfaction of his religious wishes, the day when this Mass is said at the beginning of each season, I say with the good faith of a doubter, “Oh God, if there is a sphere where, after their death, you place all those who have been perfect, think of good Bourgeat. And if there is anything for him to suffer, give me his sufferings so that he may enter more quickly into what is called Paradise.”That, my dear fellow, is the most that a man with my opinions can allow himself. God must be a decent chap; he couldn’t hold it against me. I swear to you, I would give my fortune to be a believer like Bourgeat.’

Bianchon, who looked after Desplein in his last illness, dares not affirm nowadays that the distinguished surgeon died an atheist. Believers will like to think that the humble Auvergnat will have opened the gate of heaven for him as, earlier, he had opened for him the gate of that earthly temple on whose doorway is written Aux grands hommes la patrie reconnaissante.[7]

[1] In 1804 Napoleon planned to invade England, using a fleet of flat- bottomed boats based on Boulogne. But he was unable to gain command of the sea, and abandoned this plan in favour of the land conquest of Europe. In 1822 the French Government wanted to intervene in the civil conflict in Spain, in spite of the vigorous protest of Great Britain. Balzac’s point is, however, unclear.

[2] L’ Hôtel- Dieu was one of the oldest and most important hospitals in Paris.

[3] Life in La Maison Vauquer is depicted in Balzac’s novel Le Père Goriot.

[4] Cabanis was the author of the Traité du pbysique et du moral de l’homme, an influential atheistic and materialistic work.

[5] The Vaudois and the Albigensians were twelfth- century heretical sects in the south of France.

[6] Le Citateur was an anti- clerical pamphlet by Pigault- Lebrun.

[7] These words (meaning ‘To our great men from their grateful country’) are inscribed above the doorway of the Panthéon in Paris where many of the great men of France are buried.

The Conscript

Sometimes they saw that, by a phenomenon of vision or movement, he could abolish space in its two aspects of Time and Distance, one of these being intellectual and the other physical.

Histoire Intellectuelle de Louis Lambert.

One evening in the month of November 1793, the most important people in Carentan were gathered together in the drawing- room of Madame de Dey, who received company every day. Certain circumstances, which would not have attracted attention in a large town but which were bound to arouse curiosity in a small one, gave an unwonted interest to this everyday gathering. Two days earlier, Madame de Dey had closed her doors to visitors, and she had not received any the previous day either, pretending that she was unwell. In normal times these two events would have had the same effect in Carentan as the closing of the theatres has in Paris. On such days existence is, in a way, incomplete. But in 1793 Madame de Dey’s behaviour could have the most disastrous consequences. At that time if an aristocrat risked the least step, he was nearly always involved in a matter of life and death. To understand properly the eager curiosity and the narrow- minded cunning which, during that evening, were expressed on the faces of all these Norman worthies, but above all to appreciate the secret worries of Madame de Dey, the part she played at Carentan must be explained. As the critical position in which she was placed at that time was, no doubt, that of many people during the Revolution, the sympathies of more than one reader will give an emotional background to this narrative.

Madame de Dey, the widow of a lieutenant- general, a chevalier of several orders, had left the Court at the beginning of the emigration. As she owned a considerable amount of property in the Carentan region, she had taken refuge there, hoping that the influence of the Terror would be little felt in those parts. This calculation, founded on an accurate knowledge of the region, was correct. The Revolution wrought little havoc in Lower Normandy. Although, in the past, when Madame de Dey visited her property in Normandy, she associated only with the noble families of the district, she now made a policy of opening her doors to the principal townspeople and to the new authorities, trying to make them proud of having won her over, without arousing either their hatred or their jealousy. She was charming and kind, and gifted with that indescribable gentleness which enabled her to please without having to lower herself or ask favours. She had succeeded in winning general esteem thanks to her perfect tact which enabled her to keep wisely to a narrow path, satisfying the demands of that mixed society without humiliating the touchy amour propre of the parvenus, or upsetting the sensibilities of her old friends.

She was about thirty- eight years old, and she still retained, not the fresh, rounded good looks which distinguish the girls of Lower Normandy, but a slender, as it were aristocratic, type of beauty. Her features were neat and delicate; her figure was graceful and slender. When she spoke, her pale face seemed to light up and come to life. Her large black eyes were full of friendliness, but their calm, religious expression seemed to show that the mainspring of her existence was no longer within herself. In the prime of her youth she had been married to a jealous old soldier, and her false position at a flirtatious court no doubt helped to spread a veil of serious melancholy over a face which must once have shone with the charms and vivacity of love. Since, at an age when a woman still feels rather than reflects, she had always had to repress her instinctive feminine feelings and emotions, passion had remained unawakened in the depths of her heart. And so her principal attraction stemmed from this inner youthfulness which was, at times, revealed in her face and which gave her thoughts an expression of innocent desire. Her appearance commanded respect, but in her bearing and in her voice there was always the expectancy of an unknown future as with a young girl. Soon after meeting her the least susceptible of men would find himself in love with her and yet retain a kind of respectful fear of her, inspired by her courteous, dignified manner. Her soul, naturally great but strengthened by cruel struggles, seemed far removed from ordinary humanity, and men recognized their inferiority. This soul needed a dominating passion. Madame de Dey’s affections were thus concentrated in one single feeling, that of maternity. The happiness and the satisfactions of which she had been deprived as a wife, she found instead in the intense love she had for her son. She loved him not only with the pure and profound devotion of a mother, but with the coquetry of a mistress and the jealousy of a wife. She was unhappy when he was away, and, anxious during his absence, she could never see enough of him and lived only through and for him. To make the reader appreciate the strength of this feeling, it will suffice to add that this son was not only Madame de Dey’s only child, but also her last surviving relative, the one being on whom she could fasten the fears, the hopes and the joys of her life. The late Comte de Dey was the last of his family and she was the sole heiress of hers. Material motives and interests thus combined with the noblest needs of the soul to intensify in the countess’s heart a feeling which is already so strong in women. It was only by taking the greatest of care that she had managed to bring up her son and this had made him even more dear to her. Twenty times the doctors told her she would lose him, but confident in her own hopes and instincts, she had the inexpressible joy of seeing him safely overcome the perils of childhood, and of marvelling at the improvement in his health, in spite of the doctors’verdict.

Due to her constant care, this son had grown up and developed into such a charming young man that at the age of twenty he was regarded as one of the most accomplished young courtiers at Versailles. Above all, thanks to a good fortune which does not crown the efforts of every mother, she was adored by her son; they understood each other in fraternal sympathy. If they had not already been linked by the ties of nature, they would instinctively have felt for each other that mutual friendship which one meets so rarely in life. At the age of eighteen the young count had been appointed a sub- lieutenant of dragoons and in obedience to the code of honour of the period he had followed the princes when they emigrated.

Madame de Dey, noble, rich and the mother of an émigré, thus could not conceal from herself the dangers of her cruel situation. As her only wish was to preserve her large fortune for her son, she had denied herself the happiness of going with him, and when she read the strict laws under which the Republic was confiscating every day the property of émigrés at Carentan, she congratulated herself on this act of courage. Was she not watching over her son’s wealth at the risk of her life? Then, when she heard of the terrible executions decreed by the Convention, she slept peacefully in the knowledge that her only treasure was in safety, far from the danger of the scaffold. She was happy in the belief that she had done what was best to save both her son and her fortune. To this private thought she made the concessions demanded by those unhappy times, without compromising her feminine dignity or her aristocratic convictions, but hiding her sorrows with a cold secrecy. She had understood the difficulties which awaited her at Carentan. To come there and occupy the first place, wasn’t that a way of defying the scaffold every day? But, supported by the courage of a mother, she knew how to win the affection of the poor by relieving all kinds of distress without distinction, and made herself indispensable to the rich by ministering to their pleasures. She entertained at her house the procureur[1] of the commune, the mayor, the president of the district, the public prosecutor and even the judges of the revolutionary tribunal. The first four of these were unmarried and so they courted her, hoping to marry her either by making her afraid of the harm they could do her or by offering her their protection. The public prosecutor, who had been procureur at Caen and used to look after the countess’s business interests, tried to make her love him, by behaving with devotion and generosity – a dangerous form of cunning! He was the most formidable of all the suitors. As she had formerly been a client of his, he was the only one who had an intimate knowledge of the state of her considerable fortune. His passion was reinforced by all the desires of avarice and supported by an immense power, the power of life and death throughout the district. This man, who was still young, behaved with such an appearance of magnanimity that Madame de Dey had not yet been able to form an opinion of him. But, despising the danger which lay in vying in cunning with Normans, she made use of the inventive craftiness with which Nature has endowed women to play off these rivals against each other. By gaining time, she hoped to survive safe and sound to the end of the revolutionary troubles. At that period, the royalists who had stayed in France deluded themselves each day that the next day would see the end of the Revolution, and this conviction caused the ruin of many of them.

In spite of these difficulties, the countess had very skilfully maintained her independence until the day on which, with unaccountable imprudence, she took it into her head to close her door. The interest she aroused was so deep and genuine that the people who had come to her house that evening became extremely anxious when they learned that it was impossible for her to receive them. Then, with that frank curiosity which is engrained in provincial manners, they made inquiries about the misfortune, the sorrow, or the illness which Madame de Dey must be suffering from. An old servant named Brigitte answered these questions saying that her mistress had shut herself up in her room and wouldn’t see anyone, not even the members of her own household. The almost cloister- like existence led by the inhabitants of a small town forms in them the habit of analysing and explaining the actions of others. This habit is naturally so invincible that after pitying Madame de Dey, and without knowing whether she was really happy or sad, everyone began to look for the causes of her sudden retreat.

‘If she were ill,’ said the first inquirer, ‘she would have sent for the doctor. But the doctor spent the whole day at my house playing chess. He said to me jokingly that nowadays there is only one illness . . . and that unfortunately it is incurable.’

This jest was made with caution. Men and women, old men and girls then began to range over the vast field of conjectures. Each one thought he spied a secret, and this secret filled all their imaginations. The next day their suspicions had grown nastier. As life is lived in public in a small town, the women were the first to find out that Brigitte had bought more provisions than usual at the market. This fact could not be denied. Brigitte had been seen first thing in the morning in the market- square and –strange to relate – she had bought the only hare available. The whole town knew that Madame de Dey did not like game. The hare became a starting point for endless conjectures. As they took their daily walk, the old men noticed in the countess’s house a kind of concentrated activity which was revealed by the very precautions taken by the servants to conceal it. The valet was beating a carpet in the garden. The previous day no one would have paid any attention to it, but this carpet became a piece of evidence in support of the fanciful tales which everyone was inventing. Each person had his own. The second day, when they heard that Madame de Dey said she was unwell, the leading inhabitants of Carentan gathered together in the evening at the mayor’s brother’s house. He was a retired merchant, married, honourable, generally respected, and the countess had a high regard for him. That evening all the suitors for the hand of the rich widow had a more or less probable tale to tell, and each one of them considered how to turn to his own profit the secret event which forced her to place herself in this compromising position. The public prosecutor imagined a whole drama in which Madame de Dey’s son would be brought to her house at night. The mayor thought that a non- juring priest had arrived from La Vendée and sought asylum with her.[2] But the purchase of a hare on a Friday couldn’t be explained by this story. The president of the district was convinced that she was hiding a chouan[3] or a Vendéen leader who was being hotly pursued. Others thought it was a noble who had escaped from the Paris prisons. In short, everyone suspected the countess of being guilty of one of those acts of generosity which the laws of that period called a crime and which could lead to the scaffold. The public prosecutor, however, whispered that they must be silent and try to save the unfor tunate woman from the abyss towards which she was hastening.

‘If you make this affair known,’ he added, ‘I shall be obliged to intervene, to search her house, and then! . . .’He said no more but everyone understood what he meant.

The countess’s real friends were so alarmed for her that, on the morning of the third day, the procureur- syndic [4] of the commune got his wife to write her a note urging her to receive company that evening as usual. Bolder still, the retired merchant called at Madame de Dey’s house during the morning. Very conscious of the service which he wanted to render her, he insisted on being allowed in to see her, and was amazed when he caught sight of her in the garden, busy cutting the last flowers from her borders to fill her vases.

‘She must have given refuge to her lover,’ the old man said to himself, as he was overcome with pity for this charming woman. The strange expression of the countess’s face confirmed his suspicions. The merchant was deeply moved by this devotion which is so natural to women, but which men always find touching because they are all flattered by the sacrifices which a woman makes for a man; he told the countess about the rumours which were all over the town, and of the danger in which she was placed. ‘For,’ he said in conclusion, ‘though some of our officials may be willing to forgive you for acting heroically to save a priest, nobody will pity you if they find out you are sacrificing yourself for the sake of a love affair.’

At these words, Madame de Dey looked at the old man with a distraught and crazy expression which made him shudder, despite his age.

‘Come with me,’ she said taking him by the hand and leading him into her room where, having first made sure that they were alone, she took a dirty crumpled letter from the bodice of her dress. ‘Read that,’ she cried pronouncing the words with great effort.

She collapsed into her chair, as if she were overcome. While the old merchant was looking for his glasses and cleaning them, she looked up at him, examined him for the first time with interest and said gently in a faltering voice, ‘I can trust you.’

‘Have I not come to share in your crime?’ replied the worthy man simply.

She gave a start. For the first time in this little town, her soul felt sympathy with another’s. The merchant understood at once both the dejection and the joy of the countess. Her son had taken part in the Granville expedition;[5] his letter to his mother was written from the depths of his prison, giving her one sad, yet joyful hope. He had no doubts about his means of escape, and he mentioned three days in the course of which he would come to her house, in disguise. The fatal letter contained heart- rending farewells in case he would not be at Carentan by the evening of the third day, and he begged his mother to give a fairly large sum of money to the messenger who, braving countless dangers, had undertaken to bring her this letter. The paper shook in the old man’s hands.

‘And this is the third day,’ cried Madame de Dey as she got up quickly, took back the letter, and paced up and down the room.

‘You have acted rashly,’ said the merchant. ‘Why did you have food bought in?’

‘But he might arrive, dying with hunger, exhausted, and . . .’ She said no more.

‘I can count on my brother,’ continued the old man, ‘I will go and bring him over to your side.’

In this situation the merchant deployed again all the subtlety which he had formerly used in business and gave the countess prudent and wise advice. After they had agreed on what they both should say and do, the old man, on cleverly invented pretexts, went to the principal houses in Carentan. There he announced that he had just seen Madame de Dey, who would receive company that evening, although she was not very well. As he was a good match for the cunning Norman minds who, in every family, cross- examined him about the nature of the countess’s illness, he managed to deceive nearly everybody who was interested in this mysterious affair. His first visit worked wonders. He told a gouty old lady that Madame de Dey had nearly died from an attack of stomach gout. The famous Doctor Tronchin had on a former, similar occasion advised her to lay on her chest the skin of a hare, which had been flayed alive, and to stay absolutely immobile in bed. The countess who, two days ago, had been in mortal danger, was now, after having punctiliously obeyed Tronchin’s extraordinary instructions, well enough to receive visitors that evening. This tale had an enormous success, and the Carentan doctor, a secret royalist, added to the effect by the seriousness with which he discussed the remedy. Nevertheless, suspicions had taken root too strongly in the minds of some obstinate people, or of some doubters, to be entirely dissipated. So, that evening, Madame de Dey’s visitors came eagerly, in good time, some to observe her face carefully, others out of friendship, most of them amazed at her recovery. They found the countess by the large fireplace in her drawing- room, which was almost as small as the other drawing- rooms in Carentan, for to avoid offending the narrow- minded ideas of her guests, she had denied herself the luxuries she had been used to and so had made no changes in her house. The floor of the reception room was not even polished. She left dingy old hangings on the walls, kept the local furniture, burnt tallow candles and followed the fashions of the place. She adopted provincial life, without shrinking from its most uncomfortable meannesses or its most disagreeable privations. But, as she knew that her guests would forgive her any lavishness conducive to their comfort, she left nothing undone which would minister to their personal pleasures. And so she always provided excellent dinners. She went as far as to feign meanness in order to please these calculating minds and she skilfully admitted to certain concessions to luxury, in order to give in gracefully. And so, about seven o’clock that evening, the best of Carentan’s poor society was at Madame de Dey’s house and formed a large circle around the hearth. The mistress of the house, supported in her trouble by the old merchant’s sympathetic glances, endured with remarkable courage her guests’detailed questioning and their frivolous and stupid arguments. But at every knock on the door, and whenever there was a sound of footsteps in the street, she hid her violent emotion by raising questions of importance to the prosperity of the district. She started off lively discussions about the quality of the ciders and was so well supported by her confidant that the company almost forgot to spy on her, since the expression of her face was so natural and her self- possession so imperturbable. Nevertheless the public prosecutor and one of the judges of the revolutionary tribunal said little, watching carefully the least changes in her expression and, in spite of the noise, listening to every sound in the house. Every now and then they asked the countess awkward questions but she answered them with admirable presence of mind. A mother has so much courage! When Madame de Dey had arranged the card- players, and settled everyone at the tables to play boston or reversis or whist, she still lingered in quite a carefree manner to chat with some young people. She was playing her part like a consummate actress. She got someone to ask for lotto, pretended to be the only person who knew where the set was, and left the room.

‘I feel stifled, my dear Brigitte,’ she exclaimed as she wiped the tears springing from her eyes which shone with fever, grief and impatience. ‘He is not coming,’ she continued, as she went upstairs and looked round the bedroom.‘Here, I can breathe and live. Yet in a few more moments he will be here! For he is alive, of that I am sure. My heart tells me so. Don’t you hear anything, Brigitte? Oh! I would give the rest of my life to know whether he is in prison or walking across the countryside. I wish I could stop thinking.’

She looked round the room again to see if everything was in order. A good fire was burning brightly in the grate, the shutters were tightly closed, the polished furniture was gleaming, the way the bed had been made showed that the countess had discussed the smallest details with Brigitte. Her hopes could be discerned in the fastidious care which had obviously been lavished on this room; in the scent of the flowers she had placed there could be sensed the gracious sweetness and the most chaste caresses of love. Only a mother could have anticipated a soldier’s wants and made preparations which satisfied them so completely. A superb meal, choice wines, slippers, clean linen, in short everything that a weary traveller could need or desire was brought together so that he should lack for nothing, so that the delights of home should show him a mother’s love.

‘Brigitte,’ cried the countess in a heart- rending voice as she went to place a chair at the table. It was as if she wanted to make her prayers come true, as if she wanted to add strength to her illusions.

‘Ah, Madame, he will come. He is not far away – I am sure that he is alive and on his way. I put a key in the Bible and I kept it on my fingers while Cottin read the Gospel of St John . . . and, Madame, the key didn’t turn.’

‘Is that a reliable sign?’ asked the countess.

‘Oh, yes! Madame, it’s well known. I would stake my soul he’s still alive. God cannot be wrong.’

‘I would love to see him, in spite of the danger he will be in when he gets here.’

‘Poor Monsieur Auguste,’ cried Brigitte, ‘he must be on the way, on foot.’

‘And there’s the church clock striking eight,’ exclaimed the countess in terror.

She was afraid that she had stayed longer than she should have done in this room where, as everything bore witness to her son’s life, she could believe that he was still alive. She went downstairs but before going into the drawing- room, she paused for a moment under the pillars of the staircase, listening to hear if any sound disturbed the silent echoes of the town. She smiled at Brigitte’s husband, who kept guard like a sentinel and seemed dazed with the effort of straining to hear the sounds of the night from the village square. She saw her son in everything and everywhere. She soon went back into the room, putting on an air of gaiety, and began to play lotto with some little girls. But every now and then she complained of not feeling well and sat down in her armchair by the fireplace.

That is how people and things were in Madame de Dey’s house while on the road from Paris to Cherbourg a young man wearing a brown carmagnole, the obligatory dress of the period, was making his way to Carentan. When the conscription of August 1793 first came into force, there was little or no discipline. The needs of the moment were such that the Republic could not equip its soldiers immediately, and it was not uncommon to see the roads full of conscripts still wearing their civilian clothes. These young men reached their halting places ahead of their battalions, or lagged behind, for their progress depended on their ability to endure the fatigues of a long march. The traveller in question was some way ahead of a column of conscripts which was going to Cherbourg and which the mayor of Carentan was expecting from hour to hour, intending to billet the men on the inhabitants. The young man was marching with a heavy tread, but he was still walking steadily and his bearing suggested that he had long been familiar with the hardships of military life. Although the meadow- land around Carentan was lit up by the moon, he had noticed big white clouds threatening a snowfall over the countryside. The fear of being caught in a storm probably made him walk faster, for he was going at a pace ill- suited to his fatigue. On his back he had an almost empty rucksack, and in his hand was a boxwood stick cut from one of the high, thick hedges which this shrub forms around most of the estates of Lower Normandy. A moment after the solitary traveller had caught sight of the towers of Carentan silhouetted in the eerie moonlight, he entered the town. His step aroused the echoes of the silent, deserted streets and he had to ask a weaver who was still at work the way to the mayor’s house. This official did not live far away and the conscript soon found himself in the shelter of the porch of the mayor’s house. He applied for a billeting order and sat down on a stone seat to wait. But he had to appear before the mayor who had sent for him and he was subjected to a scrupulous cross- examination. The soldier was a young man of good appearance who seemed to belong to a good family. His demeanour indicated that he was of noble birth and his face expressed that intelligence which comes from a good education.

‘What’s your name?’ asked the mayor looking at him knowingly.

‘Julien Jussien,’ replied the conscript.

‘And where do you come from?’ asked the official with an incredulous smile.

‘From Paris.’

‘Your comrades must be some distance away,’ continued the Norman half jokingly.

‘I am three miles ahead of the battalion.’

‘Some special feeling attracts you to Carentan, no doubt, citoyen réquisitionnaire,’[6] said the mayor shrewdly.

‘It is all right,’ he added, as with a gesture he imposed silence on the young man who was about to speak. ‘We know where to send you. There you are,’ he added giving him his billeting order. ‘Off you go, citoyen Jussien.’

There was a tinge of irony in the official’s tone as he pronounced these last two words and handed out a billet order giving the address of Madame de Dey’s house. The young man read the address with an air of curiosity.

‘He knows quite well that he hasn’t far to go. And once he’s outside he’ll soon be across the square,’ exclaimed the mayor talking to himself as the young man went out. He’s got some nerve! May God guide him! He has an answer to everything. Yes, but if anyone but me had asked to see his papers, he would have been lost.’

At this moment, the Carentan clocks had just struck half past nine. The torches were being lit in Madame de Dey’s ante- chamber; the servants were helping their masters and mistresses to put on their clogs, their overcoats or their capes; the card- players had settled their accounts and they were all leaving together, according to the established custom in all little towns.

‘It looks as if the prosecutor wants to stay,’ said a lady, who noticed that this important personage was missing when, having exhausted all the formulae of leave- taking, they separated in the square to go to their respective homes.

In fact that terrible magistrate was alone with the countess who was waiting, trembling, till he chose to go.

After a long and rather frightening silence, he said at last, ‘I am here to see that the laws of the Republic are obeyed . . .’

Madame de Dey shuddered.

‘Have you nothing to reveal to me?’ he asked.

‘Nothing,’ she replied, amazed.

‘Ah, Madame,’ cried the prosecutor sitting down beside her and changing his tone, ‘at this moment, one word could send you or me to the scaffold. I have observed your character, your feelings, your ways too closely to share the mistake into which you managed to lead your guests this evening. I have no doubt at all that you are expecting your son.’

The countess made a gesture of denial, but she had grown pale and the muscles of her face had contracted under the necessity of assuming a false air of calmness.

‘Well, receive him,’ continued the magistrate of the Revolution, ‘but don’t let him stay under your roof after seven o’clock in the morning. At daybreak, tomorrow, I shall come to your house armed with a denunciation which I shall have drawn up . . .’

She looked at him with a dazed expression which would have melted the heart of a tiger.

He went on gently, ‘I shall demonstrate the falsity of the denunciation by a minute search, and by the nature of my report you will be protected from all further suspicion. I shall speak of your patriotic gifts, of your civic devotion, and we shall all be saved.’

Madame de Dey was afraid of a trap. She stood there motionless but her face was burning and her tongue was frozen. The sound of the door- knocker rang through the house.

‘Ah,’ cried the terrified mother, falling on her knees.‘Save him, save him!’

‘Yes, let us save him!’ replied the public prosecutor, looking at her passionately, ‘even at the cost of our lives.’

‘I am lost,’ she cried as the prosecutor politely helped her to rise.

‘Ah! Madame,’ he replied with a fine oratorical gesture,‘I want to owe you to nothing . . . but yourself.’

‘Madame, he’s –,’ cried Brigitte thinking her mistress was alone.

At the sight of the public prosecutor, the old servant who had been flushed with joy, became pale and motionless.

‘Who is it, Brigitte?’ asked the magistrate gently, with a knowing expression.

‘A conscript sent by the mayor to be put up here,’replied the servant showing the billet order.

‘That’s right,’ said the prosecutor after reading the order. ‘A battalion is due in the town tonight.’ And he went out.

At that moment the countess needed so much to believe in the sincerity of her former lawyer that she could not entertain the slightest doubt of it. Quickly she went upstairs, though she scarcely had the strength to stand. Then she opened her bedroom door, saw her son, and fell half- dead into his arms. ‘Oh, my child, my child,’ she cried sobbing and covering him with wild kisses.

‘Madame,’ said the stranger.

‘Oh! It’s someone else,’ she cried. She recoiled in horror and stood in front of the conscript, gazing at him with a haggard look.

‘Oh, good God, what a strong resemblance!’ said Brigitte.

There was silence for a moment and even the stranger shuddered at the sight of Madame de Dey.

She leaned for support on Brigitte’s husband and felt the full extent of her grief; this first blow had almost killed her. ‘Monsieur,’ she said, ‘I cannot bear to see you any longer; I hope you won’t mind if my servants take my place and look after you.’

She went down to her own room half carried by Brigitte and her old manservant.

‘What, Madame!’ cried the housekeeper as she helped her mistress to sit down. ‘Is that man going to sleep in Monsieur Auguste’s bed, put on Monsieur Auguste’s slippers and eat the pâté that I made for Monsieur Auguste? If I were to be sent to the guillotine, I . . .’

‘Brigitte,’ cried Madame de Dey.

Brigitte said no more.

‘Be quiet, you chatterbox,’ said her husband in a low voice. ‘You’ll be the death of Madame.’

At this moment, the conscript made a noise in his room as he sat down to table.

‘I can’t stay here,’ exclaimed Madame de Dey. ‘I shall go into the conservatory. From there I shall be able to hear better what’s going on outside during the night.’

She was still wavering between the fear of having lost her son and the hope of seeing him come back. The silence of the night was horrible. When the conscript battalion came into town and each man had to seek out his lodgings, it was a terrible time for the countess. Her hopes were dashed at every footstep, at every sound; then soon the awful stillness of Nature returned. Towards morning, the countess had to go back to her own room. Brigitte, who was watching her mistress’s movements, did not see her come out; she went into the room and there found the countess dead.

‘She must have heard the conscript finishing dressing and walking about in Monsieur Auguste’s room singing their damned Marseillaise, as if he were in a stable,’ cried Brigitte. ‘That will have killed her!’

The countess’s death was caused by a more important feeling and, very likely, by a terrible vision. At the exact moment when Madame de Dey was dying in Carentan, her son was being shot in Le Morbihan. We can add this tragic fact to all the observations that have been made of sympathies which override the laws of space. Some learned recluses, in their curiosity, have collected this evidence in documents which will one day serve as a foundation for a new science – a science that has hitherto failed to produce its man of genius.

[1] An official elected to represent the central government on local courts and administration.

[2] The priests often helped the inhabitants of La Vendée in the west of France in their risings against the Revolution.

[3] The chouans were royalist insurgents from Western France who engaged in guerrilla warfare against the Revolution.

[4] See note 1 above.

[5] Granville is a small town, south- west of Carentan, on the other side of the Cotentin peninsula. In 1793 the Vendéens tried unsuccessfully to capture it for the royalists.

[6] Citoyen was a form of address during the Revolution replacing monsieur. A decree passed by the National Convention in 1793 called for military service all men between eighteen and twenty- five. The conscripts were known as réquisitionnaires.

墙中门

第一章

不到三个月前，莱昂内尔·华莱士在向我推心置腹那个夜晚，给我讲了“墙中门”的故事。当时，我认为至少在他看来，这是一个真实的故事。

在讲述的过程中，他那坚信不疑的态度直接而单纯，让我无法不相信他。但第二天清晨，我从自己的公寓醒来后，却有了不同的感受。我躺在床上，回忆起昨晚他告诉我的一切，剥去他诚挚而缓慢的声线魅惑，抛开那光线集中而幽暗的桌灯，在那样的夜晚，包裹着我俩的暧昧气氛，那些让人愉悦的闪闪发光的物件，我俩在晚餐间分享的甜点、酒杯以及餐巾——这所有的一切都让我们置身于彻底与现实脱离的明亮小世界当中，坦白说，我觉得这一切太难以令人相信了。“他在故弄玄虚！”我恍然大悟，“他装得也太像了！我万万没想到的是，他能装得这么好。”

随后，我起身坐在床上，啜着清晨的第一杯茶，试图从中重新品味出现实的味道，因为他的记忆太难以置信，让我不知所措，可不得不承认，它们的确在某种程度上暗示、呈现或是传达——我都不知道该用哪个词——出了只能以这种方式讲述的经历。

好吧，无论如何，现在我并不太倾向于这个解释，该怀疑的我也怀疑过了。我现在就如同昨晚一样，相信华莱士尽他最大的努力把自己秘密中最真实的部分剥离出来告诉我。但究竟他是否曾经看见，还是他自认为看到过，究竟自己是无价特权的持有者还是痴人说梦的受害者，我无法肆意妄测。就连他身亡这一事实，虽然彻底地了断了我的各种猜疑的念头，却也没有给我带来任何答案。

这只能由读者自己判断了。

我一时半会儿也想不起来，究竟是我发表过的什么意见或者是评论，能够打动如此沉默寡言的一个男人，让他产生向我吐露心声的想法。在一次重大公共运动中，我曾因为他的懈怠和不靠谱而谴责过他，那次他让我失望透顶，我觉得他当时是在为自己辩护。他突然插进来说：“我被其他事情占据了思绪……”他在停顿了一下后继续说道：“我知道，我最近有些玩忽职守。事实是——这并不是鬼魂或者是幽灵什么的——但，这实在是太难以启齿了。列德蒙，我被缠上了。我被什么东西给缠上了——它让一切都黯淡无光，它让我充满渴求……”

他停了下来，每当我们英国人谈论到感人的、严肃的或是其他美丽事物的时候所呈现出特有的羞怯打断了他。“你一直都在圣·阿瑟尔斯坦吧。”他说道。当时在我看来，这根本毫无关联。“好吧。”他又顿了一下。然后，他起初讲话的时候支支吾吾，慢慢地顺畅起来。他开始讲述一直掩藏在生命当中，那段让他念念不忘的回忆，这段美好回忆使他内心充满幸福和无法满足的渴望，却同时也让尘世间的一切利益和奇观显得枯燥乏味和徒有其表。

既然我现在有了头绪，那时他脸上的表情其实说明了一切。我有这么一张照片，他那疏离的神情彻底呈现在照片之上，甚至更加凸显了。这让我想起有一位女士曾这样描述过他——这位女士曾深深地爱着他。“突然间，”她说，“他对一切都失去了兴趣。他忘记了你的存在，哪怕你就在他鼻子底下，他也一点都不在乎……”

但是华莱士并不是一直对什么都毫无兴趣，当他全神贯注的时候，他能够设法取得巨大的成功。毫无疑问，他的事业打从一开始就非常成功。他早就把我甩在了身后；他在我身旁一飞冲天，在社会上占据了一席之地，无论如何，那是我所无法达成的。他还差一年才满四十岁，现在人们都说，如果他还活着的话，肯定能继续任职，还很有可能进入内阁。在学校的时候，他总是能够毫不费力地击败我——就好像他天生理当如此。我们是一起在西肯辛顿的圣·阿瑟尔斯坦学院上学的，一起度过了整个学生生涯。他入校的时候和我旗鼓相当，但很快就凭借奖学金和出色的表现远远地超越了我。当然我觉得我也差不多尽力了。正是在学校里，我第一次听到了“墙中门”——在他去世的一个月前，是我第二次听到它。

至少对他来说，“墙中门”是一扇真实存在的门，穿过真实存在的墙到达永恒的现实。对于这点，我现在是十分确信的。

而这扇门出现在他人生很早期，大概还是五六岁小孩的时候。我之所以记得，是因为他在向我坦白的时候，沉重而缓慢地推理和计算出了当时的日期。“当时有，”他说，“一株猩红色的五叶地锦，在琥珀色的阳光下，一整片深红色在白墙的映衬下格外显眼。我还记得，虽然不是特别清晰，绿色门外的人行道上散落着七叶树的叶子。它们是斑驳的黄绿色的，你知道，并不是棕色，也不脏，所以肯定刚从树上落下来。我觉得这意味着那是十月份。我每年都留意着七叶树树叶，我肯定知道的。”

“如果没记错的话，那我当时应该是五岁零四个月大。”

他说自己是个早熟的孩子——他学会讲话的年龄异常早，条理清晰，还有点“老派”，正如人们所说，这让他获取了其他小孩在七八岁不可能得到的自主权。他的母亲在他两岁时候去世了，家庭教师的管教相对来说没有那么严苛。他的父亲是一名严肃的、业务繁忙的律师，他的注意力没过多地放在儿子身上，却对他期待很高。我觉得作为一个聪明绝顶的小孩，他认为生活单调乏味。有一天，他溜了出去。

他已经记不清具体是谁的疏忽让他能有机会溜出来的，也记不清走的是西肯辛顿哪一条路。所有的一切都从模糊的记忆中彻底褪去。但关于白墙和绿门的记忆是清晰可见的。

追溯儿时的记忆，他记得第一眼看到那扇门，就感受到一种特别的情绪，那是一种吸引力，一种让他想要打开门走进去的欲望。但与此同时，他又确信向这吸引力屈服是不理智或是错误的——究竟是不理智还是错误，他无从知晓。自打一开始，他就知道那扇门并没有锁，而且如果他乐意，就可以走进去，为什么对这件事如此肯定，他也觉得很是奇怪——当然除非这一切都是记忆和他开了一个最诡异的玩笑。

我似乎都能看见那个内心挣扎着的小男孩的样子，而且他脑袋里清楚地知道——虽然也没法儿解释他为什么会知道——如果父亲发现他进入那扇门会勃然大怒。

华莱士极其详尽地向我描述了他的犹豫不决。他走过了那扇门，双手插着口袋，笨拙地吹着口哨，溜达到了墙的尽头。他记得那里有几家寒酸、脏乱的商店，他尤其记得有一个水管工和装潢工人在卖缸瓦管、薄铅板、浮球栓和墙纸的样品簿，还有一罐瓷漆，东西都布满灰尘，堆得乱七八糟。他停下来，假装在打量这些东西，觊觎着，热烈地渴望着那扇绿色的门。

他说，接下来有一股强烈的情绪涌上心头。这一丁点的犹豫不决无法再阻挠他，他直接奔向那扇门，蓦地一冲，伸手打开绿门，只身进入，把门甩在自己身后。于是就在一转眼间，他走进了那座纠缠他至今的花园。

对华莱士来说，他很难向我表达走进那座花园的全部感受。

那里的空气中有一股让人愉悦的气氛，它让人感到轻松，有种好事将至的幸福感；它让一切颜色看起来干净、完美并且微微地透着光。人一走进这里，立刻感到快乐至极——因为在我们生活的世界里，只有在很少数的时刻，当人们在年轻和愉快的时候，才会感到快乐，而且那里的一切都那么美丽……

华莱士在告诉我之前冥思了一阵。“你看，”他的声音就像普通人讲到让人无法置信的事情时，会变得有点可疑，“那里有两头美洲豹，就在那儿，是的，长着斑点的美洲豹。而我一点都不害怕。那里还有一条宽敞而悠长的道路，两旁的花径用的是大理石镶边，这两头柔软的野兽在那儿玩着球。有一头美洲豹抬起头，向我走来，看起来有点好奇。它径直走向我，用它柔软的圆耳朵轻轻地蹭着我伸出去的小手，发出咕噜咕噜的声响。我告诉你，这是一座施了魔法的花园。我确定。而它有多大？噢！它延绵不绝伸向四面八方。我相信在更远处还有山丘。天知道突然之间西肯辛顿跑到哪儿去了。但不知为何，那种感觉就像是回到了故乡。”

“你要知道，就在我关上那道门的那一刻，我忘记了门外飘落在道路上的七叶树树叶；我忘记了门外的马车和商人的货车；我忘记了那股像引力一样把我拉回充满纪律和服从的家中的力量；我忘记了所有的犹豫和恐惧，忘记了谨慎，忘记了现实生活中所熟悉的一切。在那一瞬间，我——在另一个世界里——成为一个快乐并且超级幸福的小男孩。那个世界有着不同的特质，那里更温暖，阳光更有穿透力却更柔软，空气里弥漫着一丝丝清澈而愉悦的味道，头顶湛蓝的天空中飘浮着一撮撮被阳光拂过的云朵。在我面前，这条又宽又长的道路延伸向前方，路两旁没有多余的杂草，花团锦簇但疏于打理，还有这两头神奇的美洲豹，仿佛都在对我发出邀请。我无畏地把双手放在它们柔软的皮毛上，轻抚着它们圆圆的耳朵和耳下敏感的地方，和它们嬉戏玩耍，那种感觉就像它们在欢迎我回家。在我脑海中，有一种强烈的回到家的感觉，紧接着一位高挑美丽的女孩出现在路上来接我，她微笑着对我说：‘来吧。’然后把我举起来亲了一口，又放了下来，拉着我往前走。当这一切发生的时候，我丝毫没有感到吃惊，反而有一种理所当然的愉悦之感，这种感觉就像是再次回忆起能够让你感到快乐的事情，而这种感觉不知为何早已被忽略。我记得那里有巨大的红色阶梯，越爬越高，映入眼帘的是一穗穗飞燕草，最后我们来到了一大片林荫道，道路两侧栽种着古老而暗沉的树木。你知道，在整条林荫道上红色的龟裂树干之间，摆放着大理石雕刻的贵宾席、雕像，还有温驯友好的白鸽……

“女伴带我走在这凉爽的林荫道上，她低头看着我——我回想起那些令人愉快的对话，她那精雕细琢的下巴和甜美的容颜——用温柔悦耳的嗓音问我问题，告诉我事情，我知道那些内容让人愉悦，虽然我再也记不起具体是些什么……不久后，一只干净的卷尾猴爬下树，它一身红棕色的毛，栗色的眼睛看起来非常友善，它靠近我们，跑到我身边，抬头看着我咧着嘴笑了起来，随后跳到了我的肩膀上。然后我俩无比快乐地继续向前走。”

他停了下来。“继续啊。”我说。“我记不住多少了，只记得我们经过了在月桂花丛中沉思的老人，还有一处栖息着各种长尾小鹦鹉的地方，穿过了荫蔽的柱廊，来到了一个宽敞而凉爽的宫殿，在那里，四处可见的是可爱的喷泉，布满了美丽的事物，都是人们内心所向往的特质和希望。而且那里有许多事、许多人，有的还让我记忆犹新，有的已经模糊不清，但所有人都美丽和善。某种程度来说——我也说不清为什么——我能够感受到他们对我的友好，我的到来让他们快乐，他们的一举一动都让我感到快乐，他们触碰我的双手、他们对我的热情以及他们眼中的关爱。是的……”

他沉思了一阵。“我在那儿找到了玩伴。这对我来说非常重要，因为我是一个孤独的小男孩。他们在铺着草皮的庭院中玩着有意思的游戏，那里有一个用花朵做成的日晷。那游戏让人爱不释手……”

“但奇怪的是，我的记忆中有一个空缺。我不记得我们玩了什么游戏。我从没记起过。在此以后，我在孩童时花了很长的时间试图记起让我感到如此幸福的游戏究竟是什么，我甚至因此而落泪。我想在幼儿园独自再玩一次这个游戏，可是都失败了！我唯一能记得的就是我当时感到多么幸福以及那两个一直陪我玩耍的玩伴……随后出现了一个阴郁的女人，她脸色苍白、神情严肃、眼神涣散，这个阴郁的女人穿着柔软的紫色长袍，她拿着一本书，召唤我到一边，带着我来到了大厅之上的画廊里——虽然我的小伙伴非常不情愿让我离开，他们停下了手中的游戏，站在那儿眼睁睁看着我被带走。‘回来找我们！’他们喊道，‘快回来找我们！’我抬头看着她，但她根本没留意到小伙伴的存在。她的表情温和而严肃。她把我带到画廊的一个座位边，我站在她身旁，她在膝盖上把书翻开，我准备看看书里面是些什么。打开书，她手指到哪儿，我看到哪儿，简直太神奇了，因为在栩栩如生的故事中，我看到了我自己——这是关于我的故事，里面讲述的是我从出生到现在所发生的一切……

“这对我来说太奇妙了，因为书里面的每一页都不是照片，你知道的，它们是真实的。”

华莱士凝重地顿了顿，疑惑地看着我。“你继续说，我明白。”我说。“那些都是真实的，是的，一定没错。里面的人和物都是鲜活的，我亲爱的母亲，我几乎都快忘记她了，还有我那严厉正直的父亲、家里的仆人，幼儿园，所有家中熟悉的一切。还有家里的前门，门外忙碌的街道，街道上的车来车往。我看着书，彻底惊呆了，再次充满疑惑地抬头看着那个女人的脸庞，然后继续翻着书，为了看更多的内容，跳过了中间的几页，翻着翻着，直到最后，我看见自己站在长长的白墙中的绿门前徘徊不定、犹豫不决，我再次感到了内心的挣扎和恐惧。”

“还有呢？”

“我哭喊起来，想要继续翻页，但严肃女人冰冷的手制止了我。”

“接下来呢？”

“我坚持着，在她手中轻轻挣扎，用一个孩子那可笑的力量扳开她的手指。最后她放弃了，我翻到了下一页，与此同时她弯下腰，一层阴影笼罩在我上方，她在我额头上亲了一下。

“但接下来的书中并没有出现那魔法花园，也没有美洲豹，没有拉着我手的女孩，更没有不情愿放我离开的玩伴们。在里面出现的是西肯辛顿冗长而灰暗的街道，在路灯点亮前的下午空旷无人。而我，这个可怜的小家伙，在那儿放声痛哭。我竭尽所能压抑自己，而我痛哭是因为不能回到我的玩伴身边了，我还能听到他们的呼唤——‘回来找我们！快回来找我们！’我在那儿，这不是书里面的某一页，而是残酷的现实，那个充满魔力的地方，我曾站在那位严肃的母亲的膝边，她制止我的手，这一切都消失了——他们都到哪里去了？”

他再次停下来，好长一段时间都只是盯着燃烧的炉火。

“噢！返回到现实世界是如此痛苦！”他喃喃自语道。“然后呢？”我等了一分多钟后问。“当时的我太可怜了！再次被带回这个灰暗的世界！当我意识到刚刚所发生的一切，便深陷于无法掌控的悲伤之中。那次在公共场合哭泣和如此丢人的回归方式给我带来的侮辱和羞愧，我直到现在还记忆犹新。我又看见那位相貌慈祥、戴着金边眼镜的老绅士，他停下来先用雨伞戳了戳我，对我说：‘可怜的小家伙，你迷路了吗？’而我不过是个五岁多大的伦敦男孩！他想必是找了一位亲切的年轻警察，在众人的围观下，把我护送回家。我害怕得边走边哭，非常引人注目，就这样从魔法花园回到了父亲住宅门前的台阶上。”

“这也就是我能记得的关于这个花园的一切——那个让我魂牵梦绕至今的花园。当然，我无法传达出那种难以描述的特质，那种清澈透明的不真实感，它与我们平常所经历到的一切完全不同，但这——这就是过去所发生的。如果这只是一场梦，我肯定它发生在大白天，而总体来说是一场非凡好梦……嗯！——自然而然，随之而来的是一系列可怕的审问，有我的姨妈、我的父亲、我的保姆，还有家教——所有人……

“我试图告诉他们，而父亲因为我说谎，第一次痛打了我一顿。之后我试着告诉姨妈，她因为我顽劣的坚持，又惩罚了我一次。之后，正如我说的，他们禁止所有人听我的故事，一个字也不准听。最后甚至把我的童话故事书也没收了一段时间——因为我的想象力太‘丰富’。呃？是的，他们真的那么做了！我父亲很保守……于是我只能自己给自己讲故事。我躺在枕头上对自己低语——枕头经常被我的口水或泪水浸湿，潮潮的、咸咸的。而我总是在每日的祷告——没那么虔诚的祷告——中加上衷心的请求：‘求求你上帝，请让我梦见那个花园。噢！把我带回到那个花园吧！’让我回到那个花园！我经常梦到那个花园。我可能添油加醋，我不确定……所有的这一切，你要知道，都是我试图重组早年经历过的破碎记忆。在小时候的那次经历和其他连续性的回忆之间，仿佛有一道鸿沟。有一阵子，我觉得甚至不应该再提到那神奇的惊鸿一瞥。”

我问了一个显而易见的问题。

“没有，”他回答说，“在早些年我不记得曾试图重返花园。现在看来有些奇怪，但我觉得很有可能是因为在那次‘历险’过后，他们对我严加看管，以防我再次走失。不，一直到我们相识，我才再次尝试寻找那个花园。而我相信有那么一段时间——现在看起来难以置信——我彻底忘记了那个花园，大概是我八九岁的时候吧。你还记得我在圣·阿瑟尔斯坦是个怎样的小孩吗？”

“记得非常清楚！”

“在那些日子里，我并没有显露出藏着一个秘密的梦境的迹象，对吧？”

第二章

他突然笑着抬起头：“你和我玩过‘西北通道’吗？”

不，你和我当然不是一路的。

“那种游戏，”他继续说，“想象力丰富的小孩整天都在玩。大致上就是找一条通往学校的‘西北通道’。每天上学的路十分无聊，游戏目标在于找一条不那么无趣的上学之路，提前十分钟出发，选一个看起来完全无望的方向，在不熟悉的街道上探索前往学校的新径。有一天，我在坎佩切山那侧的底层街区迷了路，还以为输掉游戏的这一天终于来临了，这下上学要迟到了。绝望之中，我选了一条看起来像死胡同的路，但却在小巷尽头，找到了一个出口。希望再次燃起，我快速走了出去。‘我能行的。’我边想边走过了一排乱糟糟的商铺，这种似曾相识的感觉让人费解，天哪，那不是把我带到魔法花园的白色长墙和绿色的门吗？”

“那时的记忆有如潮水向我猛然袭来。而那花园，那美好的花园，终归不仅仅是一场梦。”

他停了下来。

“我觉得和绿门的第二次相遇标志着忙碌的中学生活和童年时期无尽的闲暇时光有着天壤之别。无论如何，第二次的时候，我完全没有想要立刻走进去。你看……首先，我一股脑儿想着的都是如何按时到达学校——为的是不能中断每天按时到校的记录。我肯定也有一点点的冲动想要去试试那扇门——是的，我肯定也感受到了那股冲动——但在我记忆中，似乎只把那扇门的吸引力看成是阻挠我雷打不动想要准时到校的障碍。当然这次发现引起了我巨大的兴趣——我满脑子都是它——可我还是继续前行。那扇门并没有让我停下脚步。我边跑边拉出怀表，发现距离上课还有十分钟，而我已经下坡回到了熟悉的环境中。我上气不接下气地赶到学校，可没骗你，我跑得一身大汗，连衣服都湿了，可我准时到校了。我还记得把大衣和帽子挂起来……就这样经过了那扇门，把它抛在身后。很奇怪，对吧？”

他若有所思地看着我。“当然我当时并不知道那扇门并不会一直在那儿。中学生的想象力有限。我觉得知道门在那儿、知道怎样走回去让我非常开心，但当时有学校拖着我。我觉得那天早晨我肯定特别心神不宁、心不在焉，回想着，如果再次与不久前见到的那些美丽的陌生人重逢会是怎样的情形。奇怪的是，当时我脑中如此确信他们再次见到我一定会感到高兴。没错，那天早晨我肯定把花园当成了一个让人可以暂时逃离紧张学业的愉快场所。”

“我那天根本没去找那扇门。第二天有半天假期，这可能影响了我的决定。或者，我漫不经心的状态给我造成了负担，让我错过了重返花园的最佳时机。我也不知道。与此同时，我只知道那个魔法花园在脑海中挥之不去，我根本无法保守这个秘密。

“我告诉了——他叫什么名字来着？——一个长得像雪貂的小孩，我们以前管他叫呆呆。”

“小霍普金斯。”我回答说。

“就是霍普金斯。我也不想告诉他，因为总觉得告诉他是违反规矩的，但我还是说了。回家有段路我俩一起走，他太能说了，而如果我们不聊魔法花园，我们就得说点别的，而对我来说，当时脑子里根本容不下其他任何话题。我就这么说漏嘴了。

“好吧，他把我的秘密说出去了。第二天课间玩耍的时候，我被六个高年级男生包围了，他们半开着玩笑，都想听我说更多关于魔法花园的事。其中有大块头福西特——你还记得他吗？还有卡纳比和莫雷·雷诺兹。你当时不会也在那儿吧？不，如果你在的话我应该会记得的……

“男孩这种生物太奇特了。抛开掩藏在内心深处的自我厌恶不说，我当时对于能够得到这么多高年级生的关注，内心深处是有点沾沾自喜的，至少我是这么认为的。我记忆尤其深刻的是得到克罗肖表扬的那一刻——你记得大一点的克罗肖，作曲家克罗肖的儿子？——他说这是他所听过的最棒的谎话。可与此同时，把在我眼中如此神圣的秘密透露出去的羞耻之感有如逆流般向我袭来。福西特那个禽兽还开起了花园里女孩的玩笑……”

因为沉浸在那段羞耻的回忆当中，华莱士的声音也低沉下来。“我假装没听见他说的是什么，”他说，“然后卡纳比突然管我叫‘小骗子’，我坚持这些都是真的，可他一点都不相信。我说我知道绿门在哪里，十分钟就可以把他们带过去。卡纳比这次已经出乎意料地善良了，他说我必须证明所说的一切，不然就要我好看。卡纳比可曾扭过你的手臂？如果有的话，那恐怕你就能理解我的处境了。我发誓我的故事是真的。当时学校里没有一个人能从卡纳比手中救下一个小屁孩，虽然克罗肖可能替我说了几句好话。卡纳比奸计得逞，我变得越来越激动，面红耳赤，也有点害怕。总体来说，我表现得就像是一个傻不拉叽的小屁孩，而最后结果就是，本该由我独自寻找的魔法花园的计划，变成了由我带领着六个恐吓我的同学一起去。他们既嘲讽，又好奇，而我则是满脸通红、耳根火热、双眼刺痛，灵魂深处饱受痛苦和屈辱的煎熬。”

“我们一直没有找到白墙和绿门……”

“你的意思是？”

“我的意思是我找不到那扇门。如果能的话，我也想找到。可就算是之后我自己一个人去，也找不到。我再也没找到过那扇门。想起来，似乎在我整个中学求学期间，都在找寻那扇门，但我再也没有见过它——再也没有。”

“那帮人——没让你好过吧？”

“卡纳比……那个禽兽，他以我荒唐的谎言为由开了会。我还记得为了不让人看见我满脸泪痕，后来我是如何悄悄回家溜上楼的。但让我哭着入睡的原因并不是卡纳比，而是那花园——我全心向往的那美丽的午后、那可爱友善的女士、那些还在等待着我的玩伴、我想要学会的游戏、遗忘的美丽游戏——我的眼泪是为它们而流的。

“我坚信如果我没有说出去……在那之后好些日子里，我状态都很糟——无数个哭泣的黑夜和心不在焉的白日。足足有两个学期，我松懈下来了，成绩下滑。你还记得吗？你当然记得！因为是你——是你数学成绩打败我这事让我重新开始用功的。”

第三章

我的朋友安静地盯着壁炉中的火苗好一阵子。随后他开口道：“直到我十七岁时，才再次见到那扇门。”

“它第三次赫然出现在我面前——我当时正在去牛津领取奖学金的路上，路过帕丁顿，就瞥了一眼。当时我正把头伸出马车挡板外抽烟，毫无疑问，觉得自己特别老成世故，而突然间，眼前一闪而过的是那扇门和那道墙，那种无法忘怀而又触手可得的珍贵感觉。

“马车咔嗒咔嗒地路过——我也吃了一惊，直到马车走到转弯处才让它停下。随后那一瞬间对我来说特别诡异，我内心陷入了怀疑和挣扎——我敲了敲马车顶的小门，伸出手掏出了怀表。‘是的，先生！’车夫利索地回答。‘呃，好吧，没什么。’我喊道，‘我的错。我们没多少时间了！继续走吧！’然后他继续前行……

“我拿到了奖学金。收到通知的第二天晚上，我回到父亲家，坐在楼上我书房的壁炉前，父亲很罕见地表扬了我，他那些合理的建议在我耳边作响，我抽着最爱的烟斗——青春期陪伴着我的斗牛犬大烟斗——想的却是嵌在白色长墙上的那一扇门。‘如果我停下来了，’我想，‘那肯定就要错过奖学金、错过牛津，把未来的大好前程搅得一团糟！我头脑更加清晰起来！’虽然思绪凝重，但当时我对于为事业牺牲这件事，没有丝毫的怀疑。

“那些亲爱的朋友和明朗的氛围的确对我很好，非常美好，却十分遥远。我的注意力现在专注于这个世界。我看到了另一扇门向我打开——事业的大门。”

他再次凝视着炉火。有那么一瞬间，他的脸庞在红色火光的映照下，露出了一丝丝坚韧的表情，可它随即便消失不见了。

“好吧，”他叹息着说道，“我已经为事业付出了很多。我非常用心地工作，非常努力。但在那之后，我上千次地梦见过那座魔法花园，也看到过那扇门，它至少四次在我面前一闪而过。在好长一段时间里，这个世界的一切看起来是如此光明而有趣，看起来是那么充满意义和可能性，而对比之下，花园日益消减的吸引力让人觉得温和而遥远。谁愿意在赶去和美丽女子、出色男子共进晚餐的途中抚摸美洲豹？我从牛津来到伦敦，必须要成就一番事业以履行我大胆的承诺。事业——当然其中也有失望……”

“我一共谈过两次恋爱——我就不细说了——但有一次和某人约会，我知道她怀疑我是否敢现身，于是我冒险抄了一条近路，那条路在伯爵阁附近，不经常走，可白墙和绿门就在那里出现了。‘奇怪，’我自言自语道，‘可我以为它在坎佩切山。那是我怎么也找不到的地方——就像数巨石阵——那个诡异的白日梦中所出现的场所。’而我心无旁骛地走过了那扇门，那天下午，它对我没有丝毫的吸引力。

“有那么一瞬间，我有股冲动想要试着打开那扇门，最多就是再走三步——虽然心底确信那扇门会为我而开，可我随即意识到这么做就会迟到，而这关乎我的荣誉。之后我情愿自己没准时到达——我至少应该偷偷看一眼花园，向那些美洲豹招招手，但这次我清楚地认识到不应该紧抓着错过的事物不放。是的，那一次让我非常后悔……

“在那之后，我努力工作好多年，一直也没再见过那扇门，直到最近它才再次出现。随之而来的，我感到似乎有一层薄锈蔓延开来，笼罩着我的世界。我开始为再也看不到这扇门而感到悲伤和苦痛。或许是因为我同样也备受超负荷工作量的折磨——或许那就是别人口中的年到四十的感觉。我也不知道。但我所肯定的是，那种让人对努力工作感到轻而易举的强烈愉悦之感已经不复存在，在所有这些新政治趋势发展的时机下，正是我应该努力工作的时候。奇怪，对吧？但生活的确开始让我感到疲惫不堪，而它的回报，当那些回报慢慢变得触手可得时，我觉得它们很廉价。就在不久前，我开始迫切地渴望那个花园。是的——而我又见过它三次。”

“你走进花园了？”

“不——是那扇门！而我并没有进去！”他朝着我的方向靠向桌子，声音里承载着巨大的伤痛，“我有三次机会——三次！如果那门再出现在我面前，我发誓，我会走进去，离开这片尘嚣和嘈杂之地，抛下这枯燥乏味的耀眼虚荣，远离这些劳神费心的徒劳无功。我要走进去，永不回头。这次我会留下……我发誓，可当时机来临——我并没有走进去。”

“这一年中，我有三次路过那扇门的机会，却没能走进去。去年一年有三次。

“第一次是在租户救赎法案的紧急投票之夜，最后以三票多数票保住了政府。你还记得吗？我们这边没人——可能对方也没几个人——预料到当晚的结果。随后的讨论像蛋壳一样分崩离析。我和霍奇基斯当时正和他的表亲在布伦特福德用餐，我俩都没携伴出席。电话一打来，我们立刻开着他表亲的车出发，差点就迟到了。在赶路的时候，经过了我的墙和门——在月光的照耀下一片苍白，刺眼的路灯在墙上投射出一大块炙热的黄斑，但不会错的。‘我的天。’我脱口而出。‘怎么了？’霍奇基斯问道。我回答说：‘没事！’然后就错过了那个时机。

“‘我做出了极大的牺牲。’在进门的时候我告诉党鞭。‘大家都是。’他匆匆走过的时候回答道。

“我不知道当时不这么做还能怎样。第二次机会是在我赶去父亲的床前，去跟这个严厉的老头子告别的时候。那一次也是，在生命的面前，这选择是毋庸置疑的。但第三次不一样，它发生在一周前。光是回忆起来，都让我悔恨不已。我当时和古尔克及拉尔夫在一起——现在已经不是什么秘密了，你知道的，我和古尔克谈过了。我们当时在弗罗比舍用餐，聊得越来越深入。而我在内阁重组当中的位置总游走在我们的话题之间。是的——是的。已经尘埃落定了。虽然还不能对外公布，不过我不认为需要向你保守秘密……是的——非常感谢！非常感谢！但让我继续给你讲我的故事。

“然后，在那个晚上，似乎一切都悬而未决。我的处境有些微妙。我非常迫切地想要从古尔克口中得到确切的答复，但拉尔夫的出现阻碍了这一切。我绞尽脑汁让那晚的对话显得轻松愉快，尽可能不把话题转移到我最关注的地方。我必须如此。拉尔夫随后的表现证实了我的谨慎是正确的。我知道拉尔夫走到肯辛顿大街就会和我们分道扬镳，之后我就可以和古尔克打开天窗说亮话。有时候人必须借助于这种小手段……而正在此时，我眼角的余光瞄见了白墙和绿门，就在路的前方。

“我们聊着天经过了那扇门。我走过了它。直到现在，我还记得古尔克醒目的侧脸所投射出的阴影，他的大礼帽向前倾斜，滑落在挺拔的鼻子上方，我们漫步在街道时，他脖间围了好几层围巾的投影总是走在我和拉尔夫的影子之前。

“路过的时候，我距离那扇门也就二十英寸1的距离。‘如果我跟他们说晚安告别，然后走进门里，’我问自己，‘接下来会发生什么？’而我当时一心想着要和古尔克谈话。在心里被其他问题占据的同时，我没法儿回答这个问题。‘他们会以为我疯了，’我想，‘而假如我现在失踪了——杰出的政治家离奇消失事件！’这影响了我当时的决定。在那紧要关头，各种各样难以想象的尘世间琐事占据了我的思绪。

“随后古尔克转过身，抱歉地笑了笑，缓慢地说：‘我到了！’

1.1英寸约等于2.5厘米。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为译者注。）

“‘我到了！’他重复了一次。而我彻底失去了我的机会。一年中，有三次进入那扇门的机会——那扇引导你走向平静、走向愉悦、走向比梦境更美、走向世上无人知晓之善的大门。而我拒绝了它，雷德蒙，它现在离我而去——”

“你怎么知道？”

“我知道。我就知道。现在我被留下来面对这一切，我曾经有机会离开，当时拖着我后腿的任务把我困在此处。你说我取得了成功——这庸俗、花哨、讨人厌、惹人妒忌的东西。我得到了。”他大手中拿着一个核桃。“如果这就是我的成功……”他说着，把手中的核桃捏碎了，随后把手伸出来让我看。

“让我告诉你吧，雷德蒙。这次的擦肩而过正在摧毁我。过去两个月里，到现在为止快十周了，除去那些必要和紧急的任务，我什么工作都没做。我的灵魂被无法平息的悔恨之感所占据。我在夜晚出门——那时候不太容易被认出来。我在街头游荡。是的，我好奇如果人们知道，会怎么看我。一个内阁大臣，所有部门里最重要的负责人在大街上独自游荡——为一扇门、一座花园默哀——有时候那悲伤过于沉重，似乎都能被听到。”

第四章

直到现在，我才意识到那晚他脸色多么苍白，眼中燃起了我所不熟悉的阴郁火光。今天晚上，他在我眼中是如此鲜活。我坐在这里，回想着他的辞藻、他的语气，而最新一期的《威斯敏斯特公报》还躺在我的沙发上，里面刊登的是他的死讯。今日午餐的时候，俱乐部里人人都关注着他的死讯。除了这个，我们没有探讨任何其他事情。

他们昨天一大早在肯辛顿东站附近的一个深坑里找到了他的尸首。为了连接向南延伸的铁路，工人挖了两个竖井。为了防止公众进入，在大街上用栅墙把坑遮挡起来，在墙上留了一个小门，以便住在另一侧的工人进出。而因为监工交接的失误，这扇门没有锁好，他就是穿过那扇门走了进去。

心中的疑惑和迷思让我心情越发沉重。

看起来他似乎当晚从议院一路走回家——在过去这段会期内，他经常走回家——因此，我猜，那个专注地走在空荡荡的街道上，包裹得严严实实的身影，就是他。是不是车站附近电灯那苍白的光线蒙骗了他，让他误以为粗糙的木板是白色的？是不是那扇致命的、没上锁的门唤醒了某些回忆？

究竟，是否存在着这样一面白墙，墙上嵌着一扇绿门？

我不知道。我一字不漏地把他讲的故事转述出来。有时候我也想相信华莱士不过是一个意外的受害者，被困在幻觉和无心的陷阱之中，这种情况很鲜有，却并不是毫无先例，但这肯定不是我最坚定的信念。如果要这么想的话，你或许认为我很迷信，还很傻，但实际上我更倾向于相信他是真的拥有某种非比寻常的天赋，一种感知力还是什么的，我也说不清楚，可这种感知力以墙和门为幌子，给他提供了一个出口、一个秘密的特别通道，让他可以逃到另一个更美好的世界。无论如何，你或许会说，这种力量最终还是背叛了他。可你确定吗？在那里，你碰触到这些造梦之人内心最深处的秘密，这些人有如此的远见和想象力。这个世界在我们眼中普通而平凡，就像那个栅墙和土坑。以日常准则看来，他走出安全区，走进了黑暗，走进了危险，走进了死亡。

可在他眼中，又是否如此呢？

显微镜下的失误

实验室的窗外湿雾弥漫，桌子对面分别摆放着两盏绿色的瓦斯灯，离得很近，昏黄的光线透着一丝暖意。每张桌子上都放着几个学生们做实验用的玻璃罐，里面装着龙虾、贻贝、青蛙以及豚鼠的残骸。房间另一头的架子正对着窗户，架上存放着解剖体，漂白过后，泡在酒精里。一排精美的解剖图悬挂在架子上方，它们镶嵌在白木框里，架子下方是一列方形的储物柜。实验室的每道门上都嵌着黑板，上面还写着前一天上课留下的部分图解。实验室里除了助教空无一人，他安静地坐在备课室的门附近，偌大空间内，只听见他手中的摇杆切片机在絮絮叨叨、低声细语。环视房内，不少学生曾驻足的痕迹还是四处可见：有手提包若干，亮闪闪的仪器箱数只；在某个角落还有藏在报纸下的巨大画幅；另外还有一册装帧得非常精致的《乌有乡消息》，这本书出现在这样的环境中，显得有些格格不入。学生们都赶着去隔壁的阶梯教室抢占座位，随手把这些东西摆放在桌上。紧闭的大门降低了教授的音量，让他韵律十足的腔调听起来就像是毫无生气的喃喃自语。

不久后，窗外传来了微弱的钟声，教堂的钟敲了十一下。切片机的声音停了下来，助教看了看表，站起身，双手插着口袋，穿过实验室，缓慢地走向阶梯教室的门口。他站在门口听了一会儿，随后眼光落在了一小册威廉·莫里斯的书上。他拿起书，扫了一眼标题，笑着打开书，看了看衬页上的名字，随手翻了几页，然后把书放回桌面。与此同时，阶梯课室内单调的呢喃止住了，屋内突然响起了铅笔摩擦桌面的沙沙声，嘈杂的脚步声和好几个人说话的声音混在一起。紧接着坚定的脚步声渐渐向门口靠近，门打开了，敞在那儿，而刚进来的人们的注意力似乎被依稀传来的发问声所吸引，停住了脚步。

助教转过身，缓慢地走过切片机，穿过备课室的门走出了实验室。在他走出门外的同时，学生们拿着课本一个接着一个从阶梯教室走回实验室，分散着坐在小桌前，有几个站在门口。这是异常混杂的一个群体，因为当牛津和剑桥还在回避不分阶层的教育方式所带来的窘况时，帝国理工学院先于美国，早在好些年前就采用了阶层混合式教学——社会地位也是一视同仁，因为学院声名在外，而奖学金的申请不受任何年龄限制，比那些苏格兰的大学招生范围更广。这个班上一共有二十一名学生，但有的人还留在教室向教授提问，有的赶在黑板擦干净前把上面的图示抄下来，还有人在仔细查看教授为了演示课专门准备的标本。走进实验室的九名学生中，有三位女生，其中一位是身材娇小的漂亮女生，她戴着眼镜，衣服是灰绿色的，正盯着窗外的浓雾。其余两位都是看起来健健康康的女生，相貌平平，纷纷解开卷好的围裙，穿在身上。这种棕色的亚麻围裙是解剖时穿的。男生中，有两位直接走到他们在实验室的座位上，其中一位以前是名裁缝，苍白的脸上长着一圈深色的胡子；另一位体格健硕的年轻人二十出头，面色红润，穿着合身的棕色西装——小韦德伯恩，是眼科医生韦德伯恩的儿子。其他几个人在课室门附近挤作一团。一个戴眼镜的小矮子驼着背，坐在横木凳上；另外两位，一个是矮个子、肤色深的年轻人，另一位年轻人长着亚麻色的头发，肤色红彤彤的，他倚在板岩水槽旁；而第四个人面对着大家，是这群人中的主要发言人。

最后一个人名叫希尔，这个身体结实的年轻小伙子，和韦德伯恩年纪相仿，他肤色很白，眼珠是深灰色的，发色说不上来，五官立体，不太对称。他说话声音大于常人，双手深深地插在口袋里，衣领上有磨痕，还有粗心的洗衣女工上浆后留下的蓝色痕迹，他的衣服明显是成衣，靴子靠近脚趾的地方还有一块补丁。当他发表意见或是倾听别人讲话时，时不时地向阶梯教室的门口张望。他们在讨论今天刚上完的那节动物学入门课程，如此冗长，多么让人绝望。“高等脊椎动物的目标是从一个卵子到另一个卵子……”讲师语气忧郁地说着，同时把他画了好久的对比解剖学图画完了。戴眼镜的驼背大声重复了一次，语气中充满了欣赏，并把话题丢向了一头秀发的学生，态度明显带着挑衅。随后便开始了那种含糊不清的讨论，不用说，像这种漫无边界的讨论，相信对全世界的学生来说都非常的熟悉。

“或者，这就是我们的目标——我承认，至少从科学的角度来说，”这是一头秀发的学生对挑衅的回应，“但总有什么是凌驾在科学之上的。”

“科学，”希尔信心十足地说，“是系统的知识。一切系统外的概念，无论如何，肯定是不靠谱的。”只有当听众把他的话当回事，他才能确定这话说得到底是高明还是愚蠢。

“我所不能理解的是，”驼背随意说道，“希尔究竟是不是唯物主义者。”

“有一样东西是凌驾于物质之上的，”希尔觉得这次能够更加清楚地表明自己的立场，同时也意识到有人在门背后，于是为了引起她的注意稍稍提高了音量，他迅速回答道，“那就是妄想有什么可以凌驾于物质之上。”

“所以我们终于听完你的传教了。”俊美的学生说，“我们对高于畜生的生活方式的渴求，我们对高于自身的一切所付出的努力，这所有一切都是妄想，是吧？但看看你是多么前后不一。比如说你的社会主义，为什么还要浪费时间关心种族？为什么还要为生活在贫民窟的乞丐费心？为什么还要自找麻烦把那本书，”他用头指了指威廉·莫里斯的书，“借给实验室的所有人？”

“女生来了。”驼背含糊地嘟囔了一句，紧张地向后瞄了一眼。

那个女孩穿着褐色的衣服，眼睛也是褐色的，她走进实验室，站在桌子的另一侧，也就是驼背身边，一手拿着卷好的围裙，转头听着大家的讨论。她没注意到驼背的存在，因为她的视线游走于希尔以及和他对话的人之间。希尔刻意忽略她的存在，这暴露了自己对她的出现有多在意，女孩读懂了这一点，感到非常满意。“我不需要理由，”他说，“就因为一个人知道没有任何事物凌驾于物质之上，也不期待自己长命百岁，他就要活得像畜生？”

“为什么不呢？”一头秀发的学生问道。

“为什么要呢？”希尔回答。

“那他的奖赏是什么？”

“你们这些信教的人，对你们来说一切都和奖赏有关。难道一个人就不能接受公义，为公义而存在吗？”

现场安静了一会儿，随后秀发男挣扎着用简单的词凑数以争取时间：“但——你看——奖赏——当我说奖赏的时候……”然后驼背突然插入的问题拯救了他。驼背的问题在辩论界是臭名昭著的，因为他的问题总是一个花样——要求对方下定义。“这就是你对公义的定义？”这就是驼背当时的问题。

希尔突然失去了回答这个问题的自信，不过虽然对方把问题丢出来了，可实验室助教布鲁克斯的出现救了场，他提着一批刚宰杀的豚鼠后腿。“这是这节课最后一批材料。”之前一直没开口的年轻人说道。布鲁克斯走向实验室前方，随手把豚鼠丢在每张桌子上。班上其他学生在远处闻到了豚鼠的味道，纷纷从阶梯教室挤回实验室，之前的讨论戛然而止，本来没坐在自己位子上的学生匆忙赶回去抢占实验样品。挂在圈上的钥匙咯咯作响，有人打开了储物柜拿出了解剖器材。希尔本来就站在自己座位旁边，他的解剖刀伸到了口袋外面。褐衣女子向前走了一步，靠着他的桌子，温柔地说：“你看到我把书还给你了吧，希尔先生？”

整个过程中，在希尔的意识里，女孩和书的存在是如此之清晰，可他笨拙地假装自己刚看到那本书。“噢，是的，”他边说边拿起书，“我知道了，你喜欢这本书吗？”

“有时间的话，我想请教你几个关于这本书的问题。”

“当然没问题，”希尔说，“这是我的荣幸。”他尴尬地停顿了一下。

“你喜欢这本书吗？”他问道。

“这本书很精彩。只是有的部分我不太理解。”

突然间，实验室响起了一阵古怪刺耳的声音，随后彻底安静下来。是助教，他已经走到黑板前，准备开始指导当日的解剖。他习惯于使用这种介乎于普通交媾时所发出的“呃”和喇叭发出的巨大声响之间的某种声音来让学生闭嘴。褐衣女子溜回自己的座位，就在希尔的正前方。希尔立刻忽略了她的存在，从桌子抽屉里拿出了笔记本，快速翻开本子，从口袋里拔出一支短胖的铅笔，准备以海量的笔记记录下助教接下来要做的示范。对于大学里的学生来说，示范和讲座是他们神圣而不可侵犯的教材。除了教授的书之外，你可以，甚至最好忽略其他教材。

希尔的父亲是兰德波特的修鞋匠，一次偶然的机会，政府下达给兰德波特技术学院的蓝皮书，让希尔拿到了奖学金。他靠着每周一几尼的零用钱留在了伦敦，发现只要精打细算，这笔钱也足够支付他的置装费——偶尔买个防水衣领，还有像墨水、针线这种城市男士生活的必需品。他第一年和第一学期就是这么过下来的，而黝黑的老头子在兰德波特几处酒馆，因为吹嘘自己的儿子是“教授”而遭到了当地人的厌恶。希尔是个精力旺盛的年轻人，他内心深处暗暗蔑视着所有宗教的神职人员，胸怀着重建世界的远大志向。在他看来，获得奖学金是一次非常好的机会。他七岁就开始读书，自那时起一直坚持着，对于身边能够接触到的书籍，无论好坏都来者不拒。他为人处世的经验仅限于波特西岛，主要是靴子批发工厂。十七岁离开寄宿学校后，他每天都在那儿上班。在演讲方面，他有着很大的天赋，并且已经得到了大学辩论社的认可，集会每次都在楼下冶金学教室碾压机和矿石模型的包围下召开，你可以从希尔每次站起来讲话时，对方拍打课桌的疯狂程度中看得出其他人对他的表现的肯定。而他正处于那个特别让人激动人心的年龄，此时的人生在羊肠小道尽头豁然开朗，就好像这一整片山谷都任其支配，未来等待着他的都是神奇的新发现和巨大的成就。除了知道自己不会拉丁语和法语之外，希尔对于自己的局限一无所知。

一开始，他的兴趣点平均地分配在学校的生物学和构建社会学和神学理论上，他十分热衷于这项工作。夜幕降临的时候，如果大博物馆的图书馆没开门，他就坐在切尔西家中的床上，穿着外套、围着围巾，誊写讲座的笔记、背诵解剖备忘录，直到索普在屋外吹起口哨——房东太太拒绝为阁楼租户的访客开门——他们俩接下来一同游走于街头，那街道在煤气灯的照射下忽明忽暗，他们几乎是照本宣科，按着刚学会的方式聊着上帝的旨意、公义、卡莱尔以及社会重组。而在所有的过程中，希尔有时赞成索普，有时赞成某个随便经过的路人的观点，但当浓妆艳抹的女性若有所思地看着他走过时，他的思绪也不免为之所动，一时迷乱，失去论点。科学和公义！但这些日子里，有那么一两次征兆，似乎他的生活中出现了第三个让他产生兴趣的事。他发现自己的注意力会从中胚层体节的命运或是胚乳的可能意义上，时不时地，游移到坐在自己前排的褐眼女孩身上。

她是自费学生，光是和他说话，她已是纡尊降贵。一想到她从小到大所接受的教育、所获得的成就，希尔的灵魂就开始感到煎熬。她第一次和希尔说话是因为兔子的翼蝶骨上有她搞不懂的地方，而这使他发现，至少在生物上，不需要自我贬低。自那以后，他们就像所有年轻人一样，随便开个头就能继续闲聊下去，而当希尔在社会主义的问题上攻击她时——本能告诉他不要直接攻击她的宗教信仰——而她则下决心，说服自己去担负起提高他审美品位的重任。她比他大一两年，虽然这对希尔来说，从来都不是问题。在《乌有乡消息》后，他们就开始频繁地把书借给彼此。希尔有个荒谬的首要原则，他从来不在诗歌上“浪费时间”，这对她来说可是很可怕的缺陷。有天在午餐的时候，她偶然撞见希尔躲在放骨架的小博物馆里吃小圆面包——这基本就是他每日的午餐，在这样的情况下被她撞见让他感到十分尴尬。难得有机会独处，她转身走出去，不一会儿，神秘兮兮地拿着一卷勃朗宁回来借给他。他侧着身子面对着她，笨手笨脚地接过了书，因为另一只手还拿着面包。事后想起来，他的语气没能像他所希望表现出来的那么愉悦爽朗。

这一切发生在比较解剖学的考试后，也是学校对外开放的最后一天，在这之后，在圣诞假期前，学校会清理所有在校生，仔细锁好校园。为了用功准备第一学期期末考试，希尔发愤图强地复习，注意力暂时从其他兴趣点上转移开来。在所有人都乐此不疲地预测这次考试以及接下来将要进行的两次考试成绩的时候，他惊奇地发现，没人认为他有竞争哈维纪念勋章的潜力。一直以来，韦德伯恩基本上默默无闻地生活在希尔认知的最边缘地带，也该轮到他以竞争对手的身份登场了。索普和希尔达成协议，在考试前的三周，不再出去夜游。而房东太太指出，以这么低的房价，她无法提供更多的灯油。于是希尔拿着帮助记忆的小纸条，往返行走于学校与住处之间，纸条上列着小龙虾的附肢、兔子的头骨还有脊椎动物的神经体统。而他也成为让反向行人十分头疼的一号人物。

可诗歌和褐眼女孩自然而然地占据了整个圣诞假期。尚未公布的考试成绩变得不再那么重要，希尔甚至为他父亲的激动而感到惊讶。

就算他想学习比较解剖学，这些书在兰德波特也无处可借，而他太穷了，也买不起新书，但图书馆里囤积了大量诗歌，这充分地满足了希尔的需求。他让自己沉浸于朗费罗和丁尼生流畅的诗篇之中，在莎士比亚身上感受到了勇气，在蒲柏身上找到了似曾相识的灵魂，在雪莱身上见识到了大师的水平，他甚至还浅尝辄止地读了伊莱莎·库克[1]和希曼太太[2]的诱人辞藻。但他没有读勃朗宁其他的作品，因为他希望回到伦敦后能够继续向希丝曼小姐借阅。

他从住处走到学校，亮闪闪的黑包里装着一卷勃朗宁，满脑子都是和诗歌相关的好话。的确，他构思好了聊天的开场白，还打好了最后用于表达对返校的欣喜的腹稿。以伦敦的标准来说，这个早晨格外怡人，可以清晰地看到厚厚的霜冻和湛蓝的天空，薄雾轻轻地勾勒出世间万物的轮廓，一缕缕阳光洒落在街区间，在向阳那侧的街道上渲染出了琥珀色和金色。到了学校大堂，他摘下手套，手指冻得太僵，以至于他在签名那一栏写出来的，是一条颤抖的黑线。他觉得希丝曼小姐应该就在附近。转身面向楼梯时，他发现在楼梯下面围了一群人，挣扎着挤在通告栏前。这估计就是生物考试的排名。那一刻，他忘记了勃朗宁和希丝曼小姐，加入到人群当中，向中间挤去。终于，在脸快被站在上层楼梯的人的袖子挤扁之时，他看到了排名表——

一等

H.J.萨默思·韦德伯恩

威廉·希尔

随后紧接着是二等成绩的学生，目前这不在我们所关心的范围之内。以他一贯的风格，希尔根本没浪费时间去查看索普在物理班的排名，他退出拥挤的人群，陷入了一种奇怪的情绪当中，这种情绪介乎比普通二等生感到更骄傲和输给韦德伯恩的巨大失落感之间，他带着这种情绪走上了楼。上去后，他在楼道里挂好了自己的大衣，动物学的助教对他表达了衷心的祝贺，这位年轻的助教来自牛津，在此之前，他私下里认为希尔是那种最糟糕的无赖混混。

希尔在实验室门口停顿了几秒，喘了口气，随后推门而入。他的目光穿过实验室，看到五位女学生站在一起，韦德伯恩——之前沉默寡言的韦德伯恩优雅地靠在窗边，把玩着窗帘的流苏，很明显在和那五位女生聊天。好吧，希尔或许能够有勇气，甚至是有些霸气地和一个女生聊天，或者也能在满满一屋的女生面前演讲，但像韦德伯恩这样从容地站在一群女生面前享受谈话、掌握局面、机智应答，希尔知道自己是做不到的。走上楼梯的时候，他对韦德伯恩的态度还是比较慷慨的，或许还带有一丝钦佩，他愿意真心诚意地在大家面前和他握手，就像两人只是结束了第一回合对决那样。但在圣诞节前，韦德伯恩从来没有走到实验室的那一头去聊天。希尔那一丝模糊的兴奋情绪转瞬即逝，快速地变成了对韦德伯恩明显的嫌恶。也可能是因为他的表情产生了变化。当他走近韦德伯恩时，韦德伯恩漫不经心地向希尔点头示意，其他人转身看了一眼。希丝曼小姐的视线投向了希尔，两人眼神稍作碰撞，很快又错开了。“韦德伯恩先生，我无法认同你的说法。”她说。

“我必须要恭喜你的一等成绩，希尔先生。”戴眼镜穿绿衣服的女生转过身，笑容满面地对他说道。

“这没什么。”希尔回答的时候，眼神一直没离开在旁聊天的韦德伯恩和希丝曼小姐，他迫切地想听他们在聊些什么。

“我们这些可怜的二等生可不这么认为啊。”戴眼镜的女生说。

韦德伯恩在说什么？好像是和威廉·莫里斯有关。希尔没有继续回答戴眼镜的女生，脸上的笑容也渐渐消失了。他听不清楚，于是也找不到加入谈话的时机。该死的韦德伯恩！他坐下来，打开包，犹豫了一下是否应该当着全班人的面，立刻把勃朗宁还回去，最后还是决定放弃，取而代之，他拿出了下堂课的笔记本，接下来要上的是基础植物学，这门课是短期课程，二月份就结束了。与此同时，一个肥硕的男人从阶梯教室走进来，穿过实验室，他面带微笑，边走边搓着双手，看起来和蔼可亲。这个肤色白皙、眼珠淡蓝的男人名叫宾顿，是植物学的教授，他从克佑来，上一、二月份的课。

在接下来的六个星期里，希尔体验到了一种快速而异常复杂的情感成长。大多数情况下，他的注意力主要集中在韦德伯恩身上——希丝曼小姐没看出这一点。她告诉希尔（因为博物馆相对来说比较隐蔽，她在那里和希尔聊了很多关于社会主义、勃朗宁还有其他方面的话题）自己在一个熟人家碰到过韦德伯恩，而他“继承了父亲的聪明才智，因为你知道，他的父亲是位出色的眼科医生”。

“我父亲是鞋匠。”希尔回答说，这两者并没有什么关联，可从他的语气中，你能感觉到他的自尊心在作祟。但他那一闪而过的嫉妒没有让她感到不适，她能够想象得到这种情绪源自何方。他从韦德伯恩身上痛苦地感受到了不公，也意识到了自己的缺陷。这个韦德伯恩，他选了一个杰出的男人当父亲，而这个优势不会让他丢分，反而对他来说是公义的。而当希尔只能在实验室的豚鼠残肢前笨拙地和希丝曼小姐搭话时，这个韦德伯恩，已经背着他攀入了她的社交圈，恐怕还能和希丝曼小姐用高雅的上层语言交谈，希尔或许也听得懂他们的对话，但自己绝对无法使用这样的语言。当然，他也并不想使用这种语言。而对于希尔来说，像韦德伯恩这样，每天穿着合身的西服、别着崭新的袖扣、梳着整齐的发型，完美地出现在学校，这本身，就是一种粗鲁的、轻蔑的行为。此外，韦德伯恩最初鬼鬼崇崇假装低调、假装谦虚的状态，让希尔幻想着自己理所当然能成为今年的头号人物，之后突然之间一跃而起，以这种方式毫无节制地膨胀，这种行径太过于鬼鬼祟祟。除此之外，韦德伯恩还越发表现出对希丝曼小姐的兴趣，无论她出现在哪个讨论组，他都试图加入，冒着风险找准一切时机，表达对社会主义和无神论的诋毁。他以类似某类领袖人物的个性——简洁、肤浅以及超高效率——刺激着希尔，让他变得失去理智，直到最后，希尔就像恨萧伯纳优雅的自负、恨威廉·莫里斯限量奢华的墙纸以及恨沃尔特·克兰对于工人阶级匪夷所思的看法一样，仇恨起韦德伯恩来。

实验室的研讨在上个学期还是希尔大放光彩的时刻，现在却变得危险起来，沦落成和韦德伯恩之间毫不体面的斗争，希尔之所以坚持下来，是因为他产生了这事关自己荣誉的奇怪想法。至于在辩论社，希尔清楚地认识到，伴随着雷鸣般的拍桌声，他可以轻而易举地战胜韦德伯恩。只是韦德伯恩并没有给他在辩论社击垮自己的机会——他“用餐很晚”——多么恶心做作！

你一定不能认为所有这一切都以如此低级的状态呈现在希尔的认知当中，他天生喜欢概括总结。韦德伯恩在他眼中并不是一个独立的障碍物，而是一类人，是一个阶层突出的那一角。经济学理论经过了发酵，在希尔的脑中已经形成固有姿态，在现实中变得异常具体。这个世界中到处充斥着像韦德伯恩这样轻慢、优雅、衣着高雅、口若悬河的人，姓韦德伯恩的主教、国会议员、教授还有地主们，他们都用着腐朽的洗指碗，引述着强劲辩手们所使用的警句式遁词。在希尔的想象中，任何衣冠不整、装扮邋遢的人，从鞋匠到车夫，都亲如兄弟，是受苦受难的同胞。于是他仿佛成为底层阶级和被压迫人士的拥护者，尽管表面看起来他只是个我行我素的粗鲁年轻人，而且还是个不太成功的拥护者。在下午茶时，一次又一次的小冲突已经开始让女学生丢下希尔一个人在那儿红着脸、发脾气，而辩论社也注意到希尔的讲话中出现了挖苦式嘲讽的新特质。

现在你就能明白，如果是为了人类利益，希尔在下一次考试中击垮韦德伯恩，并且在希丝曼小姐眼中把他比下去，是多么有必要的。而且你或许也能察觉，希丝曼小姐误入了某种常见的女性的认知误区。因为韦德伯恩以一种低调的方式应对希尔掩藏不住的敌意，这场希尔和韦德伯恩的争执成为对她无尽魅力的颂词——她就是这场充斥着手术刀和粗短铅笔的竞赛之中的绝世佳人。让希丝曼小姐的密友私下感到为难的是，这甚至让她良心不安，因为她是个好女孩，通过拉斯金和当代小说痛苦地认识到，男人所有的行为都是由女性的态度决定的。而如果万一希尔从未向她提及“爱情”这个话题，她也只会认为他避而不谈，只不过是因为过于害羞。

紧接着，第二次考试马上就要到了，希尔越发苍白的面容证实了他在发奋学习的谣言。你能在肯辛顿南站附近的加气面包[3]店里看到他，掰着面包，小口地啜着牛奶，眼睛一直没有离开过面前那张记着密密麻麻笔记的纸张。在卧室的镜子周围，他贴满了芽和茎的提示，在洗手池上，如果肥皂没有遮挡的时候，有一张图表可供阅读。他缺席了几次辩论社的聚会，但他还是挤出了和希丝曼小姐碰面的时间，有时在附近宽敞的艺术博物馆里，有时在学校楼上的小博物馆里，更平常的是在学校走廊，这里更安静，不容易受到打扰。他们还特别喜欢在靠近艺术图书馆的一个小画廊里见面，里面到处是铸铁箱子和门。在那里，希尔在她崇拜的眼神鼓励下，谈论着勃朗宁还有自己的雄心壮志。她在他身上发现了一个非比寻常的特质，那就是他一点也不贪婪。他冷静地深思熟虑过，自己未来可以靠年收入一百镑过活。但他立志要出名，在被自己的同类认可的同时，要把世界变得更好。他以布拉德劳和约翰·伯恩斯为领袖和榜样，这两位都是穷困潦倒的伟人。但希丝曼小姐认为这样的生活在审美方面是有缺陷的，虽然她没意识到，但她所指的是美丽的墙纸和室内装潢、精致的书本、优雅的服装、演唱会以及精心准备的食物和恭敬的服务。

最后，第二次考试终于到来了，植物学教授是个挑剔认真的人，他把所有书桌都重新排放在一个狭长的实验室里，为的是防止抄袭。他在桌子上放了把椅子，让自己的助教坐在上面（据助教自己说，坐在上面感觉像个印度神明），这样就能够看到任何作弊的人。他还在门口贴了一张“此门不通”的告示，可根本没什么人能看得到那张告示。整个早上，从十点到下午一点，韦德伯恩的奋笔疾书——手中鹅毛笔摩擦纸张所发出的尖锐响声，就是对希尔的挑衅，教室里的其他人也不屈不挠地追赶着这两个领军人物。随后就到了下午，韦德伯恩比往常安静了一些，而希尔的双颊一整天下来都是滚烫的。他外套口袋塞满了前一分钟还在复习的课本和笔记本。第二天早上和下午都是实操考试，有一门是切片，另外一门是读玻片。希尔早上很郁闷，因为他知道自己切片切得太厚，而神秘的玻片就是在下午出现的。

这是植物学教师一直做的事情。就像报收入税一样，它提供了作弊的诱惑。这是个放在显微镜下的标本，一个小玻片，用金属压夹片固定在显微镜的载物台上，而按照规定不能移动这个玻片。每个学生轮流上去，把看到的画下来，在本子上写下自己认为正确的答案，然后回到自己的座位。好吧，如果有人手指不小心动了一下，在那一瞬间，就有可能移动整个玻片。教授之所以命令大家不能移动玻片，是因为他想让大家辨认的是某种树茎的特征。按照他所摆放的位置，很难认出这是什么植物，可是一旦移动了玻片，看到里面其他的部分后，它的属性就一目了然了。

希尔走过来，上一门考试中和染色试剂的一番搏斗让他满脸通红。他坐在了显微镜前的小凳子上，移动反光镜寻找最佳光线。随后，只是个习惯性动作，他移动了玻片。他立刻想起来这是禁止的，于是紧接着立刻用手把玻片推了回去，他被自己的行为吓了一跳，坐在那儿一动也不敢动。

随后，他缓缓地转过头。教授在考场外，助教高坐在临时搭建的“神坛”上，读着科学期刊，其他考生背对着他，忙着答题。他是否应该坦白交代这次意外？他现在清楚地知道那个玻片上是什么，这个分类鉴定标本是皮孔，取自接骨木树。他的目光徘徊于专心答题的同学身上，突然之间，韦德伯恩转过头以一种奇怪的眼神瞄了他一眼。让希尔在过去这两天保持着士气高昂状态的精神亢奋突然被奇怪的精神压力取而代之。写答案的本子放在身边，他没有在上面写下答案，但他一边单眼看着显微镜，一边潦草地把看到的东西画下来。突然之间，关于道德规范的怪诞难题在他脑海中翻江倒海。他到底应该写出答案，还是把这个问题的答案空出来？可如果这样的话，韦德伯恩在第二次考试中恐怕也还会排在第一。他现在怎么知道如果没移动玻片的话，自己是不是能认出里面的东西？当然，韦德伯恩也有可能认不出来。可假如他也移动了玻片呢？他抬头看了看表，还有十五分钟去做最后决定。他收起答题本和画答案用的彩色铅笔，走回到自己的座位上。

他把自己的答案从头到尾检查了一遍，然后坐在那儿思索着，啃着自己的指节。如果现在才跳出来承认，看起来会显得可疑。他必须要打败韦德伯恩。于是他忘记了像约翰·伯恩斯和布拉德劳那样耀眼绅士的榜样。而且在他看来，这种瞥见玻片其余部分的行为毕竟只是场意外，这是强加在他身上的，更像是上天的旨意而并非不公平待遇。对他来说，利用这个机会也并不见得是那么不诚实，因为像布鲁姆就相信祷告的作用，他每天都在祈祷着能够拿到第一名。“还有五分钟。”助教一边说，一边折起文章，开始仔细巡视考场。希尔盯着时钟，直到指针走到还剩两分钟交卷时，他打开答题本，两耳通红、佯装镇定地在画好的皮孔旁边写上了名称。

当第二次考试成绩公布后，韦德伯恩和希尔的排名和上一次对调了。认识助教的穿绿衣服戴眼镜的女生（助教私底下也是个普通人）告诉大家，两次考试成绩加一起，在满分是200分的情况下，希尔得了167分，以一分领先于166分的韦德伯恩。在某种意义上，每个人都很佩服希尔，虽然怀疑自己“夺取别人成绩”的想法萦绕在他心头。而且希尔慢慢地发现，无论是别人的恭喜还是希丝曼小姐对他好感加剧，甚至是韦德伯恩在如日中天时明显下滑的地位，都被那不开心的回忆给玷污了。一开始，他感到全身上下充满了能量，辩论词中再次出现了民主主义迈向胜利的语句。他把大量的热情和精力投入在对比解剖学上，也在继续提升自己的审美修养。但在这一切背后，他脑海中不断地出现这个清晰的画面——一个移动了玻片的卑鄙小人。

没有一个人看到那一幕，而他也确信没有神圣的力量能看到他的所作所为，但尽管如此，他还是很担心。记忆并不是死物，而是有生命的，如果不再碰触，它们会慢慢褪色，可如果时常为之懊恼，它们会茁壮成长成各种可疑的形态。奇怪的是，虽然当时他清楚地意识到移动玻片只是一个意外，可随着时间的流逝，他的记忆开始变得混乱，直到最后，他无法确定——虽然他向自己保证是确定的——移动玻片究竟是否是完全下意识的动作。当然，很有可能希尔的饮食习惯也导致了这种病态的自责。他早餐一般都吃得很草率，午饭吃个面包，为了方便，晚上进餐一般在五点之后，肉的选择由他的收入决定，通常是在远离布朗普顿主路的后街里面的一个小餐馆里解决。偶尔，他犒劳自己，来一份三便士或者九便士的经典套餐，而通常端上来的时候，碟子里不是缺点土豆就是少点排骨。这种自我厌恶的爆发和情绪的复苏，毫无疑问和那段时间生活上物资的匮乏有明显的关系。而抛开这对情绪的影响不算，还有就是兰德波特鞋匠——希尔那亵渎神祇的父亲，在他对希尔从儿时起反反复复的暴力教育和语言灌输下，希尔对虚伪深恶痛绝。对于公开宣称自己是无神论者的人，我有一样很确定，那就是他们很可能（通常）都是傻瓜，神经大条，喜欢谩骂神职机构，说话蛮不讲理，是爱捉弄人的恶棍，但他们通常都不善于撒谎。如果他们不是这样，如果他们哪怕能做到有一丝丝的妥协，大概也就变成了自由派教徒。此外，这段记忆还破坏了他对希丝曼小姐的感情。因为比起韦德伯恩，她现在非常明显更喜欢希尔，希尔也确信自己喜欢她，于是开始以腼腆的敬慕方式来回报她对自己的关心。有一次他甚至买了一把紫罗兰，装在口袋里带到铸铁画廊，支支吾吾地解释着把花献给她，而花儿早已凋零枯萎。这记忆同样妨碍了他对于资本家不忠行为的谴责，这一直以来都是他生活的一大乐趣。而最后，它还侵蚀了击败韦德伯恩所带来的喜悦。在此之前，他一直自以为比韦德伯恩高尚，而内心燃起怒火仅仅是因为想要得到认可。现在他开始苦恼，偷偷怀疑这一切是不是源于自卑作祟。他幻想着能从勃朗宁的作品中找到对自己目前情况的辩解，但它们在分析过后就烟消云散了。终于——诡异的是，他被当初让他做出不诚实举动的相同动力所打动——他去找宾登教授，向他坦白了整个事件。因为希尔不是自费学生，宾登教授并没有招呼他坐下，他就这样站在教授的书桌前坦白了一切。

“这件事太奇怪了。”宾登教授说，随后缓慢地意识到自己对这件事的态度，怒火渐渐燃烧起来，“这件事实在太让人震惊了。我不明白你为何会做出这样的事，而我也不明白你为什么要坦白。你是那种学生……剑桥人做梦也不敢……我应该早点想到……你为什么要作弊？”

“我没有作弊。”希尔回答说。

“但你刚刚才告诉我你作弊了。”

“我以为我解释清楚了……”

“你要不就是作弊了，要不就是没有作弊……”

“我说了我的动作是无意识的。”

“我不是个形而上学者，我是科学——也就是事实——的仆人。你得到的命令是不要移动那个玻片。而你的确移动了玻片。如果这不是作弊的话……”

“如果我想作弊”，希尔的声音变得歇斯底里起来，“我为什么要来这里向你坦白？”

“你的忏悔为你挽回了一点，”宾登教授说，“但这并不能改变最初的真相。”

“的确不能，先生。”希尔彻底向自卑举旗投降。

“现在你甚至带来了很大的麻烦。考试排名必须要修正。”

“我想是的，先生。”

“你想是的？当然必须修正。而我不认为我的良心能够过得去，让你通过这次考试。”

“不让我通过？”希尔问，“要给我不及格？”

“这是所有考试的规定。不然我们还能怎么样？你还能期待什么？你不是想逃避自己的所作所为带来的后果吧？”

“我以为，或者……”希尔紧接着说，“让我挂科？我以为，如果我告诉你，你只会把玻片那一题的分数给扣掉。”

“这是不可能的！”宾登说，“而且，扣掉那题的分，你还是排在韦德伯恩前面。只是把那个分扣了？简直荒谬！学院规章制度明确地指出……”

“但我是自己坦白的，先生。”

“规章制度说，无论是什么原因或者以什么方式发现这种行为，他们只不过提供——”

“这会毁了我的，如果我这次考试不及格，他们就不会续发我的奖学金了。”

“你之前就应该想到这一点。”

“但先生，考虑到我的处境……”

“我什么也考虑不了。在这所学校里，教授也只是机器。规章制度甚至不让我们给学生推荐职位。我只是个机器，而你已经让我开始运转了。我必须这么做……”

“这太严苛了，先生。”

“可能是吧。”

“如果我这次考试没法儿通过，那我不如直接回家算了。”

“这就要由你自己考虑清楚了。”宾登的语气软了一点。他意识到自己有点不公平，假如他不是自相矛盾的话，他的确想要改正。“从个人而言，”他说，“我认为你的坦白能够大大地减轻你的过错。但你已经开启了这个机器，现在它只能尽自己的本分。我，我真的很抱歉你把真相说出来了。”

一波强烈的情绪让希尔说不出话来。突然之间，他清晰地看到兰德波特的老鞋匠——他父亲——布满皱纹的脸庞。“我的天！我太蠢了！”他突然之间激动地说道。

“我希望，”宾登说，“这能够让你吸取教训。”

但，诡异的是，他们脑海中所谓的教训，根本不是一回事。

随后两人都没说话。

“我希望能够考虑一下，先生，之后我会告诉你我的决定——我的意思是，关于回不回家。”希尔边说边走向门口。

第二天，希尔没来上课。穿绿衣服戴眼镜的女生一如既往地抢先得到了消息。她说起这件事的时候，韦德伯恩和希丝曼小姐正在探讨诗乐协会会员的表演。

“你们听说了吗？”她问。

“听说什么？”

“上次考试抓到了作弊。”

“作弊？”韦德伯恩的脸突然红了起来，“怎么会？”

“那个玻片……”

“有人动了？不可能！”

“就是有人动了，那个我们不能动的玻片……”

“一派胡言！”韦德伯恩说，“为什么？他们怎么能发现？他们知道是谁……？”

“是希尔先生。”

“希尔！”

“希尔先生！”

“不，肯定不是那个纯洁的希尔吧？”韦德伯恩慢慢恢复正常。

“我不相信。”希丝曼小姐说，“你是怎么知道的？”

“我之前不知道，”戴眼镜的女生说，“但是现在我知道这是真的。希尔先生自己去宾登教授那儿坦白了。”

“我的天哪！”韦德伯恩说，“偏偏是希尔。不过我一直都不太信得过这些原则上的博爱主义……”

“你敢肯定？”希丝曼小姐呼吸急促地问。

“非常确定。这太可怕了，不是吗？但你知道，不然你以为呢？他父亲是个鞋匠。”

随后希丝曼小姐把戴眼镜的女生吓了一跳。

“我不在乎。我是不会相信的。”她柔和的肤色变得越来越红。“除非他自己当面告诉我，否则我不会相信的。就算那样，我也不太能相信。”然后她突然转身背对着戴眼镜的女生，走回到自己的座位去了。

“但这还是真的。”戴眼镜的女生说，微笑着盯着韦德伯恩。

但韦德伯恩没有回答。她似乎注定是那一类人——说出来的话，总是让人没有回答的欲望。

[1] 伊莱莎·库克，生于1818年12月24日，英国女诗人、作家，支持女性政治自由。

[2] 即菲利西亚·海曼斯，生于1793年9月25日，英国女诗人。

[3] 用二氧化碳充气面团制成的面包。

明天

在海港小镇科尔布鲁克，汉格伯船长的名声并不好。他本是外乡人，去该地定居的动机，虽荒诞不经，却根本谈不上神秘。毕竟，当初，他很爱对人说起自己为何去该地。此外，汉格伯船长显然有些小钱，因为他买下一块地，雇人用黄砖匆匆盖起两栋难看的简陋小屋：一栋自住，一栋租给乔赛亚·卡尔维。瞎子卡尔维曾是造船工人，现已退休，因对家人专横跋扈而臭名昭著。

这两栋小屋有一堵共同的墙，前后院子分别以铁栅栏和木篱笆相隔。贝茜·卡尔维小姐理直气壮地在那道木篱笆上晾晒擦拭茶具用的茶巾、蓝色的破旧衣服或围裙，仿佛这是她的正当权利。

“贝茜啊，我的孩子，这会使木头腐烂的。”每次撞见贝茜行使此项“特权”，汉格伯船长都会隔着木篱笆，和蔼地提醒。

贝茜个子高挑，而木篱笆低矮，所以她能将胳膊肘支到木篱笆上。其双手因刚洗了东西而变得通红，但小臂白皙且匀称。她一言不发地注视着房东，沉默中透着理解、期待与渴望。

“这会使木头腐烂的。”汉格伯船长重复了一遍，接着说，“我发现这是你唯一一个浪费而粗心的习惯。为什么不在后院拉一根晾衣绳呢？”

对此，卡尔维小姐不做任何回应，只是不以为然地摇摇头。她那边的狭小后院里，有几处以石块垒就、里面是黑土的小花坛。她抽空栽种的那些普通花儿，不知怎的，生机盎然，十分繁茂，仿佛长在热带。木篱笆另一侧，却杂草蔓生。挺拔而硬朗的汉格伯船长，经常从齐膝高的草丛中突然冒出来，从头到脚以一号厚篷帆布蔽体——用这种材料制衣，实在出人意外，而一有谁对此发表意见，他就嘟哝着回道：“暂时凑合一下。”那身行头的颜色和粗粝梆硬的质地，使他整个人看上去，犹如毛糙的花岗石雕像，矗立在荒芜已久、小得连像样的台球室都做不了的院子里。这尊“石像”身材魁梧；红色的脸庞仍显英俊，蓝色的独眼目光恍惚；胡子皓白而浓密，垂至腰间，而且自到科尔布鲁克至今，从未修剪过。

七年前的一天，汉格伯船长走进港湾附近的“新酒馆”，准备购买一盎司烟叶，恰逢当地有名的巧嘴，也是理发师，傲慢地坐在酒吧间。面对理发师以打趣的口吻招徕生意，汉格伯船长一本正经地回答：“下月吧。”最后，他自袖口掏出手帕，又从手帕边角摸出三枚面值半便士的硬币，付了账并随即离去。一等酒馆的门关闭，理发师便哈哈大笑。“不久，一老一少将胳膊挽着胳膊，一块儿溜达来我店里刮胡子。裁缝、理发师和蜡扦匠都将开始忙碌。科尔布鲁克必将重现往日盛景，绝错不了。以前，一直是‘下周’，现在变成了‘下月’；照此下去，说不定，很快就变成‘下个春天’。”

登时，理发师发现一个陌生人咧着嘴，正一脸茫然地笑着，在听自己说话，于是他边毫无顾忌地舒展双腿，边解释道：那怪老头汉格伯曾是沿海小商船的船长，现已退休，正在此地等儿子回来。那孩子很可能让父母赶出家门，然后跑去当水手，从此杳无音信。这些年中，说不定早已葬身海底。三年前，那老头急匆匆赶来科尔布鲁克：穿一身黑色细平布衣服（当时刚没了老伴），迫不及待地跳下火车三等吸烟车厢，仿佛魔鬼就在身后追赶似的。他之所以来，仅仅是因为一封信。不过，那信很可能是恶作剧。有爱开玩笑的家伙写信告诉他：据传，一位名字相似的水手正在科尔布鲁克或附近，与某个姑娘鬼混。“很可笑，对吧？”此前，那老兄一直通过伦敦各家报纸发布寻找哈里·汉格伯的启事，称对提供任何可信线索者，都会给予酬金。继而，理发师以嘲讽的口吻，兴致勃勃地描述：有人目睹那个身着丧服的外乡老头，或坐运货马车，或步行，遍访周围的乡村；向所有人诉说自己的心事；走进方圆数英里内的每一家旅店和酒馆；当路拦下行人询问；甚至查看几乎每一条沟渠。刚开始，他满怀期待，无比兴奋，后来全凭意念苦苦坚持，行动变得越来越缓慢。而且，他甚至说不清，自己儿子究竟长什么样。曾有两名水手离开一艘木材运输船，估计其中之一便是他儿子。有人看到该水手在追求某个姑娘。可根据那老头的描述，他儿子只有十四岁上下，是“一个看起来既聪明又有冲劲的男孩”。对此，听者往往一笑置之。此时，他会困惑地摸摸自己额头，接着面带愠色，逃之夭夭。自然，那老头没找到任何人，哪怕只是影子——至少，从未打探到任何可靠的消息。但不知为何，他就是待在科尔布鲁克不走。

“也许是因为找儿子未果的打击，加上刚没了老伴，他终于疯了。”理发师做出论断——说话时的神态，俨然一位心理学大师。一段时间以后，那老头不再积极寻找。他儿子显然已离开科尔布鲁克。但那老头住了下来，打算就在此地等。至少有过一次，他儿子曾选择来科尔布鲁克，而不是回家乡。这一定是有原因的，他似乎认为，一定存在什么巨大的诱惑，而这诱惑会让他儿子再次回到科尔布鲁克。

“哈，哈，哈！哎呀，当然会来科尔布鲁克。除此以外，还能去哪儿呢？英国虽大，但所有失踪已久的儿子只会选择来科尔布鲁克。于是，他卖掉在科尔切斯特[1]的老宅，来到这里。嗨，他绝对疯了，毫无疑问。要是我的哪个孩子离家出走，我绝不会发疯。我可有八个孩子呢。”在声震酒吧间的大笑中，理发师神气地夸耀自己意志坚强。

不过，奇怪的是，这种疯症似乎具有传染性，理发师坦言——听其口吻，俨然一位聪慧过人的智者。比方说，其理发店位于港湾附近，每逢水手上门理发或刮胡子，假如是一张陌生面孔，他会立即情不自禁地想：“说不定，这人就是汉格伯老头的儿子！”说完，理发师哈哈大笑，以示自嘲。这是一种传染性很强的疯症，一度席卷整个海港小镇。对此，理发师记忆犹新。不过，他对那老兄仍抱有希望，相信能用一系列审慎的玩笑，治愈对方。而且，他一直在密切监控治疗的进展。下周——下月——明年！等那老船长把幻想儿子回来的时间推迟至明年，过不了多久，他将再也不会提及此事。对于别的事情，那老船长神志十分清楚，所以在这件事上，也一定会恢复理智。对此，理发师满怀信心。

理发师从未遭到反驳。自那以后，他的头发逐渐斑白，而汉格伯船长的胡子更是变得皓白而浓密，垂至腰间，同时天天身穿用一号厚篷帆布缝制的衣服。汉格伯船长亲手用浸过柏油的麻线，秘密缝制了那身行头，然后在一个晴朗的早晨，突然穿着那身行头出门。要知道，就在前一晚，有人看到他回家时还穿着之前的细平布丧服。汉格伯船长的这次亮相，在镇中心大街引起了轰动。众店主全部走到店门边，街上居民也纷纷抓起帽子，跑出家门。看到这番情景，汉格伯船长自己反倒大吃一惊，接着开始害怕。不过，面对好奇之人的询问，他一概惊恐而含糊地回答：“暂时凑合一下。”

当时的轰动，早已无人记得。连汉格伯船长本人，大家即便没有遗忘，也已不再理睬。这是习以为常的后果，就像谁也不会留意太阳，除非太阳把人晒得受不了。汉格伯船长的动作，瞧不出丝毫年老体衰的迹象：穿那身帆布行头的他，走起路来，四肢直挺，模样奇特而惹眼；只有目光显得比过去更加恍惚、鬼祟。不过，他举手投足间完全没了当初的兴奋与机警，而是变得困惑且羞怯，似乎在怀疑自己身上出现了有失体面、令人尴尬的怪癖，却又始终无法弄清究竟哪里不对劲。

现在，汉格伯船长不愿再与镇上居民搭话。在生活上，他得了铁公鸡、守财奴的恶名：在店里买什么东西，总要懊悔地嘟哝一阵；犹豫半天，才舍得买一点不好的边角肉。此外，他决不允许任何人提起他的那身行头。一切正如理发师所料。在别人看来，汉格伯船长的病已经痊愈，即不再抱有希望。唯有贝茜·卡尔维小姐知道，汉格伯船长之所以绝口不提等儿子回来的事，是因为在他的幻想中，那个时间已不再是“下周”“下月”甚或“明年”，而是“明天”。

在没有别人的前院或后院相遇时，汉格伯船长总和贝茜搭话，说话过程中不仅如慈父般语重心长，而且通情达理，尽管难免自以为是，还有点武断。他俩相识，出于毫无保留的信任——表现为汉格伯船长不时满怀关爱地冲对方眨眼睛。渐渐地，贝茜开始有些期待汉格伯船长的这一举动。起初，她对此很不安，认为这个可怜的家伙疯了；后来往往一笑置之，因为对方全无恶意；如今会不由得感到快乐却又不愿相信，并微微脸红。汉格伯船长眨眼睛，毫无猥亵的意味。那张瘦削的红脸，配上高挺的鹰钩鼻，显得气宇不凡，尤其是在与贝茜说话时。因为此时，他的目光会变得更加坚定而睿智。这男人虽胡子皓白，却英俊、硬朗、挺拔、干练，使你不会留意他的年纪。他声称，其儿子打出生就长得非常像自己，和他简直是从一个模子刻出来的。

明年七月，哈里就三十一岁了，汉格伯船长说。正该找个明事理、重家庭的好姑娘结婚。哈里这孩子很有冲劲。有冲劲的丈夫最好管束。至于那些没什么能力的软蛋，你可能觉得在他们嘴里连黄油都不会融化，但其实他们才会让女人过得非常悲惨。另外，没什么能比得上自己的家——有炉火取暖、有结实屋顶的家。有了家，管它什么天气，你都不用被迫离开温暖的被窝。“对吧，亲爱的孩子？”

有一类水手所干的行当，是在看得见陆地的沿海活动。汉格伯船长便是其中之一。其父是农民，子女众多，后来破了产，于是匆匆送他去给某位海滨小商船的船长做学徒。从此，他在海滨度过了整个水手生涯。那种日子，对汉格伯船长而言，刚开始绝非易事：他从未喜欢过海上的漂泊，反而逐渐迷恋陆地、陆地上数不清的房屋和千家万户聚在炉边烤火的平静生活。许多水手基于理性考虑，不喜欢航海，并直言不讳，而汉格伯船长不喜欢航海，却是出于个人情感，且到了深恶痛绝的地步，仿佛对安稳生活的渴慕，是他家代代相传的基因。

“世人不知道，让儿子去海上讨生活，就是把他们往火坑里推。”汉格伯船长对贝茜解释，“与其那样做，还不如立即送他们去坐牢呢。”他决不信，有谁能适应航海生活。相反，年纪越大，就会越感到厌倦。这到底是一种什么行当？入了行，竟大半时间都回不成家？一旦出海，便完全无法了解家里的情况。有人可能认为，汉格伯船长之所以这么说，是因为厌倦了远洋航行。其实，就算他水手生涯最长的一次航行，也仅仅持续了两周，而且大部分时间都在抛锚停泊，躲避恶劣天气。在他妻子从自己叔叔那里继承一所房子和足够维持生计的钱财后（该叔叔生前做煤炭生意赚了一些钱，但打了一辈子光棍），他立即辞去东海岸某运煤船船长职务，并为此感到庆幸，犹如从古罗马舰队眼皮底下死里逃生一般。干了那么多年水手，汉格伯船长看不见英国的日子，两只手就能数得过来。他从未在深度超过六百英尺的深海航行，而且经常吹嘘的其中一句话，便是“我从没离开陆地超过八十英寻[2]”。

上述这一切，贝茜·卡尔维并非首次听闻。在他们父女租住的小屋前，有一株低矮的白蜡树。夏日午后，她常常搬出椅子，坐在树底草坪上，做针线活儿。此刻，汉格伯船长总会穿着那身帆布行头，拄着铁锹。他天天在自己前院的空地挖土，每年都要把那块空地反复翻整多遍，但“暂时”——他的原话——什么也不种。

对贝茜·卡尔维，汉格伯船长会说得更加明确：“等明天我们的哈里回来再种。”这充满希望的套话，只能唤起贝茜的些许同情，因为她已听那位满怀希望的老人重复过无数遍了。

一切都如这般再三拖延，一切都是为明天而做的准备。汉格伯船长攒了满满一箱品种众多、小袋分装的花籽，以备在前院播种。“选种什么花，他肯定会听取你的意见，亲爱的孩子。”汉格伯船长隔着铁栅栏，向贝茜暗示。

贝茜小姐对此也已听过无数遍，所以仍埋头做针线活儿，不予理睬。不过，她偶尔也会起身，放下手中的活儿，缓步踱向铁栅栏。这些善意的疯话，透着某种魔力。汉格伯船长认定，儿子一旦回来，就不会再走，因为此处有个为其准备好一切的家。多年来，汉格伯船长自住的小屋逐渐塞满各种各样的家具。贝茜想象，那些家具都是崭新的，清漆完好，而且重叠堆放，如在仓库。其中，可能有几张裹着粗麻布的桌子，几捆卷成圆筒状的地毯——又粗又直，好像断柱。此外，在窗帘紧闭、一片昏暗的屋内，某些家具的白色大理石表面可能散发着淡淡的光泽。汉格伯船长每次都向贝茜详细描述购置的家具，仿佛那些也是她的合法财产。过了明天，他还要打理其杂草蔓生的后院，并浇注混凝土……

“我们不妨把木篱笆拆了。这样，你就可以拉一条晾衣绳，又绝不会碰到你的那些花儿。”汉格伯船长说着，眨了眨眼。贝茜不由得微微脸红。

贝茜心地善良，所以汉格伯船长才会对她说些疯言疯语。但这些疯话并非全是无稽之谈。万一哪天，他儿子回来了，该怎么办？但贝茜甚至不太确定，汉格伯船长是否真有儿子。就算真有儿子，那人也已久无音信。汉格伯船长说着，说着，可能变得非常激动。为使他恢复平静，贝茜会假装对他的话深信不疑，并微微笑一笑，以减轻心中内疚。

唯有一次，贝茜出于同情，试着对那个注定破灭的希望表达了些许疑虑，结果把自己吓了一大跳。只见汉格伯船长顿时露出既万分惊恐又不敢相信的神色，犹如目睹天空开裂。

“你——你——他不会淹死的！”

在贝茜看来，汉格伯船长平时没别人想的那么不正常，但那一刻，她觉得后者即将彻底发疯。不过，随着失控的情绪逐渐平复，汉格伯船长变得如慈父般和蔼可亲，而且极为谦恭。

“别担心，亲爱的孩子。”汉格伯船长带着一丝狡黠说，“大海无法留住他。他也不属于大海。我们汉格伯家，世世代代，从没出过属于大海的人。瞧瞧我——并未淹死在海里。再说，他压根儿不是水手。而如果不是水手，必定会回来。没有什么——”

汉格伯船长的眼神开始变得恍惚。

“——阻碍他明天回来。”

贝茜再未对汉格伯船长的希望表达过任何疑虑，以免他当场发疯。汉格伯船长完全信赖贝茜，认为她是全镇唯一明事理的人，还会当她的面，毫不掩饰地庆幸给儿子物色了这样一个头脑清楚的好妻子。曾有一次，汉格伯船长在气头上向贝茜吐露，镇上其他人脑子都不正常，绝错不了。他们瞧你的眼神、对你说话的口气，暴露无遗！这里的人，从未有谁与自己合得来。他不喜欢他们。显而易见，要不是儿子非常喜欢科尔布鲁克，他决不会离开家乡。

贝茜不做任何反驳，只是默默地站在木篱笆旁，一边耐心听汉格伯船长诉说，一边低垂眉眼，用钩针编织着什么。她面色煞白，脸红起来并不明显；浓密的红褐色头发，胡乱盘在头顶——她父亲的头发就呈橘红色，而且非常红。

贝茜身材丰满，面色总是显得疲倦而没有精神。每逢汉格伯船长大谈有个家是多么必要且应当、在自家炉边烤火又是多么幸福，她只是动动嘴唇，报以微微一笑。在人生最美好的十年，只能守在家里，伺候父亲，这便是家给予她的全部“幸福”。

从楼上窗户会传来犹如野兽发出的咆哮，打断他俩的谈话。一听到那声音，贝茜立即开始收拾手中的编织或针线活儿，但丝毫不显慌张。与此同时，呼喊她名字的咆哮仍在继续。如果恰巧有渔夫在路对面海堤上溜达，他们便会纷纷扭头，望向那两栋小屋。收起手中的活儿后，贝茜慢悠悠地走进自家前门。过了片刻，他们父女租住的小屋便陷入一片沉寂。不久，她再次现身：牵着一个男人的手，引领其走出门来。那男人肥硕而笨拙，活像河马，而且脸色极其阴沉。

那男人已丧偶，曾是造船工人；多年前，正当事业蒸蒸日上时，突然双目失明。他对待女儿的态度，就像眼睛无法治愈全都怪女儿似的。有人曾听到那鳏夫仿佛出于对上帝的藐视，声嘶力竭地吼道：他对失明毫不在乎，因为赚的钱，足够天天早餐吃火腿煎蛋。他为能过这样的生活而感谢上帝，但听其口气，更像恶魔在诅咒。

汉格伯船长极不喜欢这位租客，所以曾对贝茜小姐说：“他是个毫不节约的家伙，亲爱的孩子。”

那天，贝茜在赶着织完给父亲穿的袜子。在其父看来，做女红是女儿的本分，但贝茜讨厌编织。由于正织到后跟部分，她不得不全神贯注地盯着手中织针。

“当然，他没有儿子需要供养。”汉格伯船长怅然若失，继续说，“女儿需要的东西，自然没那么多，唔——唔。她们也不会离家出走，亲爱的孩子。”

“是的。”贝茜平静地附和。

汉格伯船长站在翻土后形成的土堆中间，咯咯地笑。他穿着那身古怪的帆布行头，配上饱经风霜的面孔和尼普顿[3]那样的长须，活像一位遭贬下凡、拿三叉戟换了铁锹的海神。

“他肯定认为，对你多少已尽了抚养的义务。这正是生女儿的最大好处。丈夫……”汉格伯船长眨了眨眼。专心织袜子的贝茜小姐，不由得微微脸红。

“贝茜！我的帽子！”卡尔维老头突然吼道。此前，他一直坐在树下，沉默不语，纹丝不动，酷似一尊神像——象征的是某种极为骇人的迷信。他要么不开口，一开口就大声咆哮：喊女儿，吼女儿，偶尔还骂女儿，而且尽用恶毒的词。贝茜的应对方法，是决不搭话。其父会不停地大吼大叫，直至得到回应：贝茜摇动他的胳膊，或把烟斗咬嘴插入他齿间。身为盲人还抽烟，真是少见。感觉帽子落到头顶，卡尔维老头立即停止吼叫。等女儿扶他起身后，两人便一块儿走出院子大门。

卡尔维老头把身体全部重量都压在女儿胳膊上。他俩缓慢而艰难地往前走，看起来就像是贝茜为了给自己赎罪，拖着那具虚弱、肥硕的躯体，负重而行。通常，他俩一出院子便横穿门前小路——两栋小屋坐落在港湾附近的野地里，门前有条小路通往两百码外的大街尽头。过了很久，仍能望见那对父女的身影，尽管瞧不出他俩正沿着通往海堤顶部的木台阶，费力地拾级而上。这条海堤沿英吉利海峡而修，东西横亘，犹如一段废弃已久、在人类记忆中从无列车驶过的铁路路堤。健壮的渔夫会成群结队，从天际冒出来，往前走一走，接着变得越来越矮，越来越矮，直至慢慢消失。一张张棕色渔网，平铺在杂草蔓生的堤坡上，酷似巨大的蛛网。来到大街尽头的镇上居民，抬眼望见那蹒跚而缓慢的步伐，立即便能认出卡尔维父女。在两栋小屋周围闲荡的汉格伯船长，经常抬头眺望，看看那对散步的父女走到哪儿了。

汉格伯船长仍在每逢周日出版的各家报纸发布寻找哈里·汉格伯的启事。他一方面告诉贝茜，这些报纸的读者，遍布全世界各个国家与地区；一方面却似乎认为，儿子就在英国，离科尔布鲁克非常近，“明天”肯定会到来。对于汉格伯船长的后一念头，贝茜并未直截了当地发表意见，而是说：既然如此，就没必要每周浪费两先令六便士，发布寻人启事，汉格伯船长还不如把那些钱用于自己身上。她还称，自己不知道汉格伯船长靠什么为生。听了贝茜的话，汉格伯船长会陷入苦思，并沮丧好一会儿。“别人都这么做。”他辩解。而且，每家报纸都设有一栏，专用于刊登寻找失踪亲属的启事。他会取来报纸，向贝茜证明自己所说属实。多年来，他们夫妇一直在各家报纸发布寻人启事。可惜，他妻子不是一个有耐心的女人。她头天刚下葬，第二天就从科尔布鲁克传来了消息。要不是那么没耐心，她可能这会儿也在这里，而且顶多再等一天，就能见到儿子。“你是一个有耐心的女人，亲爱的孩子。”

“有时候，我对您真的失去了耐心。”贝茜会说。

汉格伯船长虽仍在各家报纸发布寻找儿子的启事，但对提供线索者，已不再给予任何酬金。因为，出于神志错乱之人自以为理智、实则糊涂的逻辑，他坚信以下这点是明摆着的，即自己已获得通过该途径所能获得的一切线索。他还想了解什么呢？儿子肯定会来科尔布鲁克。知道这一点，便足够了。卡尔维小姐夸其明智，令汉格伯船长大为宽慰。在他看来，贝茜不仅肯定了他那个已成痴心妄想的希望，而且也赞同他的判断——这判断使他看不见事实真相与其他可能，恰如另一栋小屋里的另一名老人，因另一种疾病而双目失明，看不见这个世界的光明与美好。

尽管如此，只要认为自己受到任何怀疑，汉格伯船长都会激动得直抽搐，并用恶毒的眼神斜睨对方：例如，向他表达赞成时口气冷淡，甚或仅仅未留意他那些计划的进展——那些计划的目的，是做好关于家庭生活的各项准备，以便儿子回来后，与儿子、儿媳共叙天伦之乐。他还会把铁锹猛地往地里一插，然后在旁边走过来，走过去。每逢此时，贝茜小姐都认为汉格伯船长在使性子，她便会用食指指着他，以示责备。汉格伯船长见状，会气冲冲地远离贝茜。但等贝茜再次来到屋外，他会用眼角余光偷瞥对方，以求发现丝毫表示鼓励的暗示，好走近铁栅栏，恢复两人之间父亲对女儿、长辈对晚辈的关系。

他俩虽相熟已有几年，但每次都隔着木篱笆或铁栅栏交谈。汉格伯船长经常告诉贝茜，自己为将来一家人生活而积攒的各种家当是多么豪华，但从未邀请贝茜过去瞧一瞧。除了哈里，谁也不能先瞧。事实上，从无别人进过汉格伯船长自住的小屋。此外，汉格伯船长不仅自己做所有家务，而且偶尔去镇上买了什么家用小物件，总是揣在帆布外套里，匆匆穿过前院，偷偷带进屋，唯恐别人先于儿子瞧见。从屋里出来后，他会为自己辩解：“不过是一只小烧水壶，亲爱的孩子。”

假如不是家务干到筋疲力尽，或不堪其父烦扰，贝茜会微微红着脸，冲汉格伯船长笑一笑，说：“没关系，汉格伯船长。我是一个有耐心的女人。”

“唔，亲爱的孩子，你不用等很久了。”汉格伯船长会如此回应，并突然变得羞怯。他不安地东张西望，仿佛早就在怀疑哪里不对劲。

每逢周一，贝茜会隔着铁栅栏，把房租递给汉格伯船长。他会贪婪地一把抓过那些先令。汉格伯船长极不情愿把钱用于必要的生活花销，哪怕仅仅一便士，而且每当告别贝茜去买东西，一到大街上，立即就像换了个人。离开贝茜的同情与鼓励，他觉得自己完全暴露于各种危险之中，所以总是肩膀贴着墙壁，沿街边行走，还认为遇到的人都很可疑。但其实，到了那会儿，就连镇上的孩童都不再追着他大呼小叫，而商店店主接待他时，也往往一言不发。汉格伯船长对自己的衣着尤为敏感：假如有谁提起，哪怕极其委婉，也会令他大感困惑和惊恐，仿佛听到什么毫无道理、匪夷所思之事。

秋天，每逢下起滂沱大雨，硕大的雨滴吧嗒吧嗒，直打在汉格伯船长那身帆布行头上。那身行头湿透后，变得几乎如铁皮般坚硬，而且雨水顺着其表面各处不断往下流淌。假如天气过于恶劣，汉格伯船长只能被迫躲在狭小的门廊下，紧贴屋门而立，眼巴巴地望着插于前院中间的铁锹。整个前院，到处挖了又挖，随着季节推移，逐渐变成一片泥淖。当地面完全冻住，他会变得忧心忡忡。哈里要是见了，会说什么呢？从另一栋小屋紧闭的窗户，不时隐隐传来卡尔维老头在屋里使唤贝茜的咆哮。由于每年这个时节，与贝茜见面的机会大为减少，汉格伯船长就对卡尔维老头的咆哮感到极为恼怒。

“那个毫不节约的家伙，为什么不给你请个用人呢？”汉格伯船长没好气地问贝茜。那天下午挺暖和，贝茜往头上随便搭了样东西，跑出来活动活动。

“我不知道。”贝茜疲惫地回答，并望向别处，眼神里全无期待。她脸色苍白，眼皮耷拉，灰色的眼睛下方总是带着两抹阴影。给人的感觉，她似乎看不到自己的人生会出现任何改变，或存在一个尽头。

“等到结婚，就好了，亲爱的孩子。”贝茜唯一的朋友边缓步走近铁栅栏，边说，“哈里会给你请一个的。”

汉格伯船长盲目乐观的疯症，在绝望的贝茜看来，是对自己赤裸裸的嘲弄。她一时激愤难当，忍不住要当场破口大骂，但最后只是像面对正常人那样自嘲道：“哎呀，汉格伯船长，说不定您儿子连瞧都不想瞧我一眼。”

汉格伯船长把脑袋往后一仰，通过喉咙，沙哑而做作地嘎嘎大笑，以示愤怒。

“什么！那小子？对方圆几英里内唯一明事理的姑娘，连瞧都不想瞧一眼？你认为，我在这里，是为了什么，亲爱的孩子？亲爱的孩子？亲爱的孩子……什么？你等着瞧吧。你等着瞧好了。明天就能见分晓。我很快就将——”

“贝茜！贝茜！贝茜！”卡尔维老头在屋里咆哮，“贝茜！我的烟斗！”那个肥硕的瞎子，懒惰到了衣来伸手、饭来张口的地步。他决不抬一抬手，自己拿女儿事先在他手肘边精心备下的东西；决不动一动腿或胳膊；决不自己从椅子上起身；虽然完全能在客厅自由穿梭，犹如双目并未失明一般，但不将女儿唤至身旁，并将肥硕躯体的全部重量压到女儿肩上，决不把一只脚迈到另一只脚前；此外，决不自己吃一口东西，只等女儿去喂。失明确实带来不便，但卡尔维老头故意表现得生活完全不能自理，好尽可能地奴役女儿。黄昏中，贝茜紧咬牙关，纹丝不动地站了一会儿，然后转身，缓步回屋。

汉格伯船长走回铁锹所插之处。从卡尔维父女租住的小屋，不再传出咆哮声。没过一会儿，那栋小屋楼下客厅的窗户里亮起灯光。有个男人迈着坚定而从容的步伐，从大街尽头走来。打两栋小屋前经过时，他似乎瞧见了汉格伯船长，于是又折回来一两步。西边的天空，尚留一抹冷冰冰的白光。来人趴在院子大门上，显得饶有兴趣。

“你一定就是汉格伯船长吧。”那人从容且胸有成竹地说。

听到陌生人的声音，老人大吃一惊，随即原地转了个身，同时顺手从土里拔出铁锹。

“是的，我就是。”老人紧张地回答。

对方边冲老人微笑，边缓缓道：“你一直在报纸上发布寻找儿子的启事，对吧？”

“我儿子哈里，”汉格伯船长嘟哝着，暂时放下戒备，但仅此一次，“他明天就会回家。”

“他会回家才怪！”陌生人既非常惊讶又不以为然地高呼，并用几乎相同的语气继续道，“瞧你留的胡子，都赶上圣诞老人了！”

汉格伯船长缓缓地朝院子大门走了几步，然后拄着铁锹而立，同时身子在铁锹上方微微前倾。“走开。”他说话的语气既愤恨又羞怯，因为一直以来，他生怕遭人嘲笑。无论处于何种精神状态的人，哪怕神志错乱的疯子，皆有自尊。自尊是其保持内心平静的基础；一旦自尊受挫，便会导致不悦。另外，汉格伯船长对生活已形成一系列根深蒂固的观念，而别人的大笑令他对这些观念心生怀疑，并因此感到痛苦。没错，看到别人冲自己大笑，非常可恶。那是在暗示什么地方不对劲。可究竟哪里不对劲呢？他弄不明白。显而易见，那陌生人正在咧嘴大笑——特意上门来这么做。在各条街上，遇到别人冲自己大笑，汉格伯船长也非常不悦，但从未如此愤怒。

陌生人并未意识到自己的脑袋差点让铁锹劈成两半，严肃地回道：“我站在这里，不算擅闯私宅，对吧？我认为，你得到的消息有误。要不让我进去再说？”

“让你进来？！”汉格伯船长嘟哝道，言语中透着无法形容的恐惧。

“我可以提供一些关于你儿子的真实情况——最新的独家消息，如果你想听的话？”

“不想听！”汉格伯船长嚷着，开始极为激动地走过来，走过去，接着又扛起铁锹，并用另一条胳膊比画各种动作。“这个咧嘴大笑的家伙，说我得到的消息有误。我知道的消息，比你多。我早就知道了所有想要知道的消息。几年前就知道了！几年前！几年前！我不再需要任何消息，只需等待明天到来。让你进来——等着吧！哈里要是知道了，会怎么说呢？”

此时，另一栋小屋楼下客厅的窗户映出贝茜·卡尔维的黑色人影。接着，伴随开门的声响，那人影从小屋前面飞掠而出：全身漆黑，头上却搭着什么白色的东西。突然听见外面这两人的说话声，屋里的贝茜激动得瞠目结舌。

汉格伯船长看上去，活像慌不择路、企图逃离牢笼的困兽。他在一片泥潭里嘎吱嘎吱地乱走——这片泥潭正是他辛勤劳动的结果；在毁坏的草坪上让坑坑洼洼绊得踉踉跄跄；还像瞎子似的乱跑，完全不顾是否撞到铁栅栏。

“喂，冷静一点！”陌生人边说，边慎重地把胳膊伸过院子大门，拽住汉格伯船长的衣袖。“有人想找到并诈骗你。嗬！你身上穿的什么东西啊？还真是厚篷帆布！”那人哈哈大笑，接着道，“哎呀，你果然是怪人！”

汉格伯船长猛地从对方手中挣脱，然后边羞怯地向后退缩，边用颓丧的语气嘟哝：“暂时凑合一下。”

“他怎么回事啊？”陌生人以解释的口吻，极其亲昵、慢条斯理地对贝茜说，“我不是故意要惊吓这老家伙的。”接着，陌生人压低声音，仿佛在和相熟多年的故友说悄悄话。“我顺道拐进一家理发店，花两便士，刮了胡子。店里那些人告诉我，他有点古怪。其实，这老家伙一辈子都是怪人。”

听到对方提及自己的衣着，汉格伯船长羞怯之下，带着铁锹，躲进屋里。冷不防响起重重的关门声，令站在院子大门处的另外两人大吃一惊。紧接着，他俩相继听到闩门闩的碰撞声、锁门锁的吧嗒声和咯咯的大笑声——这装腔作势的笑声在屋里回荡不止。

“我不是故意要刺激他的。”沉默了片刻，陌生人说，“这一切究竟是什么意思啊？他并未完全发疯呀。”

“这么多年来，他一直在为离家出走的儿子感到担忧。”贝茜以抱歉的口吻，低声回答。

“唔，我就是他儿子。”

“哈里！”贝茜不由得惊呼，但随即紧紧地闭住嘴。

“知道我的名字？和这老家伙是朋友，嗯？”

“他是我们的房东。”贝茜伸手抓住铁栅栏，结结巴巴地回答。

“这两栋兔笼似的小破屋都是他的，对吧？”小汉格伯不屑地说，“能让他引以为傲的，就是这些东西。明天要来的那小子是谁，你能告诉我吗？你对此肯定有所了解。我告诉你，这老家伙遇到了诈骗——绝错不了。”

贝茜一时沉默不语。她完全不知如何回答，惊愕地愣在原地：自知必须做出解释，却不可能也惧怕那么做，因为如果把整件事的来龙去脉解释清楚，似乎难免会让对方觉得，她也是疯子。

“唉——真对不起。”贝茜嗫嚅道。

“怎么回事？”小汉格伯平静地说，“别担心，我不会不高兴。另一个小子才会不高兴，因为事情的结果将完全出乎他意料。我对这事一点也不在乎。不过，明天，等那小子露面，将有好戏上演。我不是为这老家伙着想，但对就是对，错就是错。你等着瞧吧，我会痛揍那骗子，不管他是谁！”

说话过程中，小汉格伯朝贝茜走近了一些。两人隔着铁栅栏而立，男的比女的高出不少。小汉格伯瞥了眼贝茜的双手，感觉她在颤抖，并突然想到：也许，明天算计他父亲的小把戏，眼前这女人也有份。幸亏自己及时赶到，使骗子的诡计无法得逞。想到这，他不免感到一阵得意——嘲笑骗子的诡计实在拙劣，轻而易举就让自己挫败。但有生以来，无论女人耍什么花招，他一直对她们极为宽容。再说，眼前这女人确实颤抖得厉害，连头上的围巾都已滑落。“可怜的女人！”小汉格伯心想，“别管另一个小子了。他明天不一定会来。可我自己该怎么办呢？总不能在院子门口一直晃悠到明天早上吧。”

贝茜突然喊道：“是你——他等的是你！明天要来的那个人是你！”

小汉格伯木然地嘟哝道：“啊！是我！”接着，两人似乎同时停止了呼吸。看起来，小汉格伯正在琢磨听到的话。过了一会儿，他说：“我不明白。我没给他写过信什么的。我朋友看到报纸上的寻人启事，然后告诉了我——就在今天早晨……嗯？什么？”他说话时并不气恼，但显得非常困惑。

小汉格伯低下头，把耳朵凑向贝茜，听她轻声而飞快地说了一些话。听的过程中，他不时嘟哝着回以“是的”“原来如此”。“可为什么今天不行呢？”最后，他问。

“你没懂我的意思！”贝茜不耐烦地叫道。西边，云层底下那抹明亮的白光已逐渐消失。小汉格伯再次微微低头，以便听得更清楚。这对男女——一个喃喃低语，一个侧耳倾听——完全消失在重重夜幕中。唯一隐约可见的是，两张脸亲昵地挨在一块儿，仿佛他俩正偷偷幽会，相互温存。

小汉格伯挺直肩膀。一顶宽檐帽的黑影，随随便便地搭在他头上。“很可笑，对吧？”小汉格伯对贝茜说，“明天？哈，哈！从没听说过这种事。看起来，永远都会是明天，绝不可能是今天。”

贝茜一动不动，默不作声。

“而你一直纵容他抱着这个可笑的念头。”小汉格伯说。

“我从不反驳他。”

“为什么不？”

“我为什么要反驳？”贝茜辩解，“那只会使他痛苦。他可能会丧失理智的。”

“他还有理智！”小汉格伯嘟哝道。接着，他听到贝茜短促而紧张地笑了笑。

“我不反驳，造成什么危害了吗？难道要我和这位可怜的老人吵架吗？我更愿意对他的话半信半疑。”

“是的，是的。”精明的小汉格伯略作沉思，接着说，“我估计，这老家伙说了什么花言巧语，把你哄得相信了。你心肠可真软。”

黑暗中，贝茜紧张地提起双手。“他的话可能是真的。确实是真的。那一天确实到来了。今天就是。今天就是我们一直等待的‘明天’。”

贝茜说完，深吸一口气。小汉格伯和气地说：“是啊，结果却不让人进门。我不在乎是否……你觉得，能说服他和我相认……嗯？什么……你能说服他？你说要一星期？唔，也许你是能说服他，可在这无聊透顶的地方，你觉得我能待住一星期吗？我待不住！我希望要么拼命干活，要么恣意玩乐，再要么去比整个英国还要广阔的地方闯荡。不过，我曾来过这里一回，而且待了一个多星期。当时，这老家伙在报纸上发布寻找我的启事。有个和我在一块儿的朋友想出一个主意：写封信，胡说八道地扯上一大通，骗他几英镑。不过，那个玩笑并未得逞。因为我们不得不离开了——那回，我在这里待了好几天。但这回，有个朋友正在伦敦等我，再说……”

贝茜·卡尔维的呼吸变得急促。

“要是我去敲门，会怎么样？”小汉格伯问。

“去试一下吧。”贝茜回道。

汉格伯船长所住小屋的院子大门发出嘎吱嘎吱的声响。小汉格伯的人影在院子里走了几步，接着驻足，再次从喉咙发出低沉的笑声——与老汉格伯的笑声很像，只不过更加温柔、悦耳。贝茜听了，顿感如梦初醒，心神荡漾。

“他不爱闹腾吧？我担心不得不控制住他。大伙总说，我不知道自己的力量有多大。”

“他是有史以来最温和的人。”贝茜插嘴道。

“你要是见过他挥舞粗硬的皮鞭，一路追打我到楼上，你就不会这么说了。”小汉格伯说，“整整十六年来，我一直没忘记这件事。”

小汉格伯说完，又一次发出低沉、悦耳的笑声。贝茜感到一股暖流从头顶蔓延到脚底。随着门环发出嘭嘭嘭的声响，她的心提到了嗓子眼。

“喂，爸！开门。我是哈里，真的。快开门！我提前一天回家了。”

小屋楼上的一扇窗户咔嗒咔嗒地拉了起来。

“一个咧嘴大笑、自称有最新消息的家伙。”从黑乎乎的高处传来汉格伯船长的声音，“别和他扯上任何瓜葛。这会毁了一切的。”

贝茜听到小汉格伯喊了声“喂，爸”，又听到哐当一响。接着，小屋楼上的窗户咔嗒咔嗒地拉下了；与此同时，小汉格伯再次站在贝茜面前。

“和过去一模一样。那会儿，他差点把我活活打死，以阻止我离开家；这会儿，我回来了，他又照着我的脑袋扔下该死的铁锹，不让我进门。那该死的铁锹擦伤了我的肩膀。”

贝茜不由得一阵哆嗦。

“我不在乎。”小汉格伯接着说，“只是我身上最后几先令用来买了火车票，最后两便士又用来刮了胡子——出于对老家伙的尊敬。”

“你真是哈里·汉格伯？”贝茜立刻问，“你能证明吗？”

“我能证明吗？除了我，还有谁能证明？”小汉格伯乐呵呵地说，“用什么证明？我要证明什么？在全世界各个角落，也许英国除外，你都能找到记得我是哈里·汉格伯的人——找到记得我是哈里·汉格伯的女人，可能性更大。我比世上任何活着的人更像哈里·汉格伯。我能当即向你证明，要是你让我走进你家院子的话。”

“进来吧。”贝茜说。

于是，小汉格伯进了卡尔维父女所租小屋的前院。他魁梧的人影，大摇大摆地往前走。贝茜转身背对楼下客厅的窗户，一面等待，一面盯着不断逼近的模糊人影——那人影最真实之处，莫过于其脚步声。窗户透出的灯光中，出现一顶歪戴的帽子、半边势要撞破夜幕的强壮肩膀、一条从黑暗中迈出的腿。小汉格伯突然转身并站定，然后面朝贝茜背后亮着灯光的客厅窗户，边左右摆动脑袋，边自顾自轻声发笑。

“稍微想象一下，要是把老家伙的胡子粘到我的下巴，会是什么样。喂？快说话呀。我打小就长得非常像他，和他简直是从一个模子刻出来的。”

“的确。”贝茜低声嗫嚅道。

“不过，我俩也就外表长得像罢了。他一直都是你们这种恋家的人。哎呀，我至今仍记得，每逢要离开家去南希尔兹[4]运煤的前三天，他就会整日愁眉苦脸。当时，他持有煤气厂发的长期执照。你可能以为，他是去远洋捕鲸，一走三年多。哈，哈！完全不是。就离家十天而已。‘海上飞掠者’是一艘不错的船。名字不赖，对吧？那艘船属于我妈的叔叔……”

小汉格伯突然转变话题，压低声音问：“我妈怎么没的，他对你提过吗？”

“提过。”贝茜小姐伤感地回答，“说是因为不够耐心。”

小汉格伯沉默片刻，接着粗鲁地说：“他俩生怕我变成一个坏人，结果反而逼得我离家出走。我妈喋喋不休地指责我游手好闲，而这老家伙说，宁可把我杀掉，也不允许我去当水手。哎呀，当时看起来，他可能真会那么做，所以我离家出走了。有时，我觉得自己投错了胎，不该出生在那个同是兔笼似的家。”

“那你本该出生在什么地方，才算投对胎呢？”贝茜不屑地打断小汉格伯。

“我本该在狂风大作的夜晚，出生于旷野之中、海滩之上。”小汉格伯倒豆子般飞快地回答，接着若有所思地缓缓道，“他俩以前就是怪人，真的。过了这么多年，这老家伙丝毫没变，对吧？该死的铁锹——听！谁在大吼大叫啊？‘贝茜，贝茜。’从你住的那栋房子传出来的。”

“那是在喊我。”贝茜漠不关心地说。

小汉格伯往旁边挪了挪，离开窗前明亮处。“你老公？”他问。听其口气，显然是惯于偷情的老手。“声音真洪亮；碰到雷电交加的暴风雨，甲板上正需要这样的人。”

“不，是我爸。我还没结婚呢。”

“你看起来是个好姑娘，亲爱的贝茜小姐。”小汉格伯立刻接嘴道。贝茜把脸转向了别处。

“嘿，我说，怎么回事？谁在谋杀他啊？”

“他想吃傍晚茶[5]。”贝茜侧着脑袋，面对父亲，纹丝不动地站在原地，显得十分高挑。她的双手十指交叉地紧握在一起，垂于身前。

“你最好进去一下吧？”小汉格伯说。开口前，他凝视了一会儿贝茜的后颈——一块白得耀眼的皮肤，往下是线条柔和、只见阴影的脖颈儿，再往下是若隐若现的肩膀。贝茜头上的围巾已滑落至手肘处。“不用多久，整个镇子的人都要过来了。我在这里等你一会儿。”

贝茜的围巾掉落在地。等小汉格伯俯身捡起时，贝茜已消失不见。小汉格伯把捡起的围巾往胳膊上一搭，径直走近楼下客厅的窗户，看到一个肥硕男人的庞大身躯、一盏无罩的灯、贝茜小姐的脑袋和胸部；那男人坐在扶手椅中，正张着阔嘴打哈欠，蓬乱的头发披散在大扁脸两侧。屋里的吼叫声停了，窗帘放了下来。小汉格伯不禁陷入沉思，觉得眼下的处境糟糕至极。父亲疯了，无法进门。没钱回去，正在伦敦挨饿的那个朋友，将认为他靠不住。“该死！”小汉格伯嘟哝道。他当然有本事硬闯其父的住所，但警察可能因此不问青红皂白，就把他关进监狱。真是那样，也没什么大不了，只不过他非常惧怕遭到监禁，哪怕纯粹出于误会。想到这，小汉格伯不由得感到一阵寒冷，于是在湿漉漉的草地上跺了跺脚。

“你是干什么的？水手？”一个不安的声音问。

贝茜的人影已从屋里飞掠而出。吸引她出来的，是另一个正在她家墙角等待、显得非常鲁莽的人影。

“什么都干。包括做一名称职的普通水手。这次正是通过做水手回家的。”

“那你是打哪里来到这里的呢？”贝茜接着问。

“我刚刚恣意快活了一把，”小汉格伯回答，“然后坐从伦敦出发的火车来到这里——知道了吧？呃！我讨厌被关在火车里。不过，我对房子没那么反感。”

“啊，”贝茜说，“幸好。”

“因为在房子里的话，可以随时打开该死的门，然后直接当着你的面走掉。”

“从此再也不回来？”

“至少在十六年里，”小汉格伯大笑着回答，“不会回到一栋兔笼似的小破屋，让该死的铁锹……”

“船也不是很大呀。”贝茜讥讽道。

“是的，可大海无边无际。”

贝茜垂下脑袋。她似乎突然对世间万物的声音变得十分敏感，并听到经历昨天的大风后，波浪不断拍击海堤另一侧的沙滩。伴随阵阵涛声，整个大地都在单调而庄严地颤抖，犹如一口正在敲响的洪钟。

“再说，哎呀，船只是船。你可以随时爱上某艘船，也可以随时离开那艘船；一次航海，不同于一次婚姻。”小汉格伯轻率地引述流行于水手之间的粗话。

“航海确实不同于婚姻。”贝茜喃喃道。

“我向来行不更名，坐不改姓，而且迄今为止，从未对任何女人说过哪怕一次谎话。什么谎话？哎呀，就是：请你选择接受还是离开我；要是接受我，那么……”小汉格伯说完，倚着墙壁，轻声哼起一支水手号子的其中几句。

啊，嗬，嗬，里奥！

再见了，再见了，

年轻漂亮的姑娘，

我们正准备起航，

去南里奥格兰德[6]。

“这是转动绞盘、拉起船锚时唱的水手号子。”小汉格伯解释道。此时，贝茜的牙齿打了一下颤。

“你很冷吧。”小汉格伯说，“这是你掉的东西。”贝茜感觉到对方的双手在她身上移动，仔细地为她裹好围巾。“抓住前面这两头。”小汉格伯吩咐。

“你来这里干什么呢？”贝茜问着，感觉自己又要打冷战，但竭力克制住了。

“来要五英镑钱。”小汉格伯立即回答，“我们玩乐的时间稍微久了点，结果把钱花光了。”

“你一直在喝酒？”贝茜又问。

“一连三天，喝得烂醉如泥——故意的。不要以为，我是让人灌醉的。世上没有任何人或任何东西能摆布我，除非我愿意。要是不合我心意，我决不屈服。今天早晨，我朋友看到报纸上的寻人启事，于是对我说：‘快去，哈里。你爸很疼你。他肯定会给你五英镑。’于是，我俩翻遍各自的所有衣服口袋，勉强凑了来这里的车费。真是偷鸡不成蚀把米！”

“我恐怕得说，你是个铁石心肠的人。”贝茜叹息道。

“为什么这样说？因为我离家出走？哎呀！他想让我做律师的文书——纯粹为了称他的心。他是家里的老爷；而我那个死去的妈呢，一直对他煽风点火——可能是为了我好吧。好吧，既然如此，那就再见。于是，我离家出走了。不，我告诉你：我离开家当天，浑身上下青一块，紫一块，而这正是拜他那伟大的父爱所赐。啊！他一直都有点古怪。瞧瞧那把铁锹。发疯了？未必。我爸向来就是这么个人。他想让我留在家乡，无非是希望身边有个可以供他呼来喝去的人。不过，眼下，我和朋友手头有点紧，而对他来说，五英镑算得了什么呢？毕竟，在艰难的十六年中，我向他要钱，只此一回。”

“啊，我真为你的遭遇感到难过。你从来没想过回家吗？”

“做律师的文书，最后烂在家乡——烂在一个像这样的地方？”小汉格伯不屑地嚷道，“什么！要是今天这老家伙把我安顿在一个家里，我将把那个家踹成平地；要不然，我会在三天之内活活憋死。”

“除了家里，你还希望自己死在哪里呢？”

“在某处荒野；在大海上；在某个该死的山顶。要是必须选择的话。在家里？好啊！整个世界就是我的家。不过，我估计将来自己会死在医院。那又有什么关系呢？只要来世上走过一遭，死在哪里都行。而且，我几乎干过你能想到的所有事情，除了做裁缝和当兵。我曾骑马巡视并修补牧场围栏、剪羊毛、背着行囊流浪、用鱼叉捕杀一头鲸鱼；还曾装配船帆、勘探金矿、给死牛剥皮。我舍弃的钱财，可能比这老家伙辛苦攒了一辈子的还要多。哈，哈！”

小汉格伯的话令贝茜大为震惊。她努力恢复镇定，最后勉强开口道：“该休息了。”

小汉格伯离开所倚墙壁，挺直身子，以严肃的口吻说：“我也该走了。”

但说归说，他并未迈动脚步，而是再次靠到墙上，若有所思地哼起一支古怪曲子的其中一两个小节。

贝茜感到自己忍不住要哭了。“你又开始哼你那些令人伤心的歌了。”她说。

“在墨西哥索诺拉[7]学的。”小汉格伯从容地说，“这是寻金人唱的歌。你没听过？就是流浪汉唱的歌。没有什么能使那些流浪汉在一个地方长待，哪怕女人也不行。过去，在希拉河以北极远处那片出产金子的地区边缘，你偶尔会遇见他们中的一个。我去过那里。在马萨特兰[8]的一位勘探工程师带我去的——让我帮忙照看马车。不管怎么说，身边带个水手，能为你提供许多方便。那片地区尽是沙漠，分布着一道道深不见底的裂口和一座座由岩石构成的悬崖峭壁——那些悬崖峭壁拔地而起，犹如无数高墙和教堂尖塔，只不过大上百倍。此外，各个峡谷中布满巨砾和黑色石块。整片地区，连一片草的叶子都见不着。那里的夕阳，也比我在其他任何地方见过的都要红——像血一样红，而且显得非常愤怒。真是美极了！”

“你不会还想去那里吧？”贝茜结结巴巴地问。

小汉格伯笑了笑。“不会。那片出产金子的地区不是人待的。在那里见到的景象，有时会让我不由得哆嗦。要知道，当时我们是一大帮人结伴同行。但那些寻金人总是独来独往。对于那片地区，早在任何人听说以前，他们就已经知道了。他们仿佛天生就懂勘探，而且也对寻找金子极为狂热，但似乎对金子本身不是很感兴趣。他们总能发现富含金子的地点，接着便转身离去；也许会拣上一些——足够一次玩乐——然后再次出发，寻找更多的金子。他们从不在有房屋的地方长待，他们没有妻子、没有鸡、没有家，也没有朋友。你无法和寻金人做朋友，因为他们永远都在流浪：今天在这里，明天就走了——天晓得去了哪里。他们绝不把发现金子的情况告诉任何人，也从无一个寻金人过上富裕的生活。令他们醉心的，并非金子本身，而是在遍地石头的沙漠一边流浪一边寻找金子的过程。正因为如此，他们永不停歇；也正因为如此，世上尚无任何女人能留住寻金人超过一个星期。这就是我哼的歌。整首歌讲的是，有个漂亮姑娘想方设法留住情郎——一个寻金人——好让对方带给自己许多金子。绝不可能！最后，寻金人还是走了，而那姑娘再也没见过他。”

“那姑娘后来怎么样了？”贝茜轻声问。

“歌里没说。可能哭了一阵吧。寻金人都这样：亲了某个女人，接着就走了。不过，重点在于寻找某样东西，某样……有时，我觉得自己也是一个寻金人。”

“这么说来，没有女人能留住你。”贝茜用粗重的声音开口道，但尚未说完，她的声音便突然开始打颤。

“不会超过一个星期。”小汉格伯开玩笑地说。他愉快而温柔的笑声，牵动着贝茜的心弦。“不过，我爱她们中的每一个人。我愿意为喜欢的女人付出一切。她们害我陷入各种困境，也帮我摆脱各种困境！我对她们一见钟情。此刻，我已经爱上了你，小姐——你叫贝茜，对吧？”

贝茜微微后退，用颤抖的声音笑着说：“你还没见过我长什么样呢。”

小汉格伯殷勤地倾身向前，说：“脸色有点苍白——有些男人会喜欢。不过，你身材不错，贝茜小姐。”

贝茜的心脏怦怦直跳。从来没人对她说过这么多话。

此时，小汉格伯语气一变，说：“不过，我现在肚子有点饿。今天没吃早饭。我看到你爸在吃傍晚茶，你能弄些面包给我吃吃吗？或者——”

小汉格伯正想请求贝茜让他进屋，贝茜却已离去。没关系。在哪儿都一样。眼下的处境真是糟透了！他朋友会怎么想呢？

“我不是向你乞讨，”面对贝茜端来的盘子，小汉格伯边从盘中拿起一片涂着黄油的面包，边开玩笑地说，“而是把你当朋友。我爸很有钱，你也知道。”

“因为你，他一直在挨饿。”

“因为他一时的心血来潮，我也挨过饿。”小汉格伯说着，又拿起一片面包。

“他在世上拥有的一切，都是为你而准备的。”贝茜替汉格伯船长辩解。

“是啊，假如我回来，像某个洞里该死的癞蛤蟆一般，坐在他那堆东西上面。谢谢你。那把铁锹又怎么解释呢，嗯？他表达父爱的方式总是这么古怪。”

“我能用一个星期的时间，说服他和你相认。”贝茜怯怯地说。

小汉格伯饿得只顾狼吞虎咽，并未回话。贝茜顺从地把盘子端近他手边，同时仰起头，开始轻声说话。她的语速极快，而且呼吸急促。小汉格伯听着，听着，变得十分惊奇，吃得也越来越慢，最后嘴巴完全停止了咀嚼。“这是他的诡计，对吧？”他逐渐提高嗓门，刻薄而轻蔑地说，同时不由自主地一挥胳膊，打飞贝茜端着的盘子。最后，他还恶狠狠地咒骂了一句。

贝茜以手扶墙，不断往后退缩。

“不！”小汉格伯发怒道，“他想得美！他盼我回来——好继承他那几个臭钱……谁稀罕他的房子？发疯了——他绝没有发疯！难道你不这么认为吗？他就是想让我任他摆布。过去，他要我做可悲的律师文书；现在，他又想把我关进笼子，使我变成一只该死的乖乖兔。使我变成乖乖兔！使我变成乖乖兔！”小汉格伯说完，发出一阵低沉而愤怒的笑声，令贝茜感到害怕。

“告诉你——叫什么来着——贝茜：全世界加一块儿，也才刚够我打开胳膊肘，更别提一栋小破屋里那该死的客厅了。结婚！他就想让我结婚并安定下来！而且，他很可能已为我选定一个姑娘——天哪！请问，你知道朱迪吗？”

贝茜强忍泪水，无声地抽噎，而且整个身子瑟瑟发抖，显得极为悲伤。但小汉格伯正怒不可遏，焦躁不安，所以并未注意。他咬着自己的大拇指，想着其父的独断专行，感到异常气愤。就在此时，一扇窗户咔嗒咔嗒地拉了起来。

“一个咧嘴大笑、自称有最新消息的家伙。”武断的汉格伯船长，以毫无起伏的语调，一字一顿地说。在贝茜听来，他的声音似乎使黑夜突然发疯，似乎将疯病与不幸倾撒到了地面。“现在，我终于明白这里的人为什么不对劲了，亲爱的孩子。哎呀，难怪！就是这个疯子在四处作梗。别和他扯上任何瓜葛，贝茜。贝茜，听到没有！”

小汉格伯与贝茜呆立原地，默不作声，犹如哑巴。楼上窗边的老人焦躁难安，嘟哝不休。突然，他尖厉地喊道：“贝茜——我看见你了。我要告诉哈里。”

贝茜做出似要逃跑的动作，但最后收住了，并把双手举向两边耳鬓。而身影高大、模糊的小汉格伯犹如一尊青铜像，纹丝不动。在他俩头顶，发疯的黑夜借助一名老人之口，时而呜咽，时而咒骂。

“把他赶走，亲爱的孩子。他只是个流浪汉。你想要的，是一个属于自己的家，一个幸福的家。那家伙没有家——他和哈里不同。他不可能是哈里。哈里明天就回来了。听到了吗？只要再等一天。”汉格伯船长变得更加激动，叽里咕噜地说，“你完全不用担心——哈里一定会娶你的。”

汉格伯船长的声音变得尖厉刺耳、歇斯底里。远处，波浪重重地席卷海堤外侧，发出阵阵低沉而有节奏的哗哗声，在夜空回荡不止。

“他必须娶你。我一定让他娶你。要是他不听，”汉格伯船长发下重誓，“明天，我就立遗嘱剥夺他的继承权，把一切统统留给你。我说到做到。统统留给你。让他饿死去吧。”

窗户咔嗒咔嗒地拉下了。

小汉格伯深吸一口气，接着朝贝茜走近一步。“原来你就是那姑娘。”他用低沉的声音说。贝茜没有动，仍双手夹头，半对着他。“天哪！”小汉格伯嘴角露出似笑非笑但难以觉察的表情，继续说，“我非常想留下来——”

贝茜的胳膊肘抖得厉害。

“——暂住一个星期。”小汉格伯毫不犹豫地说。

贝茜猛地用双手捂住脸。

小汉格伯走到贝茜跟前，轻轻抓住她的两只手腕。贝茜能通过耳朵感觉到对方呼出的气息。

“眼下，我陷入了困境。你必须帮我渡过难关。”小汉格伯试图把贝茜的双手从她脸上扳开，但贝茜坚决不从。于是，小汉格伯放开贝茜的手腕，微微后退。“你有钱吗？”他问，“我必须走了。”

满脸羞愧、浑身颤抖的贝茜飞快地点了点头，随即弯下脖子，开始急急忙忙地摸找连衣裙的口袋。小汉格伯把头转向别处，等待着。

“给你！”贝茜轻声说，“唉，快走！看在上帝的分儿上，快走！要是我有更多——更多——的钱，我会通通给你，好让自己忘记——好让你忘记我。”

小汉格伯伸出手，并说：“绝不可能！我从未忘记你们中的任何一个。有些不止给过我钱——不过，我现在是一个乞丐。你们女人无一例外，必定会帮我摆脱困境。”

小汉格伯大摇大摆地走近楼下客厅的窗户，然后站在从窗帘透出的暗淡灯光中，低头查看掌心的钱：一枚面值半英镑的金币。他随即将之放入衣服口袋。贝茜略微退向窗户边缘。她站在那里，低着脑袋，好像受伤了；双臂无力地垂于体侧，又好像死了。

“别以为用钱就能和我扯上瓜葛。”小汉格伯说，“别以为用钱就能让你撇清关系。”

小汉格伯轻轻一拍，固定好头上的帽子。紧接着，贝茜发觉对方用强有力的臂膀把她整个人抱了起来，导致她双脚离地，脑袋后仰。小汉格伯对着贝茜的脸一阵狂吻。在此过程中，他一言不发，并表现出令人无力抵挡的激情，仿佛急不可耐地想触及对方的灵魂。贝茜苍白的脸颊、坚硬的额头、耷拉的眼皮、没有血色的嘴唇，他一一吻了个遍。让强有力的臂膀紧紧抱住，感受着无力抵挡的狂吻，听着上涨潮水有节奏的哗哗声：对贝茜来说，仿佛保护全镇所有家庭的海堤已经溃决，一个浪头正朝她劈头盖脸打下来。浪头终于过去了；贝茜踉跄着不断后退，直至双肩碰上墙壁。她感到筋疲力尽，仿佛不幸遭遇暴风雨引发的海难，最后让海浪冲到此地。

过了一会儿，贝茜睁开眼睛。坚定而从容的脚步声逐渐远去，带走一个俘获的灵魂。她开始整理所穿连衣裙的下摆，同时呆呆地凝望前方。突然，她冲出院子大门，冲向无边无际的黑夜和空无一人的大街。

“停下！”贝茜喊道，“别走！”

她侧耳倾听，但分不清究竟是雷鸣般的浪涛声，还是另一人要命的脚步声，在无情地击打她的心。不久，所有声音变得越来越微弱，仿佛她正慢慢化作石头。可怕的寂静逐渐笼罩大地——比死亡更可怕。贝茜聚集不断衰退的力量，喊出最后一声恳求：

“哈里！”

脚步声已经消失，连逐渐减弱的回音也听不见了。什么也听不见。拍打海堤的激浪和波涛汹涌的大海，似乎也都没了声音。万籁俱寂，死气沉沉，仿佛她正独自迷失于刚才小汉格伯提起的、遍地石头的沙漠中：许多疯子在那里一边流浪，一边寻找金子，找到后却对金子不屑一顾。

在漆黑的小屋里，汉格伯船长一直密切留意着外面的动静。一扇窗户咔嗒咔嗒地拉了起来。贝茜头顶高高的夜空中，出现一个不可理喻、充斥谎言、令人绝望却又永远透着希望的声音，打破了在遍地石头的沙漠才有的死寂。“他走了吗——那个自称有最新消息的家伙？你听到他还在附近吗，亲爱的孩子？”

贝茜忍不住流下眼泪。“不！不！不！我没再听到他的动静。”她抽泣着回答。

高处的汉格伯船长咯咯地笑了起来，听着十分得意。“你把他吓跑了。真是好姑娘。现在没事了。不要着急，亲爱的孩子。只要再等一天就好。”

在另一栋小屋里，卡尔维老头皇帝似的安坐在扶手椅中，旁边桌上点着一盏球形灯。他用恶魔般的声音吼道：“贝茜！贝茜！叫你呢，贝茜！”

最后，贝茜终于听到其父的咆哮。仿佛屈服于命运一般，她开始默默而踉跄地返回那处压抑的小小地狱——他们父女租住的小屋。那处地狱既无高耸的入口，也无可怕的铭文——用来明示所有失去的希望。贝茜不明白，自己究竟犯了什么罪。

高处的汉格伯船长吵吵嚷嚷，已乐得忘乎所以。

“进去！别吵了！”泪流满面的贝茜，站在门阶处，突然呵斥汉格伯船长。

汉格伯船长毫不理会。他正为终于摆脱使自己“哪里不对劲”的那个人而欣喜若狂：大喊大叫，对永不会到来的明天满怀希望。在贝茜听来，仿佛世上所有盲目乐观的疯子都聚到了一块儿，并集体发作，以令她感到深深的恐惧。

[1] 科尔切斯特，位于英国英格兰埃塞克斯郡。（说明：本书脚注均为译者注。）

[2] 英寻，长度单位，1英寻合6英尺或1.8288米。

[3] 尼普顿，罗马神话中的海神，也就是希腊神话中的波塞冬。

[4] 南希尔兹，英国英格兰东北部港城市。

[5] 傍晚茶，傍晚五六点钟吃的茶点。

[6] 南里奥格兰德，巴西南部的一个州。

[7] 索诺拉，墨西哥西北部的一个州。

[8] 马萨特兰，墨西哥西部港市。

信仰与沮丧

“冬风萧瑟而狂烈，

亲爱的孩子，到我身边来歇；

抛开你的书本和无人陪伴的游戏；

趁夜色渐起，

让我们说着话，打发夜的愁绪。

　　“伊尔妮，在我们栖身的四壁周遭，

十一月的狂风正无声地呼啸；

没有一丝微风能闯进这里，

将我爱女的发丝掀动些许，

我望着炉火，心中欢喜，

她的目光也同样光彩熠熠；

我感到她那柔嫩的脸庞，

欢愉而静默地贴在我的胸膛。

　　“然而，纵使一切如此宁谧，

我心中仍泛起苦涩和忧虑；

绯红的火光欢快地飞舞，

我的思绪却徘徊在冰封的幽谷；

我梦见沼泽，和迷蒙的山岗，

日暮在此没入黑暗与森凉；

因为，在那些凄寒的山间，

我曾钟爱的人们正孤独长眠。

我肝肠寸断，心痛难抑，

惘然的追悔令我身心俱疲，

因为我再也无缘与他们相聚！”

　　“父亲啊，当我年幼，

当你远在海的那头，

这些思虑曾完全将我左右！

我时常枯坐良久，

熬过凄风苦雨的长夜悠悠，

也曾从枕上抬头，却只窥见

暗月徒然挣扎在天间；

还曾惶然聆听声声巨响，

那是惊涛拍岸，浪碎石上；

我满心惊惧，彻夜警觉，

侧耳倾听，不敢安歇。

人生在世，有如此多的恐惧，

可我的父亲啊，逝者却不必这样忧虑。

　　“噢！我们不必为他们忧伤，

坟茔凄凉，却实非他们的眠床；

他们的身躯虽已归入尘土，

快乐的灵魂在上帝身侧享福！

你话虽如此，却嗟叹不止，

怅惋你的挚友终有一死。

啊！亲爱的父亲，可否将原因揭示？

因为，如果一切的确如你所述，

如此伤怀岂不毫无用处；

恰似为一粒渺小的种子叹息，

只因它原本结在树上无人注意，

如今却坠入肥沃的土地，

破壳新生，焕发灿烂的生机——

深深扎根，拔地而起，

葱郁的枝条招摇在天际。

　　“而我，每当念及逝者已矣

却不会恐惧，也不会哭泣，——

我深知彼岸有一片神圣的天地，

　　那港口正为我与至亲开启；

我凝望时间之河浩瀚无际，

　　心中渴望早日抵达那圣地，

我们诞生在那里，我和你

死后也会在此与至亲相遇；

让痛苦与腐坏远离，

再度与上帝合而为一。”

　　“甜美可靠的孩子，你所言极是！

　　你比你的父亲更加睿智；

尘世的风暴怒号不止，

　　却只会增强你渴望的意志——

和你热切的期盼，去穿越风暴与波涛，

　　去经受狂风呼号、海浪咆哮，

最终抵达那永恒的家园，

　　那岿然不渝的彼岸！”

哲人

“停止思索吧，哲人！

　　你沉湎幻梦已经太久

闭塞地囿于这暗室阴沉，

　　不顾夏日的艳阳当头！

环视宇宙的灵魂啊，你的这番思悟

又将以怎样的悲歌结束？”

　　“‘噢，因为有朝一日，

　　我将睡去，湮没无闻，

　　毫不在意

　　雨水浸透或冰雪覆身！

　　天堂的承诺，这些狂烈的火焰

　　无法完全或一半兑现；

　　地狱的威胁，和那永恒的烈焰，

　　无法压抑这不灭的意愿！’”

“我曾这样说过，也依然这样坚称；

　　面对死亡也决不改口——

我小小的躯壳中有三位神明，

　　日日夜夜交战不休；

他们在天堂无法共容

　　却在我的心中相聚；

他们将始终寓于我的心胸

　　直到我遗忘自己的本体！

噢，但愿终有一天，我心间

　　不再有他们彼此纠缠！

噢，但愿终有一日，我能安眠，

　　内心不再苦闷忧烦！”

“一小时前，我看见

　　一个幽灵就站在你这里，

三条河流淌过他脚边，

　　深度相同，流速相一——

一条金黄——一条红得像血一样；

　　另一条如宝石般莹蓝；

但在它们汇合的地方，

　　河流却坠入漆黑的海面。

幽灵将闪烁的目光，

　　投向脚下暗夜般的海洋

突然间，那美好的深处迸发光芒

　　把四下照得通明透亮——

它白亮胜似日光

　　美丽远在它分开的源头之上！”

“即使只为那幽灵、先知，

我也已穷尽一生去观察与找寻；

　　我在天堂、地狱、人间与空中寻觅他的影子——

无止境地探寻，却始终不得要领！

只要能看到他灿烂的双眼

　　点亮那蒙蔽我的阴云，

我就不会这样懦弱地呻唤

　　说要停止思索，放弃生命；

也不会视遗忘为福分，

　　或急切地向死亡伸出手臂，

祈求用这鲜活的呼吸和敏锐的灵魂

　　换取毫无知觉的长眠安息——

噢，就让我死去——好让那力量和意愿

　　停止残酷的交战；

就让失败的正义，与胜利的邪念

　　消弭在长眠之间！”

追忆

你冰冷地躺在地下——身上白雪堆积，

远远地、远远地离去，冷却在阴郁的墓地！

我唯一的爱人啊，难道说，我已忘记去爱你，

时间横扫一切的浪潮，我是否终究无法抵御？

如今，难道我独自一人时，思绪

已不再飞越崇山，徘徊在北部的海岸，

或收拢双翼，在石楠与蕨叶间小憩

看它们覆盖你高贵的心，直到永远？

你冰冷地躺在地下——而在棕褐的山间，

已有十五个寒冬化为春天：

但那不肯遗忘的灵魂依然痴心不变，

纵然已在变迁与挣扎中熬煎多年！

年少时甜蜜的爱人啊，当世俗的潮汐将我卷去，

请原谅，如果我把你忘记；

困扰我的是别的渴望和别的希冀，

那希望只会蒙蔽，却无法让我辜负于你！

再没有新的光芒照亮我的天际，

再没有第二个清晨为我放亮；

我毕生的幸福都由你宝贵的生命赐予，

我毕生的幸福都已与你一同埋葬。

然而，当时光带走往日金色的美梦，

就连绝望都丧失了摧毁的能力；

我才明白生命该如何去珍重，

去巩固与丰富，即使没有欢愉。

于是我告别枉然的激情，止住了泪滴——

抽离我年轻的灵魂，不再渴慕于你；

我抵御那灼人的渴望，好让灵魂不至随你而去，

钻入那早已被我视为己有的墓地。

即便如此，我仍不敢任心灵受苦，

不敢在记忆醉人的疼痛中沉溺；

一旦深陷那美丽的痛楚，

我又如何再将世间的一切舍弃？

期望

对于你，人间依旧是多么美好，

——多么充满幸福！

真正的邪恶是那么地少，

也罕有不幸虚妄的幻影！

春日还能给你那么多的荣光，

夏日还能令你那么快地遗忘

十二月阴郁的日子！

你为何紧抓不放，

青春的珍宝，那欢愉的韶光，

　　当青春已逝，而你已盛年将至？

当你的同辈，

与你财富、年纪相当的同类，

泪眼看他们的晨晖，

　　化作浑噩而沮丧的白昼；

倒不如死时少不更事，

尚未在流浪中迷失心智，

不幸的奴隶，被强烈的激情钳制，

　　沦为虚弱而绝望的鱼肉！

“因为，他们享受时我却在希望，

而满足会将希望摧残；

我如孩童般深信不疑地盼望，

等待至福——和珍贵的安眠。

不久，一个善思的灵魂教导了我，

我们必将渴望，直至生命陨落；

　世间的每一种欢愉

　最终都将逝去，终将遭到厌弃！

“这我早已预见——也不会去追赶

　　那些倏然飞逝的背弃；

但是，我双脚稳固、面色淡然，

那诱人的角逐，我决不参与，

我凝望冲刷沙滩的波浪，

　　融入亘古不变的海洋——

我在此抛下欲望的船锚，

让它深深扎进未知的永恒；

但愿我的心永不疲劳，

始终期待将来的前程！

“如今，在我眼里

是希望的魔力

如青春般，美化了自然界的万般神秘，

　　无论可怖还是美丽——

希望抚慰我的哀愁；

宽解我，当我为他人心忧，

她让我坚强，让我能去承受

　　我命中注定的际遇。

“快乐的抚慰者啊！难道我会胆寒，

难道我会畏惧坟墓的黑暗？

难道我不会含笑倾听死亡的狂澜——

　　只要有你支持，我的向导？

当下的命运愈是偏倚，

我胸中愈是胀满快意，

我会凭借你赋予的力量，坚强地去希冀

　　命运的回报！”

囚徒（节选）

我在地牢中悠闲地漫步，

毫不在意在此受苦的人物；

“严厉的狱卒，拉开沉重的铁条吧！开门！”

他不敢不从——铰链转动，发出刺耳的尖声。

“我们的客人身处黑暗。”我低声说道，望向那地牢，

格栅窗外的天空失却了蓝色，变得又灰又小；

（此时正值美好的春日放声大笑，尽显苏醒的骄傲）

“是啊，黑暗至极！”说话的是我阴沉的向导。

请上帝宽恕我那时年少无知，口不择言；

我开始讥诮，当潮湿的石板上响起冰冷的铁链：

“关押在三重墙内，难道你竟如此可怖，

必须被我们捆绑于此，再用脚镣束缚？”

囚徒抬起头来，她的面容是那么柔和温婉

如同大理石雕刻的圣人，或熟睡婴孩的脸；

她的神情是如此温柔和缓、甜美清丽，

没有一丝悲伤的阴影，或痛苦的痕迹！

囚徒抬手按住前额；

“我挨了打，”她说，“我在忍受折磨；

但你们坚实的门闩和铁条毫无用处，

它们纵是钢铁铸就，也无法将我久久困住。”

冷酷的狱卒嘶声大笑：“难道我该听你胡言乱语；

痴心妄想的可怜人，依你所见，你的请求我会同意？

况且，你以为你的呻吟会融化我主人的心？

哈！那你还不如等太阳熔化花岗岩的坚硬。

“我的主人说话轻声细气，外表温文和善，

但他背后那个灵魂，却比燧石更坚；

我虽看似凶悍粗野，但要论凶暴乖戾，

却远远无法与我体内的鬼魂相比。”

她唇上浮现一抹轻笑，近乎鄙夷，

“我的朋友，”她柔声说，“你何曾听我哀恸哭泣；

除非与至亲重逢，或重返我往日的生活，

我才会流泪控诉——但朋友，不到那时我的眼泪绝不掉落！

“不过还请你转告我那位暴君，我不是注定

长年在忧郁、苍凉与绝望中承受厄运；

每个夜晚，希望的信使都会来到我心头，

许我短暂的生命，与永恒的自由。

“他乘着暮色中涌动的清气，带来西风阵阵，

还有天边最明亮的黄昏与最灿烂的星辰。

风儿戚戚低语，星辰放射温柔的光芒，

眼前的景象瞬息万变，令我深陷渴望。

“我渴望的不是壮年所知的景象，

那时，当我细数未来的悲伤，惊惧让欢愉变得疯狂。

那时，纵使我灵魂的天空布满温暖的光芒，

我也不知它们来自何方，是雷暴还是太阳。

“不过，首先，一切归于宁静——安详悄然降临；

绝望的挣扎不再，骇人的焦躁骤停。

无声的音符抚慰我的心，奏响沉默的乐章，

那种和谐，我今生今世都难以想象。

“随后那无形之物出现；揭示它那看不见的真相；

我摆脱了外在的感官，只用内在的精神感知猜想：

它的羽翼近乎自由——找到了它的家园与海港，

它丈量那海峡，俯冲而下，去挑战最后的边疆。

“噢，但受阻是多么可怕——痛苦是多么巨大——

当耳朵开始倾听，眼睛开始观察；

当脉搏开始跳动，大脑重启思考，

灵魂就触到肉体，肉体就触到镣铐。

“但我依然宁愿忍受剧痛，不肯免去煎熬，

疼痛越是剧烈，幸福就越早降临；

无论它身披地狱的烈焰，抑或天堂的璀璨，

若这幻象是死亡的使者，它就神圣非凡！”

她不再说话，我们默然转身离去——

我们的力量再不能令这囚徒恐惧：

她的脸颊和闪光的双眼，似在向我们宣示，

人类擅自的判决，已被天国废止。

致想象

当我厌倦了终日忧伤，

　　当我尝尽了世间的苦难，

当我迷失方向心中绝望，

　　是你亲切的声音将我呼唤：

噢，我真挚的朋友！我并不孤单，

每当听到你这样细语轻言！

外部的世界已毫无希望；

　　内心的世界我加倍珍惜；

你的世界从不会滋长

　　诡计、仇恨、顾虑和冰冷的怀疑；

在这里，我、自由与你，

拥有统治全境的绝对权力。

即使被危险、愧疚与黑暗环绕，

　　又有什么关系？

只要我们胸怀

　　一片澄明的天宇，

那里有千万道光芒撒播温暖，

无数颗太阳驱散冬的严寒。

理智确会抱怨不停

　　怪真实的自然太过灰暗，

还会告诉那颗受苦的心灵，

　　它珍藏的梦是多么无用，注定枉然；

真理也会粗暴地践踏

那刚刚绽放的幻想之花。

但你始终守在一旁，

　　召回萦绕我心的幻景，

为萎靡的春日注入新的荣光，

　　从死亡中召唤更加鲜活的生命，

再用美妙的轻声细语，

描述那光明如你的真实天地。

你至福的幻景我并不相信，

　　但置身傍晚宁静的时光，

我依然怀着永远感恩的心，

　　欢迎你，仁慈的力量；

你抚慰人类的烦恼忧伤，

当希望枯竭，你就是更好的希望！

她闪耀得多么明亮

她闪耀得多么明亮！

　　我躺在她守护的光辉之下；

当天堂与人间对我轻唱：

　　“明天你要醒来，今夜尽情梦吧。”

好了，来吧，幻想，我美好的爱人！

　　请在我悸动的两鬓上轻吻；

请在我寂寞的卧榻上俯身：

　　赐我安眠，赐我福分。

世界渐渐远去；黑暗的世界，再见！

　　严酷的世界啊，请你回避，直到白天；

纵然这颗心有你无法驯服的骁悍，

　　但它仍需抵抗，若你执意拖延！

你的爱我不愿、不愿分享；

　　你的仇恨只令我笑容绽放；

你的悲伤教人心痛——你的冤屈让人神伤，

　　可是，噢，我决不会轻信你说的谎！

我举头凝望繁星点点

　　闪烁在那永无风浪的海洋，

我唯愿造物所知的一切苦难

　　都包含在你身上！

这就是我今夜的梦境；

　　梦中的天堂绚烂光明

沐浴永恒的福祉，历经无尽的光景

　　在光的轨道上运转不停；

我想象天外另有一重世界，

　　疲惫的双眼无法企及，

在那里智慧从不对爱情不屑，

　　恶名无法将美德遮蔽；

在那里，遍体鳞伤的弱者不必强带笑意，

　　当他被“命运”抽打得痛苦扭曲，

也不必强忍着包容她的恨意，

　　只将叛逆深埋心底。

在那里欢愉不会铸成大错，

　　理智不会徒然地劝说；

背叛绝无力量，真理绝不虚弱，

　　痛苦不是喜悦的必然结果；

在那里平静绝非了无生气的悲叹，

　　希望，不会是灵魂的幻影；

生命不是一场劳役，空虚而短暂；

　　死亡不是主宰一切的暴君！

为我辩护

噢，你明亮的眼睛必须立即回应，

当理性用轻蔑的神情，

嘲笑我的不幸！

噢，你如簧的巧舌必须为我辩护，

说明我为何选择与你共度！

严厉的理性前来审判，

她特意穿上一身晦暗：

你，我的辩护人，会否哑口无言？

不，炫目的天使，请你申辩，

我为何将世界疏远。

为何我竟执意想要

与世间众人分道扬镳，

独自走上无人问津的小道，

权力与财富统统不要——

也没有荣誉的桂冠或快乐的花束环绕。

这些于我确曾美好非凡；

它们或许也曾听我许下誓言，

看我将供品呈上它们的祭坛；

但轻率的赠礼常被无视，

我的供品自然受到鄙视。

于是我衷心起誓，

不再寄望它们祭坛的圣石；

改用整个心灵去崇敬

你，无所不在的幻影；

我的奴隶，我的挚友，我的国君，

你是奴隶，因为你依然听我号令；

必须服从我多变的心情，

作用好坏都由我来决定：

你是挚友，因为无论黑夜天明

你总带给我无间的欢欣，——

我亲爱的痛楚，你撕裂灼烧

让我无法感知世俗的烦恼，

再从我的眼泪中榨取祝祷；

你是国君，纵然克己慎行

却将反叛教给了你的子民。

难道我不该去崇尚，

坚定的信仰，和不竭的希望，

只因我能凭自己的灵魂如愿以偿？

开口吧，幻象之神，为我辩护，

诉说我为何选择与你共度！

1. Faith and Despondency

‘The winter wind is loud and wild,

Come close to me, my darling child;

Forsake thy books, and mateless play;

And, while the night is gathering grey,

We’ll talk its pensive hours away; –

　‘Iernë, round our sheltered hall

November’s gusts unheeded call;

Not one faint breath can enter here

Enough to wave my daughter’s hair,

And I am glad to watch the blaze

Glance from her eyes, with mimic rays;

To feel her cheek so softly pressed,

In happy quiet on my breast.

　‘But, yet, even this tranquillity

Brings bitter, restless thoughts to me;

And, in the red fire’s cheerful glow,

I think of deep glens, blocked with snow;

I dream of moor, and misty hill,

Where evening closes dark and chill;

For, lone, among the mountains cold,

Lie those that I have loved of old.

And my heart aches, in hopeless pain

Exhausted with repinings vain,

That I shall greet them ne’er again!’

　‘Father, in early infancy,

When you were far beyond the sea,

Such thoughts were tyrants over me!

I often sat, for hours together,

Through the long nights of angry weather,

Raised on my pillow, to descry

The dim moon struggling in the sky;

Or, with strained ear, to catch the shock,

Of rock with wave, and wave with rock;

So would I fearful vigil keep,

And, all for listening, never sleep.

But this world’s life has much to dread,

Not so, my Father, with the dead.

　‘Oh! not for them, should we despair,

The grave is drear, but they are not there;

Their dust is mingled with the sod,

Their happy souls are gone to God!

You told me this, and yet you sigh,

And murmur that your friends must die.

Ah! my dear father, tell me why?

For, if your former words were true,

How useless would such sorrow be;

As wise, to mourn the seed which grew

Unnoticed on its parent tree,

Because it fell in fertile earth,

And sprang up to a glorious birth –

Struck deep its root, and lifted high

Its green boughs, in the breezy sky.

‘But, I’ll not fear, I will not weep

For those whose bodies rest in sleep, –

I know there is a blessed shore,

Opening its ports for me, and mine;

And, gazing Time’s wide waters o’er,

I weary for that land divine,

Where we were born, where you and I

Shall meet our Dearest, when we die;

From suffering and corruption free,

Restored into the Deity.’

‘Well hast thou spoken, sweet, trustful child!

And wiser than thy sire;

And worldly tempests, raging wild,

Shall strengthen thy desire –

Thy fervent hope, through storm and foam,

Through wind and ocean’s roar,

To reach, at last, the eternal home,

The steadfast, changeless, shore!’

2. Stars

Ah! why, because the dazzling sun

　　Restored our Earth to joy,

Have you departed, every one,

　　And left a desert sky?

All through the night, your glorious eyes

　　Were gazing down in mine,

And with a full heart’s thankful sighs,

　　I blessed that watch divine.

I was at peace, and drank your beams

　　As they were life to me;

And revelled in my changeful dreams,

　　Like petrel on the sea.

Thought followed thought, star followed star,

　　Through boundless regions, on;

While one sweet influence, near and far,

　　Thrilled through, and proved us one!

Why did the morning dawn to break

　　So great, so pure, a spell;

And scorch with fire, the tranquil cheek,

　　Where your cool radiance fell?

Blood- red, he rose, and, arrow- straight,

　　His fierce beams struck my brow;

The soul of nature, sprang, elate,

　　But mine sank sad and low!

My lids closed down, yet through their veil,

　　I saw him, blazing, still,

And steep in gold the misty dale,

　　And flash upon the hill.

I turned me to the pillow, then,

　　To call back night, and see

Your worlds of solemn light, again,

　　Throb with my heart, and me!

It would not do – the pillow glowed,

　　And glowed both roof and floor;

And birds sang loudly in the wood,

　　And fresh winds shook the door;

The curtains waved, the wakened flies

　　Were murmuring round my room,

Imprisoned there, till I should rise,

　　And give them leave to roam.

Oh, stars, and dreams, and gentle night;

　　Oh, night and stars return!

And hide me from the hostile light,

　　That does not warm, but burn;

That drains the blood of suffering men;

　　Drinks tears, instead of dew;

Let me sleep through his blinding reign,

　　And only wake with you!

3. The Philosopher

‘Enough of thought, philosopher!

Too long hast thou been dreaming

Unenlightened, in this chamber drear,

While summer’s sun is beaming!

Space- sweeping soul, what sad refrain

Concludes thy musings once again?

　　‘ “Oh, for the time when I shall sleep

　　Without identity,

　　And never care how rain may steep,

　　Or snow may cover me!

　　No promised heaven, these wild desires,

　　Could all, or half fulfil;

　　No threatened hell, with quenchless fires,

　　Subdue this quenchless will!” ’

‘So said I, and still say the same;

　　Still, to my death, will say –

Three gods, within this little frame,

　　Are warring night and day;

Heaven could not hold them all, and yet

　　They all are held in me;

And must be mine till I forget

　　My present entity!

Oh, for the time, when in my breast

　　Their struggles will be o’er!

Oh, for the day, when I shall rest,

　　And never suffer more!’

‘I saw a spirit, standing, man,

　　Where thou doth stand – an hour ago,

And round his feet three rivers ran,

　　Of equal depth, and equal flow –

A golden stream – and one like blood;

　　And one like sapphire seemed to be;

But, where they joined their triple flood

　　It tumbled in an inky sea.

The spirit sent his dazzling gaze

　　Down through that ocean’s gloomy night

Then, kindling all, with sudden blaze,

　　The glad deep sparkled wide and bright –

White as the sun, far, far more fair

　　Than its divided sources were!’

‘And even for that spirit, seer,

　　I’ve watched and sought my life- time long;

Sought him in heaven, hell, earth, and air –

　　An endless search, and always wrong!

Had I but seen his glorious eye

　　Once light the clouds that wilder me,

I ne’er had raised this coward cry

　　To cease to think, and cease to be;

I ne’er had called oblivion blest,

　　Nor, stretching eager hands to death,

Implored to change for senseless rest

　　This sentient soul, this living breath –

Oh, let me die – that power and will

　　Their cruel strife may close;

And conquered good, and conquering ill

　　Be lost in one repose!’

5. A Death- Scene

‘O Day! he cannot die

When thou so fair art shining!

O Sun, in such a glorious sky,

So tranquilly declining;

‘He cannot leave thee now,

While fresh west winds are blowing,

And all around his youthful brow

Thy cheerful light is glowing!

‘Edward, awake, awake –

The golden evening gleams

Warm and bright on Arden’s lake –

Arouse thee from thy dreams!

‘Beside thee, on my knee,

My dearest friend! I pray

That thou, to cross the eternal sea,

Wouldst yet one hour delay:

‘I hear its billows roar –

I see them foaming high;

But no glimpse of a further shore

Has blest my straining eye.

‘Believe not what they urge

Of Eden isles beyond;

Turn back, from that tempestuous surge,

To thy own native land.

‘It is not death, but pain

That struggles in thy breast –

Nay, rally, Edward, rouse again;

I cannot let thee rest!’

One long look, that sore reproved me

For the woe I could not bear –

One mute look of suffering moved me

To repent my useless prayer:

And, with sudden check, the heaving

Of distraction passed away;

Not a sign of further grieving

Stirred my soul that awful day.

Paled, at length, the sweet sun setting;

Sunk to peace the twilight breeze:

Summer dews fell softly, wetting

Glen, and glade, and silent trees.

Then his eyes began to weary,

Weighed beneath a mortal sleep;

And their orbs grew strangely dreary,

Clouded, even as they would weep.

But they wept not, but they changed not,

Never moved, and never closed;

Troubled still, and still they ranged not –

Wandered not, nor yet reposed!

So I knew that he was dying –

Stooped, and raised his languid head;

Felt no breath, and heard no sighing,

So I knew that he was dead.

7. Anticipation

How beautiful the earth is still,

To thee – how full of happiness!

How little fraught with real ill,

Or unreal phantoms of distress!

How spring can bring thee glory, yet,

And summer win thee to forget

December’s sullen time!

Why dost thou hold the treasure fast,

Of youth’s delight, when youth is past,

　　And thou art near thy prime?

When those who were thy own compeers,

Equals in fortune and in years,

Have seen their morning melt in tears,

　　To clouded, smileless day;

Blest, had they died untried and young,

Before their hearts went wandering wrong,

Poor slaves, subdued by passions strong,

　　A weak and helpless prey!

‘Because, I hoped while they enjoyed,

And, by fulfilment, hope destroyed;

As children hope, with trustful breast,

I waited bliss – and cherished rest.

A thoughtful spirit taught me, soon,

That we must long till life be done;

That every phase of earthly joy

Must always fade, and always cloy:

‘This I foresaw – and would not chase

　　The fleeting treacheries;

But, with firm foot and tranquil face,

Held backward from that tempting race,

Gazed o’er the sands the waves efface,

　　To the enduring seas –

There cast my anchor of desire

Deep in unknown eternity;

Nor ever let my spirit tire,

With looking for what is to be!

‘It is hope’s spell that glorifies,

Like youth, to my maturer eyes,

All Nature’s million mysteries,

　　The fearful and the fair –

Hope soothes me in the griefs I know;

She lulls my pain for others’ woe,

And makes me strong to undergo

　　What I am born to bear.

‘Glad comforter! will I not brave,

Unawed, the darkness of the grave?

Nay, smile to hear Death’s billows rave –

　　Sustained, my guide, by thee?

The more unjust seems present fate,

The more my spirit swells elate,

Strong, in thy strength, to anticipate

　　Rewarding destiny!’

8. The Prisoner (A Fragment)

In the dungeon- crypts, idly did I stray,

Reckless of the lives wasting there away;

‘Draw the ponderous bars! open, Warder stern!’

He dared not say me nay – the hinges harshly turn.

‘Our guests are darkly lodged,’ I whisper’d, gazing through

The vault, whose grated eye showed heaven more grey than blue;

(This was when glad spring laughed in awaking pride;)

‘Aye, darkly lodged enough!’ returned my sullen guide.

Then, God forgive my youth; forgive my careless tongue;

I scoffed, as chill chains on the damp flag- stones rung:

‘Confined in triple walls, art thou so much to fear,

That we must bind thee down and clench thy fetters here?’

The captive raised her face, it was as soft and mild

As sculptured marble saint, or slumbering unwean’d child;

It was so soft and mild, it was so sweet and fair,

Pain could not trace a line, nor grief a shadow there!

The captive raised her hand and pressed it to her brow;

‘I have been struck,’ she said, ‘and I am suffering now;

Yet these are little worth, your bolts and irons strong,

And, were they forged in steel, they could not hold me long.’

Hoarse laughed the jailer grim: ‘Shall I be won to hear;

Dost think, fond, dreaming wretch, that I shall grant thy prayer?

Or, better still, wilt melt my master’s heart with groans?

Ah! sooner might the sun thaw down these granite stones.

‘My master’s voice is low, his aspect bland and kind,

But hard as hardest flint, the soul that lurks behind;

And I am rough and rude, yet not more rough to see

Than is the hidden ghost that has its home in me.’

About her lips there played a smile of almost scorn,

‘My friend,’ she gently said, ‘you have not heard me mourn;

When you my kindred’s lives, my lost life, can restore,

Then may I weep and sue, – but never, friend, before!

‘Still, let my tyrants know, I am not doomed to wear

Year after year in gloom, and desolate despair;

A messenger of Hope, comes every night to me,

And offers for short life, eternal liberty.

‘He comes with western winds, with evening’s wandering airs,

With that clear dusk of heaven that brings the thickest stars.

Winds take a pensive tone, and stars a tender fire,

And visions rise, and change, that kill me with desire.

‘Desire for nothing known in my maturer years,

When Joy grew mad with awe, at counting future tears.

When, if my spirit’s sky was full of flashes warm,

I knew not whence they came, from sun, or thunder storm.

‘But, first, a hush of peace – a soundless calm descends;

The struggle of distress, and fierce impatience ends.

Mute music soothes my breast, unuttered harmony,

That I could never dream, till Earth was lost to me.

‘Then dawns the Invisible; the Unseen its truth reveals;

My outward sense is gone, my inward essence feels:

Its wings are almost free – its home, its harbour found,

Measuring the gulf, it stoops, and dares the final bound.

‘Oh, dreadful is the check – intense the agony –

When the ear begins to hear, and the eye begins to see;

When the pulse begins to throb, the brain to think again,

The soul to feel the flesh, and the flesh to feel the chain.

‘Yet I would lose no sting, would wish no torture less,

The more that anguish racks, the earlier it will bless;

And robed in fires of hell, or bright with heavenly shine,

If it but herald death, the vision is divine!’

She ceased to speak, and we, unanswering, turned to go –

We had no further power to work the captive woe:

Her cheek, her gleaming eye, declared that man had given

A sentence, unapproved, and overruled by Heaven.

11. To Imagination

When weary with the long day’s care,

　　And earthly change from pain to pain,

And lost and ready to despair,

　　Thy kind voice calls me back again:

Oh, my true friend! I am not lone,

While thou canst speak with such a tone!

So hopeless is the world without;

　　The world within I doubly prize;

Thy world, where guile, and hate, and doubt,

　　And cold suspicion never rise;

Where thou, and I, and Liberty,

Have undisputed sovereignty.

What matters it, that, all around,

　　Danger, and guilt, and darkness lie,

If but within our bosom’s bound

　　We hold a bright, untroubled sky,

Warm with ten thousand mingled rays

Of suns that know no winter days?

Reason, indeed, may oft complain

　　For Nature’s sad reality,

And tell the suffering heart how vain

　　Its cherished dreams must always be;

And Truth may rudely trample down

The flowers of Fancy, newly- blown:

But, thou art ever there, to bring

　　The hovering vision back, and breathe

New glories o’er the blighted spring,

　　And call a lovelier Life from Death,

And whisper, with a voice divine,

Of real worlds, as bright as thine.

I trust not to thy phantom bliss,

　　Yet, still, in evening’s quiet hour,

With never- failing thankfulness,

　　I welcome thee, Benignant Power;

Sure solacer of human cares,

And sweeter hope, when hope despairs!

12. How Clear She Shines

How clear she shines! How quietly

　　I lie beneath her guardian light;

While heaven and earth are whispering me,

　　‘Tomorrow, wake, but, dream tonight.’

Yes, Fancy, come, my Fairy love!

　　These throbbing temples softly kiss;

And bend my lonely couch above

　　And bring me rest, and bring me bliss.

The world is going; dark world, adieu!

　　Grim world, conceal thee till the day;

The heart, thou canst not all subdue,

　　Must still resist, if thou delay!

Thy love I will not, will not share;

　　Thy hatred only wakes a smile;

Thy griefs may wound – thy wrongs may tear,

　　But, oh, thy lies shall ne’er beguile!

While gazing on the stars that glow

　　Above me, in that stormless sea,

I long to hope that all the woe

　　Creation knows, is held in thee!

And this shall be my dream tonight;

　　I’ll think the heaven of glorious spheres

Is rolling on its course of light

　　In endless bliss, through endless years;

I’ll think, there’s not one world above,

　　Far as these straining eyes can see,

Where wisdom ever laughed at Love,

　　Or Virtue crouched to Infamy;

Where, writhing ’neath the strokes of Fate,

　　The mangled wretch was forced to smile;

To match his patience ’gainst her hate,

　　His heart rebellious all the while.

Where Pleasure still will lead to wrong,

　　And helpless Reason warn in vain;

And Truth is weak, and Treachery strong;

　　And Joy the surest path to Pain;

And Peace, the lethargy of Grief;

　　And Hope, a phantom of the soul;

And Life, a labour, void and brief;

　　And Death, the despot of the whole!

14. Plead for Me

Oh, thy bright eyes must answer now,

When Reason, with a scornful brow,

Is mocking at my overthrow!

Oh, thy sweet tongue must plead for me

And tell, why I have chosen thee!

Stern Reason is to judgment come,

Arrayed in all her forms of gloom:

Wilt thou, my advocate, be dumb?

No, radiant angel, speak and say,

Why I did cast the world away.

Why I have persevered to shun

The common paths that others run,

And on a strange road journeyed on,

Heedless, alike, of wealth and power –

Of glory’s wreath and pleasure’s flower.

These, once, indeed, seemed Beings Divine;

And they, perchance, heard vows of mine,

And saw my offerings on their shrine;

But, careless gifts are seldom prized,

And mine were worthily despised.

So, with a ready heart I swore

To seek their altar- stone no more;

And gave my spirit to adore

Thee, ever- present, phantom thing;

My slave, my comrade, and my king,

A slave, because I rule thee still;

Incline thee to my changeful will,

And make thy influence good or ill:

A comrade, for by day and night

Thou art my intimate delight, –

My darling pain that wounds and sears

And wrings a blessing out from tears

By deadening me to earthly cares;

And yet, a king, though Prudence well

Have taught thy subject to rebel.

And am I wrong to worship, where

Faith cannot doubt, nor hope despair,

Since my own soul can grant my prayer?

Speak, God of visions, plead for me,

And tell why I have chosen thee!

15. Self- Interrogation

‘The evening passes fast away,

　　’Tis almost time to rest;

What thoughts has left the vanished day,

　　What feelings, in thy breast?’

‘The vanished day? It leaves a sense

　　Of labour hardly done;

Of little, gained with vast expense, –

　　A sense of grief alone!

‘Time stands before the door of Death,

　　Upbraiding bitterly;

And Conscience, with exhaustless breath,

　　Pours black reproach on me:

‘And though I’ve said that Conscience lies,

　　And Time should Fate condemn;

Still, sad Repentance clouds my eyes,

　　And makes me yield to them!’

‘Then art thou glad to seek repose?

　　Art glad to leave the sea,

And anchor all thy weary woes

　　In calm Eternity?

‘Nothing regrets to see thee go –

　　Not one voice sobs “farewell”,

And where thy heart has suffered so,

　　Canst thou desire to dwell?’

‘Alas! The countless links are strong

　　That bind us to our clay;

The loving spirit lingers long,

　　And would not pass away!

‘And rest is sweet, when laurelled fame

　　Will crown the soldier’s crest;

But, a brave heart, with a tarnished name,

　　Would rather fight than rest.’

‘Well, thou hast fought for many a year,

　　Hast fought thy whole life through,

Hast humbled Falsehood, trampled Fear;

　　What is there left to do?’

‘’Tis true, this arm has hotly striven,

　　Has dared what few would dare;

Much have I done, and freely given,

　　But little learnt to bear!’

‘Look on the grave, where thou must sleep,

　　Thy last, and strongest foe;

It is endurance not to weep,

　　If that repose seem woe.

‘The long war closing in defeat,

　　Defeat serenely borne,

Thy midnight rest may still be sweet,

　　And break in glorious morn!’

16. Death

Death! that struck when I was most confiding

In my certain faith of joy to be –

Strike again, Time’s withered branch dividing

From the fresh root of Eternity!

Leaves, upon Time’s branch, were growing brightly,

Full of sap, and full of silver dew;

Birds beneath its shelter gathered nightly;

Daily round its flowers the wild bees flew.

Sorrow passed, and plucked the golden blossom;

Guilt stripped off the foliage in its pride;

But, within its parent’s kindly bosom,

Flowed for ever Life’s restoring tide.

Little mourned I for the parted gladness,

For the vacant nest and silent song –

Hope was there, and laughed me out of sadness;

Whispering, ‘Winter will not linger long!’

And, behold! with tenfold increase blessing,

Spring adorned the beauty- burdened spray;

Wind and rain and fervent heat, caressing,

Lavished glory on that second May!

High it rose – no winged grief could sweep it;

Sin was scared to distance with its shine;

Love, and its own life, had power to keep it

From all wrong – from every blight but thine!

Cruel Death! The young leaves droop and languish;

Evening’s gentle air may still restore –

No! the morning sunshine mocks my anguish –

Time, for me, must never blossom more!

Strike it down, that other boughs may flourish

Where that perished sapling used to be;

Thus, at least, its mouldering corpse will nourish

That from which it sprung – Eternity.

17. Stanzas to —

Well, some may hate, and some may scorn,

And some may quite forget thy name;

But my sad heart must ever mourn

Thy ruined hopes, thy blighted fame!

’Twas thus I thought, an hour ago,

Even weeping o’er that wretch’s woe;

One word turned back my gushing tears,

And lit my altered eye with sneers.

Then ‘Bless the friendly dust,’ I said,

‘That hides thy unlamented head!

Vain as thou wert, and weak as vain,

The slave of Falsehood, Pride, and Pain, –

My heart has nought akin to thine;

Thy soul is powerless over mine.’

But these were thoughts that vanished too;

Unwise, unholy, and untrue:

Do I despise the timid deer,

Because his limbs are fleet with fear?

Or, would I mock the wolf’s death- howl,

Because his form is gaunt and foul?

Or, hear with joy the leveret’s cry,

Because it cannot bravely die?

No! Then above his memory

Let Pity’s heart as tender be;

Say, ‘Earth, lie lightly on that breast

And, kind Heaven, grant that spirit rest!’

18. Honour’s Martyr

The moon is full this winter night;

　　The stars are clear, though few;

And every window glistens bright,

　　With leaves of frozen dew.

The sweet moon through your lattice gleams

　　And lights your room like day;

And there you pass, in happy dreams,

　　The peaceful hours away!

While I, with effort hardly quelling

　　The anguish in my breast,

Wander about the silent dwelling,

　　And cannot think of rest.

The old clock in the gloomy hall

　　Ticks on, from hour to hour;

And every time its measured call

　　Seems lingering slow and slower:

And oh, how slow that keen- eyed star

　　Has tracked the chilly grey!

What, watching yet! how very far

　　The morning lies away!

Without your chamber door I stand;

　　Love, are you slumbering still?

My cold heart, underneath my hand,

　　Has almost ceased to thrill.

Bleak, bleak the east wind sobs and sighs,

　　And drowns the turret bell,

Whose sad note, undistinguished, dies

　　Unheard, like my farewell!

Tomorrow, Scorn will blight my name,

　　And Hate will trample me,

Will load me with a coward’s shame –

　　A traitor’s perjury.

False friends will launch their covert sneers;

　　True friends will wish me dead;

And I shall cause the bitterest tears

　　That you have ever shed.

The dark deeds of my outlawed race

　　Will then like virtues shine;

And men will pardon their disgrace,

　　Beside the guilt of mine.

For, who forgives the accursed crime

　　Of dastard treachery?

Rebellion, in its chosen time,

　　May Freedom’s champion be;

Revenge may stain a righteous sword,

　　It may be just to slay;

But, traitor, traitor, – from that word

　　All true breasts shrink away!

Oh, I would give my heart to death,

　　To keep my honour fair;

Yet, I’ll not give my inward faith

　　My honour’s name to spare!

Not even to keep your priceless love,

　　Dare I, Beloved, deceive;

This treason should the future prove,

　　Then, only then, believe!

I know the path I ought to go;

　　I follow fearlessly,

Inquiring not what deeper woe

　　Stern duty stores for me.

So foes pursue, and cold allies

　　Mistrust me, every one:

Let me be false in others’ eyes,

　　If faithful in my own.

20. My Comforter

Well hast thou spoken, and yet, not taught

　　A feeling strange or new;

Thou hast but roused a latent thought,

A cloud- closed beam of sunshine, brought

　　To gleam in open view.

Deep down, concealed within my soul,

　　That light lies hid from men;

Yet, glows unquenched – though shadows roll,

Its gentle ray cannot control,

　　About the sullen den.

Was I not vexed, in these gloomy ways

　　To walk alone so long?

Around me, wretches uttering praise,

Or howling o’er their hopeless days,

　　And each with Frenzy’s tongue; –

A brotherhood of misery,

　　Their smiles as sad as sighs;

Whose madness daily maddened me,

Distorting into agony

　　The bliss before my eyes!

So stood I, in Heaven’s glorious sun,

　　And in the glare of Hell;

My spirit drank a mingled tone,

Of seraph’s song, and demon’s moan;

What my soul bore, my soul alone

　　Within itself may tell!

Like a soft air, above a sea,

　　Tossed by the tempest’s stir;

A thaw- wind, melting quietly

The snow- drift, on some wintry lea;

No: what sweet thing resembles thee,

　　My thoughtful Comforter?

And yet a little longer speak,

　　Calm this resentful mood;

And while the savage heart grows meek,

For other token do not seek,

But let the tear upon my cheek

　　Evince my gratitude!

亚当的诅咒

有一年夏末，我们一起坐着，

有一个美丽文雅的女人，你的密友

还有你和我，在谈论诗歌。

我说：“一行诗也许要花几小时；

但它如果不似灵感迸发的神思，

我们是否打磨都没有用。

擦洗厨房地面，或像老乞丐

去采石，无论在何种天气；

要清晰地发出甜美的声音，

远要比这些困难，然而

我们却被一帮人嘈杂地称为懒人，

那些银行家、校长和教士

殉道者所说的俗世。”

　　　　　　　随后

那美丽文雅的女人，为她

很多人因发现她的声音甜美

低沉而悲叹不已，

回答说：“生为女人要知道——

尽管他们在学校里不说——

变得美丽必须劳作。”

我说：“无疑，自亚当堕落以来，

所有美好的事物都要付出辛劳。

恋人们曾以为爱情应该

大量混杂着高度的殷勤，

他们叹息，带着学者的神色

引用美丽古书里的先例；

而现在看来正是一件闲散的事。”

说到爱，我们都变得沉静；

我们看着白日将尽时的余烬，

在天空颤动着的蓝绿色中，

月亮残损，像被时间之水

冲洗的贝壳，随着星辰

反复起落，在年岁间破碎。

我有个想法，只说给你听：

你是美丽的，而我致力于

以古老高贵的方式爱你；

那看起来很幸福，但我们

已深感倦怠，如那空洞的月亮。

一九一三年九月

一旦苏醒，你们所需做的

仅仅是在油腻的钱箱里摸索，

将半便士加到一便士，

颤抖着，祈祷再祈祷，直到

你们已榨干骨头里的髓液；

因为人生来就是为了祈祷和储蓄：

浪漫的爱尔兰已死去、消失，

和奥利里[1]一起躺在坟墓里。

但他们是不同的种类，

他们的名字终止了你们幼稚的游戏，

他们像风，走遍世界，

但鲜有时间祈祷，

因刽子手的绳索已为他们转动，

上帝保佑，他们能攒什么钱？

浪漫的爱尔兰已死去、消失，

和奥利里一起躺在坟墓里。

为此，野天鹅展开

灰色的翅膀，在每次的潮汐之上？

所有的血为此而流？

爱德华·菲茨杰拉德为此而死？

还有罗伯特·艾米特和沃尔夫·托尼？

以及所有那些勇士的狂热？

浪漫的爱尔兰已死去、消失，

和奥利里一起躺在坟墓里。

但我们也可以将时间再次倒转，

将他们称为流亡者，当他们

受尽了孤独和伤痛，

你会呼喊“某个女人的黄发

让所有母亲的儿子发狂”：

他们对付出看得那么轻，

但就让他们这样吧，他们死去、消失，

和奥利里一起躺在坟墓里。

[1] 奥利里（O’Leary）,即约翰·奥利里，爱尔兰民族主义者，在英格兰囚禁五年，流亡十五年后，1885年返回都柏林。

一九一六年复活节[1]

白日结束时，我遇见他们

带着鲜活的面容，

从灰暗的十八世纪房子

那些柜台或办公桌走来。

我路过时，点点头

或者说些客套的闲话，

或者逗留一会儿，说些

客套的闲话，

尽管这之前，我已想到用

讽刺的故事或挖苦的言语

去取悦我的同伴，

在俱乐部的炉火旁，

确信他们和我一样

不过是生活在小丑之地：

一切都变了，完全变了：

一种可怕的美诞生了。

那个女人将白天消耗

在无知的良好意愿里，

她的夜晚用于争论，

直到声音变得尖锐。

还有什么声音比她的更甜美，

当，她年轻美丽

骑马猎兔？

这个男人办了所学校，

骑着我们的飞马[2]；

那是他的助手和朋友

正加入他的部队；

他可能最终赢得声名，

他的天性多么敏感，

他的思想多么大胆甜美。

另一个人，我曾认为

是个酒鬼，虚荣自负的蠢人。

他对我某个心爱的人

做过最痛心的错事，

但我将他列入歌中；

他，也放弃了他的角色，

在那偶然的喜剧中。

轮到他时，他也变了，

完全变了：

一种可怕的美诞生了。

众多的心怀着一个目的

历经夏日和冬季，似乎

中了魔法，变成石头

去扰乱活跃的溪流。

从路上而来的马匹，

骑手，在翻滚的云朵间

排列的鸟群，

它们每一分钟都在改变；

一只马蹄滑落到水边，

一匹马在水中泼溅；

一只长腿母松鸡俯冲而下

对着公松鸡呼叫。

它们每一分钟都在生活：

石头居于这一切的中心。

太漫长的牺牲

能将一颗心造就成石头，

哦，何时才能到头？

只有上天才能回答，我们

只能低声念着一个个名字，

像母亲叫唤他的孩子，

当睡意最终降临

在跑得狂野的四肢之上，

除了夜晚还能是什么？

不，不，这不是夜晚而是死；

这死终究是不必要的吗？

因为英格兰也许会信守承诺

为它做过和说过的一切。

我们知道他们的梦想，知道

他们梦想过然后死了，这就足够；

假如爱的过量

使他们迷惑至死又能怎样？

我在诗中写下——

麦克唐纳和麦克布莱德，

康诺利和皮尔斯，

现在，以及以后，

在任何身着绿装的地方，

一切都变了，完全变了：

一种可怕的美诞生了。

1916年9月25日

[1] 1916年4月24日，复活节的第二天，爱尔兰共和兄弟会在都柏林起义，宣告爱尔兰共和国成立。不久被英格兰镇压，包括诗中提及的麦克唐纳、麦克布莱德、康诺利、皮尔斯等十五位领导人遇害。

[2] 飞马（winged horse）,指的是希腊神话中的飞马珀伽索斯，相传珀伽索斯在赫利孔山上踏过时踩出了泉水，诗人饮之可获灵感，因此它也被视为文艺缪斯的标志。

在学童中间

Ⅰ

我走过长长的教室询问；

戴白头巾的和善老修女作答；

孩子们要学习算术和唱歌，

学习阅读和历史，

学习剪裁缝补，以最现代的方式

规整所有事物——孩子们的双眼

带着瞬间的惊奇，凝视着

一个六十岁微笑的公众人物。

Ⅱ

我梦见一个丽达似的身体，俯身

在沉没的火堆上，她讲一个故事，

有关刺耳的谴责或微小的事件

将稚气的一天变成悲剧——

说完，出于年轻人的同感，

我们两种天性混合为一个球体，

或者，改一下柏拉图的比喻，

成为同一个壳里的蛋黄和蛋清。

Ⅲ

想起那一阵悲伤或愤怒，

我看着这个或那个小孩，

想知道她在那个年纪是否也这样站过——

因为即使是天鹅的女儿也能分享

每一个涉水者所传承的事物——

是否有那种颜色的脸颊或头发，

因此我的心变得狂野：

她站在我面前，像个鲜活的孩子。

Ⅳ

她现在的形象飘进我的心中——

是十五世纪的匠人将它塑造

成脸颊凹陷的模样，像啜饮了风

吞食了大量的阴影？

尽管我从不是丽达的种类，

但也曾有美丽的羽毛——那足够了，

最好是以微笑面对所有微笑，显示出

这是一个知足的老稻草人。

Ⅴ

什么样年轻的母亲，膝上的身形

已被生殖之蜜背叛，

不得不睡觉、尖叫，挣扎着逃离，

如回忆或药物所决定的那样，

如果看见那身形，头上带着六十个

或更多的严冬，她会认为她的儿子

是一种补偿吗，对生他的剧痛，

或是对他前程的不确定性？

Ⅵ

柏拉图认为自然不过是泡沫，

在万物幽灵般的范式上游戏；

更为结实的亚里士多德执鞭

抽打万王之王的下体；

举世闻名的金大腿毕达哥拉斯

用手指拨弄琴弓或琴弦，

演凑一曲星辰之歌，被无心的缪斯听见；

老手杖上的旧衣裳吓坏了一只鸟。

Ⅶ

修女和母亲们都崇拜偶像，

但那些烛光所照亮的并不是

赋予母亲的空想以生命的东西，

不过是维护了大理石和青铜像——哦，诸神

那激情、虔诚或喜爱所知道的，

那所有天国的荣耀所象征的——

哦，人类事业自我生长的嘲弄者。

Ⅷ

劳作是开花或舞蹈，在那儿

身体不会因取悦灵魂而挫伤，

美不会诞生于自身的绝望，

老眼昏花的智慧不会出自午夜的油灯。

哦，栗子树，根系粗壮的绽放者，

你是叶子、花朵还是树干？

哦，随音乐摇摆的身体，哦，明亮的眼神，

我们如何能分辨舞蹈和舞者？

青金石雕

（致哈里·克里夫顿）

我听到那些歇斯底里的女人说，

她们已厌倦了总是很快乐的

诗人的调色板和琴弓，

因为每个人都知道或应该知道

如果没有激烈的事情发生，

飞机和飞艇将会出现，

像比利王[1]投掷炸弹，

直到将城镇夷为平地。

所有人都在表演他们的悲剧，

这是高傲的哈姆雷特，这是李尔王，

那是奥菲利亚，那是科迪莉亚；

但他们到了最后一幕，

巨大的帷幕将会落下，

如果配得上剧中的重要角色，

他们不会中断台词而哭泣。

他们知道哈姆雷特和李尔王是快乐的；

快乐改变了所有那恐惧的。

所有人都有目标，寻找和失落；

终止；天国的光照进头脑：

悲剧行进到高潮。

尽管哈姆雷特在漫步，李尔王在愤怒，

所有的幕布立即垂落，

在一万个舞台上，

它不能增长一英寸或一盎司。

他们来了，步行，坐船，

或骑着骆驼、马、驴、骡，

古老的文明惨遭屠戮。

接着，他们和他们的智慧陷于毁灭。

不再有卡利马科斯[2]的手工艺品了，

他雕刻大理石像是在铸造青铜，

塑造看起来飘动的衣物，

仿佛有海风吹过角落，挺立着；

他那长长的灯罩，形状像是

细长棕榈树的枝干，但也只立了一天；

万物崩溃，而又重建，

而那些重建的人是快乐的。

两个中国人，第三个在他们身后，

被刻在青金石雕上，

他们头上，飞过一只长腿的鸟，

象征着长寿；

第三个人，无疑是仆人，

背着一件乐器。

石头上每一处褪色的斑点，

每一处偶然的裂缝或凹痕，

看起来像是一条河或一次雪崩，

或是仍在落雪的高耸的斜坡，

而确切无疑地，李子树或樱桃枝

美化了半途上的小屋。

那些中国人向上爬着，而我

乐于想象他们坐在那儿；

凝望着山和天空，

以及所有悲剧的场景。

其中一个要求听首悲伤的曲子；

娴熟的手指便开始弹奏。

他们的眼睛，四周布满皱纹，他们的眼睛，

他们古老的、闪烁的眼睛，是快乐的。

[1] 比利王（King Billy），即威廉三世，小名比利。

[2] 卡利马科斯（Callimachus）,古希腊建筑家、雕塑家。

马戏团动物的逃亡

Ⅰ

我寻找一个主题，徒劳地寻找，

有六个星期左右，我每天都在找。

可能到最后，我会一无所有，

但我必须满足我的心，尽管

历经冬日和夏季，直至老年开始，

我的马戏团动物都在表演，

那些踩高跷的男孩、油亮的战车，

狮子，以及女士和先生们知道的那些。

Ⅱ

除了列举古老的主题，我能做什么？

首先是海骑士奥辛牵着我的鼻子

穿过三座迷人的岛，寓言般的梦境，

徒劳的快乐，徒劳的战斗，徒劳的休眠，

诸多怨恨之心的主题，或者看起来是，

用来装饰古老的歌或宫廷表演；

但我让他驰骋又有什么可忧虑的，

我，渴求他仙女般新娘的胸脯？

然后一个相反的事实填入戏剧中，

我给它起名为《凯瑟琳女伯爵》，

她，极度的怜悯，让她放弃了灵魂，

但主宰一切的上天干预，拯救了它。

我以为我亲爱的必将毁灭她的灵魂，

让执着和憎恨奴役它，

而这催生了一个梦，并且很快

这个梦本身就拥有了我所有的思想和爱。

当蠢货和盲人偷走了面包，

库丘林则与不受支配的海战斗；

这就是心的神秘之处，而当所有都已说尽，

是梦本身迷住了我：

角色被一份事业所隔绝

去独占现在，去支配记忆。

演员和多彩的舞台占据了我所有的爱，

而不是那些它们所象征的事物。

Ⅲ

那些主宰一切的形象因其完整

在纯洁的心智中成长，但又从何开始？

一堆垃圾，或者街道上的残渣，

旧水壶，旧瓶子，和一个破烂的罐子，

老铁，老骨头，老旧的破衣服，那守着

钱柜的疯狂的荡妇。既然我的梯子已被撤去，

我必须躺下，在所有梯子起始的地方，

在我的心，那污秽的破烂商铺里。

Easter 1916

I have met them at close of day

Coming with vivid faces

From counter or desk among grey

Eighteenth- century houses.

I have passed with a nod of the head

Or polite meaningless words,

Or have lingered awhile and said

Polite meaningless words,

And thought before I had done

Of a mocking tale or a gibe

To please a companion

Around the fire at the club,

Being certain that they and I

But lived where motley is worn:

All changed, changed utterly:

A terrible beauty is born.

That woman’s days were spent

In ignorant good- will,

Her nights in argument

Until her voice grew shrill.

What voice more sweet than hers

When, young and beautiful,

She rode to harriers?

This man had kept a school

And rode our wingèd horse;

This other his helper and friend

Was coming into his force;

He might have won fame in the end,

So sensitive his nature seemed,

So daring and sweet his thought.

This other man I had dreamed

A drunken, vainglorious lout.

He had done most bitter wrong

To some who are near my heart,

Yet I number him in the song;

He, too, has resigned his part

In the casual comedy;

He, too, has been changed in his turn,

Transformed utterly:

A terrible beauty is born.

Hearts with one purpose alone

Through summer and winter seem

Enchanted to a stone

To trouble the living stream.

The horse that comes from the road,

The rider, the birds that range

From cloud to tumbling cloud,

Minute by minute they change;

A shadow of cloud on the stream

Changes minute by minute;

A horse- hoof slides on the brim,

And a horse plashes within it;

The long- legged moor- hens dive,

And hens to moor- cocks call;

Minute by minute they live:

The stone’s in the midst of all.

Too long a sacrifice

Can make a stone of the heart.

O when may it suffice?

That is Heaven’s part, our part

To murmur name upon name,

As a mother names her child

When sleep at last has come

On limbs that had run wild.

What is it but nightfall?

No, no, not night but death;

Was it needless death after all?

For England may keep faith

For all that is done and said.

We know their dream; enough

To know they dreamed and are dead;

And what if excess of love

Bewildered them till they died?

I write it out in a verse –

MacDonagh and MacBride

And Connolly and Pearse

Now and in time to be,

Wherever green is worn,

Are changed, changed utterly:

A terrible beauty is born.

September 25, 1916

Among School Children

I

I walk through the long schoolroom questioning;

A kind old nun in a white hood replies;

The children learn to cipher and to sing,

To study reading books and histories,

To cut and sew, be neat in everything

In the best modern way – the children’s eyes

In momentary wonder stare upon

A sixty- year- old smiling public man.

II

I dream of a Ledaean body, bent

Above a sinking fire, a tale that she

Told of a harsh reproof, or trivial event

That changed some childish day to tragedy –

Told, and it seemed that our two natures blent

Into a sphere from youthful sympathy,

Or else, to alter Plato’s parable,

Into the yolk and white of the one shell.

III

And thinking of that fit of grief or rage

I look upon one child or t’other there

And wonder if she stood so at that age –

For even daughters of the swan can share

Something of every paddler’s heritage –

And had that colour upon cheek or hair,

And thereupon my heart is driven wild:

She stands before me as a living child.

IV

Her present image floats into the mind –

Did Quattrocento finger fashion it

Hollow of cheek as though it drank the wind

And took a mess of shadows for its meat?

And I though never of Ledaean kind

Had pretty plumage once – enough of that,

Better to smile on all that smile, and show

There is a comfortable kind of old scarecrow.

V

What youthful mother, a shape upon her lap

Honey of generation had betrayed,

And that must sleep, shriek, struggle to escape

As recollection or the drug decide,

Would think her son, did she but see that shape

With sixty or more winters on its head,

A compensation for the pang of his birth,

Or the uncertainty of his setting forth?

VI

Plato thought nature but a spume that plays

Upon a ghostly paradigm of things;

Solider Aristotle played the taws

Upon the bottom of a king of kings;

World- famous golden- thighed Pythagoras

Fingered upon a fiddle- stick or strings

What a star sang and careless Muses heard:

Old clothes upon old sticks to scare a bird.

VII

Both nuns and mothers worship images,

But those the candles light are not as those

That animate a mother’s reveries,

But keep a marble or a bronze repose.

And yet they too break hearts – O Presences

That passion, piety or affection knows,

And that all heavenly glory symbolise –

O self- born mockers of man’s enterprise;

VIII

Labour is blossoming or dancing where

The body is not bruised to pleasure soul,

Nor beauty born out of its own despair,

Nor blear- eyed wisdom out of midnight oil.

O chestnut- tree, great rooted blossomer,

Are you the leaf, the blossom or the bole?

O body swayed to music, O brightening glance,

How can we know the dancer from the dance?

Lapis Lazuli

(for harry CLIfToN)

I have heard that hysterical women say

They are sick of the palette and fiddle- bow,

Of poets that are always gay,

For everybody knows or else should know

That if nothing drastic is done

Aeroplane and Zeppelin will come out,

Pitch like King Billy bomb- balls in

Until the town lie beaten flat.

All perform their tragic play,

There struts Hamlet, there is Lear,

That’s Ophelia, that Cordelia;

Yet they, should the last scene be there,

The great stage curtain about to drop,

If worthy their prominent part in the play,

Do not break up their lines to weep.

They know that Hamlet and Lear are gay;

Gaiety transfiguring all that dread.

All men have aimed at, found and lost;

Black out; Heaven blazing into the head:

Tragedy wrought to its uttermost.

Though Hamlet rambles and Lear rages,

And all the drop- scenes drop at once

Upon a hundred thousand stages,

It cannot grow by an inch or an ounce.

On their own feet they came, or on shipboard,

Camel- back, horse- back, ass- back, mule- back,

Old civilisations put to the sword.

Then they and their wisdom went to rack:

No handiwork of Callimachus,

Who handled marble as if it were bronze,

Made draperies that seemed to rise

When sea- wind swept the corner, stands;

His long lamp- chimney shaped like the stem

Of a slender palm, stood but a day;

All things fall and are built again,

And those that build them again are gay.

Two Chinamen, behind them a third,

Are carved in lapis lazuli,

Over them flies a long- legged bird,

A symbol of longevity;

The third, doubtless a serving- man,

Carries a musical instrument.

Every discoloration of the stone,

Every accidental crack or dent,

Seems a water- course or an avalanche,

Or lofty slope where it still snows

Though doubtless plum or cherry- branch

Sweetens the little half- way house

Those Chinamen climb towards, and I

Delight to imagine them seated there;

There on the mountain and the sky,

On all the tragic scene they stare.

One asks for mournful melodies;

Accomplished fingers begin to play.

Their eyes mid many wrinkles, their eyes,

Their ancient, glittering eyes, are gay.

Cuchulain Comforted

A man that had six mortal wounds, a man

Violent and famous, strode among the dead;

Eyes stared out of the branches and were gone.

Then certain Shrouds that muttered head to head

Came and were gone. He leant upon a tree

As though to meditate on wounds and blood.

A Shroud that seemed to have authority

Among those bird- like things came and let fall

A bundle of linen. Shrouds by two and three

Came creeping up because the man was still;

And thereupon that linen- carrier said:

‘Your life can grow much sweeter if you will

‘Obey our ancient rule and make a shroud.

Mainly because of what we only know

The rattle of those arms makes us afraid.

‘We thread the needles’ eyes and all we do

All must together do.’ That done, the man

Took up the nearest and began to sew.

‘Now must we sing and sing the best we can

But first you must be told our character:

Convicted cowards all by kindred slain

‘Or driven from home and left to die in fear.’

They sang, but had nor human tunes nor words,

Though all was done in common as before;

They had changed their throats and had the throats of birds.

January 13, 1939

The Circus Animals’ Desertion

I

I sought a theme and sought for it in vain,

I sought it daily for six weeks or so.

Maybe at last being but a broken man

I must be satisfied with my heart, although

Winter and summer till old age began

My circus animals were all on show,

Those stilted boys, that burnished chariot,

Lion and woman and the Lord knows what.

II

What can I but enumerate old themes?

First that sea- rider Oisin led by the nose

Through three enchanted islands, allegorical dreams,

Vain gaiety, vain battle, vain repose,

Themes of the embittered heart, or so it seems,

That might adorn old songs or courtly shows;

But what cared I that set him on to ride,

I, starved for the bosom of his faery bride?

And then a counter- truth filled out its play,

The Countess Cathleen was the name I gave it,

She, pity- crazed, had given her soul away

But masterful Heaven had intervened to save it.

I thought my dear must her own soul destroy

So did fanaticism and hate enslave it,

And this brought forth a dream and soon enough

This dream itself had all my thought and love.

And when the Fool and Blind Man stole the bread

Cuchulain fought the ungovernable sea;

Heart mysteries there, and yet when all is said

It was the dream itself enchanted me:

Character isolated by a deed

To engross the present and dominate memory.

Players and painted stage took all my love

And not those things that they were emblems of.

III

Those masterful images because complete

Grew in pure mind, but out of what began?

A mound of refuse or the sweepings of a street,

Old kettles, old bottles, and a broken can,

Old iron, old bones, old rags, that raving slut

Who keeps the till. Now that my ladder’s gone

I must lie down where all the ladders start

In the foul rag and bone shop of the heart.

致《布莱克伍德》杂志编辑书

先生：

我们都听说过“道德腐化促进会”“地狱之火俱乐部”诸如此类的团体。我想，是在布莱顿，有人成立了一个“镇压美德协会”。而这个协会本身已遭镇压。但遗憾的是，伦敦还有一个这样的组织，其邪恶程度更甚。究其脾性，该团体取名为“谋杀促进会”或许更合适。不过，他们采用了雅致的Ευφημισμὸς（希腊语：婉词），称自己为“谋杀艺术鉴赏家协会”。他们声称，渴望了解杀人的奥秘，业余爱好各种方式的流血艺术，简而言之，就是谋杀发烧友。他们聚在一起，像评判一幅画、一尊雕像或者其他类型的艺术品那样，评价欧洲警察年鉴提供的每一桩新鲜命案。但他们是秉着何种精神展开这些活动的，我毋庸赘述，因为您将读到该协会去年面向全员宣读的“月度讲座系列”中的一个，也能从中更好地领悟这种精神。尽管他们保持警惕尽量避开公众耳目，会刊却意外落入我手。讲座内容的发表将给他们以警告，而我本意正是如此。尽管我更希望通过您引导公共舆论，从而悄然将他们镇压，而不是曝光他们的名字，然后向弓街[1]提出上诉；不过，如果公开他们的讲座没有取得应有的效果，我最终必将诉诸法律。因为这种事竟然发生在一个基督教国度里，这是不可原谅的。就算发生在异教徒国家，公众对于谋杀的宽容在某位基督教作家看来，仍是对社会公德最强烈的声讨。这位作家就是拉克唐修[2]。他的话极适用于当前的情况，用他的话说：“世上有什么能比杀人更恐怖、更有冒犯性？正因此，我们的生命才受到最严厉的法律保护，也正因此，人类掀起可怕的战争。然而，人们通过风俗习惯找到了杀人的办法，不用诉诸战争，也不触犯法律。这是娱乐，却也是犯罪，理应受到惩罚。如果处在谋杀现场，我们就成了共犯，观看罪行，我们就和行凶者同罪；那么在角斗士的谋杀中，观众的手和胜利者的一样血腥；想看血流的人洗不清身上的血渍；未亲手杀人，却为谋杀者鼓掌、求奖励的人也脱不了干系[3]。”“人的生命，”他说，“受最严厉的法律保护。然而为了谋杀，风俗习惯设计出一套逃避法律责任的办法。不过现在，欢娱（voluptas[4]）和不被约束的罪行一样，要付出同样的代价。”让业余爱好者协会的先生们想想这段话吧，他们要特别注意最后一句，关系如此重大，我必须要用英语表述一下：“现在，如果仅因身处谋杀现场，某人就成了共犯，如果只是目睹了谋杀，我们就要与行凶者同罪，那么同样，在露天竞技场的谋杀中，看台上观众的手和给对方致命一击的角斗士的手一样血腥，支持谋杀者洗清罪证，为谋杀者鼓掌、求奖励的人也只能是共犯。”虽然我还没有听说伦敦谋杀爱好者男士俱乐部受到“præmia postulavit”（要求奖励谋杀者）的指控，但是他们的活动无疑是有这种倾向的。不过，这个俱乐部的名称以及我寄给您的那个讲座的字里行间均充满“interfectori favil”（为谋杀者鼓掌）的意味。——我是……

X.Y.Z.

（编者按：感谢这位朋友的来信，也感谢他摘引的拉克唐修的话，很好地呼应了他对这个事情的看法。但是坦白地说我们的观点是不同的。我们不能假设主讲人是认真的。他的态度不会比伊拉斯谟写《愚人颂》或者迪恩·斯威夫特提议吃小孩更认真。不过，我们双方都认为应该把这个讲座公布于世。）

[1] 弓街：伦敦的一条街道。弓街治安法庭曾数年主管伦敦的治安事务，相当于伦敦历史上首个警察局。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为译者注。）

[2] 拉克唐修（250—325），早期基督教作家，是第一位基督教徒罗马皇帝康斯坦丁一世的宗教政策顾问。著有《神圣原理》，书中他对异教徒宗教和哲学进行批判，又对基督教的合理性和真实性进行论述。

[3] 原文为拉丁语。

[4] 拉丁语，意为欢乐、欢娱。

讲座内容

先生们，我很荣幸，委员会将如此艰难的任务指派给我，让我朗读威廉姆斯系列“关于谋杀是一门艺术”的讲座。要是在三四个世纪之前，这个任务或许相当好办。那时人们对谋杀知之甚少，也鲜有佳作可当典范。但在当代，职业人士已创作出不少杰作，因而显然，公众必然也期待谋杀的评论方法有相应的提升。实践与理论必须Pari Passu（同步发展）。人们开始意识到，一例精巧的谋杀，在两个蠢人简单的杀与被杀、一把匕首、一只钱包和一条黑灯瞎火的巷子之外，更多的是前期的构思。先生们啊，如今，若要谋杀，构思、选址、光影、诗歌、情绪都是必要元素。威廉姆斯先生已提高了我们所有人心中的谋杀理想，因而让我的任务尤其难上加难。正如埃斯库罗斯或弥尔顿之于诗歌，米开朗基罗之于绘画，威廉姆斯先生已把他的谋杀艺术提升到了极高的境界。如华兹华斯先生所言，某种程度上，他“创造了一种人们可用于品鉴他的作品的审美力”。勾勒这一艺术之历史、批判性地审视其原则，是留给鉴赏家们的职责。他们是另一种“法官”，跟最高巡回法庭[1]的就颇为不同了。

在我开始之前，容我对某些自命清高的人说两句，他们说起本俱乐部就好像我们多少是有点不道德的。不道德！愿主保佑我的灵魂。先生们，那些人想表达什么啊？我是拥护道德准则的，永远拥护，拥护一切美德。我坚决认为，永远坚定地认为，（不管结果如何）谋杀是不当的行径，极为不当。但我并不认为，所有谋杀者都得有非常错误的思考方式，或者很不正确的行为准则。某位伟大的德国伦理学家[2]说过，把杀害对象的藏身之地告诉谋杀者，协助和支持他是每个善人应尽的本分。我非但不会这么做，相反，我愿意捐出一先令六便士将其逮捕，这比名气最大的道德学家们所捐的数额也要多出十八便士。但那又能怎样呢？世上的一切皆有两个把柄。例如谋杀，它可能要受到道德把柄的控制（就像在所有的布道中，以及老贝利那里[3]）。这一点，我承认，是谋杀站不住脚的一面。但另外一面，它也可能成为一种审美对象，就像德国人说的，跟好品味有关。

为了证明这个观点，我将郑重地请出三位著名的权威人士，即S.T.科勒律治、亚里士多德和外科医生霍希普先生[4]。先说科勒律治。多年前的一个夜晚，我和他正在伯尔尼街喝茶（顺便提一句，此街虽然不长，却出奇地人才济济）。在场的除我之外还有其他人。在饮茶配吐司满足口腹之欲的同时，我们都在听科勒律治文雅地谈一篇关于普罗提诺的论文。突然传来一声：“失火了！失火了！”所有人，不管老师还是学生，柏拉图或是οίπερί τον Πλάτωνα（希腊语：他周围的人），全都立刻冲出门外，盼着旁观大火。火情发生在牛津街上的一家钢琴制作商家。当时来看，火势很可能发展成一场可观的大火，所以很遗憾在危急关头到来之前我有事必须离开科勒律治先生的聚会。数天后，我又遇到了那位柏拉图式的聚会主人。我向他提起那场大火，求他告知那场可能的好戏是如何被终止的。“哦，先生，”他说，“那场戏后来太糟了，我们全都骂了起来。”那么有谁认为科勒律治先生（尽管他太胖了，不是一个拥有主动美德的人，但他绝对是名副其实的基督徒），可以说是好人的S.T.C.，是纵火犯吗？或者他会希望可怕的事发生在那个可怜的男人和他的钢琴身上吗（毫无疑问，很多钢琴都增加了额外的琴键[5]）？相反，我知道他的为人，尽管他是被火灾考验过美德的人中最胖的一个，但我敢用生命打赌，必要时，他会操作消防车参与灭火。但情况到底是怎样的呢？根本就不需要美德。消防车一到，道德就全盘把责任交给了保险公司。事情就是这样，所以他就有权饱眼福。他为此离开了茶桌，难道让他一无所获吗？

我认为，在上述前提下，最高尚的人有权奢侈一回，去享受那场火灾，去发出不满的嘘声，就像对待任何先吊起了人们的胃口，后又让人扫兴的表演一样。接下来，让我们看看另一位伟大的权威人士，那位斯塔吉亚人（亚里士多德）是怎么说的。他（我想应该是在《形而上学》第五卷中）描述了κλεπτήν τέλειον，即，完美的盗贼形象。至于霍希普先生，在一篇关于消化不良的论文中用赞美的口吻谈到他看到的一种溃疡，称其为“一块美丽的溃疡”，也没见其良心不安。那么有人会说，亚里士多德不经大脑就会觉得盗贼品性完美，或者霍希普先生可能迷恋一块溃疡吗？众所周知，亚里士多德本人是个品德非常高尚的人，甚至写了八开纸一卷本的《尼各马可伦理学》也不满足，他后来又写了另外一套伦理学著作，名为Magna Moralia，即《大伦理学》。那么只要是撰写伦理学的人，不管是大伦理学还是小伦理学，都不可能赞美偷盗本身。至于霍希普先生，众所周知，他向所有的溃疡开战。他没有被溃疡的魅力蛊惑，相反他正努力将它们从米德尔塞克斯郡消除干净。不过，其实不管本身多么令人讨厌，跟同类相比的话，一个盗贼或者一块溃疡都可能有无数种优点。二者确实都不完美，但是它们本质上的不完美，这种不完美所蕴含的伟大恰恰构成了它们的完美。Spartam nactus es， henc exorna（“斯巴达现在归你了，尽你所有让其生辉”）。像奥托吕科斯[6]和巴灵顿先生[7]这样的贼，和性状明晰、稳步发展的可怕的崩蚀性溃疡，说他们与从长出蓓蕾直至开出“鲜艳完美的花”都堪称无懈可击的花魁洋蔷薇一样，是同类中的完美典范，也并不过分。或可比作美人中，最雍容华贵的妙龄少女。因此，不光是墨水台有可以想象的完美典范（正如柯勒律治先生在他那封与布莱克伍德先生著名的信里说明的），尽管也没多少想象的空间，因为墨水台本身就值得赞美，是对社会有用之物。甚至可以想象，不完美本身也可能有自己的典范和完美的状态。

先生们，我真是抱歉，一下子说这么多哲理。现在让我结合实践说明。当谋杀将要发生（不久后的将来时时态），且我们听到了传闻的时候，我们务必以道德的态度视之。但是假定谋杀已完成，你可以说：Τετέλεσαι（谋杀完成了），或者（用美狄亚式的坚定的三音步）说：ε’ίργασαι（结束了）。假定受害者断了气不再痛苦挣扎，恶棍随即逃走，无人知其行踪。假定，最后我们尽力了，在那人逃跑的时候伸腿绊倒了他，可是也于事无补啊：“abiit， evasit”（他离开了，逃走了）……那为什么我说，再多的美德又有什么用呢？我们给道德的已足够多，现在该轮到品味和艺术了。毫无疑问，人被害死是件令人难过的事，非常难过，但我们也无力回天。那么就让这件坏事物尽其用吧。既然拼尽全力也不可能再在道德方面有所作为，就让我们以审美的态度视之，看看能不能加以利用。理智的人一般都是这样想的。那么会怎样呢？我们擦干眼泪，也许会心满意足地发现， 一桩在道德上骇人、站不住脚的买卖，若用审美的标准衡量，却会是一场值得赞美的表演。这样一来全世界都高兴了。老谚语还是有道理的，世上没有对人人都不利的事。谋杀爱好者本来因为太在意美德显得暴躁阴郁，现在开始变废为宝，变得欢腾起来。美德的权势日渐衰微，今后谋杀艺术爱好者和鉴赏家们可以满足自己的日常所需。先生们，基于这个原则，我计划引导你们学习从该隐到特尔泰[8]以来的谋杀案。就让我们心悦诚服地携手共同漫步于这条伟大的艺术长廊。我会尽力将你们的目光引向有批判价值的作品。

第一例谋杀你们都很熟悉。该隐，这位谋杀的发明人，这门艺术的先祖，必定是位一流的天才。该隐家族都是天才。土八·该隐[9]发明了管子，或这类东西，我想。但，不管艺术家多具原创性或多么才华横溢，在那个时代所有艺术都才萌芽，所以要评价那时的作品必须谨记这一时代背景。即使是土八的作品，今天放在设菲尔德[10]看，也可能不尽如人意。所以如果说该隐（我是指老该隐）的艺术水平不过尔尔，也并非贬低。然而弥尔顿应该另有想法。从他叙述的方式看，这个作品似乎应该是他心爱的谋杀案，因为在他的诗中明显能感受到他对谋杀场景进行润色想取得生动效果时的焦虑。

为此他内心狂怒，趁谈话之际，

将石块投向对方的腹部，给以致命一击：

他倾倒在地，面色苍白像死了一样，

随着鲜血不断喷涌，呻吟出最后一丝气息。

《失乐园·十一卷》

对于此段描写，擅长鉴赏效果的画家理查德森在《失乐园笔记》中如是评论道：“人们都以为该隐是用一块大石把他弟弟砸死的（按照普遍说法）。弥尔顿算认可这种说法，不过他又增加了一个巨大的伤口。”此处的添加很明智。因为杀人武器简单粗暴，除非用一种温暖的血色提亮和丰富，否则场面就会像野蛮派那样显得过于直白，就仿佛是独眼巨人行的凶，他没有技巧，事先也未经构思，只用了一根羊骨。不过，我对这个提升总体上还是满意的，因为这暗示了弥尔顿是个谋杀爱好者。至于莎士比亚，他没能写得更好。《亨利六世》中格洛斯特公爵的谋害，以及邓肯和班科[11]等的死，都足以证明这一点。

一旦这门艺术奠定了基础，眼见它久久停滞不前，实在是可惜。确切地说，我将不得不跳过接下来所有的谋杀案，不管是宗教的还是世俗的，因为它们毫无价值，一直要到基督诞生很久之后。即使在伯里克利[12]的时代，希腊也没能产生任何有丁点价值的谋杀。罗马的谋杀案例几乎没有任何后来艺术的原创性，罗马模式辜负了自己。事实上，拉丁语在表述谋杀思想时意味单薄，词不达意。“这个人被谋杀了。”用拉丁语说是何感觉？Interfectus est， interemptus est（他被杀了，他被消灭了），这仅仅表达出了杀人的行为。因此，中世纪基督教的拉丁语用法只好引入了一个新词，它有单薄的经典词语从未传达出的丰满。Murdratus est[13]，哥特时代更高级的方言这样讲。在这个时期，犹太学派鲜活地保留了尚未被这门艺术了解的知识，而后逐渐传入西方世界。的确，犹太学派素来让人敬佩，甚至在黑暗时期。林肯郡的休一案就说明了这点，这个案子光荣地得到了乔叟的认可，借修道院院长之口，他把案件嵌进了犹太学派的另一场表演中[14]。

不过，现在让我们暂时回到古典时期。我不由得想到喀提林[15]、克洛狄乌斯[16]以及该小团体的其他人，他们本可以成为一流的艺术家。令人无比遗憾的是，西塞罗以其迂腐不化剥夺了他的祖国在这个领域里唯一出彩的机会。作为谋杀的对象，没人比他自己更能解释遗憾的原因。主啊！如果西塞罗听到塞西格斯[17]躲在他的床下，得怕得喊成什么样啊。要是能听到他的喊声，那一定很有趣。想到他宁愿选择爬着躲进柜子里的vtile（权宜之计），甚至是cloaca（阴沟里），也不敢hones tum（保留颜面）地直面无畏的艺术家，先生们，我就感到很满足。

现在时间来到了黑暗时代（我们都是讲求精准的人，所以准确地说黑暗时代是指最卓越的10世纪及前后紧邻的年代），这一时期，就像对教堂建筑、彩色玻璃等艺术一样，自然也是对谋杀艺术发展有利的时期。所以，临近黑暗时代尾声的时候，我们这门艺术相应地崛起了一位伟大的人物，我指的是“山中老人”[18]。他就宛若一盏明亮的灯，是的。不用我说，你们都知道，“刺客”这个词正是起源于他。他是如此热爱这门艺术，甚至某次，他中意的一个刺客企图杀他的时候，施展的才华让他如此欣喜，艺术家虽然刺杀失败了，但他当场封刺客做了公爵，赐给他可养三口人的生活津贴，死后爵位可由在世的妻儿继承。刺杀是谋杀这门艺术的一个分支，需要单独注意。我会专门针对刺杀做个讲座，其中，我的分析将会只围绕它的怪异之处：为什么这门艺术的这一分支会出现间歇性的蓬勃发展。刺杀案的发生从不像下雨那样均匀散落，都是如洪水一般倾泻而来。我们当代就有一些不错的范例可以吹嘘一番。而两个世纪前发生的一系列刺杀案则非常出色。显然，我专门提到的就是那五个杰作——奥兰治亲王威廉一世[19]刺杀案，法国亨利四世[20]刺杀案，白金汉公爵[21]刺杀案（大英博物馆的埃利斯先生已发表的信中有精彩的案件描述），古斯塔夫·阿道夫二世[22]刺杀案，以及华伦斯坦[23]刺杀案。马上就会有很多作家质疑说瑞典国王不是遇刺身亡的，其中就包括哈德[24]。他是死于谋杀。我认为他的案例是独一无二的杰作，因为他是中午在战场上被谋害，这一点极具原创性，据我所知是其他艺术作品都没有的。是的，所有的这些刺杀案可供高级鉴赏家们研究，是颇有价值的。它们全都是范本，可以说：

Nocturnâ versatâ manu, versate diurne;

翻起书来，日夜兼程。

nocturnâ.（夜晚）尤甚。

这些王公政客遭刺杀，没什么好惊奇的。他们只有死了才会发生重大变化。因为他们身份显赫，所以对恰好迷恋事件效果的艺术家来说，正中下怀。但从17世纪早期就流行的另一种刺杀类型着实让我感到惊讶。我是指哲学家的遇刺案。因为，先生们，实际上在过去两个世纪中，所有杰出的哲学家们要么被谋害，要么至少几近遇害。因此，如果某人自称是哲学家，但却从未被打过谋杀的主意，放心，那他肯定胸无点墨。尤其是洛克[25]的哲学理论。我认为，否定它的不争事实（如果还需要的话）是，尽管他带着喉咙行走于世七十二年，却从未有人屈尊去切断它。鉴于这些哲学家的谋杀案不太为人所知，而从细节看，它们都很好，构思也不错，那么我就在此附带来讨论一下这方面的案例，主要是为了展现我自己的学识。

17世纪第一位伟大的哲学家（如果不算伽利略的话）是笛卡尔[26]。如果要说曾经有那么一个人差点儿，但没被谋害——就差一丁点——那个人一定是他。巴耶[27]在他的《笛卡尔传》卷一第102页到103页里报告过此事。事情是这样的。1621年，笛卡尔约莫二十六岁的时候，他像往常一样四处旅行（他就像一只不安分的土狼）。他来到易北河[28]，在格吕克施塔特或者汉堡乘船前往东弗吕斯兰。至于他有何贵干不得而知。也许只有他自己知道，因为一到埃姆登他就决定即刻驶往西弗吕斯兰。无法忍受行程的耽搁，他租了一条三桅帆船，由几个水手负责驾驶。船刚驶进海域，他就获得一个喜人的发现，那就是他把自己关进了一窝杀人犯中。贝耶先生写道，他很快就发现水手都是“恶棍”。先生们，不是我们这样的发烧友，是专业的。那时，他们的最大野心就是切断他的喉咙。因为故事实在太精彩无法删减，所以我就一字不差引述笛卡尔的法语传记：“笛卡尔先生只带了一个仆人，他们正用法语交谈。水手们以为他是外国商贩，不是骑士，断定他身上肯定带钱了。因而，他们做了一个毫不利于笛卡尔钱包的决定。海上的盗贼和森林里的是有区别的，后者因为没有风险，会放过过路人的性命。但是像笛卡尔这样的情况，海盗无法冒着被捕的风险把乘客放生到岸上去。笛卡尔先生的水手们绝不准备冒那样的风险。他们思忖着，这位来自远方的异客在本国又没熟人，万一他没出现，quand il viendroit à manquer（他应该是恰好失踪），也不会有人劳神来东问西问。”想想看，先生们，这些弗吕斯兰恶狗讨论一位哲学家的时候就像在讨论一桶朗姆酒。“他们说，他的性情非常温和且很有耐心，并且，他彬彬有礼，待他们也很客气，想必是初出茅庐的年轻人，所以他们断定解决他的性命应该是轻而易举的。他们毫不顾忌，就在他的面前讨论所有事宜，没想到除了和仆人交谈使用的语言之外，他还懂别的语言。他们的打算是：杀了他，抛尸大海，然后分赃。”

抱歉，我没忍住笑，先生们。不过一想到这个案例，我总是要笑。它看上去这么滑稽，主要是两点。一是令人不快的恐惧，或叫恐慌（伊顿公学的人都这么说）。听到歹人用这样常规的剧本勾勒他的死法、葬礼、财产继承和财产管理，笛卡尔肯定很害怕。但另一点让我觉得更滑稽。如果这些弗吕斯兰的败类够果敢的话，也许我们就不会有笛卡尔主义了。我们怎么可能没有笛卡尔主义，想想因它出版的那些卷帙浩繁的书吧，还是请尊敬的短裤制造商[29]发表看法。

好了，继续讲故事。尽管面对巨大的恐慌，笛卡尔还是表现出了斗志，这让“反笛卡尔（主义）”的恶棍对他心生敬畏。“发现事情不是玩笑，”贝耶先生写道，“笛卡尔顷刻间跳将起来，正颜厉色。这些懦夫万万没想到，他开口说话，用的是他们的语言，威胁要就地刺穿他们所有人，如果他们胆敢对他有丁点不敬的话。”当然了，先生们，像云雀一样穿在笛卡尔之剑上，有这等荣幸太便宜这些一文不值的恶棍了。因此，我很高兴笛卡尔先生没有打劫绞刑架擅自处死威胁者。尤其是，如果杀了船员，他就无法驾船回港。那样一来，他就得永生在南海航行，也许会被水手们误认为是驶向家乡的鬼船船长[30]。“笛卡尔先生展示的精神对这帮恶棍来说有魔法一般的效果。”他的传记作者写道，“突然的惊慌让他们茫然不知所措，忘记了自己的优势，而后他们如他所愿，平静地载着他抵达目的地。”

也许，先生们，你们幻想笛卡尔会像凯撒那样对可怜的船夫说：Caesarem vehis et fortunas ejus（尔载的是凯撒和他的财物），但他只需说：你们这些恶狗，不能杀我，因为你们载的是笛卡尔和他的哲学。这样也许就能有把握地阻止他们采取极端行动。某位德国皇帝也具备这种意识，一次有人让他远离连续炮击的路径以防不测，他回道：嘘！闭嘴。你听过有哪个炮弹炸死个皇帝的？皇帝我说不好，但是稍小的事就足以摧毁一位哲学家。接下来的这位欧洲伟大的哲学家就肯定是被谋杀的。这位就是斯宾诺莎。

我很清楚一般大家都说他死在床上，也许吧，不过就算死在床上，也是被谋杀的。这一点我要用一本题为《斯宾诺莎传》的书证明。此书于1731年在布鲁塞尔出版，作者是让·克罗鲁斯先生。传记里有些附加信息是来自斯宾诺莎一位朋友写的他生平的手稿，并未出版。斯宾诺莎死于1677年2月21日，刚过四十四岁，这本身就很可疑。让先生坦言，在他的传记手稿里，有个说法证明了这个结论：“他的死也并非完全正常。”生活在荷兰这样一个阴湿乏味的国家，一个水手的国度，想来他也本应沉迷格罗格酒[31]的，特别是当时刚发掘出来的潘趣酒[32]。是的，他本可能是这样，但实际上并非如此。让先生称他：“是一个饮食上非常有节制的人。”尽管坊间流传，斯宾诺莎饮曼陀罗草汁[33]，吸鸦片[34]，但是这两样东西都没出现在药剂师的账单上。所以，既然他活得这么清醒节制，怎么可能四十四岁就自然死亡了？听听传记作家是怎么说的：“ 2月21号的周日早晨，还没到做礼拜的时间，斯宾诺莎下楼和房东夫妇交谈。”所以，这个时候，可能是周日早上10点，你看斯宾诺莎还是活着的，而且身体相当好。但是似乎“他已从阿姆斯特丹叫了某位医生过来”，传记作者写道，“要不是L.M.这两个字母，我也没注意到他”。经这位L.M.指导，住在此处的人去买来一只老公鸡，然后立刻炖了，这样斯宾诺莎中午就能喝上一点鸡汤。事实上，他确实喝了，胃口不错，还吃了点老公鸡的肉。这发生在房东夫妇从教堂回来之后。

“下午，L.M.单独和斯宾诺莎待在一起，屋里其他人都回教堂去了。他们一出教堂，就得知斯宾诺莎约在下午3点去世，很是吃惊。去世时，L.M.在场。当天夜晚，L.M.就连夜乘船返回阿姆斯特丹了，对死者一点也不在乎。毫无疑问，他早想好了要免去那些道德义务，因为他把斯宾诺莎的一达克通[35]和少量的银币，连同一把银柄匕首全部据为己有，然后带着赃物潜逃了。”到这儿，先生们，你们就明白，谋杀及其方式都是很清晰的。是L.M.为了钱财杀害了斯宾诺莎。可怜的斯宾诺莎，瘦弱多病。因为现场没有血迹，所以L.M.肯定是将他推倒在床，然后用枕头闷死的。可怜他已经被该死的老公鸡汤噎得半死了。但，L.M.是谁？肯定不可能是林德利·穆雷。1825年我还在约克见过他。而且，我不相信他会干出这种事，至少不会对一位语法家同仁下手。因为大家都知道，斯宾诺莎写了一本非常好的希伯来语语法书。

可为什么或者是根据什么原则，霍布斯没被谋杀？我从来也没想明白。这是17世纪职业人士的重大失误。因为除了瘦得皮包骨头，无论从哪方面看，他都是个优质的谋杀对象。因为我能证明他有钱，而且（非常好笑的是）他无权做出任何反抗。因为，根据他的理论，专制政权产生至高无上的权力，因此当一支具备充足战斗力的军队似乎要杀你的时候，你要是拒绝被杀，就是对政权最大的反叛，罪大恶极。但是，先生们，尽管他没被谋杀，我很高兴地向你们保证（据他自己的描述），他有三次差点被害了。第一次是在1640年的春天。他自称，当时他有一小本手稿在流传，代表君主对抗国会。顺便说一句，他不可能印制这本手稿。但是他说“要是陛下（5月份）还不解散国会的话”，“他的性命就会有危险。”然而，解散国会是没用的。因为同年11月，长期国会成立，霍布斯又一次害怕被谋害，于是逃去了法国。这看上去就像约翰·丹尼斯的疯狂想法。他认为除非法国将他交于西班牙让其实施报复，不然路易十四不可能和安妮女王和解。而实际上，他就是带着这种想法逃离了海岸。在法国，十年来，霍布斯努力地照看好自己的脖子，效果相当不错。但最后的阶段，为了向克伦威尔示好，他发表了《利维坦》。现在，这个老懦夫开始第三次极度“惊慌”。他幻想着骑士们的剑不断地出现在他的喉咙上，脑海里浮现它们是怎么伺候海牙和马德里的国会大使的。那时，他用蹩脚的拉丁语说：

Tum venit in mentem mihi Dorislaus et Ascham;

Tanquam proscripto terror ubique aderat.

（那时多里斯劳斯和阿斯克姆出现在我的脑海里，

就像被判死刑的人眼里到处都是恐惧。）

因此他逃回英格兰老家去了。当然了，写《利维坦》的人确实应该被棒打一顿，而把五音步结尾写得这么拙劣的应该被打两顿或三顿——“terror ubique aderat”[36]。可是从未有人想过对他用点棒刑之外的惩罚。而且，事实上，整个故事都是他的自我吹嘘。因为在写给一位渊博之人（数学家瓦里斯）的一封极具诽谤意味的信中，他给了另外一种颇为不同的说法，他说，他逃回家“是因为他无法将自己的安危托付给法国教会”，言下之意，他可能因为信仰的问题被谋害。这可真是个大笑话[37]——汤姆会因宗教问题被判刑。

不管是不是自我吹嘘，可以确定的是，霍布斯至死都在担心有人会谋害他。这点，我接下来要讲的故事可以证明。这个故事不是出自某个未出版的手稿，而是（如科勒律治所言）出自和手稿一样好的一本完全被遗忘的书，即《探究霍布斯先生的信仰，一场他与神学学生的讨论》（出版于霍布斯去世十年前）。书是匿名出版的，但是是丁尼生写的，就是那位三十年后，接替迪罗生成为坎特伯雷大主教的丁尼生。书以一则逸事开头：“某位牧师（无疑是丁尼生本人）似乎每年都会花一个月的时间去岛上四处走走。”一次远足（1670年），他来到德贝郡的匹克区，部分原因是读了霍布斯的描述。到了那一带，就不能不去邻近的巴克斯顿看看。就在他刚抵巴克斯顿之时，幸运如他，正好有一群绅士在客栈门口下马，其中一位身形瘦长，正是霍布斯本人。他可能刚从查茨沃斯骑马过来。对于一位寻觅美景的游客来说，偶遇如此伟大的名人，他能做的至少是上前叨扰。他的计划受到了命运眷顾，霍布斯先生的两个同伴突然收到差遣任务被叫走了，所以在巴克斯顿的剩余时光里，利维坦完全属于他，晚上他有幸和他一起痛饮。霍布斯一开始似乎表现得很僵硬，因为他对神学家总是有所畏惧。但这个顾虑逐渐消失，他变得友善风趣起来，之后他们决定一同入浴。丁尼生怎么敢和利维坦[38]在同一片水域里嬉戏？我无法解释。然而就是这样。尽管霍布斯已寿比南山，但他们在水中四处嬉戏，宛若两尾海豚。而且“在游泳停下来和再扎入水中之间的间歇里（也就是潜入水中），他们讨论了很多‘古人沐浴’以及‘溪水之源’的问题”。就这样，一小时过去后，他们出浴了。擦干身体更衣后，他们坐下，满怀期待地等着这种地方会提供的晚餐，计划像《哲人之宴》里写的那样恢复精气神，宁愿多想，不多饮。然而，他们纯真的愿望被一阵骚动打破了。屋里有几个粗人发生了短暂的口角。尽管离那几个人尚有一段距离，但霍布斯似乎特别关注此事。那么，先生们，他为什么关注呢？不错，你会想，从对和平与和谐抱有仁慈而无私的爱看来，那确实是值得一位老人和哲学家关注的。但是，听着：“不一会儿他就不安起来，但他说了一两遍赛克斯图斯·罗修斯晚饭后是怎么在帕拉西那的浴池附近被谋杀的，声音很低很小心，像是在自言自语。”霍布斯怕成这样，刚好可以用西塞罗的话概括。西塞罗对伊壁鸠鲁这位无神论者这样评价：所有人中就属他最害怕自己批判的事物——死亡和上帝。仅仅因为是晚饭时间，在浴池附近，霍布斯就一定会走上赛克斯图斯·罗修斯的老路。这是什么逻辑？除非他老想着被谋杀。这时的利维坦，不再害怕英国骑士的短剑或者法国教会，而是在酒馆里，被德贝郡几个老实巴交的庄稼汉的争吵“吓得失了分寸”。不过，他自己形容枯槁，老得看起来有几百岁了，可能也会把人家吓得魂飞魄散吧。

马勒伯朗士是被谋杀的。他的故事将给你们带去欢乐。杀他的人很有名，就是伯克利主教。故事大家都熟悉，不过至今还没得到正确理解。伯克利年轻的时候，去巴黎拜访皮埃尔·马勒伯朗士。到了他修道院的房间发现他正在做饭。厨师向来是genus irritabile（脾气暴躁的物种），作家更是如此，而马勒伯朗士身兼这两种角色。他们争吵起来。老神父本来就激动，现在更激动了。厨师的火气加上哲学家的愤怒让他大动肝火：他卧床不起，然后就死了。这是大家熟知的版本，“所以说整个丹麦都被谎言欺辱了”。实际上，出于对伯克利的保护，实情被隐瞒了，因为（正如教皇所言）伯克利是天下最有德之人。否则广为人知的就是这个版本了：伯克利被法国老头的暴躁激怒了，摆开架势，接着就是一场搏斗。马勒伯朗士第一轮便被打倒在地，彻底消除了自负，他也许已经投降了。但是伯克利此时血脉偾张，他坚持要求法国老头收回偶因论学说[39]。老头太过虚荣拒绝收回。他可笑的固执，加上爱尔兰青年的冲动，最终葬送了自己的性命。

莱布尼茨各方面都在马勒伯朗士之上，所以你可能更有理由指望他被谋杀，但，事实并非如此。我认为，他被这种忽视激怒了，安全度日令他感到耻辱。不然我无法解释他晚年的行为。他下决心，要变得非常贪婪，决定在自己家里囤一大笔金子。他死在了维也纳。他对自己喉咙的安危感到无比焦虑，至今描述他这一焦虑的信件还在。尽管无比焦虑，可他的野心——那种至少也得有人试图加害他的野心——如此之大，导致他不愿放弃危险。来自伯明翰，爱卖弄学问的已故英国教师——帕尔博士[40]，在同样的情形下，采取了更自私的路线。他囤了数目相当可观的金银餐具，一度存放在他牧师住宅的卧室里。但是他对谋杀的担忧日渐增长，他清楚自己无法忍受这种忧虑（对此，他的确从未有过一丝夸大），就把所有的金银餐具都转移到哈顿的铁匠那里。毫无疑问，他想的是，杀死一个铁匠对于Salus reipublicae（共和政体的安全）打击要比杀老师轻。但我听说这种说法存在很大的争议。似乎现在普遍认为，一个优质马掌的价格值2.25个斯佩尔布道[41]。

莱布尼茨纵然不是被杀身亡，但可以说他的死，部分源自对谋杀的恐惧，部分是因为没被谋杀恼怒所致。可康德在这方面又没啥野心，却差点死在谋杀者的手里，比上文提到的除笛卡尔之外的任何人都更惊险。真是造化弄人！这个案例，我想，在一本这位伟人的匿名传记中有所记载。为了健康，康德逼自己每天沿着一条大道一气走上六英里。一个因私意欲谋杀的人得知了此事。他在距哥尼斯堡三英里处，等待像邮车一样准时出现的“猎物”。要不是意外发生，康德必死。不巧，杀手看到路上有个正在玩耍的小孩。出于“道德”的考虑，比起老先验主义者，他更想杀小孩，所以小孩被杀了，康德得以逃脱。这是德国人对此事的描述。但依我看，杀手是个谋杀发烧友，他觉得杀一个形容枯槁面若死灰的老形而上学家，对谋杀的审美事业贡献不大，而且也没有展示的空间，因为康德死了也不会比活着更像干尸。

先生们，至此，我追踪了哲学与我们这门艺术的关系。不觉我已信步走进了我们这个时代。我不用费劲解释它跟之前年代之间的区别，因为实际上这个时代的艺术作品并无鲜明的特征。17世纪、18世纪，以及有很多作品我们还没赏析的19世纪，共同构成了谋杀的黄金时代。毫无疑问，17世纪最好的谋杀作品是埃德蒙贝里·戈弗雷爵士被害案，我完全赞同。同时，我们必须要看到，本世纪的谋杀作品数量不多，至少本国艺术家的作品不多。也许是因为我们缺少开明有识的赞助人。Sint Mæcenates， non deerunt， Flacce， Marones（愿我们有很多梅塞纳斯[42]，那么就不会缺少贺拉斯[43]、维吉尔[44]这样的诗人）。参看葛兰特的《对死亡率表的观察》（第四版，牛津，1665），我发现17世纪某二十年间死于伦敦的229250人中，只有86个是死于谋杀，即，每年约为4.3个人。先生们，要成立一个学会，这点数字是少了。当然，数量不多的时候，我们就可以期待质量一流。也许这个世纪的谋杀案质量是一流，但我仍然认为17世纪最好的艺术家是无法与18世纪最好的艺术家相提并论的。比如，不管埃德蒙贝里·戈弗雷爵士的案子多令人赞叹（没有人能比我更清楚它好在哪里），我仍然认为它不能与布里斯托的拉斯康贝夫人谋杀案媲美，不管是构思的原创性，还是风格的大胆和涵盖的广度。这位好夫人的谋杀案发生在乔治三世早期。总的来说乔治三世的统治对艺术发展非常有利。她住在学院绿地，家中只有一个女仆。主仆二人除了从我正在记录的这位伟大艺术家的手艺所收获的，再没有什么是值得让历史注意的。某个晴朗的早晨，整个布里斯托城一片生机盎然。可疑的情况发生了，邻居们闯入拉斯康贝夫人的房屋，发现她被杀害在床，女仆被杀死在楼梯上。这可是中午，而且不到两小时前，还有人看到主仆二人还活着。我如果没记错的话，这事发生在1764年，而今六十多年的时光已消逝，可作案的艺术家仍不知姓甚名谁。后世对于嫌疑犯的猜测落在了两个冒牌货身上：一个面包师和一个扫烟囱的。但他们错了。经验不足的艺术家不可能有这么大胆的构思，把谋杀时间设在中午，地点还选在了一座大城市的中心地段。先生们，这件作品肯定不是由默默无闻的面包师或者无名的扫烟囱的完成的，这点确信无疑。我知道是谁（这时现场的人们纷纷交头接耳低声讨论，最终大家爆发出一阵掌声，演讲人脸红了，然后一本正经继续讲）。天哪，先生们，不要误会，不是我做的。我还没自负到以为自己可以取得这样的成就。你们是大大高估了我贫瘠的才华。拉斯康贝夫人的谋杀远超出我有限的能力。不过，我是从一位著名的外科医生那里了解到艺术家的身份的，他参与解剖了他的尸体。这位医生拥有一座私人医学博物馆，在其中一角有一具人体模型，是一个身材比例非常好的男性。

“那具骨骼，”外科医生说，“是著名的兰开夏郡公路大盗的。他有段时间成功向邻居隐瞒了自己的职业，把羊毛长筒袜套在马腿上，因为往马厩去的巷子里铺的是石板路面，这样就能消掉马走在上面必然会发出的嗒嗒声。他因抢劫被处决的时候，我正在克鲁克山手下学习。盗贼的身材出奇地好，所以刻不容缓，必须要立刻拿到他的尸体，没有多余的金钱和精力浪费在耽搁上。在代理郡长的默许下，刽子手在法定的时间内将他砍倒在地，然后立刻装进四匹马拉的轻便马车，所以当他到达克鲁克山的解剖室的时候，还没死透。当时有个叫某某先生的年轻学生，有幸给了他最后一击，完成了法律的判决。”这段不同寻常的逸事对我震动很大。它似乎暗示了，解剖室里所有的男士们都是我们这种谋杀发烧友。一天，我跟一位兰开夏郡的女士复述此事，她当即告诉我，她就住在那个大盗家附近，她清楚地记得两件事，这两件事让邻居们认定他就是杀死拉斯康贝夫人的凶手。一是，在谋杀发生前后，他整整消失了两周。二是，谋杀发生之后，很快盗贼家附近到处是五先令硬币。大家都知道拉斯康贝夫人囤了两千枚那种硬币。但无论艺术家是谁，这个谋杀案都是展示其天赋的不朽丰碑。这例谋杀案所展现的想象力，让人们一直感到敬畏和震撼，所以直到那时（我听说的时候是1810年），仍没人敢租拉斯康贝夫人的房子。

不过，在我赞颂拉斯康贝案的同时，也不要让别人误会，说我忽略了分布于这一世纪不同时期的其他杰作。但像布兰德小姐的创作，或是唐奈伦上尉谋杀西奥菲勒斯·鲍顿这样的作品，我确实永远也不会认同的。我鄙视这些下毒的人。他们就不能继续沿用割喉这种古老诚实的办法吗？不要从意大利引进这么糟糕的新方法。我认为，跟正统的做法比，所有的毒杀案都显得拙劣，效果堪比雕塑旁边的蜡像或者摆在精致的沃尔帕托雕刻品旁边的平版印刷品。不过，尽管这些作品不值得玩味，但还是有很多风格纯正的优秀作品的，凡公正的鉴赏家都会承认，所以有这样的风格也不必觉得丢人。注意，我说的是，公正。因为人们必须要充分考虑这些案子的难处，没有哪位艺术家能确定可以顺利完成预先精心的构思。中间会出各种状况。人们不会乖乖地任由自己被切断喉咙的。他们会逃，会踢，会咬。当肖像画家时不时总要抱怨模特太没生气的时候，对我们这行的艺术家而言，总的来说，难的地方恰恰在于模特太有生气。而且，不管艺术家本人多不顺心，谋杀过程中往往让模特兴奋的做法，对这个世界来说绝对是它的一个优点。我们不该忽视这个优点，因为它会促进潜能的发展。杰里米·泰勒就满是赞赏地注意到，人在恐惧的作用下会跳得特别远。最近艾姆金德兄弟的作品中就有一个引人注目的例子。男仆情急之下跳过的高度，他这辈子到死也再不可能跳过去了。而且，顶尖的重拳手，他们天分的发展有时就是受到这种常伴我们艺术家的恐慌的刺激。实际上对于所有运动项目的顶尖选手来说皆是如此。否则，他们的才华就会被埋没，锋芒被遮蔽，不为人知，亦不自知。我想起一个有趣的例证，是我在德国听说的一个案例。

某天，我骑马走在慕尼黑一带，追上了我们协会一个著名发烧友，名字我就不说了。这位先生告诉我，他已厌倦了这种索然无味的发烧友娱乐方式（按照他的说法）。所以他就离开英格兰前往欧洲大陆，想稍试身手。为此他选择了德国，他以为在整个欧洲此地的警察最笨重呆滞。他的从业处女秀创作于曼海姆。因为知道我是同道中人，他也未加掩饰，就把首次历险和盘托出。他说：“我对面住着一个面包师。他为人相当吝啬，所以基本上独自生活。不知是因为他那张沾着面粉的大脸，还是其他原因，我也不清楚，但我就是‘迷’他，决定拿他的咽喉开张，而他总是敞着脖子，这点非常刺激我的欲望。我观察到，他每晚八点整准时关上所有的窗户。一天夜晚，我见他在关窗户，迅速随他进屋，锁上门，然后非常温文尔雅地对他说话，让他熟悉我此行的目的，同时也建议他不要做任何反抗，不然双方都不会愉快。说着，我掏出了工具，准备开始动手。我刚开口表明来意的时候，面包师像僵硬症发作一动不动。这时，他回过神来，狂躁不安。‘我不要被杀死！’他大声尖叫道，‘我为什么要失去宝贵的生命？’‘为什么？’我说，‘如果不为别的，就是为这个，你在面包里加了明矾。但不管有没有明矾（因为我决定先发制人不给他反驳的机会），你要知道，我是谋杀艺术的鉴赏家，我渴望在细节上提升自己，你粗大的咽喉让我迷恋，我决定一定要享受一番。’‘是吗？’他说，‘但我看你先享受下别的服务吧。’说着，他摆出了拳击的姿势。他居然有搏击的想法，这让我觉得很荒唐。不错，伦敦有个面包师在拳坛赫赫有名，人称筋斗大师，可人家年轻体健。而这人本身就像一大床丑陋的羽毛床垫，五十岁了，身体完全不行。但，尽管如此，跟我这种拳击高手打的时候，他拼死防守，有很多次我都害怕他会反败为胜，然后我这个谋杀发烧友，反可能会被一个无赖的面包师杀了。情况十分危急！心思细腻的人会感受我当时的焦虑。有多严峻呢？这么说吧，前十三回合，面包师是占上风的。第十四回合，我右眼挨了一拳，合上了。我认为，最终是这一拳救了我，因为它大大激怒了我，所以这一回合以及随后的三个回合，我都把面包师打倒在地。”

“第十八回合。面包师打上来，虚弱地哼唧了一声，明显疲惫不堪。前四回合被打趴下对他没有好处。不过，当我向他面若死灰的大脸发送拳头的时候，他还是展现了某些阻击的技巧。我出拳的时候，脚打滑，摔倒了。

“第十九回合。我仔细打量面包师，心想自己居然被这么一大块不成形的面团扰乱这么久，真是可耻。于是我出击猛烈了起来，给了他重重的几拳。出现逆转，双方均被击倒，面包师次数更多，对发烧友比分为10：3。

“第二十回合。面包师跳了起来，惊人地敏捷。考虑到他浑身汗湿，腿部运用得的确一流，打得也精彩。但是他的光芒已不再，打比赛不过是惊恐使然。现在他明显不可能坚持多久了。本回合中，我们尝试了移动闪躲技巧，我大大占了上风，不断地击中他的鼻子。我这么打的原因是，他的鼻子长满了疖子，我想我这么随便地动他的鼻子，他应该会很恼火，结果正如所料。

“接下来三个回合，筋斗大师踉跄得就像冰上行走的奶牛。眼见胜负已分，第二十四回合时，我在他耳边小声嘀咕几句，他随即倒下。我说的不过是我对他这条命还能值多少年金的个人看法罢了。这个小小的亲密私语大大影响了他。他脸上的汗凝住了，接下来的两个回合，任我处置。而当我宣布第二十七回合时间已到的时候，他直挺挺地躺在地上像根木头。”

发烧友说完后，我对他说：“可以推断你应该完成了你的目标。”“你说的没错，”他和善地说，“我完成了，而且很满足。你要知道，对我来说，这种方式是一石二鸟。”也就是说他既拳打了面包师，又杀了他。可是，不管怎样，我是不明白的。因为，在我看来，正相反，他似乎是一鸟二石，先不得不用拳头去除他的自负，然后再用工具杀他。但也无所谓他的逻辑了。他的故事的寓意是好的，因为其证明了，只要对被谋杀的情景进行合理的想象，就可以激发出惊人的潜能。在谋杀的刺激下，曼海姆一个肥胖笨拙、身体半僵硬的面包师都能和技艺高超的英国拳击手大战二十六个回合。是谋杀者的出现和他和蔼可亲的态度，让面包师的天赋得到如此高的提升。

真的，先生们，大多数人谈到谋杀都是苛责的态度，所以听说了这样的事，也许，不再那么苛责就变成了大家的某种义务。听人们说，你会以为被人杀害是最不利、最不便的事，而对于没被害的人来说，这些都不存在。但审慎的人不这么看。“当然，”杰里米·泰勒说，“倒在粗暴的刀剑和斧头之下，比经受发烧的折磨来得痛快（他也许还加了造船工的木锤和铁撬棍）。”“比痛性尿淋漓的折磨好太多。”说得非常对。主教大人讲起话来像智者一般，也像个谋杀发烧友，他的确是。另一位伟大的哲人马可·奥勒留在这个问题上的见解也同样高于世俗的偏见。他声称，“理智最高贵的功能”之一“就是知道是否到了离开世界的时候”。没有哪种知识比此更珍贵，当然这种人必定是非常博爱的物种，会无偿指导别人去了解这方面的知识，而自己却冒着不小的风险。不过，我抛出这些说法，是留给未来的道德家思考的。同时，我要发表我个人的看法，即很少有人杀人是基于博爱或者爱国的道义的，我要重申此前说过至少一次的话，即，多数杀人凶手都是不对的。

威廉姆斯的谋杀作品的高度和完整度都是史无前例的。我不允许自己随口聊几句他的作品就完事。要想详细讲解它们的优点，不花上一整个讲座，或者甚至一系列讲座，是不够的。但是他的案子有一处奇怪的地方，我要讲一下，因为那一点似乎暗示了，他的天才光芒太耀眼，让司法人员一时也难辨方向。你们一定都记得他创作第一个伟大作品（玛尔一家谋杀案）时使用的工具，是一把造船工的木锤和一把匕首。这把木锤属于一个瑞典老人，叫约翰·皮特森，木锤上有他名字的首字母。威廉姆斯把工具落在了玛尔家的屋里，后来落到了地方法官手中。注意，先生们，实际上首字母的细节一经公布，威廉姆斯就立刻被捕，而且，如果早公布的话，本来是可以阻止他完成第二件伟大作品（威廉姆森一家谋杀案）的，正好是十二天之后。然而地方法官把首字母的事向公众隐瞒了整整十二天，直至第二件作品完成。作品完成，他们公布名字，显然是因为觉得威廉姆斯的成就足以不朽，也已经证明他的荣誉也绝非偶然所得。

至于特尔泰先生的案件，我不知道要说什么。很显然我这个现任协会主席是非常尊重前任主席的。我承认他的讲座是很完美。但是，坦率地说，我认为作为艺术家，他最重要的表演真的被高估了。我承认一开始我自己也被大家的狂热带跑了。谋杀案公布的那个早晨，伦敦聚集了自威廉姆斯时代以来我认识的所有发烧友，有史以来最齐的一次。长期卧床的老鉴赏家们，动不动就脾气暴躁，嘲讽加抱怨说：“没事干。”现在他们都蹒跚下床来到我们俱乐部。这样的狂欢，大家这么良好地表达满足之情，我是很少目睹的。随处可见人们握着手，向彼此表示祝贺，相约晚上一聚。除了得意扬扬的疑问，听不见其他的话：“那么！这件如意吗？”“这件对了吗？”“你总算满意了吧？”但是，在这之中，我记得，当听到愤世嫉俗的老发烧友L.S.，laudator temporis acti（这位逝去时光的歌颂者），拖着他那条木腿进来的时候，大家都安静了下来。他像往常一样满脸怒色，一边走，一边嘴里不停地嘟哝，断断续续说了一路。“整个作品没有一个原创的点子，全都是剽窃，卑劣地抄袭我说的点子！而且，他的风格和阿尔布莱希特·丢勒[45]的一样硬气，和菲斯利[46]的一样粗糙。”很多人以为他纯属嫉妒，就是普通的刻薄。但是我要说的是，当第一丝狂热退却，我发现大部分明智的评论家都认为特尔泰的风格中含有虚假的成分。实际上，因为他是我们俱乐部的成员，所以我们的评判自然会友好地偏袒他。再加上伦敦佬都熟悉他这个人，所以一时之间他受到了整个伦敦的欢迎，但是这种欢迎是他的虚假无法长久维系的，因为opinionum commenta delet dies， naturae judicia confirmat（时间会抹去人的意见，却会让真理的判定更清晰）。不过，特尔泰有一个未完成的计划，是要用一副哑铃[47]杀人。我非常钦佩他这个想法，但却只是一个他未竟的草稿。不过在我看来，再怎么样也比他的主要作品好。我记得一些发烧友对这样的草稿竟未能完成深表遗憾。这一点我是无法赞同的，因为对于原创艺术家来说，作品片段和开头大胆的构思往往都蕴含一种精妙，这种精妙通常会在处理细节时消失。

艾姆金德兄弟的作品在我看来远高于特尔泰被大肆吹嘘的表演，的确令人赞叹不已。实际上，它仿照了威廉姆斯不朽的杰作，就像《埃涅阿斯纪》仿照了《伊利亚特》。

不过，现在我要讲讲谋杀的原则，并非要规范你们的实际操作，而是要规范你们的赏析判断。老年妇女和看报纸的乌合之众，只要够血腥，对什么都满意。但这无法满足感知力敏锐的心灵。下面，让我们来讲一讲，一、哪类人适合成为谋杀对象；二、地点的选择；三、时间的选择，以及其他的小条件。

关于人的选择，我想很明显他应当是个好人。因为如果他不是好人，很可能他自己被杀的时候也正在盘算杀别人。而且，这种棋逢对手的争斗尽管足够有趣，最是激动人心，但真的不是评论家会允许自己称之为谋杀的东西。我可以举某些被杀死在漆黑巷子里的人的例子（我不说名字）。乍一看似乎没什么问题，但再细看案情，公众就注意到了，当时被害方自己是打算，轻则抢劫，重则杀掉凶手，前提是他自己够强壮。只要这种情况发生，或者人们这样想了，那这门艺术就得跟一切真诚的效果作别。因为谋杀这门艺术的最终目的与悲剧完全一致，用亚里士多德的话说，即，“通过唤起悲悯和畏惧来净化人心”。而现在，畏惧可能是有，但如果只是两恶相争死了一个，如何能有悲悯可言？

同样，选择的谋杀对象显然不应该是公众人物。比如，明智的艺术家都不会选择谋杀亚伯拉罕·纽伦。因为实际上，虽然大家都读过很多关于亚伯拉罕·纽伦的事，见过他的人却很少，以至于人们形成了一个固定的看法：他是一个抽象的概念。记得某次，我正好说到和亚伯拉罕·纽伦一起在一家咖啡馆吃饭，所有人都轻蔑地看着我，就好像我自称和祭司王约翰一起打过台球，或者和教皇决斗过。顺便提一句，教皇是非常不合适的谋杀人选，因为他作为基督教世界之父几乎无处不在，而且就像布谷鸟一样，人们如此频繁地听说，却从未真正见过，所以我怀疑大多数人也当他是个抽象的概念。如果某个公众人物经常举办宴会，宴会上“满是时下的美味佳肴”，情况就会大为不同。大家都确信他不是一个抽象的概念，因此谋杀他也就没什么不合适，只不过他的谋杀就要被归类成刺杀。这方面，我尚未做讨论。

还有，所选的谋杀对象应当身体健康，因为谋杀病人是极其野蛮的行径。一般病人也不撑不了多久。因此，就不要选二十五岁以上的伦敦佬了，因为过了二十五岁，伦敦佬肯定都有胃病。如果非要去街道狭窄人口密集的伦敦寻找猎物，他应该一次起码杀掉两个人。万一选中的是个裁缝，他心里当然清楚，根据早就算好的等式，他得杀掉十八个裁缝[48]才算尽了本分。现在，考虑到病人需要慰藉，你们将在谋杀中看到一门艺术通常会取得的效果：感化人心。先生们，总的来说，世人是非常残忍的。他们想看到的谋杀不过是血浆喷涌的场面。只要花哨地展示这种场面对他们来说就足够了。但是有见识的鉴赏家可不行，他们的品味要高雅得多。和所有的人文教育一样，我们这门艺术，经过全面细致的研修后，也能增加同情心，使人更具人情味。千真万确，正如古语所说：

Ingenuas didicisse fideliter artes,

Emollit mores, nec sinit esse feros.

真正的人文教育使人举止高雅，

让人不再野蛮无情。

有位良友，因为博爱和一贯的善举而被熟知，他建议，选择的作案对象也应是那种家中有很多小孩完全靠他生活的人，以此来强化悲剧的效果。这的确是一个明智的提醒。但我不想过于强调这个条件。一丝不苟的好品味肯定会这样要求，不过，只要选中的人道德和健康方面无可厚非，我不想再去苛求这个条件，这样可能会缩小艺术家的选择范围。

谋杀对象就讲到这里。关于谋杀时间、地点和工具，我有很多要讲，但是今天暂时没有机会了。好的艺术直觉通常会指导从业者选择夜晚和隐蔽的地方，但也不乏背离这条原则却卓有成效的案例。在作案时间上，拉斯康贝夫人案是个漂亮的例外，我已经说过了。在作案时间和地点这两个方面，爱丁堡年报（1805年）上就有一个不错的例外，爱丁堡的孩童人人都知道此案，但不知何故，它在英格兰的谋杀迷中却被遗漏，没能获得应有的名声。我说的是一个银行搬运工的谋杀案，被害的时候，搬运工正在搬一袋钱，就在光天化日之下，一出高街的拐弯处，而此街是欧洲最有名的街道之一。凶手是谁到现在也不知道。

Sed fugit interea, fugit irreparabile tempus,

Singula dum capti circumvectamur amore.

但此时，时光飞逝，去而不返，

而我们，迷恋细节，徘徊不前。

那么，先生们，最后，让我再次严肃声明，我绝不是什么职业人士。除了1801年在一只公猫身上行凶之外，我此生再未有过任何杀戮。杀猫的结果和我的打算相去甚远。我本来只是想杀死他。“什么？我毕生只能做一名听众吗？”我说，“我永远不能把话讲出来吗？”在一个漆黑的夜晚，凌晨1点，我下楼找公猫，我满心歹意，肯定一脸谋杀者凶狠的模样。可当我找到他时，他正在偷袭食品储存室，里面有面包和其他东西。这就让事情发生了新的变化。在一个物资匮乏的时期，连基督徒们都只能吃马铃薯面包、米粉面包之类的东西，一只公猫居然这样浪费优质的小麦面包，这是十足的叛国。处死他立刻变成了一种应尽的爱国义务。当我高高举起并挥动闪闪发光的刀时，我幻想自己像布鲁图斯[49]一样站起来，在一群爱国者中间格外耀眼。当我刺向他时，我

大声呼叫图利[50]的名字，

向他的国父致以敬意！

从此，我就会有些杂念，像杀一头老母羊，或者杀一只不能再生蛋的老母鸡。这些“小鹿”们都被锁进我胸中的秘密里。至于这门艺术更高阶的知识范畴，坦白地说是完全不适合我的。我的野心没长那么大。没有，先生们，用贺拉斯的话说——

fungos vice cotis, ex cutumReddere ere quæferrum valet, exsorsipsasecandi.

我就充当磨石的角色，它磨快铁器，自己却不能用于切割。

[1] 最高巡回法庭，位于伦敦的高等法院的法官前往英国主要县镇审理重犯，如杀人犯、抢劫犯、强奸犯等。

[2] 指康德。他在无条件诚实论的道路上走得太远，甚至要求，倘若一个人看到无辜的受害者逃脱了凶手的追杀，凶手要是问他，即使明知凶手要杀人，他也有义务说实话，说出逃跑者的去向。生怕一旦争论激烈就想不起这个原则，在受到法国某著名作家抨击后，他又重申了这一原则，并给出自己的理由。——原文注

[3] 位于伦敦的中央刑事法庭。

[4] 英国外科医生约翰·霍希普。

[5] 第一架五个半八音阶钢琴出现在18世纪晚期，到了19世纪早期钢琴有了六个半八音阶键盘。

[6] 奥托吕科斯是莎士比亚的《冬天的故事》里的贼。

[7] 乔治·巴灵顿（1755—1804）是爱尔兰臭名昭著的扒手。

[8] 约翰·特尔泰（1794—1824）因怀疑赌伴威廉姆·维尔骗走了他300英镑，把他引到乡下杀死。

[9] 土八·该隐是该隐的后代。土八，Tubal，是tube（管子）的形容词。在 《创世记》中土八·该隐发明了铜器和铁器。

[10] 设菲尔德位于英国的约克郡，19世纪时是世界高规格钢铁产品的制造中心。

[11] 邓肯和班科出自《麦克白》。

[12] 伯里克利（约公元前495—前429），雅典黄金时期（希波战争至伯罗奔尼撒战争之间）具有重要影响的领导人。

[13] 拉丁语，意为被谋杀。

[14] 在《坎特伯雷故事》中，修道院院长讲了一个犹太人杀害基督教小孩的故事，其中提到了1255年真实发生在英国林肯郡八岁小孩休身上的事。

[15] 喀提林（约公元前108—前62），罗马的阴谋叛变者，公元前63年蓄意刺杀执政官西塞罗和其他对他有敌意的元老。

[16] 克洛狄乌斯·普尔喀（约公元前93—前52），罗马共和国末年制造事端的政客，是西塞罗的护卫之一，但是参与了喀提林策动的刺杀西塞罗行动。

[17] 塞西格斯（公元前93—前63），上文提到的罗马阴谋叛变小团体成员之一，曾企图谋杀西塞罗等显赫人物未遂，被捕后被处以绞刑。

[18] “山中老人”指拉希德丁·锡南，12世纪后半叶活跃于叙利亚地区的一位伊斯兰教阿萨辛派首领。其活跃的年代正处于十字军东征期间，欧洲人称其为“山中老人”，策划刺杀了多个政要。

[19] 奥兰治亲王威廉一世（1533—1584），荷兰“国父”，曾任荷兰共和国第一任执政，1584年遭西班牙间谍刺杀身亡。

[20] 亨利四世（1553—1610），“贤明王亨利”，1610年在巴黎被刺身亡。

[21] 白金汉公爵（1592—1628），英国第一世白金汉公爵，1628年被刺身亡。

[22] 古斯塔夫·阿道夫二世（1594—1632），瑞典瓦萨王朝国王，即位后与神圣罗马帝国相争，不幸于吕岑会战中阵亡。

[23] 阿尔布雷赫特·冯·华伦斯坦（1583—1634），波西米亚（现属捷克）杰出的军事家，1634年吕岑会战后，在海布被他的军官暗杀。

[24] 沃尔特·哈德，18世纪英国作家，著有《瑞典国王，大帝，古斯塔夫·阿道夫生平史》。

[25] 约翰·洛克（1632—1704），英国哲学家，在知识论上，与乔治·布克莱和大卫·休谟共同成为英国经验主义的代表人物。

[26] 笛卡尔（1596—1650），法国哲学家、物理学家、数学家，黑格尔称其为近代“哲学之父”，二元论的代表。

[27] 安德里安·巴耶（1649—1706），笛卡尔的传记作家。

[28] 中欧主要的航运水道之一，全长1165公里，三分之一流经捷克，三分之二流经德国。

[29] 卖不出去的书都被拿去做短裤里衬。

[30] 欧洲海上的传说，鬼船是一艘幽灵船，注定永远在大海上航行，它的出现预示着灾难即将发生。

[31] 掺水烈酒。

[32] “1675年6月1日。喝了三碗潘趣酒（一种很奇怪的酒），没全喝掉。”亨利·狄昂志神父在他最近出版的日记中写道。这段文字的注释中提到福莱尔1672年出版的《东印度群岛之行》，他提到“那个叫潘趣（印度语是五的意思）的让人堕落的酒，由五种配料组成”。因此，医生们都管它叫 “五度音程”。如果只有四种配料，就叫“四福音合参”。毫无疑问，正是它的福音名将自己推荐给了狄昂志神父。——原文注

[33] 《斯宾诺莎传》一书中所提及的内容。

[34] 《斯宾诺莎传》一书中所提及的内容。

[35] 达克通：曾在欧洲的意大利等国流通的银币。

[36] 意为：“到处都是恐惧”，从音步看，在音节que和a的影响下，这个挽联的最后半句显得笨拙。

[37] 《利维坦》被广泛批评为愤世嫉俗和反对宗教。

[38] 一种巨大的水怪。

[39] 马勒伯朗士在笛卡尔的基础上更好地发展完善了偶因论：人类不可能了解内部和外部世界，除非将人类和上帝联系在一起。不管是物体位置的改变还是个人思想的改变，都不是直接由物体或者个人引起的，而是上帝。所谓的原因，不过是上帝制造效果的场合。

[40] 英国伯明翰18世纪工业革命后成为世界制造业中心。塞缪尔·帕尔（1747—1825）1783年成为英国沃里克郡哈顿地区的牧师。哈顿位于沃里克和伯明翰之间。

[41] 帕尔于1800年4月15日做了斯佩尔布道，之后又发表了布道，作者对他的布道评价很低。

[42] 盖乌斯·梅塞纳斯（公元前70—前8），罗马帝国皇帝奥古斯都的谋臣，同时还是艺术保护人，诗人维吉尔和贺拉斯都曾经得到过他的帮助。他的名字因此变成了艺术赞助人的代名词。

[43] 贺拉斯·弗拉库斯（公元前65—前8），罗马帝国奥古斯都时代的著名诗人，罗马文学“黄金时代”的代表人物。

[44] 维吉利乌斯·马罗（公元前70—前19），英语中称维吉尔，罗马帝国奥古斯都时代的著名诗人，著有《埃涅阿斯纪》。

[45] 阿尔布莱希特·丢勒（1471—1528），德国中世纪末、文艺复兴时期著名的油画家、版画家、雕塑家。

[46] 约翰·亨利希·菲斯利（1741—1825），德国—瑞士裔英国画家。

[47] 特尔泰是一名出色的业余拳击手，所以想用哑铃杀人是自然的事。

[48] 谚语，九个裁缝才算一个男人。

[49] 马尔库斯·尤里乌斯·布鲁图斯（公元前85—前42），罗马共和国晚期的一名元老院议员，组织并参与了对凯撒的刺杀。

[50] 马库斯·图利乌斯·西塞罗。

亨利与伊丽莎

谨将本篇小说献给库珀[8]小姐。

她恭顺又卑微的仆人

作者敬上

这天，乔治爵爷和哈考特夫人在监督晒干草的工人干活，见着勤快的便赞许地笑笑，对着偷懒的就打几棍子。恰在此时，他俩看见一垛干草堆底下躺着个漂亮的小女孩，最多不过三个月大，差点就被那茂密的草叶给挡住了。

夫妇俩自己并没有孩子，看到她那可爱秀美的面容，听到她活力十足的儿语，似在回答他俩那许许多多的疑问，不禁深受感动、大为欣喜，于是决定把她带回家，悉心照料，供她念书。

这夫妻俩本身都是好人，所以他俩认为，最首要也是最主要的就是激励她热爱美德、憎恨恶行，在这一点上，他们做得非常成功（伊丽莎的天性本就如此）。待到她长大以后，凡是认识她的人，都觉得她很讨人喜欢。

哈考特夫人宠着她，乔治爵爷疼着她，全世界都爱着她，这孩子一直过得快快乐乐，从未吃过一点苦，直到她十八岁这年。有一天，她那冷酷无情的恩主夫妇发现她偷了一张五十英镑的钞票，便将她逐出家门。对于那些没有伊丽莎这般伟大高尚思想的人而言，要是他们遭逢如此剧变，肯定就只有死路一条，不过伊丽莎知道自己是出类拔萃之人，于是开开心心地自娱自乐起来。她坐在一棵树下，现编现唱了下面这段歌词。

歌

尽管我双脚踏进不幸的阴影，

可我希望自己永远不会缺了友情，

只因我将永葆心灵的无邪，

绝不背离美德的疆界。

她唱着这支歌儿，愉快地想着心事，如此消遣了几个钟头才站起身来，走上通往M镇的那条公路。M是一个小小的集镇，她最要好的朋友就在那里，经营着一家名叫红狮[9]的小酒馆。

她径直来到朋友这里，向她讲述了自己新近的不幸遭遇，同时表明心愿，说她想要去人家家里做个卑微的女伴。

要伊丽莎说，这世上最可亲的人，那就是威尔逊太太了。她刚一知晓伊丽莎的愿望，便在酒馆里坐下来，给她最为敬重的F公爵夫人修书一封，信中这样写道：

F公爵夫人　敬启

恳请贵府收留一名年轻女子，她的人品高洁无瑕，不想去做女佣，却愿意与您做伴。请快些将她从我的怀抱里带走吧。

萨拉·威尔逊敬上

这位公爵夫人和威尔逊太太友谊深厚，就算为她付出一切代价也在所不惜，现如今这么一个大好机会摆在面前，让她能够为威尔逊太太效劳，公爵夫人自是大喜过望。因此，收到信以后她即刻就启程上路，当天晚上便到了红狮酒馆。F公爵夫人年约四十五六，很容易激动，交了朋友便死心塌地，结了仇恨也绝不会回心转意。她是个寡妇，唯一的女儿眼下正在跟一个极为富有的年轻人谈婚论嫁。

公爵夫人一看到咱们的女主角，就张开双臂搂住她的脖子，宣称自己对她十分喜欢，并决定今后和她永不分离。听到她这一番友情宣言，伊丽莎很是欣喜，她洒泪挥别亲爱的威尔逊太太，次日一早陪着公爵夫人来到了她位于萨里郡的宅第。

公爵夫人将她介绍给女儿哈丽雅特小姐[10]认识，言辞之间尽显殷殷关切。哈丽雅特小姐非常喜欢她的相貌，于是恳求与她以姐妹相待，伊丽莎纡尊降贵地答应了。

哈丽雅特小姐的恋人塞西尔先生常常到公爵夫人家里来，因而也就经常见到伊丽莎。他和伊丽莎互生情愫，塞西尔先开口表白了自己的爱，并劝说伊丽莎跟他私订终身。他没费什么力气便得到伊丽莎的应允，而且，他俩确信，公爵夫人的牧师也深爱着伊丽莎，只要是为她效劳，他什么都愿意做。

有天晚上，公爵夫人和哈丽雅特小姐去参加一个集会，他俩便趁着她们离家的大好机会，在那位倾心于伊丽莎的牧师主持下结为夫妻。

夫人和小姐回到家才大吃一惊地发现，伊丽莎不见了，只留下一张便条，上面写道：

夫人：

我们结婚了，就此别过。

亨利·塞西尔和伊丽莎·塞西尔

这封信已经足以将整件事情解释得一清二楚，夫人读完之后勃然大怒，用尽了她盛怒之下所能想到的一切难听字眼大骂他们，舒舒服服骂了半小时。随后派出三百人带着武器去追他们，同时下令说，活要见人，死要见尸，决不允许空手而归。夫人的打算是，如果这些人真的将他俩活着带回来了，她就先把他俩关上几年，再折磨至死。

与此同时，逃跑在外的塞西尔和伊丽莎来到了欧洲大陆。他俩认为在这里比在祖国要安全一些，可以免遭公爵夫人的可怕报复——他们的担心是极有道理的。

他俩在法兰西先后生下两个男孩，只是结婚才三年伊丽莎就成了寡妇，无力养活她自己和两个孩子。自从结婚以来，他们几乎是挣多少花多少，没存下几个钱来。他们每年的花销是一万两千磅，可是塞西尔先生留下的遗产却连这个数字的二十分之一都不到。

伊丽莎深知这摊子事是没法儿理清爽了，丈夫一死，她便乘着一艘装有五十五门大炮的军舰回到英格兰，这军舰还是他俩当初手头比较宽裕的时候建造的。可是她一手牵着一个孩子刚刚踏上多佛尔的海岸，就被公爵夫人派来的军官抓住，送进了地牢。这里地方虽小，倒也温暖舒适，恰似夫人私家的新门[11]监狱，是公爵夫人专为款待她的秘密囚犯而建。

进了地牢之后，伊丽莎第一桩想到的事就是如何离开这里。

她来到门口，门是锁着的。她看看窗户，窗上有铁条。两条路都不通，她好生沮丧，觉得逃跑无望，正在万念俱灰之际，居然瞧见监房一角摆着一把小锯子和一架绳梯，这可真是鸿运当头。她立刻就拿起锯子动起了手，几个礼拜之后，她已经锯掉了所有的铁条，只留下一根用来拴绳梯。

接下来又遇到的一个难题，她想了好些时候才找到解决的法子。她的孩子们年纪还太小，没法儿自己从绳梯上爬下去，而她下去的时候又不可能抱着他俩一起。最后她决定，先把她所有的衣物都扔下去——她多的就是衣服，再严令孩子们切不可伤了自己，然后把他们也扔下去。她自己则轻轻松松地顺着绳梯往下爬，到了底下，她满意地发现两个小家伙都完好无损、睡得正香。

如今她觉得，她和孩子们要想活下去，这些衣服就非卖不可了。挥泪告别昔日辉煌仅存的遗迹之后，她用所得的钱财去买了些其他更有用处的东西——给孩子们买了些玩具，又给她自己买了块金表。

上述这些生活必需品刚刚拿到手，她就开始觉得饥肠辘辘，并且有理由相信她的两个孩子也差不多是同样的情形，因为他们正要啃下她的两根手指头。

眼见得大难临头、躲避不过，为了做些补救，她只好下定决心，仍旧回去找她的老朋友——乔治爵爷和哈考特夫人，他二人慷慨大度，她曾多次亲身体会，只盼着如今也能再度亲历。

他们那舒适宜人的大宅距此还有四十英里，她马不停蹄地走了三十英里，发现前方是一座小镇。在从前那段幸福的时光，她常常陪着乔治爵爷和哈考特夫人来到这里，在其中一家客栈里吃顿冷餐。

往事历历涌上心头，她记起自己最后一次开心地这样吃吃喝喝，记起自己从那以后所经历的桩桩奇遇，一时间想出了神，便在一位先生家门前的台阶上坐下了。往昔忆完，她立起身，决心就在那家给她留下愉快回忆的客栈安营扎寨，指望着从进进出出的宾客那里讨些赏钱。

她刚刚在客栈院子里选定位置站好，一辆马车便驶将出来，在转过她所站的角落时停下，以便车夫能有机会欣赏一番她美丽的芳容。伊丽莎于是走到车旁，打算向他们乞求施舍，可是一看到车里的那位夫人，她便惊叫起来。

“哈考特夫人！”

听到这话，那位夫人答道：“伊丽莎！”

“是的，夫人，我正是可怜的伊丽莎。”

乔治爵爷也在马车里，吃惊得说不出话来，他正要请伊丽莎说说她眼下这是什么处境，哈考特夫人却喜不自胜地喊道：“乔治爵爷，乔治爵爷，伊丽莎不仅是咱们的养女，她还是咱们的亲生女儿。”

“咱们的亲生女儿！哈考特夫人，你这话从何说起？你也知道自己从未生过一男半女，求你说说清楚吧。”

“乔治爵爷，你一定还记得，当初你乘船去往美洲的时候，我已经怀孕了。”

“我记得，我记得，请继续说吧，亲爱的波莉。”

“你离开四个月之后，我生下了这个女孩，可我害怕你会不高兴，因为你想要的是男孩。于是我带着她来到一垛干草堆旁，将她放在那里。又过了几个礼拜，你回来了，万幸的是，你并未向我问起此事。我以为自己的孩子过得很好，觉得心满意足，很快就忘了自己曾有过孩子。所以，不久之后咱们在那垛干草底下发现她时，不仅你没想到她是我的孩子，就连我自己都没有想到，尽管我当初正是在那里把她放下的。冒昧地说，本来没什么会让我想起此事，但是刚才偶然间听到她的声音，我忽然意识到，这跟我自己那孩子的声音正是一模一样。”

“这事的来龙去脉你解释得合情合理，令人信服，”乔治爵爷说道，“毫无疑问，她就是咱们的女儿，既是如此，对她当年犯下的盗窃罪行，我便既往不咎了。”

双方就此言归于好，伊丽莎带着她的两个孩子登上马车，回到她已阔别近四年的那个家。

伊丽莎在哈考特庄园重拾往日威势，随即便募集了一支军队，带着他们将公爵夫人那温暖舒适的监狱夷为平地，此举为她赢得了千万人的称道，她心里也觉得自己做得极好。

[8]Jane Cooper（简·库珀，1771—1798），作者的表姐兼儿时好友，大约在1789年年初的时候拜访过奥斯汀一家。索瑟姆在《简·奥斯汀文学手稿》中推测，《亨利与伊丽莎》的写作时间是在1787年至1790年。

[9]Red Lion（红狮），英国最受欢迎的酒馆名称。缘自1603年，伊丽莎白一世死后无嗣，苏格兰国王詹姆士六世继承英国王位，称詹姆士一世。他下令英国所有重要建筑（包括酒馆在内）均需涂上代表苏格兰的红狮纹章，以象征苏格兰和英格兰的统一。目前全英仍有七百多家酒馆名为“红狮”。

[10]Lady Harriet，公爵之女可称“Lady”。

[11]Newgate，著名监狱，位于伦敦西门。

漂亮的卡桑德拉

经奥斯汀小姐[12]许可，特将本篇小说敬献于她，共十二章。

献词

小姐：

您就如同凤凰[13]一般。您品位高雅、情怀高尚、美德无数。您容颜秀丽、体形优美、风姿绰约。您举止优雅、言谈理性、相貌出众。如果下面这篇小说能供您消遣一时，我也就再无所求了。

您最最恭顺卑微的仆人

作者敬上

一

卡桑德拉是邦德街[14]上一位著名女帽制造商的独生女儿。她的父亲出身高贵，和某某公爵夫人的管家是近亲。

二

到了十六岁这年，卡桑德拉已经出落得美丽动人，性子也很和气。她刚巧看上了一顶精致优雅的帽子——这是一位伯爵夫人订做的，她的母亲才刚刚做好。她将这顶帽子戴在自己那漂亮的脑袋上，然后走出她母亲的商店，出门闯荡去了。

三

她遇见的第一个人是一位子爵，这个大名鼎鼎的年轻人不仅德才兼备，而且风度翩翩、相貌英俊。她对他屈膝一礼，随后继续前进。

四

她走进一家糕点店，风卷残云般吞下六份冰激凌，却拒绝付钱，将糕点师打倒在地，然后扬长而去。

五

接下来，她登上了一辆出租马车，命车夫前往汉普斯特德，可是刚到那里，她却又命令车夫掉转车头送她回来。

六

回到了出发时的同一条街、同一个地点，车夫向她索要车钱。

七

她在衣兜里搜了一遍又一遍，却一无所获，一分钱也找不到。车夫强横起来，她便将帽子往他头上一戴，拔腿跑了。

八

跑过一条又一条街道，她一直平安无事，直到经过布鲁斯伯里广场的转角，在这里她遇见了玛丽亚。

九

卡桑德拉吓了一跳，玛丽亚似乎也大吃一惊；她俩颤抖着，脸色由红转白，然后一语不发地擦肩而过。

十

有人和卡桑德拉搭讪，那人是个寡妇，跟卡桑德拉是朋友。她的脑袋小，窗户却更小，她便将脑袋从窗户里挤出来，向卡桑德拉问好。卡桑德拉屈膝一礼，然后继续前进。

十一

又走过四分之一英里，卡桑德拉回到了邦德街上的家里，此时她已经离家近七小时了。

十二

她走进家门，被母亲紧紧拥在怀里。这真是位贤妻良母。卡桑德拉微微一笑，低声自语道：“今天过得可真充实。”

[12]Cassandra-Elizabeth Austen（卡桑德拉-伊丽莎白·奥斯汀，1773—1845），作者的姐姐。本篇作品很可能创作于1787年至1788年之间，因为作者一家曾于1788年8月到访过作品中的背景地伦敦。

[13]作者在献词中将姐姐卡桑德拉喻为“凤凰”，这一点颇令人费解。据R. W.查普曼编纂的《简·奥斯汀作品集第六卷：次要作品》，这可能是指卡桑德拉像凤凰一样以虚构的形式重现在这篇由十二个章节构成的小说里。

[14]Bond Street，伦敦市中心一条著名购物街，自18世纪开始，已成为伦敦的时尚购物中心。

一位处境困难的年轻女子写给友人的信[15]

几天以前，我去参加阿什伯纳姆先生举办的一场私人舞会。因为家母从不出去交际，她便将我托付给格雷维尔夫人照顾，夫人赏光同意顺道来接我，并且允许我面向前方坐着——对于这一优待，我倒是无所谓，尤其是我深知夫人将之视为赐予我的莫大恩惠。“哎，玛丽亚小姐”（夫人看见我朝着马车车门走来，便开口说道），“今天晚上你看起来特别漂亮——我可怜的女儿们在你身旁可就被比下去了。但愿你妈妈别因为让你出门而担心。你这是穿了一件新礼服吗？”

“是的，夫人。”我尽量不动声色地答道。

“对嘛，我也觉得这件挺好（她用手摸了摸，因为我是蒙她恩准坐在她旁边的），我敢说这礼服非常时髦，不过我得直说——你知道我总是想到什么就说什么，我觉得这钱花得冤枉。你为什么不能穿你那件条纹的旧礼服呢？我这人不会因为人家穷就横加挑剔，我一向认为，穷人应该被人瞧不起，被人可怜，但不该受人责备，特别是那些身不由己的穷人。可是另一方面我也得说，在我看来，你那件条纹的旧礼服穿在你身上就已经很不错了，跟你说实话吧（我这人向来想到什么就说什么），我想舞会上恐怕有一半的人压根儿就不会知道你有没有礼服，不过我估摸着你是打算今天晚上钓个金龟婿。嗯，那就是越快越好了，祝你成功。”

“夫人，其实我并无此意——”

“谁听过哪位年轻姑娘承认自己想嫁个有钱人啊？”格雷维尔小姐大笑着说，不过我相信埃伦肯定是同情我的。

“你走之前，你母亲已经睡下了吗？”夫人问道。

“亲爱的夫人，”埃伦说，“现在才九点。”

“话是不假，埃伦，但蜡烛是要花钱买的，威廉斯夫人这么明智，她可不会铺张浪费。”

“夫人，我走的时候，她刚刚坐下来准备吃夜宵。”

“她夜宵吃什么？”“我没看到。”“我猜是面包和奶酪吧。”“我觉得这就是最好的夜宵了。”埃伦说道。“这话真没道理，”她母亲反驳道，“你哪天吃得都比这个好。”格雷维尔小姐夸张地大笑起来，她听见她妈妈说俏皮话时总是这个反应。

这便是我乘坐夫人的马车时被迫面临的屈辱境地。我却不敢失礼，母亲总是告诫我，要想立足于世，就须谦卑忍耐。她坚持认为，只要格雷维尔夫人开口相邀，我就不可拒绝。若非如此，我是断然不会踏进她家一步的，也绝不会登上她的马车，因为肯定会不愉快——她总是对我恶语相向，缘由不过是我穷罢了。我们到达阿什伯纳姆府上时已近十点，比预期晚了一个半小时；不过格雷维尔夫人是个时髦的人（或者说她自以为很时髦），自然是不会守时的。舞会尚未开始，专为等着格雷维尔小姐。进屋之后不久，伯纳德先生便来邀我跳舞，我们正要起身，他却记起自己的白手套还在仆人那里，于是立刻跑出去取。就在此时，舞会开始了，走向另一个房间的格雷维尔夫人刚好从我面前经过，她看见我，随即停下脚步，也不管近旁还有好几个人，开口说道：

“你好啊，玛丽亚小姐！找不到舞伴吗？可怜的姑娘！我看你的新礼服怕是白穿了。不过别灰心，今天晚上这舞会结束前，没准你还是能跳上一支舞的。”她一边这么说，一边继续走，尽管我一再保证已经有人邀请过我，她却根本不听，让我因为她在人前如此说我而大为光火——不过伯纳德先生很快就回来了，他一进房间就来到我身边，当着那些老夫人的面带我走向跳舞的人群。这些人刚才可都是听见了她那一席话的，但愿格雷维尔夫人对我人品所泼的脏水可以就此洗清。没过多久，跳舞的乐趣就使我忘却了一切烦恼，我拥有全场的最佳舞伴，并且他还是一大笔财产的继承人。我看得出格雷维尔夫人似乎很不高兴，因为她发现伯纳德先生竟然选了我做舞伴。她打定主意要给我难堪，于是当我们在跳舞间隙坐下休息时，她便带着梅森小姐朝我走来，比平日更加盛气凌人，大声开了口，全场有一半人都能听到她的声音：“请问，玛丽亚小姐，令祖是做哪个行当的？梅森小姐和我对此有点分歧，不知道他究竟是杂货商还是订书匠。”我明白她是想羞辱我，便决心尽量不让她的奸计得逞。“夫人，都不是；他是一名红酒商人。”“是了，我就知道他的工作低贱得很——他破产了不是吗？”“夫人，我想他并不曾破产。”“难道他没有潜逃吗？”“此事我闻所未闻。”“总之他死的时候还欠着债吧？”“从没有人如此说过。”“怎么，难道令尊不是穷得叮当响吗？”“我认为不是。”“他有一回是不是被人给告了？”“我倒不曾见过他出入法庭。”她狠狠地看了我一眼，怒气冲冲地转身走了；我却是喜忧参半，喜的是我没有对她恭敬有礼，忧的是怕旁人会觉得我太过粗鲁。格雷维尔夫人被我气极了，一晚上都不再搭理我了，不过，即便她对我青眼有加，也同样会无视我的存在，因为她喜欢跟一群大人物待在一起，除非是实在找不到人说话了，否则她可不会理睬我。吃夜宵时，格雷维尔小姐跟她母亲那一帮人坐在一起，不过埃伦更愿意和我以及伯纳德一家待在一块儿。我们跳舞跳得很开心，回家的路上格雷维尔夫人一直在睡觉，所以这一路我还是挺自在的。

第二天我们吃晚餐的时候，格雷维尔夫人的马车来到门口停下了，她一般认为就该这个时候来。她叫仆人进来传话，说她“不能下车，但有话要对玛丽亚小姐讲，所以请小姐务必去到马车门口，而且要赶紧去、马上就去”！“妈妈，这话可真是太无礼了！”我说。她却答道：“去吧，玛丽亚。”于是我只得出去，被迫听凭夫人摆布，顶着刺骨的狂风站在那里。

“玛丽亚小姐，我怎么觉得你没有昨晚那么漂亮了——不过我可不是来查看你穿了什么衣裳的，只是想告诉你一声，后天你可以来和我们共进晚餐。不是明天。记好了，明天别来，因为我们要宴请克莱蒙特勋爵和夫人以及托马斯·斯坦利爵爷一家。我后天不会派马车来接你，所以你得委屈一下，要是下雨的话，你就把伞带上——”听到她恩准我不让自己淋湿，我差点就忍不住大笑起来。“还有，请你务必记住要准时，我可不会等着你。我讨厌食物被煮过头。不过你倒也不必提前来。你母亲还好吗？她在吃晚餐是吧？”“是的，夫人，您大驾光临的时候，我们刚好在用晚餐。”“玛丽亚，你恐怕很冷吧。”埃伦说。“是很冷，这东风[16]吹得真是吓人——”她母亲说道，“实话对你说，这窗子开着我都要受不了了。不过，玛丽亚小姐，你已经被风吹习惯了吧，所以你的肤色才会如此红润粗糙。你们这些不常有马车坐的年轻姑娘从来就不在意辛苦赶路时是什么天气，也无所谓风吹起裙子露出了腿。我是不会让我的女儿们在这种天气像你这样站在外头的。可是有一种人，要么就是感觉不到冷，要么就是不知道体贴别人。好了，别忘记礼拜四下午五点钟到我们家里来。你千万要叫女仆晚上来接你，那天不会有月光，你走回家这一路会很可怕。替我向你母亲问好。恐怕你的晚餐都要凉了。赶车走吧。”她就这么走了，我却被她气得怒火中烧。她每次都是如此。

玛丽亚·威廉斯

[15]本篇出自A Collection of Letters（《书信集》），是第三封信。该书信集由五封风格各异、相互独立的书信组成，均敬献给作者的表姐Jane Cooper（简·库珀）。

[16]英国的东风系从欧洲大陆北部吹来，类似于我国的西北风，非常寒冷。

一位热恋中的年轻女子写给友人的信[17]

我叔叔越来越小气，我婶婶越来越挑剔，而我却一天比一天爱恋更深。如此发展下去，到了年底不知会是何等光景！今天早晨，我有幸收到亲爱的默斯格罗夫写来的信，内容如下：

萨克维尔街：1月7日

自我初见美丽的亨丽埃塔那天起，迄今已有整整一月，这是个神圣的纪念日，必须以某种与之相称的方式记录下来，所以我便写信给她。我永远也不会忘记她的美貌第一次展露在我眼前的那一刻——如您所知，时间绝不可能将此刻从我记忆中抹去。我和她相遇在斯库达摩尔夫人家里。夫人何其有幸，住处竟与亨丽埃塔女神的居所相距不足一英里！当这可爱的人儿踏进房间之时，哦！我的感觉是怎样的？见到您，我惊为天人，一脸爱慕地注视着您，您的魅力似乎每一刻都有增无减。不幸的默斯格罗夫未及环顾左右便为您的妩媚所俘虏。是的，小姐，我爱上了您，这是我的幸运，亦是我的不幸，对此我却只有无尽感激。我扪心自问：“默斯格罗夫，你凭着哪一点能为亨丽埃塔牺牲呢？你这令人羡慕的凡夫俗子！你为伊人憔悴，伊人却不只为你一人所独钟，有位上校也倾心于她，还有位准男爵为了她举杯祝酒！”迷人的亨丽埃塔，您是多么美丽！我宣布，您就是女神！您并非一介凡人，您是天使，维纳斯就是您。总而言之，小姐，我此生从未见过比您更漂亮的姑娘。您允许默斯格罗夫爱您，给我以希望，您在我眼中便更加美丽动人。

啊！天使般的亨丽埃塔小姐，我是多么热切地期盼着您那可憎的叔父和缺德的婶娘早赴黄泉，此心此情，苍天可鉴。我的佳人非要等他们死了才肯答应嫁给我，因为他们的遗产可以让她过上富足的生活，而我的财产却不足以做到。尽管我的产业还是有可能会增加的，可是狠心的亨丽埃塔决意如此，不肯动摇！我目前和姐姐住在一起，我自己的房子虽好，眼下却有些破败失修，在修葺完毕可以住人之前，我打算一直住在姐姐家里。再见了，我心中温柔可亲的公主，我用这颗心颤抖着签下自己的名字。

您最狂热的崇拜者以及忠实卑微的仆人

T.默斯格罗夫

玛蒂尔达，这就是一封典型的情书啊！如此富有见地，如此充满感情，思想如此纯洁，语言如此流畅，如此情真意切，全都集于这一张纸上。你从前可曾读过这样的杰作？不，这个问题我可回答不了，像默斯格罗夫这样的人是可遇不可求的。哦！我多么想和他在一起！我打算明天把下面这封信寄给他作为回复。

最最亲爱的默斯格罗夫，来信收到，吾心甚喜，无以言表；我以为自己会喜极而泣，因我爱你胜过爱这世上任何人。在我眼中，你是英格兰最可亲、最英俊的男人，你肯定就是如此。这是我此生读过的最甜蜜的来信，再像这样给我写一封吧，把字里行间都写满你对我的爱。我迫不及待想要见你。咱们怎么才能设法见上一面？我们是如此相爱，分离会要了我们的命。哦！亲爱的默斯格罗夫，你无法想象我是多么盼望叔父和婶娘快点死，简直都等不及了。我对你的爱恋与日俱增，如果他们不早点死的话，我想我一定会发疯的。你的姐姐何其幸福，能够享受到你在家中与她为伴的乐趣；伦敦的众人何其幸福，因为有你在那里。亲爱的默斯格罗夫，希望能很快再次收到你的信，我以前可从未读到过如此甜蜜的来信。

永远最忠于您的亨丽埃塔·霍尔顿敬上

但愿他会喜欢我的回信，我也只能写到这样了，不过跟他的信还是不能相提并论；事实上，我一贯听人说他很会写情书。你知道，我跟他第一次见面是在斯库达摩尔夫人的家里。后来我见到夫人的时候，她便问我对她的表弟默斯格罗夫印象如何。

“哎，不瞒您说，”我说道，“我觉得他是个非常英俊的年轻人。”

“你这么想，我很高兴，”她答道，“因为他已经疯狂地爱上了你。”

“天哪！斯库达摩尔夫人，”我说，“您怎么能说出如此荒唐的话来？”

“这话不仅不荒唐，而且是千真万确，”她答道，“我敢担保，他从见到你的那一刻起就爱上你了。”

“但愿如此，”我说，“一见钟情还是有些道理的，对于其他的种种爱情，我都不屑一顾。”

“好啦，恭喜你，这就把他给征服了，”斯库达摩尔夫人说道，“我相信他已经完全没有招架之力。我表弟是个很迷人的小伙子，见过许多世面，还很会写情书，我读过最好的情书都是他写的，所以你这也算是一场大胜了。”

听了这话，我非常高兴，对我的爱情俘虏更是极为满意。不过我觉得自己还是应该摆摆架子，于是我对她说：“斯库达摩尔夫人，这当然好，不过您也知道，我们这些将要继承大笔遗产的年轻小姐可万万不能委身下嫁身无分文的男人。”

“亲爱的霍尔顿小姐，”她说，“关于这一点，我和你一样确信无疑。而且，我向你保证，不管是谁，要是他没有指望发财，我是断然不会怂恿你嫁给他的。默斯格罗夫先生远远谈不上身无分文，他继承了一笔遗产，每年大约有几百镑的收入，将来可能还会大大增加，他还有一处极好的房产，只是眼下仍需要修葺一番才是了。”

“如果是这样的话，”我答道，“那我就说不出什么来反对他了。要是如您所言，他是个见多识广的年轻人，又写得一手好情书，我相信我没有道理因为他倾慕于我而对他挑三拣四。不过，斯库达摩尔夫人，我恐怕不会因此就嫁给他。”

“你当然不是非得嫁给他不可，”夫人说道，“不过你会心甘情愿听凭爱情的摆布。要是我猜得差不离的话，此刻你已经对他情根深种，只是还不自知罢了。”

“啊呀，斯库达摩尔夫人，”我红着脸答道，“您怎么会想到那儿去呢？”

“因为你的眼神、言谈无一不在泄露你的心事，”夫人说道，“得啦，亲爱的亨丽埃塔，把我当作朋友，跟我实话实说吧，在所有认识的男子当中，你是不是最喜欢默斯格罗夫先生？”

“斯库达摩尔夫人，请不要问我此类问题，”我背过脸说道，“我是不好回答的。”

“才不是呢，我的宝贝，”她答道，“现在你已经证实了我的猜测。可是，亨丽埃塔，你既然是爱得其所，却又为何羞于承认，为何不肯向我吐露实情？”

“我并没有羞于承认，”我鼓起勇气说道，“也并非不肯向你吐露实情，厚着脸皮说一句，我确实爱着您的表弟默斯格罗夫先生，这是真心诚意的爱恋，爱上一个相貌英俊的男子并不丢脸。要是他平平无奇，我也许还有理由对这份感情感到羞耻，因为所爱之人不值得，所以这爱情本身也必定低贱。可是您的表弟有着这样的身材与面孔，还有那么漂亮的头发，如此出众的品质令我印象深刻，我为何要羞于承认呢？”

“我的好姑娘（斯库达摩尔夫人说着就热情洋溢地来拥抱我），在这些事情上头，你的看法可真是周到细致，像你这个年纪的人倒很少有这般机敏的洞察力！哦！你这高尚的情怀令我肃然起敬！”

“夫人，果真如此吗？”我说道，“您真是太热心了。不过，斯库达摩尔夫人，请您告诉我，是您的表弟亲口对您说他爱慕我的吗？如果是这样，那我就会更喜爱他几分，要是连个红颜知己都没有，那他还算哪门子的情郎呢？”

“哦！我的宝贝，”她答道，“你们俩简直是天生的一对。你说的每一个字都让我更加深刻地确信，你们俩意气相投，你们的头脑仿佛受到一股无形的力量驱使，因为你们俩的想法和观点竟是分毫不差。不，就连你们头发的颜色都很相近。是的，亲爱的姑娘，正是可怜又绝望的默斯格罗夫本人对我透露了他的情事。我倒是没觉得吃惊，虽然不知道为什么会这样，但我有种预感，他一定会爱上你。”

“那么，他是如何对您说的？”

“那是在用完夜宵之后，我们围坐在炉火旁，聊着无关紧要的话题，其实基本上都是我一个人在说，他心事重重、一言不发，可就在我话说到一半的时候，他突然打断了我，用一种夸张至极的语气喊道——

‘是的，我恋爱了，现在我才明白我已拜倒在亨丽埃塔·霍尔顿的石榴裙下——’”

“哦！他这表白的方式，”我说道，“还真是甜蜜！竟然为我作了如此动听的两句诗！只可惜并不押韵！”

“看到你喜欢这两句诗，我也很欣慰，”她答道，“这里头肯定是值得好好品味一番的。‘那么你爱她吗，表弟？’我说道，‘我真替你感到惋惜，尽管你方方面面都无懈可击，有一笔可能大幅增加的可观财产，又有一栋破败失修的漂亮房子，可她是迷人的亨丽埃塔，有位上校向她求过婚，还有位准男爵曾为她举杯祝酒，谁能指望抱得美人归呢？’”

“我曾——”我喊道。

斯库达摩尔夫人却还在往下说。“‘啊，亲爱的表姐，’他答道，‘有这么多人爱慕着她，我也相当确信自己不大可能赢得她的芳心，不需要您再来泼冷水。不过，我想要为她赴死，成为她迷人魅力的牺牲品，相信无论是您还是美丽的亨丽埃塔本人，肯定都会成全我这美好的心愿。待我死后’他继续说道——”

“哦，斯库达摩尔夫人，”我擦着眼睛说，“这么一个漂亮的人儿竟然会说到死！”

“此情此景，的确感人至深。”斯库达摩尔夫人答道，“‘待我死后，’他说，‘请将我抬去放在她的脚边，也许她会收起不屑，在我那可怜的尸体上洒下一滴同情的泪水。’”

“亲爱的斯库达摩尔夫人，”我打断她道，“快别说这个叫人伤心的话题了，我受不了。”

“哦！我可真喜欢你这温柔可人的性子，无论如何我都不会让你太过伤心的，那我就不说了。”

“还请您接着说吧。”我说道。她便继续说了下去。

“‘到了那时，’他又说道，‘啊！表姐，想象一下吧，当我感觉到那宝贵的泪水一滴滴落在我脸上，我该会是何等激动！为了一尝这般狂喜的滋味，谁会不愿赴死呢！等我下葬之后，但愿某个比我幸运的年轻人能得到亨丽埃塔女神的青睐，但愿他亦如不幸的默斯格罗夫一般对她一往情深，待我化为尘土之时，但愿他俩成为幸福夫妻的楷模！’”

“你可曾听过如此感伤的话语？等他死后叫人将他抬到我的脚边，多么可爱的心愿啊！哦！能怀有这样一个心愿，他的思想必然崇高无比！”

斯库达摩尔夫人接着说道：“‘啊！亲爱的表弟，’我对他说，‘任何女人见到你这高尚的行为，无论她生来是怎样的铁石心肠，也一定会被你融化的；要是亨丽埃塔女神听到你这一番对她幸福的慷慨祝愿，似她那般心软的人，我想她定会怜惜你的情意，努力回报于你。’‘哦，表姐，’他答道，‘请不要试图用这种安慰人的好听话来给我希望。不，我不敢奢望能讨得这天使般女子的欢心，除了一死，我已别无他法。’‘真爱总是叫人意志消沉的，’我答道，‘可是，亲爱的汤姆，我还要给你更大的希望，你是有望征服佳人芳心的。你且放心，我密切关注了她整整一天，我看得明明白白，她心中已然对你情根深种，只是她还不自知罢了。’”

“亲爱的斯库达摩尔夫人，”我喊道，“这事就连我都不知道呢！”

“我适才不是说了吗？你对此尚不自知。我继续对他说道：‘我可没有一开始就把这事说出来给你鼓劲儿，意外之喜才更让人高兴。’‘不，表姐’，他说道，声音无精打采的，‘你说什么我都不会相信自己能够令亨丽埃塔·霍尔顿心动，要是你在欺骗自己，就请你不要试图来欺骗我。’总而言之，亲爱的，我劝了这灰心丧气的可怜年轻人好几个小时，说你真的喜欢他；到了最后，他终于不再否认我那强有力的论据，相信了我的话，那一刻他激动不已、欣喜若狂，我简直没法儿形容。”

“哦！亲爱的人儿，”我大声地说，“他爱我爱得多么深情！可是，亲爱的斯库达摩尔夫人，你有没有对他说，我是完全依赖叔父和婶娘过活的？”

“当然，我什么都对他说了。”

“那他怎么说？”

“他大喊大叫，把所有的叔伯姑婶都刻毒抨击了一通；又指责英格兰的法律有问题，明明侄儿侄女缺钱，法律却容许当长辈的将财产抓住不放，还说他要是下议院的议员，就要改革立法机关，消除其一切弊病。”

“哦！这个大好人！他多么有志气啊！”我说。

“他还说，就算他的房子已经一切就绪待你入住，他也不敢自作多情，以为美丽的亨丽埃塔会为他自降身份，放弃已经习以为常的奢华与尊荣，却只换得他那有限的收入所能负担的舒适雅致。我对他说，她是不可能这么做的，如今她有权有势且行事高贵，用手中的权力对同胞中的贫穷民众广施善行，要是你认为她能够仅仅为了成全你和她自己而放弃权势，这对她可不公平。”

“那是当然，”我说，“我确实时不时地会做点善事。默斯格罗夫先生听了这话怎么说？”

“他回答说，他虽然忧伤，却不得不承认我所说的就是事实，所以如果他有这个福分，注定要和美丽的亨丽埃塔结为夫妻，那么不论他有多么迫不及待，他都得下定决心等下去，等待那幸运的日子来临，等到她脱离那些坏亲戚的辖制，等到她能够嫁与他为妻的那一天。”

他是多么高尚的人啊！哦！玛蒂尔达！我是何其幸运，竟然将要成为他的妻子！我的婶婶在喊我过去做馅饼了。再见，我亲爱的朋友。

H.霍尔顿敬上

[17]本篇亦出自A Collection of Letters（《书信集》），是第五封。

一位年轻女子的来信[18]
（她的感情过于强烈，判断力却不足，因而犯下许多违心之过）

亲爱的埃莉诺，我曾有过许多烦恼，也曾历经浮浮沉沉，虽然吃了苦头，但唯一令我觉得安慰的就是，在仔细审视自己的所作所为之后，我相信这些完全是我咎由自取。我很小的时候便谋害了自己的父亲，其后又害死了母亲，现在我打算要去谋杀自己的姐姐了。我的宗教信仰经常变来变去，如今我也不知道自己还相信什么。过去这十二年来，我在每一场公开审判中都做了伪证，还伪造了我自己的遗嘱。总而言之，几乎没有哪一种罪行是我不曾犯过的，不过现在我要改过自新了。皇家骑兵卫队的马丁上校向我求婚了，我们不日即将完婚。我俩的恋爱颇不寻常，我来给你讲一讲。马丁上校是已故约翰·马丁爵士的次子。爵爷过世的时候富可敌国，却将大部分财产——大约八百万镑——都留给了现任的托马斯爵士，只给三位幼子留下每人十万镑遗产。凭着他这一点点微薄的收入，上校过了近四个月还算惬意的生活，然后他突然心血来潮，决意将长兄的财产全都夺来。他伪造了一份新遗嘱在法庭上出示，可是除了他自己，再没有别人愿意宣誓，保证这才是真遗嘱，然而他发了太多誓，没人相信他。当时我刚好从法庭门口经过，法官便召我进去，他对上校说我是一位淑女，愿意为了正义的目标见证一切，所以建议他来请求我。简而言之，这桩事件很快便妥善解决。上校和我宣誓说这份遗嘱属实，托马斯爵士只得交出他非法获得的财富。满怀感激的上校隔天便来拜访我，向我求了婚。现在我要去谋杀我姐姐了。

安娜·帕克敬上

[18]出自Scraps（《涂鸦集》），该集子包含五篇小短文，本文是第三篇。

少女奥斯汀——《漂亮的卡桑德拉》译后记

《漂亮的卡桑德拉》这本小集子收录了简·奥斯汀少女时代的六篇作品，其中前三篇勉强可算完整的短篇小说，后三篇就只能算作练笔片段了。这些作品全都创作于1787年至1793年之间，彼时奥斯汀才不过是个尚未成年的小姑娘，大约相当于如今的中学生。记得曾经看过一部传记电影——《成为简·奥斯汀》，如果说这部电影试着还原了奥斯汀的感情生活，那么这个小小的选集则让读者可以一窥她在创作方面的成长历程。

说实话，翻译时我是吃了一惊的，尤其是前三篇的荒谬与幼稚，其中有些地方甚至不合逻辑到令人难以置信的地步。比如在《杰克与爱丽丝》一文中，作者描写约翰逊家的起居室有“半英里宽、3/4英里长”，这相当于八百多米宽、一千两百多米长，即便是用了夸张的修辞手法，恐也有过度之嫌。再比如在《亨利与伊丽莎》一文中，奥斯汀大笔一挥，让公爵夫人派了三百人带着武器去追捕私奔的亨利与伊丽莎。还有《漂亮的卡桑德拉》，虽然由十二章构成，然而每章只有短短一句话，就连正文之前的献词都比任何一个章节要长。看到这三篇小说里漏洞百出的情节，再想想这些乃是出自一个十二三岁的小女孩之手，我不由得暗笑自己太过较真。她写作一是因为自己热爱，二是为了娱乐家人，不过是些练笔之作，有多少人在这个年纪还在努力消除语法错误呢，她却已经刻画出了个性鲜明的众多人物。

后三篇的书信体片段写作时间略晚一些，笔触也稍显成熟。其中《一位处境困难的年轻女子写给友人的信》是全书我最爱的篇章，格雷维尔夫人身上可不就能看见《傲慢与偏见》中凯瑟琳·德波夫人的影子？她势利专横，自以为是，允许玛丽亚小姐在马车上面朝前方坐着便觉得这是赐予她的莫大恩惠；她认为穷人就不该穿新衣，晚上也不应该吃夜宵，而应当为了节省蜡烛早早睡下；她明知人家家里正是用餐时间，却特地赶在此时到访，可是又不肯下车，叫玛丽亚冒着刺骨寒风听她在马车里絮絮叨叨，还说出了这样的话：“我是不会让我的女儿们在这种天气像你这样站在外头的。可是有一种人，要么就是感觉不到冷，要么就是不知道体贴别人。”鲜活生动的人物形象跃然纸上，对话中的讽刺意味读来令人忍俊不禁，稍加改动便能拍出一集精彩的好剧。

“世界上这一半人的乐趣，那一半的人不会懂。”（One half of the world cannot understand the pleasures of the other.）年届四旬的简·奥斯汀在《爱玛》一书中借由双十年华的女主角之口说出了这句至理名言。不经历少女时代的那些稚嫩可笑，何来成熟之后的睿智洞明？从译近十载，这是我译得最开心的一本书。得遇才华横溢的少女奥斯汀，并穿越时空与她同行一段，我何其幸运。

夏星

2018年8月

Jack and Alice

a novel

Is respectfully inscribed to Francis William Austen Esqr Mid-shipman on board his Majesty’s Ship the Perseverance

by his obedient humble

Servant The Author

CHAPTER THE FIRST

Mr Johnson was once upon a time about 53; in a twelve-month afterwards he was 54, which so much delighted him that he was determined to celebrate his next Birth day by giving a Masquerade to his Children and Freinds. Accordingly on the Day he attained his 55th year tickets were dispatched to all his Neighbours to that purpose. His acquaintance indeed in that part of the World were not very numerous as they consisted only of Lady Williams, Mr and Mrs Jones, Charles Adams and the 3 Miss Simpsons, who composed the neighbourhood of Pammydiddle and formed the Masquerade.

Before I proceed to give an account of the Evening, it will be proper to describe to my reader, the persons and Characters of the party introduced to his acquaintance.

Mr and Mrs Jones were both rather tall and very pas-sionate, but were in other respects, good tempered, wellbehaved People. Charles Adams was an amiable, accomplished and bewitching young Man; of so dazzling a Beauty that none but Eagles could look him in the Face.

Miss Simpson was pleasing in her person, in her Man-ners and in her Disposition; an unbounded ambition was her only fault. Her second sister Sukey was Envious, Spitefull and Malicious. Her person was short, fat and disagreable. Cecilia（the youngest）was perfectly hand-some but too affected to be pleasing.

In Lady Williams every virtue met. She was a widow with a handsome Jointure and the remains of a very hand-some face. Tho’Benevolent and Candid, she was Generous and sincere; Tho’Pious and Good, she was Religious and amiable, and Tho’Elegant and Agreable, she was Pol-ished and Entertaining.

The Johnsons were a family of Love, and though a little addicted to the Bottle and the Dice, had many good Qualities.

Such was the party assembled in the elegant Drawing Room of Johnson Court, amongst which the pleasing figure of a Sultana was the most remarkable of the female Masks. Of the Males a Mask representing the Sun, was the most universally admired. The Beams that darted from his Eyes were like those of that glorious Luminary tho’infinitely superior. So strong were they that no one dared venture within half a mile of them; he had therefore the best part of the Room to himself, its size not amount-ing to more than 3 quarters of a mile in length and half a one in breadth. The Gentleman at last finding the feirce-ness of his beams to be very inconvenient to the concourse by obliging them to croud together in one corner of the room, half shut his eyes by which means, the Company discovered him to be Charles Adams in his plain green Coat, without any mask at all.

When their astonishment was a little subsided their attention was attracted by 2 Dominos who advanced in a horrible Passion; they were both very tall, but seemed in other respects to have many good qualities. ‘These,’ said the witty Charles, ‘these are Mr and Mrs Jones,’ and so indeed they were.

No one could imagine who was the Sultana! Till at length on her addressing a beautifull Flora who was reclining in a studied attitude on a couch, with ‘Oh Cecilia, I wish I was really what I pretend to be’, she was discovered by the never failing genius of Charles Adams, to be the elegant but ambitious Caroline Simpson, and the person to whom she addressed herself, he rightly imagined to be her lovely but affected sister Cecilia.

The Company now advanced to a Gaming Table where sat 3 Dominos （each with a bottle in their hand） deeply engaged; but a female in the character of Virtue fled with hasty footsteps from the shocking scene, whilst a little fat woman representing Envy, sate alternately on the fore-heads of the 3 Gamesters. Charles Adams was still as bright as ever; he soon discovered the party at play to be the 3 Johnsons, Envy to be Sukey Simpson and Virtue to be Lady Williams.

The Masks were then all removed and the Company retired to another room, to partake of an elegant and well managed Entertainment, after which the Bottle being pretty briskly pushed about by the 3 Johnsons, the whole party not excepting even Virtue were carried home, Dead Drunk.

CHAPTER THE SECOND

For three months did the Masquerade afford ample sub-ject for conversation to the inhabitants of Pammydiddle; but no character at it was so fully expatiated on as Charles Adams. The singularity of his appearance, the beams which darted from his eyes, the brightness of his Wit, and the whole tout ensemble of his person had subdued the hearts of so many of the young Ladies, that of the six present at the Masquerade but five had returned uncap-tivated. Alice Johnson was the unhappy sixth whose heart had not been able to withstand the power of his Charms. But as it may appear strange to my Readers, that so much worth and Excellence as he possessed should have conquered only hers, it will be necessary to inform them that the Miss Simpsons were defended from his Power by Ambition, Envy, and Selfadmiration.

Every wish of Caroline was centered in a titled Hus-band; whilst in Sukey such superior excellence could only raise her Envy not her Love, and Cecilia was too tenderly attached to herself to be pleased with any one besides. As for Lady Williams and Mrs Jones, the former of them was too sensible, to fall in love with one so much her Junior and the latter, tho’very tall and very passionate was too fond of her Husband to think of such a thing.

Yet in spite of every endeavour on the part of Miss Johnson to discover any attachment to her in him; the cold and indifferent heart of Charles Adams still to all appearance, preserved its native freedom; polite to all but partial to none, he still remained the lovely, the lively, but insensible Charles Adams.

One evening, Alice finding herself somewhat heated by wine （no very uncommon case） determined to seek a releif for her disordered Head and Love-sick Heart in the Con-versation of the intelligent Lady Williams.

She found her Ladyship at home as was in general the Case, for she was not fond of going out, and like the great Sir Charles Grandison scorned to deny herself when at Home, as she looked on that fashionable method of shut-ting out disagreable Visitors, as little less than downright Bigamy.

In spite of the wine she had been drinking, poor Alice was uncommonly out of spirits; she could think of noth-ing but Charles Adams, she could talk of nothing but him, and in short spoke so openly that Lady Williams soon discovered the unreturned affection she bore him, which excited her Pity and Compassion so strongly that she addressed her in the following Manner.

‘I perceive but too plainly my dear Miss Johnson, that your Heart has not been able to withstand the fascinating Charms of this Young Man and I pity you sincerely. Is it a first Love?’

‘It is.’

‘I am still more greived to hear that; I am myself a sad example of the Miseries, in general attendant on a first Love and I am determined for the future to avoid the like Misfortune. I wish it may not be too late for you to do the same; if it is not endeavour my dear Girl to secure yourself from so great a Danger. A second attachment is seldom attended with any serious consequences; against that therefore I have nothing to say. Preserve yourself from a first Love and you need not fear a second.’

‘You mentioned Madam something of your having yourself been a sufferer by the misfortune you are so good as to wish me to avoid. Will you favour me with your Life and Adventures?’

‘Willingly my Love.’

CHAPTER THE THIRD

‘My Father was a gentleman of considerable Fortune in Berkshire; myself and a few more his only Children. I was but six years old when I had the misfortune of losing my Mother and being at that time young and Tender, my father instead of sending me to School, procured an able handed Governess to superintend my Education at Home. My Brothers were placed at Schools suitable to their Ages and my Sisters being all younger than myself, remained still under the Care of their Nurse.

‘Miss Dickins was an excellent Governess. She instructed me in the Paths of Virtue; under her tuition I daily became more amiable, and might perhaps by this time have nearly attained perfection, had not my worthy Preceptoress been torn from my arms, e’er I had attained my seventeenth year. I never shall forget her last words. “My dear Kitty” she said. “Good night t’ye.” I never saw her afterwards,’ continued Lady Williams wiping her eyes, ‘She eloped with the Butler the same night.

‘I was invited the following year by a distant relation of my Father’s to spend the Winter with her in town. Mrs Watkins was a Lady of Fashion, Family and fortune; she was in general esteemed a pretty Woman, but I never thought her very handsome, for my part. She had too high a forehead, Her eyes were too small and she had too much colour.’

‘How can that be?’ interrupted Miss Johnson redden-ing with anger; ‘Do you think that any one can have too much colour?’

‘Indeed I do, and I’ll tell you why I do my dear Alice; when a person has too great a degree of red in their Com-plexion, it gives their face in my opinion, too red a look.’

‘But can a face my Lady have too red a look?’

‘Certainly my dear Miss Johnson and I’ll [tell] you why. When a face has too red a look it does not appear to so much advantage as it would were it paler.’

‘Pray Ma’am proceed in your story.’

‘Well, as I said before, I was invited by this Lady to spend some weeks with her in town. Many Gentlemen thought her Handsome but in my opinion, Her forehead was too high, her eyes too small and she had too much colour.’

‘In that Madam as I said before your Ladyship must have been mistaken. Mrs Watkins could not have too much colour since no one can have too much.’

‘Excuse me my Love if I do not agree with you in that particular. Let me explain myself clearly; my idea of the case is this. When a Woman has too great a proportion of red in her Cheeks, she must have too much colour.’

‘But Madam I deny that it is possible for any one to have too great a proportion of red in their Cheeks.’

‘What my Love not if they have too much colour?’

Miss Johnson was now out of all patience, the more so perhaps as Lady Williams still remained so inflexibly cool. It must be remembered however that her Ladyship had in one respect by far the advantage of Alice; I mean in not being drunk, for heated with wine and raised by Pas-sion, she could have little command of her Temper.

The Dispute at length grew so hot on the part of Alice that ‘From Words she almost came to Blows’ When Mr Johnson luckily entered and with some difficulty forced her away from Lady Williams, Mrs Watkins and her red cheeks.

CHAPTER THE FOURTH

My Readers may perhaps imagine that after such a fracas, no intimacy could longer subsist between the Johnsons and Lady Williams, but in that they are mistaken for her Ladyship was too sensible to be angry at a conduct which she could not help perceiving to be the natural conse-quence of inebriety and Alice had too sincere a respect for Lady Williams and too great a relish for her Claret, not to make every concession in her power.

A few days after their reconciliation Lady Williams called on Miss Johnson to propose a walk in a Citron Grove which led from her Ladyship’s pigstye to Charles Adams’s Horsepond. Alice was too sensible of Lady Wil-liams’s kindness in proposing such a walk and too much pleased with the prospect of seeing at the end of it, a Horsepond of Charles’s, not to accept it with visible delight. They had not proceeded far before she was roused from the reflection of the happiness she was going to enjoy, by Lady Williams’s thus addressing her.

‘I have as yet forborn my dear Alice to continue the narrative of my Life from an unwillingness of recalling to your Memory a scene which （since it reflects on you rather disgrace than credit） had better be forgot than remembered.’

Alice had already begun to colour up and was begin-ning to speak, when her Ladyship perceiving her displeasure, continued thus.

‘I am afraid my dear Girl that I have offended you by what I have just said; I assure you I do not mean to dis-tress you by a retrospection of what cannot now be helped; considering all things I do not think you so much to blame as many People do; for when a person is in Liquor, there is no answering for what they may do.’

‘Madam, this is not to be borne; I insist—’

‘My dear Girl don’t vex yourself about the matter; I assure you I have entirely forgiven every thing respecting it; indeed I was not angry at the time, because as I saw all along, you were nearly dead drunk. I knew you could not help saying the strange things you did. But I see I distress you; so I will change the subject and desire it may never again be mentioned; remember it is all forgot-I will now pursue my story; but I must insist upon not giving you any description of Mrs Watkins; it would only be reviving old stories and as you never saw her, it can be nothing to you, if her forehead was too high, her eyes were too small, or if she had too much colour.’

‘Again! Lady Williams：this is too much—’

So provoked was poor Alice at this renewal of the old story, that I know not what might have been the conse-quence of it, had not their attention been engaged by another object. A lovely young Woman lying apparently in great pain beneath a Citron-tree, was an object too interesting not to attract their notice. Forgetting their own dispute they both with simpathizing Tenderness advanced towards her and accosted her in these terms.

‘You seem fair Nymph to be labouring under some misfortune which we shall be happy to releive if you will inform us what it is. Will you favour us with your Life and adventures?’

‘Willingly Ladies, if you will be so kind as to be seated.’ They took their places and she thus began.

CHAPTER THE FIFTH

‘I am a native of North Wales and my Father is one of the most capital Taylors in it. Having a numerous family, he was easily prevailed on by a sister of my Mother’s who is a widow in good circumstances and keeps an alehouse in the next Village to ours, to let her take me and breed me up at her own expence. Accordingly I have lived with her for the last 8 years of my Life, during which time she provided me with some of the first rate Masters, who taught me all the accomplishments requisite for one of my sex and rank. Under their instructions I learned Dan-cing, Music, Drawing and various Languages, by which means I became more accomplished than any other Tay-lor’s Daughter in Wales. Never was there a happier Creature than I was, till within the last half year-but I should have told you before that the principal Estate in our Neighbourhood belongs to Charles Adams, the owner of the brick House, you see yonder.’

‘Charles Adams!’ exclaimed the astonished Alice; ‘are you acquainted with Charles Adams?’

‘To my sorrow madam I am. He came about half a year ago to receive the rents of the Estate I have just men-tioned. At that time I first saw him; as you seem ma’am acquainted with him, I need not describe to you how charming he is. I could not resist his attractions;—’

‘Ah! who can,’ said Alice with a deep sigh.

‘My Aunt being in terms of the greatest intimacy with his cook, determined, at my request, to try whether she could discover, by means of her freind if there were any chance of his returning my affection. For this purpose she went one evening to drink tea with Mrs Susan, who in the course of Conversation mentioned the goodness of her Place and the Goodness of her Master; upon which my Aunt began pumping her with so much dexterity that in a short time Susan owned, that she did not think her Master would ever marry, “for （said she） he has often and often declared to me that his wife, whoever she might be, must possess, Youth, Beauty, Birth, Wit, Merit, and Money. I have many a time （she continued） endeavoured to reason him out of his resolution and to convince him of the improbability of his ever meeting with such a Lady; but my arguments have had no effect and he continues as firm in his determination as ever.” You may imagine Ladies my distress on hearing this; for I was fearfull that tho’possessed of Youth, Beauty, Wit and Merit, and tho’the probable Heiress of my Aunts House and business, he might think me deficient in Rank, and in being so, unworthy of his hand.

‘However I was determined to make a bold push and therefore wrote him a very kind letter, offering him with great tenderness my hand and heart. To this I received an angry and peremptory refusal, but thinking it might be rather the effect of his modesty than any thing else, I pressed him again on the subject. But he never answered any more of my Letters and very soon afterwards left the Country. As soon as I heard of his departure I wrote to him here, informing him that I should shortly do myself the honour of waiting on him at Pammydiddle, to which I received no answer; therefore choosing to take, Silence for Consent, I left Wales, unknown to my Aunt, and arrived here after a tedious Journey this Morning. On enquiring for his House I was directed thro’this Wood, to the one you there see. With a heart elated by the expected happiness of beholding him I entered it and had proceeded thus far in my progress thro’it, when I found myself suddenly seized by the leg and on examin-ing the cause of it, found that I was caught in one of the steel traps so common in gentlemen’s grounds.’

‘Ah,’ cried Lady Williams, ‘how fortunate we are to meet with you; since we might otherwise perhaps have shared the like misfortune—’

‘It is indeed happy for you Ladies, that I should have been a short time before you. I screamed as you may easily imagine till the woods resounded again and till one of the inhuman Wretch’s servants came to my assistance and released me from my dreadfull prison, but not before one of my legs was entirely broken.’

CHAPTER THE SIxTH

At this melancholy recital the fair eyes of Lady Williams, were suffused in tears and Alice could not help exclaiming,

‘Oh! cruel Charles to wound the hearts and legs of all the fair.’

Lady Williams now interposed and observed that the young Lady’s leg ought to be set without farther delay. After examining the fracture therefore, she immediately began and performed the operation with great skill which was the more wonderfull on account of her having never performed such a one before. Lucy, then arose from the ground and finding that she could walk with the greatest ease, accompanied them to Lady Williams’s House at her Ladyship’s particular request.

The perfect form, the beautifull face, and elegant man-ners of Lucy so won on the affections of Alice that when they parted, which was not till after Supper, she assured her that except her Father, Brother, Uncles, Aunts, Cousins and other relations, Lady Williams, Charles Adams and a few dozen more of particular freinds, she loved her better than almost any other person in the world.

Such aflattering assurance of her regard would justly have given much pleasure to the object of it, had she not plainly perceived that the amiable Alice had partaken too freely of Lady Williams’s claret.

Her Ladyship （whose discernment was great） read in the intelligent countenance of Lucy her thoughts on the subject and as soon as Miss Johnson had taken her leave, thus addressed her.

‘When you are more intimately acquainted with my Alice you will not be surprised, Lucy, to see the dear Creature drink a little too much; for such things happen every day. She has many rare and charming qualities, but Sobriety is not one of them. The whole Family are indeed a sad drunken set. I am sorry to say too that I never knew three such thorough Gamesters as they are, more particu-larly Alice. But she is a charming girl. I fancy not one of the sweetest tempers in the world; to be sure I have seen her in such passions! However she is a sweet young Woman. I am sure you’ll like her. I scarcely know any one so amiable. - Oh! that you could but have seen her the other Evening! How she raved! and on such a trifle too! She is indeed a most pleasing Girl! I shall always love her!’

‘She appears by your ladyship’s account to have many good qualities’, replied Lucy. ‘Oh! a thousand,’ answered Lady Williams; ‘tho’I am very partial to her, and perhaps am blinded by my affection, to her real defects.’

CHAPTER THE SEvENTH

The next morning brought the three Miss Simpsons to wait on Lady Williams, who received them with the utmost politeness and introduced to their acquaintance Lucy, with whom the eldest was so much pleased that at parting she declared her sole ambition was to have her accompany them the next morning to Bath, whither they were going for some weeks.

‘Lucy,’ said Lady Williams, ‘is quite at her own disposal and if she chooses to accept so kind an invitation, I hope she will not hesitate, from any motives of delicacy on my account. I know not indeed how I shall ever be able to part with her. She never was at Bath and I should think that it would be a most agreable Jaunt to her. Speak my Love,’ continued she, turning to Lucy, ‘what say you to accompanying these Ladies? I shall be miserable without you - t’will be a most pleasant tour to you - I hope you’ll go; if you do I am sure t’will be the Death of me-pray be persuaded’—

Lucy begged leave to decline the honour of accompany-ing them, with many expressions of gratitude for the extream politeness of Miss Simpson in inviting her.

Miss Simpson appeared much disappointed by her refusal. Lady Williams insisted on her going - declared that she would never forgive her if she did not, and that she should never survive it if she did, and inshort used such persuasive arguments that it was at length resolved she was to go. The Miss Simpsons called for her at ten o’clock the next morning and Lady Williams had soon the satisfaction of receiving from her young freind, the pleasing intelligence of their safe arrival in Bath.

It may now be proper to return to the Hero of this Novel, the brother of Alice, of whom I beleive I have scarcely ever had occasion to speak; which may perhaps be partly oweing to his unfortunate propensity to Liquor, which so compleatly deprived him of the use of those faculties Nature had endowed him with, that he never did anything worth mentioning. His Death happened a short time after Lucy’s departure and was the natural Conse-quence of this pernicious practice. By his decease, his sister became the sole inheritress of a very large fortune, which as it gave her fresh Hopes of rendering herself acceptable as a wife to Charles Adams could not fail of being most pleasing to her - and as the effect was Joyfull the Cause could scarcely be lamented.

Finding the violence of her attachment to him daily augment, she at length disclosed it to her Father and desired him to propose a union between them to Charles. Her father consented and set out one morning to open the affair to the young Man. Mr Johnson being a man of few words his part was soon performed and the answer he received was as follows—

‘Sir, I may perhaps be expected to appear pleased at and gratefull for the offer you have made me：but let me tell you that I consider it as an affront. I look upon myself to be Sir a perfect Beauty - where would you see afiner figure or a more charming face. Then, sir I imagine my Manners and Address to be of the most polished kind; there is a certain elegance a peculiar sweetness in them that I never saw equalled and cannot describe—. Partiality aside, I am certainly more accomplished in every Lan-guage, every Science, every Art and every thing than any other person in Europe. My temper is even, my virtues innumerable, my self unparalelled. Since such Sir is my character, what do you mean by wishing me to marry your Daughter? Let me give you a short sketch of yourself and of her. I look upon you Sir to be a very good sort of Man in the main; a drunken old Dog to be sure, but that’s nothing to me. Your daughter sir, is neither sufficiently beautifull, sufficiently amiable, sufficiently witty, nor suf-ficiently rich for me—. I expect nothing more in my wife than my wife will find in me - Perfection. These sir, are my sentiments and I honour myself for having such. One freind I have and glory in having but one—. She is at present preparing my Dinner, but if you choose to see her, she shall come and she will inform you that these have ever been my sentiments.’

Mr Johnson was satis fied; and expressing himself to be much obliged to Mr Adams for the characters he had favoured him with of himself and his Daughter, took his leave.

The unfortunate Alice on receiving from her father the sad account of the ill success his visit had been attended with, could scarcely support the disappointment - Sheflew to her Bottle and it was soon forgot.

CHAPTER THE EIGHTH

While these affairs were transacting at Pammydiddle, Lucy was conquering every Heart at Bath. A fortnight’s residence there had nearly effaced from her remembrance the captivating form of Charles - The recollection of what her Heart had formerly suffered by his charms and her Leg by his trap, enabled her to forget him with tolerable Ease, which was what she determined to do; and for that purpose dedicated five minutes in every day to the employment of driving him from her remembrance.

Her second Letter to Lady Williams contained the pleasing intelligence of her having accomplished her undertaking to her entire satisfaction; she mentioned in it also an offer of marriage she had received from the Duke of——an elderly Man of noble fortune whose ill health was the chief inducement of his Journey to Bath.‘I am distressed （she continued） to know whether I mean to accept him or not. There are a thousand advantages to be derived from a marriage with the Duke, for besides those more inferior ones of Rank and Fortune it will pro-cure me a home, which of all other things is what I most desire. Your Ladyship’s kind wish of my always remaining with you, is noble and generous but I cannot think of becoming so great a burden on one I so much love and esteem. That One should receive obligations only from those we despise, is a sentiment instilled into my mind by my worthy Aunt, in my early years, and cannot in my opinion be too strictly adhered to. The excellent woman of whom I now speak, is I hear too much incensed by my imprudent departure from Wales, to receive me again—. I most earnestly wish to leave the Ladies I am now with. Miss Simpson is indeed （setting aside ambition） very ami-able, but her 2d Sister the envious and malvolent Sukey is too disagreable to live with. - I have reason to think that the admiration I have met with in the circles of the great at this Place, has raised her Hatred and Envy; for often has she threatened, and sometimes endeavoured to cut my throat. - Your Ladyship will therefore allow that I am not wrong in wishing to leave Bath, and in wishing to have a home to receive me, when I do. I shall expect with impatience your advice concerning the Duke and am your most obliged

etc etc - Lucy.’

Lady Williams sent her, her opinion on the subject in the following Manner.

‘Why do you hesitate my dearest Lucy, a moment with respect to the Duke? I have enquired into his Character and find him to be an unprincipaled, illiterate Man. Never shall my Lucy be united to such a one! He has a princely fortune, which is every day encreasing. How nobly will you spend it!, what credit will you give him in the eyes of all! How much will he be respected on his Wife’s account! But why my dearest Lucy, why will you not at once decide this affair by returning to me and never leav-ing me again? Altho’I admire your noble sentiments with respect to obligations, yet, let me beg that they may not prevent your making me happy. It will to be sure be a great expence to me, to have you always with me - I shall not be able to support it - but what is that in comparison with the happiness I shall enjoy in your society?—’twill ruin me I know-you will not therefore surely, withstand these arguments, or refuse to return to yours most affectionately-etc etc.

C. Williams’

CHAPTER THE NINTH

What might have been the effect of her Ladyship’s advice, had it ever been received by Lucy, is uncertain, as it reached Bath a few Hours after she had breathed her last. She fell a sacrifice to the Envy and Malice of Sukey who jealous of her superior charms took her by poison from an admiring World at the age of seventeen.

Thus fell the amiable and lovely Lucy whose Life had been marked by no crime, and stained by no blemish but her imprudent departure from her Aunts, and whose death was sincerely lamented by every one who knew her. Among the most afflicted of her freinds were Lady Wil-liams, Miss Johnson and the Duke; the 2 last of whom had a most sincere regard for her, more particularly Alice, who had spent a whole evening in her company and had never thought of her since. His Grace’s affliction may likewise be easily accounted for, since he lost one for whom he had experienced during the last ten days, a tender affection and sincere regard. He mourned her loss with unshaken constancy for the next fortnight at the end of which time, he grati fied the ambition of Caroline Simp-son by raising her to the rank of a Dutchess. Thus was she at length rendered compleatly happy in the gratifica-tion of her favourite passion. Her sister the perfidious Sukey, was likewise shortly after exalted in a manner she truly deserved, and by her actions appeared to have always desired. Her barbarous Murder was discovered and in spite of every interceding freind she was speedily raised to the Gallows—. The beautifull but affected Cecilia was too sensible of her own superior charms, not to imagine that if Caroline could engage a Duke, she might without censure aspire to the affections of some Prince - and knowing that those of her native Country were cheifly engaged, she left England and I have since heard is at present the favourite Sultana of the great Mogul—.

In the mean time the inhabitants of Pammydiddle were in a state of the greatest astonishment and Wonder, a report being circulated of the intended marriage of Charles Adams. The Lady’s name was still a secret. Mr and Mrs Jones imagined it to be, Miss Johnson; but she knew better; all her fears were centered in his Cook, when to the astonishment of every one, he was publicly united to Lady Williams—

Finis

Henry and Eliza

a novel

Is humbly dedicated to Miss Cooper by her obedient

Humble Servant

The Author

As Sir George and Lady Harcourt were superintending the Labours of their Haymakers, rewarding the industry of some by smiles of approbation, and punishing the idleness of others, by a cudgel, they perceived lying closely concealed beneath the thick foliage of a Haycock, a beautifull little Girl not more than 3 months old.

Touched with the enchanting Graces of her face and delighted with the infantine tho’sprightly answers she returned to their many questions, they resolved to take her home and, having no Children of their own, to edu-cate her with care and cost.

Being good People themselves, their first and principal care was to incite in her a Love of Virtue and a Hatred of Vice, in which they so well succeeded （Eliza having a natural turn that way herself） that when she grew up, she was the delight of all who knew her.

Beloved by Lady Harcourt, adored by Sir George and admired by all the World, she lived in a continued course of uninterrupted Happiness, till she had attained her eighteenth year, when happening one day to be detected in stealing a banknote of 50£, she was turned out of doors by her inhuman Benefactors. Such a transition to one who did not possess so noble and exalted a mind as Eliza, would have been Death, but she, happy in the conscious knowledge of her own Excellence, amused herself, as she sate beneath a tree with making and singing the following Lines.

SONG.

Though misfortunes my footsteps may ever attend

I hope I shall never have need of a Freind

as an innocent Heart I will ever preserve

and will never from Virtue’s dear boundaries swerve.

Having amused herself some hours, with this song and her own pleasing reflections, she arose and took the road to M.a small market town of which place her most intim-ate freind kept the red Lion.

To this freind she immediately went, to whom having recounted her late misfortune, she communicated her wish of getting into some family in the capacity of Hum-ble Companion.

Mrs Wilson, who was the most amiable creature on earth, was no sooner acquainted with her Desire, than she sate down in the Bar and wrote the following Letter to the Dutchess of F., the woman whom of all others, she most Esteemed.

‘TO THE DUTCHESS OF F.’

Receive into your Family, at my request a young woman of unexceptionable Character, who is so good as to choose your Society in preference to going to Service. Hasten, and take her from the arms of your

Sarah Wilson.

The Dutchess, whose freindship for Mrs Wilson would have carried her any lengths, was overjoyed at such an opportunity of obliging her and accordingly sate out immediately on the receipt of her letter for the red Lion, which she reached the same Evening. The Dutchess of F. was about 45 and a half; Her passions were strong, her freindships firm and her Enmities, unconquerable. She was a widow and had only one Daughter who was on the point of marriage with a young Man of considerable fortune.

The Dutchess no sooner beheld our Heroine than throwing her arms around her neck, she declared herself so much pleased with her, that she was resolved they never more should part. Eliza was delighted with such a pro-testation of freindship, and after taking a most affecting leave of her dear Mrs Wilson, accompanied her grace the next morning to her seat in Surry.

With every expression of regard did the Dutchess intro-duce her to Lady Harriet, who was so much pleased with her appearance that she besought her, to consider her as her Sister, which Eliza with the greatest Condescension promised to do.

Mr Cecil, the Lover of Lady Harriet, being often with the family was often with Eliza. A mutual Love took place and Cecil having declared his first, prevailed on Eliza to consent to a private union, which was easy to be effected, as the Dutchess’s chaplain being very much in love with Eliza himself, would they were certain do anything to oblige her.

The Dutchess and Lady Harriet being engaged one evening to an assembly, they took the opportunity of their absence and were united by the enamoured Chaplain.

When the Ladies returned, their amazement was great at finding instead of Eliza the following Note.

‘Madam

We are married and gone.

Henry and Eliza Cecil.’

Her Grace as soon as she had read the letter, which sufficiently explained the whole affair, flew into the most violent passion and after having spent an agreable half hour, in calling them by all the shocking Names her rage could suggest to her, sent out after them 300 armed Men, with orders not to return without their Bodies, dead or alive; intending that if they should be brought to her in the latter condition to have them put to Death in some torture-like manner, after a few years Confinement.

In the mean time Cecil and Eliza continued their flight to the Continent, which they judged to be more secure than their native Land, from the dreadfull effects of the Dutchess’s vengeance, which they had so much reason to apprehend.

In France they remained 3 years, during which time they became the parents of two Boys, and at the end of it Eliza became a widow without any thing to support either her or her Children. They had lived since their Marriage at the rate of 12，000£ a year, of which Mr Cecil’s estate being rather less than the twentieth part, they had been able to save but a trifle, having lived to the utmost extent of their Income.

Eliza, being perfectly conscious of the derangement in their affairs, immediately on her Husband’s death set sail for England, in a man of War of 55 Guns, which they had built in their more prosperous Days. But no sooner had she stepped on Shore at Dover, with a Child in each hand, than she was seized by the officers of the Dutchess, and conducted by them to a snug little Newgate of their Lady’s which she had erected for the reception of her own private Prisoners.

No sooner had Eliza entered her Dungeon than the first thought which occurred to her, was how to get out of it again.

She went to the Door; but it was locked. She looked at the Window; but it was barred with iron; disappointed in both her expectations, she dispaired of effecting her Escape, when she fortunately perceived in a Corner of her Cell, a small saw and Ladder of ropes. With the saw she instantly went to work and in a few weeks had dis-placed every Bar but one to which she fastened the Ladder.

A difficulty then occurred which for some time, she knew not how to obviate. Her Children were too small to get down the Ladder by themselves, nor would it be possible for her to take them in her arms, when she did. At last she determined to fling down all her Cloathes, of which she had a large Quantity, and then having given them strict Charge not to hurt themselves, threw her Chil-dren after them. She herself with ease discended by the Ladder, at the bottom of which she had the pleasure of finding Her little boys in perfect Health and fast asleep.

Her wardrobe she now saw a fatal necessity of selling, both for the preservation of her Children and herself. With tears in her eyes, she parted with these last reliques of her former Glory, and with the money she got for them, bought others more usefull, some playthings for her Boys and a gold Watch for herself.

But scarcely was she provided with the above-mentioned necessaries, than she began to find herself rather hungry, and had reason to think, by their biting off two of her fin-gers, that her Children were much in the same situation.

To remedy these unavoidable misfortunes, she deter-mined to return to her old freinds, Sir George and Lady Harcourt, whose generosity she had so often experienced and hoped to experience as often again.

She had about 40 miles to travel before she could reach their hospitable Mansion, of which having walked 30 without stopping, she found herself at the Entrance of a Town, where often in happier times, she had accom-panied Sir George and Lady Harcourt to regale themselves with a cold collation at one of the Inns.

The reflections that her adventures since the last time she had partaken of these happy Junketings, afforded her, occupied her mind, for some time, as she sate on the steps at the door of a Gentleman’s house. As soon as these reflections were ended, she arose and determined to take her station at the very inn, she remembered with so much delight, from the Company of which, as they went in and out, she hoped to receive some Charitable Gratuity.

She had but just taken her post at the Innyard before a Carriage drove out of it, and on turning the Corner at which she was stationed, stopped to give the Postilion an opportunity of admiring the beauty of the prospect. Eliza then advanced to the carriage and was going to request their Charity, when on fixing her Eyes on the Lady, within it, she exclaimed,

‘Lady Harcourt!’

To which the lady replied,

‘Eliza!’

‘Yes Madam it is the wretched Eliza herself.’

Sir George, who was also in the Carriage, but too much amazed to speek, was proceeding to demand an explan-ation from Eliza of the Situation she was then in, when Lady Harcourt in transports of Joy, exclaimed.

‘Sir George, Sir George, she is not only Eliza our adopted Daughter, but our real Child.’

‘Our real Child! What Lady Harcourt, do you mean? You know you never even was with child. Explain your-self, I beseech you.’

‘You must remember Sir George that when you sailed for America, you left me breeding.’

‘I do, I do, go on dear Polly.’

‘Four months after you were gone, I was delivered of this Girl, but dreading your just resentment at her not proving the Boy you wished, I took her to a Haycock and laid her down. A few weeks afterwards, you returned, and fortunately for me, made no enquiries on the subject. Satisfied within myself of the wellfare of my Child, I soon forgot I had one, insomuch that when, we shortly after found her in the very Haycock, I had placed her, I had no more idea of her being my own, than you had, and nothing I will venture to say would have recalled the cir-cumstance to my remembrance, but my thus accidentally hearing her voice, which now strikes me as being the very counterpart of my own Child’s.’

‘The rational and convincing Account you have given of the whole affair,’ said Sir George, ‘leaves no doubt of her being our Daughter and as such I freely forgive the robbery she was guilty of.’

A mutual Reconciliation then took place, and Eliza, ascending the Carriage with her two Children returned to that home from which she had been absent nearly four years.

No sooner was she reinstated in her accustomed power at Harcourt Hall, than she raised an Army, with which she entirely demolished the Dutchess’s Newgate, snug as it was, and by that act, gained the Blessings of thousands, and the Applause of her own Heart.

Finis

The beautifull Cassandra

a novel in twelve Chapters dedicated by permission to Miss Austen.

DEDICATION.

Madam

You are a Phoenix. Your taste is refined, your Sentiments are noble, and your Virtues innumerable. Your Person is lovely, your Figure, elegant, and your Form, magestic. Your Manners are polished, your Conversation is rational and your appearance singular. If therefore the following Tale will afford one moment’s amusement to you, every wish will be gratified of

your most obedient

humble Servant

The Author

CHAPTER THE FIRST

Cassandra was the Daughter and the only Daughter of a celebrated Millener in Bond Street. Her father was of noble Birth, being the near relation of the Dutchess of——’s Butler.

CHAPTER THE 2 D

When Cassandra had attained her 16th year, and amiable and chancing to fall in love with an elegant Bonnet, her Mother had just compleated bespoke by the Countess of——she placed it on her gentle Head and walked from her Mother’s shop to make her Fortune.

CHAPTER THE 3 D

The first person she met, was the Viscount of——a young Man, no less celebrated for his Accomplishments and Virtues, than for his Elegance and Beauty. She curtseyed and walked on.

CHAPTER THE 4 TH

She then proceeded to a Pastry-cooks where she devoured six ices, refused to pay for them, knocked down the Pastry Cook and walked away.

CHAPTER THE 5 TH

She next ascended a Hackney Coach and ordered it to Hampstead, where she was no sooner arrived than she ordered the Coachman to turn round and drive her back again.

CHAPTER THE 6 TH

Being returned to the same spot of the same Street she had sate out from, the Coachman demanded his Pay.

CHAPTER THE 7 TH

She searched her pockets over again and again; but every search was unsuccessfull. No money could she find. The man grew peremptory. She placed her bonnet on his head and ran away.

CHAPTER THE 8 TH

Thro’many a street she then proceeded and met in none the least Adventure till on turning a Corner of Blooms-bury Square, she met Maria.

CHAPTER THE 9 TH

Cassandra started and Maria seemed surprised; they trem-bled, blushed, turned pale and passed each other in a mutual silence.

CHAPTER THE 10 TH

Cassandra was next accosted by her freind the Widow, who squeezing out her little Head thro’her less window, asked her how she did? Cassandra curtseyed and went on.

CHAPTER THE 11 TH

A quarter of a mile brought her to her paternal roof in Bond Street from which she had now been absent nearly 7 hours.

CHAPTER THE 12 TH

She entered it and was pressed to her Mother’s bosom by that worthy woman. Cassandra smiled and whispered to herself‘This is a day well spent.’

Finis

Letter the third

From A young Lady in distress’d Circumstances to her freind

A few days ago I was at a private Ball given by Mr Ash-burnham. As my Mother never goes out she entrusted me to the care of Lady Greville who did me the honour of calling for me in her way and of allowing me to sit for-wards, which is a favour about which I am very indifferent especially as I know it is considered as confering a great obligation on me. ‘So Miss Maria’ （said her Ladyship as she saw me advancing to the door of the Carriage） ‘you seem very smart to night - My poor Girls will appear quite to disadvantage by you - I only hope your Mother may not have distressed herself to set you o≠. Have you got a new Gown on?’

‘Yes Ma’am,’ replied I with as much indifference as I could assume.

‘Aye, and a fine one too I think—’ （feeling it, as by her permission I seated myself by her） ‘I dare say it is all very smart - But I must own, for you know I always speak my mind, that I think it was quite a needless peice of expence - Why could not you have worn your old striped one? It is not my way to find fault with people because they are poor, for I always think that they are more to be despised and pitied than blamed for it, especially if they cannot help it, but at the same time I must say that in my opinion your old striped Gown would have been quite fine enough for its Wearer - for to tell you the truth （I always speak my mind） I am very much afraid that one half of the people in the room will not know whether you have a Gown on or not - But I suppose you intend to make your fortune tonight—：Well, the sooner the better; and I wish you success.’

‘Indeed, Ma’am, I have no such intention—’

‘Who ever heard a Young Lady own that she was a Fortune-hunter?’ Miss Greville laughed, but I am sure Ellen felt for me.

‘Was your Mother gone to bed before you left her?’ said her Ladyship—

‘Dear Ma’am,’ said Ellen, ‘it is but nine o’clock.’

‘True, Ellen, but Candles cost money, and Mrs Williams is too wise to be extravagant.’

‘She was just sitting down to supper, Ma’am—’

‘And what had she got for Supper?’ ‘I did not observe.’ ‘Bread and Cheese I suppose.’ ‘I should never wish for a better supper,’ said Ellen. ‘You have never any reason’replied her Mother, ‘as a better is always provided for you.’ Miss Greville laughed excessively, as she constantly does at her Mother’s wit.

Such is the humiliating Situation in which I am forced to appear while riding in her Ladyship’s Coach - I dare not be impertinent, as my Mother is always admonishing me to be humble and patient if I wish to make my way in the world. She insists on my accepting every invitation of Lady Greville, or you may be certain that I would never enter either her House, or her Coach, with the disagrea-ble certainty I always have of being abused for my Poverty while I am in them. - When we arrived at Ash-burnham, it was nearly ten o’clock, which was an hour and a half later than we were desired to be there; but Lady Greville is too fashionable （or fancies herself to be so） to be punctual. The Dancing however was not begun as they waited for Miss Greville. I had not been long in the room before I was engaged to dance by Mr Bernard, but just as we were going to stand up, he recollected that his Servant had got his white Gloves, and immediately ran out to fetch them. In the mean time the Dancing began and Lady Greville in passing to another room went exactly before me - She saw me and instantly stopping, said to me though there were several people close to us;

‘Hey day, Miss Maria! What cannot you get a partner? Poor Young Lady! I am afraid your new Gown was put on for nothing. But do not despair; perhaps you may get a hop before the Evening is over.’So saying, she passed on without hearing my repeated assurance of being engaged, and leaving me very provoked at being so exposed before every one - Mr Bernard however soon returned and by coming to me the moment he entered the room, and leading me to the Dancers, my Character I hope was cleared from the imputation Lady Greville had thrown on it, in the eyes of all the old Ladies who had heard her speech. I soon forgot all my vexations in the pleasure of dancing and of having the most agreable partner in the room. As he is moreover heir to a very large Estate I could see that Lady Greville did not look very well pleased when she found who had been his Choice - She was determined to mortify me, and accordingly when we were sitting down between the dances, she came to me with more than her usual insulting importance attended by Miss Mason and said loud enough to be heard by half the people in the room, ‘Pray, Miss Maria, in what way of business was your Grandfather? for Miss Mason and I cannot agree whether he was a Grocer or a Bookbinder.’ I saw that she wanted to mortify me, and was resolved if I possibly could to prevent her seeing that her scheme succeeded. ‘Neither Madam; he was a Wine Merchant.’ ‘Aye, I knew he was in some such low way - He broke did not he?’ ‘I beleive not Ma’am.’ ‘Did not he abscond?’ ‘I never heard that he did.’ ‘At least he died insolvent?’‘I was never told so before.’ ‘Why, was not your Father as poor as a Rat?’ ‘I fancy not.’ ‘Was not he in the King’s Bench once?’ ‘I never saw him there.’ She gave me such a look, and turned away in a great passion; while I was half delighted with myself for my imperti-nence, and half afraid of being thought too saucy. As Lady Greville was extremely angry with me, she took no further notice of me all the Evening, and indeed had I been in favour I should have been equally neglected, as she was got into a party of great folks and she never speaks to me when she can to any one else. Miss Greville was with her Mother’s party at Supper, but Ellen pre-ferred staying with the Bernards and me. We had a very pleasant Dance and as Lady G——slept all the way home, I had a very comfortable ride.

The next day while we were at dinner Lady Greville’s Coach stopped at the door, for that is the time of day she generally contrives it should. She sent in a message by the Servant to say that ‘she should not get out but that Miss Maria must come to the Coach-door, as she wanted to speak to her, and that she must make haste and come immediately—’ ‘What an impertinent Message Mama!’ said I—‘ Go Maria—’ replied She - Accordingly I went and was obliged to stand there at her Ladyship’s pleasure though the Wind was extremely high and very cold.

‘Why I think, Miss Maria, you are not quite so smart as you were last night - But I did not come to examine your dress, but to tell you that you may dine with us the day after tomorrow - Not tomorrow, remember, do not come tomorrow, for we expect Lord and Lady Clermont and Sir Thomas Stanley’s family - There will be no occa-sion for your being very fine for I shan’t send the Carriage - If it rains you may take an umbrella—’ I could hardly help laughing at hearing her give me leave to keep myself dry - ‘And pray remember to be in time, for I shan’t wait - I hate my Victuals over-done - But you need not come before the time-How does your Mother do? She is at dinner is not she?’ ‘Yes, Ma’am, we were in the middle of dinner when your Ladyship came.’ ‘I am afraid you find it very cold, Maria,’ said Ellen. ‘Yes, it is an horrible East wind’—said her Mother—‘I assure you I can hardly bear the window down - But you are used to be blown about the wind, Miss Maria, and that is what has made your Complexion so ruddy and coarse. You young Ladies who cannot often ride in a Carriage never mind what weather you trudge in, or how the wind shews your legs. I would not have my Girls stand out of doors as you do in such a day as this. But some sort of people have no feelings either of cold or Delicacy - Well, remem-ber that we shall expect you on Thursday at 5 o’clock - You must tell your Maid to come for you at night - There will be no Moon - and you will have an horrid walk home - My Compliments to your Mother - I am afraid your dinner will be cold - Drive on—’And away she went, leaving me in a great passion with her as she always does.

Maria Williams

From a Young Lady very much in love to her Freind

My Uncle gets more stingy, my Aunt more particular, and I more in love every day. What shall we all be at this rate by the end of the year! I had this morning the happi-ness of receiving the following Letter from my dear Musgrove.

Sackville St：Janry 7th

It is a month to day since I beheld my lovely Henrietta, and the sacred anniversary must and shall be kept in a manner becoming the day-by writing to her. Never shall I forget the moment when her Beauties first broke on my sight - No time as you well know can erase it from my Memory. It was at Lady Scudamore’s. Happy Lady Scudamore to live within a mile of the divine Henrietta! When the lovely Creature first entered the room, Oh! what were my sensations? The sight of you was like the sight of a wonderful fine Thing. I started-I gazed at her with Admiration - She appeared every moment more Charming, and the unfortunate Musgrove became a Cap-tive to your Charms before I had time to look about me. Yes Madam, I had the happiness of adoring you, an unhappiness for which I cannot be too grateful. ‘What,’ said he to himself, ‘is Musgrove allowed to die for Hen-rietta? Enviable Mortal! and may he pine for her who is the object of universal Admiration, who is adored by a Colonel, and toasted by a Baronet!—’ Adorable Henrietta how beautiful you are! I declare you are quite divine! You are more than Mortal. You are an Angel. You are Venus herself. Inshort, Madam, you are the prettiest Girl I ever saw in my Life - and her Beauty is encreased in her Mus-grove’s Eyes, by permitting him to love her and allowing me to hope. And Ah! Angelic Miss Henrietta, Heaven is my Witness how ardently I do hope for the death of your villanous Uncle and his Abandoned Wife, Since my fair one will not consent to be mine till their decease has placed her in affluence above what my fortune can procure—. Though it is an improvable Estate—. Cruel Henrietta to persist in such a resolution! I am at present with my Sister where I mean to continue till my own house which tho’an excellent one is at present somewhat out of repair, is ready to receive me. Amiable princess of my Heart farewell-Of that Heart which trembles while it signs itself your most ardent Admirer

and devoted humble Servt

T. Musgrove

There is a pattern for a Love-letter Matilda! Did you ever read such a masterpeice of Writing? Such Sense, Such Sentiment, Such purity of Thought, Such flow of Language and such unfeigned Love in one Sheet? No, never I can answer for it, since a Musgrove is not to be met with by every Girl. Oh! how I long to be with him! I intend to send him the following in answer to his Letter tomorrow.

My dearest Musgrove—. Words can not express how happy your Letter made me; I thought I should have cried for Joy, for I love you better than any body in the World. I think you the most amiable, and the handsomest Man in England, and so to be sure you are. I never read so sweet a Letter in my Life. Do write me another just like it, and tell me you are in love with me in every other line. I quite die to see you. How shall we manage to see one another? for we are so much in love that we cannot live asunder. Oh! my dear Musgrove you cannot think how impatiently I wait for the death of my Uncle and Aunt-If they will not die soon, I beleive I shall run mad, for I get more in love with you every day of my Life. How happy your Sister is to enjoy the pleasure of your Company in her house, and how happy every body in London must be because you are there. I hope you will be so kind as to write to me again soon, for I never read such sweet Letters as yours. I am, my dearest Musgrove, most truly and faithfully yours for ever and ever

Henrietta Halton

I hope he will like my answer; it is as good a one as I can write, though nothing to his; Indeed I had always heard what a dab he was at a Love-letter. I saw him you know for the first time at Lady Scudamore’s - And when I saw her Ladyship afterwards she asked me how I liked her Cousin Musgrove?

‘Why upon my word’said I, ‘I think he is a very hand-some young Man.’

‘I am glad you think so,’ replied she, ‘for he is distract-edly in love with you.’

‘Law! Lady Scudamore,’ said I, ‘how can you talk so ridiculously?’

‘Nay,’ tis very true,’ answered She, ‘I assure you, for he was in love with you from the first moment he beheld you.’

‘I wish it may be true,’ said I, ‘for that is the only kind of love I would give a farthing for - There is some Sense in being in love at first sight.’

‘Well, I give you Joy of your conquest,’ replied Lady Scudamore, ‘and I beleive it to have been a very complete one; I am sure it is not a contemptible one, for my Cousin is a charming young fellow, has seen a great deal of the World, and writes the best Love-letters I ever read.’

This made me very happy, and I was excessively pleased with my conquest. However I thought it was proper to give myself a few Airs - So I said to her—

‘This is all very pretty, Lady Scudamore, but you know that we young Ladies who are Heiresses must not throw ourselves away upon Men who have no fortune at all.’

‘My dear Miss Halton,’ said She, ‘I am as much con-vinced of that as you can be, and I do assure you that I should be the last person to encourage your marrying any one who had not some pretensions to expect a fortune with you. Mr Musgrove is so far from being poor that he has an estate of Several hundreds an year which is capable of great Improvement, and an excellent House, though at present it is not quite in repair.’

‘If that is the case,’ replied I, ‘I have nothing more to say against him, and if as you say he is an informed young Man and can write good Love-letters, I am sure I have no reason to find fault with him for admiring me, tho’perhaps I may not marry him for all that, Lady Scudamore.’

‘You are certainly under no obligation to marry him,’ answered her Ladyship, ‘except that which love himself will dictate to you, for if I am not greatly mistaken you are at this very moment unknown to yourself, cherishing a most tender affection for him.’

‘Law, Lady Scudamore,’ replied I blushing, ‘how can you think of such a thing?’

‘Because every look, every word betrays it,’ answered She; ‘Come, my dear Henrietta, consider me as a freind, and be sincere with me - Do not you prefer Mr Musgrove to any man of your acquaintance?’

‘Pray do not ask me such questions, Lady Scudamore,’ said I turning away my head, ‘for it is not fit for me to answer them.’

‘Nay my Love,’ replied she, ‘now you confirm my sus-picions. But why, Henrietta, should you be ashamed to own a well-placed Love, or why refuse to confide in me?’

‘I am not ashamed to own it;’ said I taking Courage. ‘I do not refuse to confide in you or blush to say that I do love your cousin Mr Musgrove, that I am sincerely attached to him, for it is no disgrace to love a handsome Man. If he were plain indeed I might have had reason to be ashamed of a passion which must have been mean since the Object would have been unworthy. But with such a figure and face, and such beautiful hair as your Cousin has, why should I blush to own that such Superior Merit has made an impression on me.’

‘My sweet Girl’ （said Lady Scudamore embracing me with great affection） ‘what a delicate way of thinking you have in these Matters, and what a quick discernment for one of your years! Oh! how I honour you for such Noble Sentiments!’

‘Do you, Ma’am?’said I; ‘You are vastly obliging. But pray, Lady Scudamore, did your Cousin himself tell you of his affection for me? I shall like him the better if he did, for what is a Lover without a Confidante?’

‘Oh! my Love’replied She, ‘you were born for each other. Every word you say more deeply convinces me that your Minds are actuated by the invisible power of sim-pathy, for your opinions and Sentiments so exactly coincide. Nay, the colour of your Hair is not very differ-ent. Yes, my dear Girl, the poor despairing Musgrove did reveal to me the story of his Love—. Nor was I surprised at it-I know not how it was, but I had a kind of presen - timent that he would be in love with you.’

‘Well, but how did he break it to you?’

‘It was not till after supper. We were sitting round the fire together talking on indifferent subjects, though to say the truth the Conversation was cheifly on my side, for he was thoughtful and silent, when on a sudden he inter-rupted me in the midst of something I was saying, by exclaiming in a most Theatrical tone—

“Yes I’m in love I feel it now

And Henrietta Halton has undone me—”’

‘Oh! What a sweet Way’replied I, ‘of declaring his Passion! To make such a couple of charming Lines about me! What a pity it is that they are not in rhime!’

‘I am very glad you like it,’ answered She; ‘To be sure there was a great deal of Taste in it. “And are you in love with her, Cousin?” said I. “I am very sorry for it, for unex-ceptionable as you are in every respect, with a pretty Estate capable of Great improvements, and an excellent House tho’somewhat out of repair, Yet who can hope to aspire with success to the adorable Henrietta who has had an offer from a Colonel and been toasted by a Baronet—”’ ‘ThatI have—’ cried I. Lady Scudamore continued. ‘“Ah, dear Cousin,” replied he, “I am so well convinced of the little Chance I can have of winning her who is adored by thousands, that I need no assurances of yours to make me more thoroughly so. Yet surely neither you or the fair Henrietta herself will deny me the exquisite Gratification of dieing for her, of falling a victim of her Charms. And when I am dead” - continued he—’

‘Oh Lady Scudamore,’ said I wiping my eyes, ‘that such a sweet Creature should talk of dieing!’

‘It is an affecting Circumstance indeed,’ replied Lady Scudamore. ‘“When I am dead,” said he, “Let me be car-ried and lain at her feet, and perhaps she may not disdain to drop a pitying tear on my poor remains.”’

‘Dear Lady Scudamore’interrupted I, ‘say no more on this affecting Subject. I cannot bear it.’

‘Oh! how I admire the sweet Sensibility of your Soul, and as I would not for Worlds wound it too deeply, I will be silent.’

‘Pray go on’said I. She did so.

‘“And then,”added he, “Ah! Cousin, imagine what my transports will be when I feel the dear precious drops trickle o’er my face! Who would not die to taste such extacy! And when I am interred, may the divine Henrietta bless some happier Youth with her affection, May he be as tenderly attached to her as the hapless Musgrove and while he crumbles to dust, May they live an example of Felicity in the Conjugal state!”’

‘Did you ever hear any thing so pathetic? What a charming wish, to be lain at my feet when he was dead! Oh! what an exalted mind he must have to be capable of such a wish!’ Lady Scudamore went on.

‘“Ah! my dear Cousin,” replied I to him, “Such noble behaviour as this, must melt the heart of any Woman however obdurate it may naturally be; and could the divine Henrietta but hear your generous wishes for her happiness, all gentle as is her Mind, I have not a doubt but that she would pity your affection and endeavour to return it.” “Oh! Cousin,” answered he, “do not endeavour to raise my hopes by such flattering Assurances. No, I cannot hope to please this angel of a Woman, and the only thing which remains for me to do, is to die.” “True Love is ever desponding,”replied I, “but I, my dear Tom, will give you even greater hopes of conquering this fair one’s heart, than I have yet given you, by assuring you that I watched her with the strictest attention during the whole day, and could plainly discover that she cherishes in her bosom though unknown to herself, a most tender affection for you.”’

‘Dear Lady Scudamore,’ cried I, ‘This is more than I ever knew!’

‘Did not I say that it was unknown to yourself? “I did not,” continued I to him, “encourage you by saying this at first, that Surprise might render the pleasure Still Greater.” “No, Cousin,” replied he in a languid voice, “nothing will convince me that I can have touched the heart of Henrietta Halton, and if you are deceived yourself, do not attempt deceiving me.” Inshort my Love it was the work of some hours for me to persuade the poor despairing Youth that you had really a preference for him; but when at last he could no longer deny the force of my arguments, or discredit what I told him, his transports, his Raptures, his Extacies are beyond my power to describe.’

‘Oh! the dear Creature,’ cried I, ‘how passionately he loves me! But, dear Lady Scudamore, did you tell him that I was totally dependant on my Uncle and Aunt?’

‘Yes, I told him every thing.’

‘And what did he say?’

‘He exclaimed with virulence against Uncles and Aunts; Accused the Laws of England for allowing them to pos-sess their Estates when wanted by their Nephews or Neices, and wished he were in the House of Commons, that he might reform the Legislature, and rectify all its abuses.’

‘Oh! the sweet Man! What a spirit he has!’ said I.

‘He could not flatter himself, he added, that the ador-able Henrietta would condescend for his Sake to resign those Luxuries and that Splendor to which She had been used, and accept only in exchange the Comforts and Elegancies which his limited Income could afford her, even supposing that his house were in Readiness to receive her. I told him that it could not be expected that she would; it would be doing her an injustice to suppose her capable of giving up the power she now possesses and so nobly uses of doing such extensive Good to the poorer part of her fellow Creatures, merely for the grat-ification of you and herself.’

‘To be sure,’ said I, ‘Iam very Charitable every now and then. And what did Mr Musgrove say to this?’

‘He replied that he was under a melancholy Necessity of owning the truth of what I said, and therefore if he should be the happy Creature destined to be the Husband of the Beautiful Henrietta he must bring himself to wait, however impatiently, for the fortunate day, when she might be freed from the power of worthless Relations and able to bestow herself on him.’

What a noble Creature he is! Oh! Matilda what a for-tunate one I am, who am to be his Wife! My Aunt is calling to me to come and make the pies. So adeiu my dear freind,

and beleive me yours etc. - H. Halton

Finis

A Letter from a Young Lady, whose feelings being too Strong for her Judgement led her into the commission of Errors which her Heart disapproved

Many have been the cares and vicissitudes of my past life, my beloved Ellinor, and the only consolation I feel for their bitterness is that on a close examination of my con-duct, I am convinced that I have strictly deserved them. I murdered my father at a very early period of my Life, I have since murdered my Mother, and I am now going to murder my Sister. I have changed my religion so often that at present I have not an idea of any left. I have been a perjured witness in every public tryal for these last twelve Years, and I have forged my own Will. In short there is scarcely a crime that I have not committed - But I am now going to reform. Colonel Martin of the Horse guards has paid his Addresses to me, and we are to be married in a few days. As there is something singular in our Courtship, I will give you an account of it. Colonel Martin is the second son of the late Sir John Martin who died immensely rich, but bequeathing only one hundred thousand pound apiece to his three younger Children, left the bulk of his fortune, about eight Million to the present Sir Thomas. Upon his small pittance the Colonel lived tolerably contented for nearly four months when he took it into his head to determine on getting the whole of his eldest Brother’s Estate. A new will was forged and the Colonel produced it in Court - but nobody would swear to it’s being the right Will except himself, and he had sworn so much that Nobody beleived him. At that moment I happened to be passing by the door of the Court, and was beckoned in by the Judge who told the Colonel that I was a Lady ready to witness anything for the cause of Justice, and advised him to apply to me. In short the affair was soon adjusted. The Colonel and I swore to its’being the right will, and Sir Thomas has been obliged to resign all his illgotten Wealth. The Colonel in gratitude waited on me the next day with an offer of his hand—. I am now going to murder my Sister.

Yours Ever,

Anna Parker

作者自述[1]

我请求读者们原谅，在本期《作家日记》[2]中，我没有采取以往的编排形式，而是只刊登了一部中篇小说。虽然这篇小说的写作占用了我将近一个月的时间，但无论如何，我还是希望大家能够谅解我的做法。

现在我们来谈谈小说中的故事。虽然我称这篇小说是“幻想的”，但我认为故事本身是非常现实的。由于小说写作过程中确实有幻想的成分，因此我认为，在这里做一些预先说明还是有必要的。

事实上，这篇小说既不是一个完整的故事，也不是一篇手记。试想一下，有这么一位丈夫，他的妻子几小时前跳楼自杀了，现在尸体就放在他旁边的桌子上。他心烦意乱，无法集中精力思考。他在自己的房间里走来走去，试图将刚才发生的事情解释清楚，他想“把自己的注意力集中到一点上”。与此同时，他又是个严重的疑病症患者，还常常自言自语。因此，大家会看到他在自己给自己描述这件事，向自己解释事情的前因后果。尽管他的话看似具有一定的连贯性，但无论在逻辑上还是感受上，都存在一些自相矛盾的地方。他为自己辩护，同时又指责妻子，而且还给出一些与此事毫无关系的解释：其中既有思想和心灵的粗鄙，又有深切的体验。他的确一步步地给自己解释清楚了事情的来龙去脉，也把自己的注意力“集中到了一点上”。他的一连串回忆最终把他引向了真理，而真理又升华了他的思想和心灵。与杂乱无章的故事开头相比，到最后，他的论调都发生了变化。至少他自己认为，对于他这个不幸的人来说，真理已经非常地清晰与明确了。

这就是故事的主题。当然，整个故事的发展持续了几个小时，中间断断续续，形式上也不连贯：他有时是自言自语，有时又好像是在讲给一位不在场的听众或一位法官听。这种情形在现实中也是存在的。如果有一位速记员能听到他的话，并把它们都记录下来，那么这篇记录读起来可能比我写的还要晦涩和不通顺，但我认为，他的心理发展脉络应该不会有太大变化。类似关于速记员记录他讲话（之后我再对记录进行加工）的假设，就是我称这篇小说具有“幻想”特点的主要原因。其实这种创作手法在文学作品中并不鲜见，例如，维克多·雨果在自己的名著《一个死囚的末日》中就使用过几乎相同的方法，虽然没有采用速记员视角，但他进行了更大胆的假设。他想象一个被判处死刑的囚犯不仅在自己最后一天，甚至在最后一小时、最后一分钟都能（而且有时间）写手记。如果他不进行这种幻想的话，大概也就不会有这部在他创作生涯中最贴近现实的杰作了。

[1]本章节收录于《温顺的女人》同期期刊之前，做解释说明之用，因感觉有助于读者理解作家的创作缘由，所以从俄文译出一并收录，英文部分没有此章节。——编者注

[2]《作家日记》是陀思妥耶夫斯基自费出版发行的一份期刊，内容涉及国家政治、外交、战争、法律、宗教、家庭、青年以及文学艺术与往事回忆等。其中，《温顺的女人》刊载于1876年11月号，占了当期的全部篇幅。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为译者注。）

一

1.我是谁，她又是谁

……只要她现在在这儿，就一切都好：我可以每隔几分钟就走过去看看她，但她明天就要被人抬走了，一想到就要剩下我一个人，我就有些不知所措。现在她正躺在客厅里由两张牌桌拼起来的桌子上，可是明天，棺材就要来了，一副白色的、铺着雪白那不勒斯绸[3]的棺材。不过我想说的并不是这件事……我在屋子里走来走去，想给自己一个解释，可就是无法集中注意力……六个小时过去了，我仍然在走、走、走……事情是这样的。我会按照先后顺序给你们讲。（按顺序！）先生们，你们可能看出来了，我不是作家，不过没关系，我会把我知道的全都讲出来。不过对于我来说可怕的地方就在于，我全都明白。

如果你们想知道，或者说，如果咱们从头开始捋，她只是来我这里当东西，据说是为了付《呼声报》的广告费。她在报纸上登了一条求职广告，广告内容大致是要找一份家庭女教师之类的工作，愿意外出或家内授课等诸如此类的话。起初我没太在意她，感觉她和别的客人没有什么不同之处。但过了一会儿，我发现有些地方不太对劲。她身材瘦削，有一头淡黄色的头发，比一般人稍高点。也许是害羞，她和我说话时，总是显得有点儿迟钝（我猜她在陌生人面前就是这样，不言而喻，我和其他人没什么不同，可能她把我也当作一个陌生人，而不是当铺掌柜）。其他人来当东西时总是不停地吵闹、哀求、讨价还价，就是为了多当些钱，而她则不是，给多少就是多少，拿了钱转身就走，一句话都不说……搞得我一头雾水……嗯……首先，她当的东西很奇怪：一对镀了层金的银耳环和一个破破烂烂的小铜牌，总共只值二十戈比[4]。她自己也清楚，这两样东西值不了多少钱，但我从她的神情中能看出来，对她来说，它们是很珍贵的。后来我才知道，这些就是她父母留给她仅有的遗物。有一次我嘲笑了她当的东西。也只有这么一次，你们看出来了吧，其实我从不允许自己这样放肆，我跟人说话时总是带着一种绅士般的口吻：话不多，有礼貌，又很严谨。“严谨、严谨、再严谨”。但这次她居然拿来了一件兔皮袄的“残片”（说是残片毫不夸张），我没忍住，突然对她说了些貌似讽刺挖苦的话。天哪，她好像发怒了。她那双淡蓝色的大眼睛总是若有所思的样子，但现在仿佛要燃烧起来似的。可她还是没有开口，带着“残片”离开了。正是这次经历让我开始对她有了“特别”的关注，而且还想到了关于她的一些事情，就是那种特别的事情。对了，我对她还有一个印象，你们想听吗？这个印象最重要，能概括其他一切印象：就是说，她真的很年轻，看上去就像十四岁。但实际上她那时还差三个月就十六岁了。不过我想说的那个能概括一切的印象不在于此。第二天，她又来了。后来我才知道，她带着那件兔皮袄还去过多布龙拉沃夫和莫泽尔两家当铺，但人家除了金子什么都不要，也懒得和她说话。相对地，有一次，我收了她的一块玉石（也是那种不值钱的玩意），但事后想起来，也觉得奇怪：我的当铺也是除了金银什么都不收啊，而我居然让她在我这儿当了那块石头。这应该是当时能让我想到她的第二个念头了，我记得这事儿。

这一次，从莫泽尔当铺出来后，她又来到我这里想当一支琥珀烟嘴，小玩意马马虎虎，喜欢这类东西的人有可能瞧瞧，但对我们来说它毫无价值，因为我们只要金子。由于昨天她带来的那场“骚乱”，我在接待她的时候，显得有点严肃。我的严肃实质上就是冷淡。但在付给她两卢布后，我还是没忍住，说了一句可能刺激到她的话：“我只对您开这个特例，要知道，莫泽尔是绝不会收您这类东西的。”我说话时，特意在“对您”两个字上加重了语气，似乎有了某种“特殊含义”。这么做确实有些恶毒。她听到这句“对您”后，又发怒了，但依然默不作声，也没有扔掉两个卢布，她把钱收下了——这就是人穷志短啊！我还记得，她是那么生气！我知道，我的话刺痛了她。她离开后，我问自己：“花两卢布战胜她，这划算吗？”嘿、嘿、嘿！而且我记得，这个问题我问了两次：“划算吗？划算吗？”我笑着给出了肯定的答案。那一刻真是太美妙了，我并没有什么负罪感：我是故意这么做的，我想试探试探她，因为当时我脑子里掠过了一些关于她的念头。这是能让我想到她的第三个念头。

……好吧，从那时起，我们的故事就算正式开头了。不用说，我开始努力从侧面打听有关她的所有情况，然后急不可耐地期盼她的到来。你瞧，我总是能预感到，她很快就要来啦。只要她一过来，我就会极其礼貌地和她攀谈一番。要知道，我受过良好的教育，也很注意举止风度。哼哼，那时我感觉她既善良，又温顺。善良和温顺的人不会总是拒人千里之外，虽然她们不太可能完全敞开心扉，但也不会拒绝一次谈话：她们回答时会非常谨慎，但只要您愿意和她们交谈，而且不会感到厌烦的话，那么她们的话会越说越多。不过她当时并没有和我多说什么。关于《呼声报》和其他事情都是我后来才知道的。那个时候，为了在报纸上登求职广告，她几乎倾尽所有，起初的广告词中还带有一丝高傲的口吻：“兹有家庭女教师愿外出工作，条件随函递送”，但没过多久，就变成了“可做任何工作，授课、女伴、管家、病人护理，能缝纫”等众人所熟悉的常见写法！不消说，这些都是不同阶段分别添加进广告内容中的。直到最后，她实在走投无路，连“不求薪酬，只需膳食”这样的字眼也都用上了。但即便如此，她依然找不到事做。那个时候，我决定对她进行最后一次试探：我突然拿出一张当日的《呼声报》，给她看上面的一条广告：“青年女子求职，本人孤儿，可做幼儿家庭教师，中老年鳏夫家庭雇用更佳，可料理家务。”

“您看，这是今天早上登出的广告，晚上大概就能找到工作。广告词就应该这样写！”

她又发怒了，眼睛似乎又要喷出火焰来，一句话没说，转身就离开了。我反倒很高兴。因为此时我已有十足的把握了，一点儿也不害怕：才不会有谁会收她的烟嘴，更何况她现在连烟嘴也已经当出去了。果不其然，三天后她又来了，面色苍白，焦虑不安。我看得出来，她家里应该是出了什么事，而且也的确是出事了。我一会儿再解释到底出了什么事，现在我只想说说当时我是如何在她面前优雅地表现自己，进而提升在她心目中的地位的。这个想法也是突然从我脑子里冒出来的。事情经过是这样的，她拿来了一尊圣像（一看就是下了狠心）……唉，听听！听听！到这里故事才真正开始，我又把它讲得一团糟……我总是想回忆所有事情，每个细节。我本来是想把注意力集中在一点上的，但好像办不到，我脑子里总是千头万绪的……

那是一尊圣母像，圣母抱着圣婴，就是普通人家里供奉的那种，看上去有点儿年头了，披着镀金的衣饰——这东西值……嗯，值六卢布。看得出来，圣像对她来说很珍贵，她没有把圣像上的衣饰拿掉，完整地拿来典当了。我对她说，最好是把衣饰摘下来留在我这儿，圣像拿回去，毕竟那是尊圣像啊。

“难道典当圣像是被禁止的吗？”

“不，可以当，只是您自己可能……”

“那就把衣饰摘下来吧。”

“不，还是别那么做了，我都收下吧，我会把它放在神龛里，”我边想边说，“和其他圣像放在一起，在神灯下面（自从我开当铺起，就一直点着神灯）。”“我直接给您十卢布，就这么简单。”

“我不要十卢布，五卢布就行，我一定把圣像赎回来。”

“您不想要十卢布吗？这圣像值这么多钱。”因为看到她眼睛里一闪而过的亮光，我便补了这么一句。她没作声。我给了她五卢布。

“您可别瞧不起任何人，我也在困境中挣扎过，而且比这还要糟，您别看我现在干这行……我也是经历了种种苦难……”

“那您是在报复社会，对吗？”她突然打断我，言语中带着一丝嘲讽，不过这种嘲讽并无恶意，反倒带着些许的天真无邪（之所以这么说，是因为她当时认为我和其他人没有区别，因而对我说这句话并无恶意）。“啊哈！”我心里想，“原来你是这样的人，性格会自己显露出来的、属于新派的那类人。”

“您看，”我马上半开玩笑又故作神秘地跟她说，“我——我是那常欲作恶，却永远为善的力量的一部分……”

她快速地看了我一眼，眼神中带着孩童般的好奇：

“等等，这是什么意思？是谁说的？我好像在哪儿听过……”

“别费脑筋了，这是梅菲斯特[5]向浮士德做自我介绍时说的话。《浮士德》读过吗？”

“没……没仔细读过。”

“那就是根本没读过。应该读读。不过我看您又面带讥讽地笑话我了。您别以为我没品位到会为了往自己当铺掌柜的身份上贴金，而试图在您面前把自己比作是梅菲斯特。开当铺的就是开当铺的。我们都懂，小姐。”

“您真奇怪……我从来都没那么想过……”

她其实想说的是：我没想到您是一个受过教育的人。虽然她没说出口，但我知道，她就是这么想的；我令她非常满意。

“您看，”我说，“无论干哪一行，人都可以做好事。当然，我不是说我自己，除了坏事，我好像什么都没做过，不过……”

“当然了，无论在何种地位，人都可以做好事。”她一边说，一边用锐利的目光飞快地看了我一眼。“不管处在什么地位，确实如此。”她又突然补充了一句。

啊，我记得，我记得每一个瞬间！我想多说一句，当一个年轻人，一个可爱的年轻人想要说一句睿智而又深刻的话时，她的脸上就会立刻浮现出过于真诚和天真的神情，仿佛是在告诉你：“现在，我，有一句睿智又深刻的话要说给你听。”这不是虚荣心在作祟，和我们不一样。你能看得出来，她自己极为珍视这一切，相信又尊重这一切。而且她会认为，我们和她一样，也尊重这一切。啊，真诚！年轻人就是用真诚来征服别人的，这在她身上得到了完美的体现。

我记得很清楚，什么都没忘！她离开后，我当机立断。就在那天，我进行了最后一次调查，把有关她的其余所有情况都打听得一清二楚，包括眼下的各种细节；过去的事情我早已从卢克里娅那里打听到了。卢克里娅那时还是她家里的用人，几天前我就买通了她。她的情况听上去非常可怕，我不明白，身处这样的恶劣环境中，她怎么还能像刚才那样笑得出来，而且还对梅菲斯特的话充满好奇。但她毕竟是个年轻人啊！我想她的时候，总能感到骄傲和兴奋，正是因为年轻人这种豁达坦荡的态度：即使处在崩溃的边缘，歌德的伟大诗句依然光芒万丈。青春就是这样的豁达坦荡，即使它极其短暂又充满曲折。你们知道，我说的是她，只有她。更重要的是，那个时候我已经认为她是我的了，而且我毫不怀疑自己的能力。要知道，当你不再有任何怀疑时，每个念头都充满了诱人的魅力。

我这是怎么了？这样下去的话，什么时候我才能集中注意力呢？快点儿，快点儿——这些根本不是重点，我的天啊！

2.求婚

我打听到的“底细”可以用一句话讲清楚：她父母三年前去世了，她和两个名声并不太好的姨妈一起生活。说她们名声不好都是客气的。其中一个是寡妇，带着六个孩子，一个比一个小，另一个是让人厌恶的老处女。两个人都不怎么样。她父亲当过公务员，但只是做文书工作，还有一个非世袭的贵族头衔。总之，一句话：我完全驾驭得了。我的社会地位似乎更高一些：毕竟我是一个退伍上尉，曾在一个有光荣历史的团里服役，我还是世袭贵族，经济独立，等等。至于我的当铺，她那两个姨妈也只有仰视的份儿了。她和姨妈们一起生活的三年过得和奴隶一样，即便如此，她还是坚持了下来，并在某个地方通过了一个考试。她试图从每日残酷无情的劳役中尽力挤出所有的时间来准备考试。这意味着，在她看来，还是有某种更美好的生活值得去追求！可我为什么要娶她呢？不过我的事不重要，一会儿再说吧……问题也不在这儿！她要教姨妈的孩子们识字，要缝补内衣，后来就不仅是内衣了，而且尽管她的肺不好，却还得擦洗地板。她们甚至还动手打她，说她是个吃闲饭的。最后，打算把她卖了。呸！那些肮脏的细节我就不讲了。后来，她把自己所有的经历都详细地告诉我了。她家邻居中有个胖老板，他不是个普通的店铺老板，而是两家食品杂货店的老板。他观察了一年，把她们家的基本情况都掌握了。他的两个老婆都被他折磨死了，现在又想找第三个，于是就看上了她，说她“安静，出身清贫，可以照顾好我家里那些孤儿”。他家里确实有孤儿。他上门求婚，和姨妈们商量。但毕竟他都五十岁了，把她吓坏了。从那时起，她就不断到我这儿来当东西，急着要在《呼声报》上登广告。最后，她央求姨妈们，给她一点儿时间来考虑一下。她们答应了，但给她的时间也不是太多，等她再请求时，她们没有再给，还假惺惺地说：“就算没你这张多余的嘴，我们自己也不知道吃啥。”这些事我都知道了，就在她来当圣像的那天上午，我做了决定。当天晚上，胖老板从杂货店里拿了值半卢布的一磅糖果去了她家。她陪他坐着，我把卢克里娅从厨房里叫出来，让她进屋传话，就说我在大门口等她，有急事要见她。我对自己的决定和行动非常满意。总的来说，那一整天我都对自己感到极其满意。

首先，把她叫出来，在大门口当着卢克里娅的面，对着已经惊呆了的她表白，我觉得这是一种幸福和荣耀……其次，我不想让她对我的举动感到诧异，我对她说：“我这个人是直性子，我考虑好了。”我没撒谎，我确实是直性子。嗨，先别管这个了。我说话的时候不但彬彬有礼，显出我是一个有教养的人，而且更重要的是，我说的话都不落俗套。我这么做不对吗？我是想评判一下自己，而且我也这么做了。赞成与反对[6]我都想说，我也这么说了。回想起当时的情况，我觉得很满意，虽然这看上去有点儿蠢：我当时直接表白，并不觉得这有什么不妥。首先我说，我没有什么过人的才能，也不太聪明，可能也不是太善良，而且我还是个非常庸俗的利己主义者（我记得这句话是在去她家的路上想出来的，当时觉得非常得意）。这些非常、非常有可能让我在其他人那里不受待见。说这些话的时候我觉得非常自豪——这种感觉你们都明白。当然咯，我还没有高尚到只坦白自己的缺点，不说优点的地步，我说：“但另一方面，我也有很多优点，如此这般，这般如此……”我发现，她这时依然很惊慌，但我并没有因为她的情绪而缓和语气；相反，看到她被吓到，我说得更直接了：我告诉她，我能让她吃喝不愁，但出席盛装舞会，去剧院听歌看戏，这些暂时还做不到，除非以后我能达到自己的目标。我缓了缓，接着说，显得随意的样子，我干这一行，开这个当铺，只有一个目的，就是……我似乎有些话中有话。但我有权这么说啊，我确实有自己的目标，但也确实有隐情。稍等，先生们，要知道，我一辈子都厌恶我那个当铺，这方面谁能比得过我，虽然自言自语的时候还故弄玄虚确实有点儿可笑，但我实质上就是在“报复社会”啊，千真万确！所以，她早上嘲笑我“报复”的那句俏皮话并不是不恰当。你们看出来了吧，要是我直接对她说“对，我就是在报复社会”，估计她会哈哈大笑，就像她那天早上一样，不过这也确实可笑。但用一句神秘兮兮的话来进行间接暗示，确实能激发想象力。况且，当时我也什么都不怕了：我知道，无论在哪方面，她都更厌恶那个胖老板，而出现在大门口的我，简直就如同救星一般。这一点我当然明白。唉，人更容易理解那些卑鄙的事！但哪些事是卑鄙的呢？如何去评判一个人呢？那时候我不是已经爱上她了吗？

别急，我还没说完……那个时候我当然不会说什么我有恩于她的话，半句都不会有；相反，我当时说的是：“是我，我是那个蒙恩之人，而不是您。”我本来不应该这么说，但没控制住，可能这句话听上去有点儿蠢，因为我注意到她皱了皱眉头。但总的来说，我还是如愿以偿。好吧，既然我把这些肮脏的事情都讲了，那就干脆把我那最后一丁点儿龌龊行为也告诉你们吧：我站在那里，脑子里冒出一句话——你身材高挑又匀称，还受过教育……还有……长相也不难看。这就是当时我脑子里想的。当然咯，最后她在大门口答应了我。不过……不过我还得说一句：她在门口想了好久才说“好”。她就在那儿想啊想……想得太久了，我真想问一句：“喂，你怎么想的？”当然，我最后还是没忍住，但很优雅地问了一句：“小姐，您意下如何？”

“等一下，让我想想。”

她那张小脸儿是那么严肃，严肃到我都能读懂她在想什么！我当时有种被冒犯的感觉，我想：“难道她还要在我和那个老板之间进行选择吗？”唉，那时候我还不明白！那时候我真是一点儿都不明白！直到现在我也不明白！我记得，我转身离开后，卢克里娅在后面追了上来，在街上拦住我，气喘吁吁地说：“先生，您要是能娶了我们家这位好小姐，上帝会保佑您的，只是您别和她这么说，她就是太清高了。”

哦，清高！我就喜欢清高的人。清高的人特别好，只要……嗯……只要你能镇得住她们，是吧？唉，我这低贱又愚蠢的人啊！我这是多么地小人得志啊！当初她站在大门口犹豫着是否答应求婚时，我还挺奇怪的，可你们知道吗，说不定那时她就在想：“既然怎么选择都是不幸的，那还不如干脆就选那个最差的，那个胖老板，让他喝多了赶紧把我打死算了！”你们说呢？你们是怎么想的，她有过这样的念头吗？

我现在还是不明白，我现在什么都不明白！我刚刚说她可能想选择最差的，就是说，那个老板。但是那个时候对于她来说，谁才是最坏的选择——我，还是他？是杂货店的胖老板，还是读过歌德的当铺掌柜？这也是一个问题！这是什么问题？看看吧，答案不就在桌子上躺着嘛，你还在想什么“问题”呢！其实我没那么重要！问题也完全不在于我……况且，现在对于我来说，问题是不是出自我这里又有什么意义呢？我根本就解决不了这个问题。还是躺下睡觉吧。我的头好疼……

3.最高贵的人，但我自己却不相信

我没睡着，感觉脑子里有东西一跳一跳的，就像脉搏那样。我想把这一切肮脏的事情弄明白。唉，这些事啊！唉，是我把她从那肮脏的烂泥里拉出来的啊！她应该明白的，她应该对我感激不尽啊！我喜欢我脑子里的各种想法，例如我已经四十一岁了，而她才十六岁。这种差距感让我着迷，多么幸福，多么甜蜜啊。

再比如说，我想举办一场英式[7]婚礼，只有我们两个人，再加上两个证婚人，其中一个应该是卢克里娅，婚礼结束我们就立刻跳上火车，可以去莫斯科（正好我在那儿有事要办），订一家旅馆，在那儿住上两个星期。但她不同意这个想法，她也不让我这么做。她要我恭恭敬敬地去见她两个姨妈，就像见岳父母那样，然后从她们那里把她娶走。好吧，我妥协了，她那两个姨妈也拿到了应得的东西。我甚至还给了那两个娘儿们每人一百卢布，还做了些承诺。当然，这件事我没有告诉她，以免她为自己曾经的处境而难过。姨妈们拿了钱立刻变得服服帖帖。在嫁妆问题上还是有些争议的：她几乎是一无所有，但她什么都不想要。不过我还是成功地说服她，一点儿嫁妆都没有是不行的，嫁妆可以由我来准备，因为还有谁能给她置办嫁妆呢？好，先不说我了。当时我把我的很多想法都跟她讲了，至少让她心里有个数。这么做可能有点儿操之过急了。但更重要的是，从求婚成功的那一刻开始，虽然她表面上依旧矜持，但却已满怀爱意地投入我的怀抱了。每次傍晚时分我去看她时，她总是兴高采烈地接待我，少女呢喃般地和我聊天，（多么迷人的天真啊！）讲她小时候的事，讲她老家，讲她父亲和母亲。而我却给她的愉悦浇了一盆冷水。我是故意那样做的。我用沉默，一种善意的沉默来回应她的欣喜，当然……她很快就看懂了，我和她不太一样，我就是一个谜。对，我就是打算要做那个谜！但我这谜面设得是多么愚蠢啊！首先，我太严肃了，严肃地把她娶回了家。虽然我心满意足，但还是定下了一套规矩。这事我做得毫不费力，这规矩是多么天经地义啊！退一步讲，考虑当时的情况，这规矩我能不定吗？这规矩理所应当，我没必要诋毁自己啊！不，听我说，如果你要评判一个人，就要把事情的来龙去脉搞清楚……别说话！

从何说起呢，这事也挺复杂的。而且，当你要开始自我辩护时，就更难了。你们知道，年轻人都鄙视金钱，但我不一样，我更重视金钱，也追逐金钱，这使她变得越来越沉默。她睁着那双大眼睛，看着、听着、沉默着。你们也知道，优秀的年轻人都道德高尚，又充满激情，但有时候不够宽容，一言不合就怒目相对。而我认为，年轻人应该更加开朗豁达，我要让她有海纳百川的心胸，对不对？举个通俗点儿的例子吧，比如说，我是怎么描述我那个当铺的呢？我当然不会直接描述个没完，那样的话，好像我是在请求别人原谅似的。我说过，我为人清高，我用沉默来讲述。我善于通过沉默的方式来表达自己，来讲述我的生活，讲述我承受的种种不幸。我是多么不幸啊！我被大家抛弃，我被人们遗忘，这一切又有谁能理解呢！然而，这个十六岁的姑娘从一些小人那里捕风捉影，听到了一些关于我的事情，她就以为掌握了我的全部情况，但隐情只能藏在这个人的心里！我仍然保持沉默，特别是在她面前，直到昨天——我为什么要沉默呢？因为我是一个清高的人啊！我希望她能够自己去了解这个人，不要来问我，也不要听那些小人的胡言乱语，她应该自己来读懂他，真正地理解他！既然我把她娶进家门，就希望她能充分尊重我。我希望她能为我的痛苦祈祷——这是我应得的。我总是这样清高，要么拥有一切，否则什么都不想要。这就是我无法与人分享幸福的原因，我要完全占有，这也正是为何我要强迫自己如此表现的原因：让她自己来读懂我、尊重我！你们也一定会同意我的想法，如果我自己去跟她解释，然后吞吞吐吐地暗示她要尊重我，这难道不就是在乞求施舍吗……可是……可是，我干吗要说这个呀！

愚蠢、愚蠢、愚蠢，太愚蠢了！我当时对她说的那几句话简直是直截了当且残酷无情（再怎么强调也不为过）：年轻人志向高远，这很好，但它一文不值。为什么这么说呢？因为“志向高远”太容易做到了，它并非来自生活的打磨，而只是“生命的第一印象”，但让我们看看你都做了些什么事？廉价的志向似乎让一切事情看起来都很容易做到，甚至连献出生命也变得很容易了。因为那只是你热血沸腾、精力旺盛，又充满对美的渴望！不信的话，你们可以尝试去做一件高尚的、艰难的、无声无息的事情，它无人喝彩，却有人诽谤，要做出巨大牺牲，又得不到一点儿荣誉。而且当一个光明磊落的人这么做时，当你是这个世界上最真诚的人时，大家将你视为卑鄙下流之徒。您可以试试看，不，我的小姐，您会拒绝的！而我，我就是这么做的，我一辈子都在这样高尚行事。一开始，她还和我激烈争论，但后来就渐渐不作声了，一言不发，只是瞪大了眼睛在那里听着，全神贯注，眼睛越瞪越大。而且……而且我还突然发现她脸上浮现出一丝质疑、冷漠、不怀好意的微笑。这种微笑在我娶她进门的那天也见过。的确，她那时也是无处可去……

4.计划，全是计划

当初我们俩是谁先开始的？

谁都没有。是这件事自己迈出的第一步。我说过，我娶她进门时很严肃，但其实从一开始我就有所和缓了。她还是我未婚妻的时候，我就对她说过，以后要帮我打理当铺生意，由她来收抵押物和付款，她当时什么也没说（这里提醒大家注意），而且工作起来也是满怀热情。还有，我们的房子和家具也都没有变化，和从前一样。房子有两个房间：一间是前厅，很宽敞，跟当铺柜台是隔开的；另一间是我们的房间，做起居室和卧室，也很大。我的家具很少，甚至还没有她姨妈家的多。我的神龛和神灯放在当铺里；我们的房间里有一个橱柜，里面有一些书，有一个小箱子，钥匙在我这儿；房间里还有一张床，几张桌子和几把椅子。她还是我未婚妻时，我就说过，我要在三年内攒到三万卢布，我、她和卢克里娅（我把她也带过来了），我们每天包括生活费在内的花销不能超过一卢布，否则的话是攒不到这个数的。她不反对，但后来我又把每天的花销标准提高了三十戈比。还有剧院的事。她是我未婚妻的时候我就说过，我们是不会去剧院看戏的，不过后来我还是决定，每个月去一次，而且是预订更体面的池座。我们一起去过三次，看的好像是《追求幸福》和《会唱歌的小鸟》。（这个无所谓！）我们来去的路上都沉默不语。为什么，为什么我们一开始就是这样？要知道，我们刚开始生活时并没有吵过架，但依然是相对无言。我记得，她那时总是偷偷看我，可她越是这样，我就越加沉默。是的，保持沉默的是我，而不是她。她有那么一两次激情迸发，扑过来拥抱我；但我认为这种情绪是病态的，歇斯底里的，我想要的是稳定的幸福，要的是她的尊重，所以我冷漠地回应了她。我的判断没错，每次她激情过后，第二天就是一顿争吵。

要想不争吵，那就只有彼此保持沉默了，但她的样子却越来越放肆。“叛逆与独立”——这大概就是她想要的，只不过她不知道应该如何表现出来。是的，这张温顺的脸变得越来越放肆了。你们相信吗，我在她眼里变得越来越可恶了，这一点我当然清楚。她有时也会为此情绪爆发，这也是自然而然的事。例如，像她这种刚刚摆脱肮脏与贫贱的生活，不需要再刷地板的人，有时竟会突然抱怨起我们太穷了！您知道吗，这不是贫穷，这是节俭，我们的家饰，哪样不是又高级又整洁？因为我以前一直认为，丈夫整洁更能讨妻子欢心。不过，她抱怨的似乎不是贫穷，而是嫌弃我太吝啬了，她仿佛想说的是：“人家可是有坚定目标的。”她突然不再去剧院了，脸上也越来越多嘲讽的神情……而我则继续沉默，更加沉默。

我怎么可以为自己辩解呢？主要的问题是我那个当铺。这么说吧，先生们：我知道，作为一个女人，而且是一个十六岁的姑娘，不可能完全不屈从于男人的意志。女性缺乏独立的见解，这是最简单不过的道理，即使是现在，即使是对于现在的我来说，它都是千真万确的。她就在那儿，躺在前厅里，那又怎样呢，真理就是真理，即便是密尔[8]本人在这里，他也不能否认这一点！一个被爱情冲昏了头脑的女人，唉，这种女人会把她所爱的人加以神化，神化他的缺陷，甚至是他的罪恶。她为他的恶行所找的借口，他自己是想不出来的。这是女人的宽容与豁达，并不是什么独立见解。缺少独立见解只会毁掉女人。你们指给我看那个躺在桌子上的人吗？我再重复一遍，“那又怎样呢？”难道那就是有独立见解的体现吗？唉！

听我说：那时候我坚信她是爱我的。她有时候会扑到我身上，抱住我的脖子。她爱我，更准确地说是——她希望爱我。不错，当时的确就是这样：她希望爱我，努力尝试着来爱我。更重要的是，我身上没有任何罪恶需要她来找理由为之辩护。当然，你们会说“你是个当铺掌柜”，你们所有人都会这么说。当铺掌柜又怎么了？这只能说明，一定有某种原因，让一个心胸最为坦荡的人成了当铺掌柜。你们瞧，先生们，有些想法……你们知道，有些想法如果用语言能够表达出来，那听上去会是非常愚蠢的。那会让你自己都感到害臊。为什么呢？不为什么。因为我们所有人都烂透了，我们不愿接受真理，如果这都不是原因的话，那我就真不知道了。我刚才说过的那句“心胸最为坦荡的人”听上去有点儿可笑，但事实就是这样的。要知道，这就是真理，千真万确的道理。那个时候我有权开这个当铺给自己的生活提供一个保障，是的，我这么做：“你们，就是你们，你们全都排斥我，用你们那轻蔑的沉默驱赶我。我对你们满腔热忱，而你们却用对我的羞辱来回应。现在我要和你们一刀两断，我有权这么做，我会攒够三万卢布，去克里米亚终老一生：在南方的海岸边，在山脚的葡萄园，在我自己购买的宅邸中。最重要的是，这能让我远离你们这些人，但我不会怨恨你们，我的灵魂中长存信念，我的心中有挚爱的伴侣，如果上帝赐福，我还会有一个家庭，还要去帮助周围的邻人。”我把这些想法说给自己听是好的，如果当初把这些都绘声绘色地给她描述一遍的话，那就太愚蠢了。这也正是我一直保持清高与沉默，又同她相对无言的原因所在。她怎么会明白我的理想呢？她只有十六岁，如此年轻，我的辩白、我的痛苦，她又能理解多少呢？她鲁莽，不懂生活，拥有年轻人那种廉价的信念，反而对“美好心灵”视而不见，更重要的是——我的当铺，够了！（难道我是个开当铺的恶人吗，难道她不了解我的为人吗，我取过不义之财吗？）啊，世上的真理是多么可怕！这个女人迷人、温顺，如天使一般圣洁，但她却是个暴君，让人无法忍受的暴君，奴役并折磨着我的灵魂。我必须要这么说，否则我就是在诋毁自己！你们认为我不爱她吗？谁能说我不爱她？你们看到了吧，这就是一种嘲弄，是来自命运和造化的恶意嘲弄！我们都是被诅咒的，人类的生命被诅咒了！（特别是我！）我现在终于知道了我错在何处！这里的确存在问题。一切都已明朗，我的计划就像天空一样清晰：“刚毅、高傲，不需要任何道德上的慰藉，默默地承受苦难。”事实如此，我没有撒谎，我没有撒谎！“她以后会明白，这就是宽宏大量，但现在她还不具备读懂这一切的能力——如果未来某一天她能醒悟的话，她将会倍加珍惜我，双膝跪地，对我顶礼膜拜。”这就是我的计划。这里我好像忘了什么东西，或是漏掉了其中一项。有什么事情我没能做成，但够了，已经足够完美了。现在还需要请求别人的谅解吗？都结束了。你勇敢一点儿，不要低头！不是你的错！……

好吧，我要实话实说，我不害怕面对真相：是她的错，她的错！……

5.温顺的女人反叛了

我们之间的争吵源于她一时兴起，竟然要自己决定付给客人多少钱，而且还高估抵押物的价值，甚至有那么两次还赏脸和我争论起这个问题。我自然是不会同意她那么做。但就在这时，来了一位上尉的遗孀。

老太太拿来了一个吊坠——是她已故丈夫留下的礼物，一看就是件纪念品。我付了她三十卢布。她一边诉着苦，一边央求我们要保管好这东西——我们当然会好好保管咯。但五天后，她又突然回来，想用一个八卢布都不值的手镯把吊坠换回去；我当然是不会同意了。不过她当时可能从我妻子的眼神中看出了什么，后来趁我不在时又来了，换走了吊坠。

我知道这事后，说了她几句，给她讲了这其中的道理，语气温和，但又不失严厉。她坐在床边，眼睛盯着地板，右脚尖敲打着地毯（她习惯的姿势），嘴角边挂着一丝坏笑。我没有提高嗓门，依然心平气和地对她讲，钱是我的，我有权从自己的角度来看待生活；我还告诉她，当初我把她娶进家门时，就没对她隐瞒什么。

她突然跳了起来，浑身颤抖——你们猜怎么着——她居然在我面前跺脚；这是头野兽，这是在发作，这是兽性的发作。我惊呆了，从没想到她会做出这样出格的举动。但我没有失态，我甚至都没有动，依然如往常一样，心平气和地对她讲，从今以后不许她再参与当铺的生意了。她冲我哈哈大笑，走出了家门。

事实上，她无权离开这间公寓。她还是我未婚妻时，我就和她定好了规矩，没有我，她哪也不许去。傍晚时分，她回来了；我一句话也没和她说。

第二天一大早，她又离开了，第三天也是这样。我关了当铺，去她姨妈那儿找她。婚礼结束后我就和她们断了联系——再也没有互相来往过。但她并不在那里。她们好奇地听着我讲的事，然后还当面嘲笑我：“您这就是活该了。”对此我并不感到意外。我私下里买通了二姨妈，就是那个老处女，答应给她一百卢布，先付二十五。两天后，她来到我家，告诉我：“我听说有一个中尉军官，叶菲莫维奇，过去和您在一个团里服役，他和你们的事有牵连。”我大吃一惊。在军队服役的时候，这个叶菲莫维奇就把我害得够惨。一个月前，他还以当东西为名，恬不知耻地来过我这儿几次，那时他就开始和我妻子有说有笑。我当时就过去警告他，不要再到我当铺来了，还提醒他我和我妻子之间的关系；但我从来没想过会发生这种事，我仅仅以为这人就是个无赖。现在她姨妈突然告诉我，他们早就见过面了，从中撮合的是一个叫尤莉娅·萨姆索诺夫娜的寡妇，曾是一位上校的夫人，是姨妈们从前的老相识。“您家那位太太现在应该就在她那儿。”她说。

长话短说。我为这事儿一共花了三百卢布，两天之内已经做好了安排，我会在隔壁房间虚掩的门后，听我妻子和叶菲莫维奇的第一次单独约会[9]。但在这前一天的晚上，我和她发生了一次小争吵，这对我来说意义重大。

临近傍晚，她回来了，坐在床边，用略带嘲弄的眼神看着我，一只脚敲着地毯。我看着她，突然想起来一件事，在最近整整一个月里，更准确地说是最近的两个星期，她的性格发生了很大变化，甚至可以说完全变了一个人——一反常态：脾气暴躁，无理取闹，行为虽谈不上不知羞耻，但也是毫无规矩，而且还有意挑衅。但她温顺的本性还是会在她想变本加厉的时候妨碍到她。她胡搅蛮缠的时候，即使行为再出格，也明显能看得出，她是在有意逼迫自己这样做，天生的纯良品性让她无法克服自己行为本身带来的羞耻感。也正因如此，这样的人有时会控制不住自己行为的尺度，她们的越轨行为可能让你无法相信自己看到的一切。反倒是那些骨子里荒淫无度的人，常常表现得温文尔雅，这种人越是做坏事，就越表现得循规蹈矩、彬彬有礼，而且在别人面前总觉得高人一筹。

“您被军队开除，是因为您不敢和别人决斗，是吗？”她突然问道，眼里还闪闪发光。

“是的，按照长官们的裁决，我必须离开军队，不过，在这之前我就已经递交了退伍申请。”

“是因为贪生怕死才被赶出来的吗？”

“他们是这么认为的。但我拒绝决斗不是因为贪生怕死，而是不愿意屈从那些专横的裁决，我当时并没有觉得自己受辱。您要明白，”说着说着，我有点儿激动，“用行动来反抗专横，并承担一切后果——这要比任何决斗都更需要勇气。”

她又不怀好意地笑了。我有点儿控制不住自己了，这句话好像是在为自己辩解，而她这么做只是想变本加厉地羞辱我。

“之后这三年您就像个流浪汉一样在彼得堡大街上游荡，讨点儿小钱，然后在台球桌下过夜，是吗？”

“实际上我甚至经常在干草广场的维亚泽姆斯基大院[10]过夜。的确，是真的，退伍后我的生活就是那样的，饱尝羞辱，也堕落过，但不是道德上的堕落，因为那个时候连我自己都很厌恶我的所作所为。其实这只是意志和心灵的颓废，是对当时处境的绝望。但这一切都过去了……”

“哦，现在您是个大人物了——是个金融家啦！”

这是在说我的当铺。但我已经冷静下来了。我知道，她非常想让我亲口说出一些自取其辱的话，但我没有给她这个机会。这时，有人摇响了当铺的铃铛，我去了前厅招呼客人。一个小时后，她突然穿戴好准备出门，还在我面前说：

“您结婚前从来没对我说过这些，对吧？”

见我没回应，她就走了。

于是第二天，我站到了那房间的门后，揣着一把左轮手枪，听一听我的命运将如何做出安排。她打扮得漂漂亮亮，坐在桌子旁，叶菲莫维奇坐在她对面，装腔作势。虽然之前我没意识到自己有什么预感，但事情还是和我的事先判断丝毫不差（这里要夸奖一下我自己）。我不知道，我说明白了没有。

事情经过就是这样。我听了整整一个小时，在这一个小时里，我仿佛见证了一位世界上最高贵的女性和一个庸俗的、堕落的、愚蠢的、灵魂卑微的无耻之徒间的决斗。我非常惊讶，我想，这个天真、温顺、沉默寡言的女人是从哪里学会这些话的？上流社会最有幽默感的喜剧作家恐怕都创作不出那种极具讽刺效果的剧本，里面充满了天真无邪的大笑与美德对丑恶的神圣鄙视。她说出的词句是多么华丽，敏捷的回应是多么机智，她的责备声中又饱含着多少真理啊！即便如此，她的话语里也完全不失少女的纯真。她嘲笑他的爱情表白，嘲笑他的腔调，嘲笑他的求婚。他没预料到她会抗拒，因此一上来就表现得十分鲁莽，这下他完全呆住了。起初我还认为，她就是在那儿卖弄风情——“这种行为虽然放荡，但能显得她俏皮可爱，这样可以提高她自己的身价。”但事实并非如此，真相就如同太阳的光芒一样，让猜忌无处容身。她的心智还没有完全成熟，决定赴这次约会只是出于对我的怨恨，突发奇想，有意为之。不过一旦事情开始，她就会立刻清醒过来。她苦思冥想，就是要找出一个能羞辱我的方法来，但真要开始做那种龌龊事时，她又忍受不了。如她这般纯洁无邪又充满理想的人，真的能被叶菲莫维奇或其他上流社会的无耻之徒引诱吗？绝无可能，他只能让她发笑。真理会从她的心灵中涌现，愤怒会激起她发自心底的嘲讽。我再说说当时的情况，那个跳梁小丑最后十分尴尬，皱着眉头坐在那里，几乎一句话也说不出来，以至于我有点儿担心，他会不会出于卑鄙的报复心理去直接羞辱她一番。我还要补充一下：我内心毫无波澜地听完了这场戏，我的表现还不赖。这场面我仿佛似曾相识，我去的原因似乎也正是要重温这一场景。我虽然带了一把枪，但我什么都不相信，什么说辞都不想听——这是真的！我怎么能把她想象成另外一种样子呢？我为什么爱她，我为什么欣赏她，我为什么要和她结婚？当然，那个时候我太执迷不悟了，认为她讨厌我，但我也坚信她是贞洁的。我终止了这场表演，推门走了进去。叶菲莫维奇吓了一跳，我抓住她的手，请求她和我回去。叶菲莫维奇回过神来，高声大笑。

“啊，我不能侵犯神圣的夫权，带她走吧，带她走吧！您知道，”他在我身后喊，“虽然一个正派的人不应该和您决斗，但看在您夫人的面子上，如果您自己愿意冒险尝试……我一定奉陪……”

“听见了吧！”在出门的一刹那我叫住她说道。

回家的路上我们一句话都没说。我挽着她的手，她并没有拒绝。相反地，她看上去有些惊慌，但这也只是在回家的路上。回家后，她就坐在椅子上盯着我看。她面色十分苍白，虽然略带嘲讽地抿着嘴唇，但眼神中已然带着一股郑重其事的挑战意味。似乎她真的相信，我马上会用左轮枪打死她。但我只是默默地从口袋中取出枪，放在了桌子上。她看了看我，又看了看枪。（请注意：她对这把枪并不陌生。当铺刚开张的时候，我就买了这把枪，装好了子弹。从准备开当铺时起，我就决定不养烈性犬，不雇像莫泽尔家的那种壮丁。如果家里有客人来，厨娘会去开门。但是干我们这一行的是不可能不有所防备的，所以我买了这支左轮枪，装上了子弹。她刚嫁到我家时，对这把枪非常感兴趣，缠着我问这问那，我甚至给她讲解了枪的原理和构造，而且还说服她做了一次打靶射击。请注意我说的这些。）我没理会她惊恐的神情，脱了外衣躺在床上，我感到筋疲力尽。已经将近十一点了，她还坐在那里一动不动，大约又过了一个小时，她熄了灯，没脱衣服，躺在了墙边的沙发上。这是她第一次没有和我一起睡——这也应该注意。

6.可怕的回忆

现在来说一说这段可怕的回忆吧……

我早上醒来时，大概不到八点，房间里早已大亮。我一下子清醒过来，猛地睁开双眼。她当时就站在桌子旁边，手里握着枪。她没注意到我已经醒了，而且还在看着她。我突然发现，她拿着枪朝我走了过来。我赶紧闭上眼，假装熟睡。

我听见她走到床边，站在那里。此时我什么都听见了，虽然房间里一片死寂，但我却能听到这寂静的声音。我突然抽搐了一下，不由自主地睁开了眼睛。她直勾勾地盯着我，看着我的眼睛，左轮枪已经指向了我的太阳穴。刹那间我们四目相对，但很快又移开了眼神。我竭尽全力把眼睛重新闭上，在那一瞬间，我下定决心，不论发生什么，我都不会动，也不会睁开眼睛。

在一般情况下，一个熟睡的人突然睁开眼睛，甚至抬起头看了一眼房间，然后又马上睡过去，这一过程应该是完全无意识的，他什么都不会记住。我和她四目相对，感觉到枪指着我的太阳穴，然后又突然闭上眼睛，一动不动，如同熟睡一样——她一定会认为，我实际上根本没醒过来，什么也没看到。而且，如果一个人看到了当时我眼前的情形，还能那样重新闭上眼睛，是完全不可思议的事。

这的确不可思议。但她可能还是弄不明白，这到底是怎么回事——其实，这就是当时我脑中瞬间闪现的念头。啊，在那一刹那，我脑中的想法和感受如旋风般疾驰而过，如闪电般的人类思维是多么伟大！面对这种情况（我切身感受到的），如果她能认识到我当时已经清醒的话，那么我这种从容赴死的勇气一定会让她感到无比震撼，她的手可能仍旧在发抖。这种非凡的印象可能会改变一个人过去的决断。有这样一种说法，人们站在高处时，总会感觉到好像有一股力量在把他们向下拉，拉向深渊。我想，很多自杀或杀死别人的人完全就是因为他们有枪在手。无底深渊也好，四十五度的斜坡也罢，人们站在这上面不可能不向下滑落，就如同你手中拿着枪，总会有某种不可阻挡的力量促使你扣动扳机。但也许她当时已经意识到，我看见了她在做什么，也意识到我是清醒的，我是在默默等待死亡的到来——正是这种意识阻止了她继续滑向深渊。

房间里的寂静仍在蔓延，而我却突然感觉到一个冰冷的铁器碰触到了我的鬓发，你们会问：当时我真的认为自己不会死吗？上帝见证，我要告诉你们：那一刻我真的不抱任何希望，除非有奇迹发生。我为什么要接受死亡？我也要问问你们：我挚爱的人举着左轮枪对着我，即使她不开枪，我之后的人生还有什么意义？而且，我非常了解我这个人，我知道，那一瞬间，我们是在进行一场战斗，是关乎生死的一场可怕对决，其中一方正是那个被视为懦夫，被赶出军队的人。这一点我很清楚，而且，如果她能看出来我当时并没睡着的话，那么她也会明白的。

可能实际情况并非完全如此，也有可能我当时并不是那样想的，但即使我没有那样想，那一刻发生的事也确实是存在的，因为日后我还能经常回想起当时做的那一切。

可你们还会问：为什么你没有把她从罪恶中拯救出来？是啊，我也不断地问自己这个问题——每次一想起那一刻，我就脊背发凉。但那时我的灵魂已深陷绝望之中：如果连我自己都死了，我还能拯救谁？你们凭什么说，我那时还能想到拯救别人？你们怎么会知道我当时的感受？

那一刻，我思绪翻腾。时间在一秒秒地流逝，房间里依然一片死寂。我感觉她一直站在我旁边——过了一会儿，心底的一丝希望让我突然浑身一颤！我马上睁开眼睛。她已经不在房间里了。我从床上坐起来：我赢了——她永远被我征服了！

我起床去喝茶。我们家的茶炊总是放在前屋，每次都是由她来斟茶。我默默地坐到桌边，从她手里接过一杯茶。五分钟后，我看了她一眼。她面色十分苍白，甚至比昨天还要严重。她也在看着我。突然，突然间——当她发现我看她时，苍白的嘴唇间露出冷冷的一笑，怯生生的眼神里似乎充满了疑问。她好像还是拿不准刚才发生的事，并在问自己：他到底是知道还是不知道，看见还是没看见？我不动声色地避开了她的眼神。喝完茶后，我关了当铺，去市场上买了张铁床和一扇屏风。回家后，我吩咐把床放在前厅里，用屏风把它围上。床是给她买的，但我并没和她说什么。看到这张床，不用说她也应该明白，我“都看见了，也都知道了”，她也不用再猜疑了。晚上我照旧把左轮枪放在桌子上，她也一声不响地睡到了自己的新床上。婚姻关系解除了，“她被征服了，但没得到宽恕”。夜里她不断呓语，第二天早上热病发作，卧床了六个星期。

[3]一种产自意大利那不勒斯的高级绸缎，价格昂贵，质地优良。

[4]1卢布等于100戈比。

[5]歌德巨著《浮士德》中引诱浮士德怠惰满足的魔鬼。

[6]原文为拉丁语。

[7]此处原文为法语。

[8]约翰·斯图亚特·密尔（旧译约翰·斯图亚特·穆勒，1806—1873），19世纪英国著名自由主义思想家。

[9]原文为法语。

[10]19世纪彼得堡市一个收容底层市民的场所。

二

1.高傲的梦

卢克里娅刚才跟我说，等太太下葬后，她不想继续在我这儿待着了，她也准备走。我已经跪着祷告五分钟了，我原本打算祷告一个小时，但我脑子里一直安静不下来，一直在想各种各样的问题，全是些病态的想法，想得我头疼——在这里祈祷有什么用呢？只不过是个罪过！说来也奇怪，我竟然不想睡觉：一般说来，人在极度悲伤的情况下，特别是在经历了最初的强烈刺激后，总是想睡觉。据说，被判处死刑的人在行刑前夜会睡得非常踏实。这也可以理解，符合人的本性，否则的话那人是熬不住的……我躺在沙发上，但睡不着……

在她生病的六个星期里，我雇了一位受过专业训练的助理护士，加上我和卢克里娅，我们三人日夜照料她。我不心疼钱，甚至想在她身上多花一点儿。我请来的施罗德医生每次的出诊费是十卢布。她清醒过来后，我就很少出现在她面前了。我说这些干吗呢？基本康复后，她就常常坐在我房间里一张专门为她买的桌子旁，一言不发……是的，我们俩基本上不说话；后来才慢慢开始有了些交流，但也仅限于一些日常杂事。我当然是有意不去多说话的，但我很清楚，不用和我说过多的废话让她也很高兴。我认为，她的这些表现都是很正常的：毕竟她受到了极大的震撼，又在和我的斗争中惨败。但我认为，她需要时间去忘记这些事，而且要习惯现在的这种状态。因此，我们就这样彼此保持着沉默，但我时时刻刻都在为自己的未来做着准备。我想她应该也是如此吧，那个时候我最大的兴趣就是猜测她的想法，猜测她心里是怎么看我的。

还有……唉，你们谁也想不到，我为她的病忍受了多少折磨。但所有的一切我都只在内心默默承受，从未表露过，甚至连卢克里娅都察觉不到。我无法想象，甚至不敢去假设，她在一无所知的情况下死去会是种什么情形。在她脱离危险、逐渐康复后，我知道，我也会很快平静下来。而且，我想让现在的状态暂时维持下去，我们的未来终会降临，但我想尽量把它推后。的确，当时我的心理状态有点儿奇怪，总有种特别的感觉……这么说吧，我觉得我胜利了，对于我来说，只要一想到这件事，我就十分满足。整个冬天就这么过去了。而我，从来没有像这个冬天那样，觉得一切如此完美。

你们要知道，在我妻子的惨剧发生前，我的人生中还有过一次可怕的经历——被迫从军队退役，这件事无时无刻不在困扰我，使我声誉受损。总之，我受到了蛮横无理的对待。是的，我的同事们不喜欢我，他们认为我性格阴郁，甚至有些可笑。事情往往就是这样的，有些东西您觉得它是高尚的，值得尊重，您把它深藏心底，但不知为什么，这竟会让有些人发笑。是啊，人们从来都不喜欢我，甚至在学校里就是这样。我总是处处不受欢迎。连卢克里娅都不喜欢我。在团里服役时，有件事可以证明我不受欢迎，虽然它是偶然发生的。有的时候厄运会像飘来的浮云一样凑到一块儿，可能发生也可能不发生的意外都会让一个人毁掉，没有什么事比这更令人反感和难以接受的了。对于一个睿智的人来说，这简直就是有辱尊严。事情的经过是这样的：

有一次我去剧院看戏，幕间休息时去了趟茶点部。这时一个叫阿×的骠骑兵突然走了进来，当着在场军官和其他观众的面，对另外两个骠骑兵大声说，我们团的别祖姆采夫上尉刚才在走廊里大吵大闹，“好像是喝多了”。他们的交谈没了下文，说的也不是真事，别祖姆采夫上尉并没有喝多，也没像他说的那样大吵大闹。几个骠骑兵又闲聊了几句，然后就走了。但第二天，这事传到了我们团里，立刻有人说，当时我们团在茶点部的只有我一人，而且骠骑兵阿×在污蔑别祖姆采夫上尉时，我也没有上去制止他。可我为什么要那样做呢？如果他对别祖姆采夫有恶意的话，那也是他们之间的私事，我干吗要蹚这浑水呢？但军官们认为，这并非只是私人恩怨，而是牵涉到了我们团，因为当时团里的军官中只有我一人在场。我的做法就等于在向其他军官和观众们证明，我们团里可能有军官不重视自己和团队的荣誉。我不同意这样的定论。有人告诉我，虽然现在有点儿晚了，但还是有机会补救的，只要我正式向阿×解释清楚当时的情况就可以了。我不想这么做，而且觉得很气愤，所以就一口回绝了。不久之后，我就退役，离开了军队。这就是事情的整个经过。我高傲地离开，但心理却崩溃了。之后便一蹶不振。恰巧这时，我在莫斯科的姐夫挥霍掉了我们本就不多的财产，其中也包括我的那一小份，致使我身无分文，流落街头。我本可以在私人机构谋个职位，但我没那样做：脱下闪亮的军装，我不想随便到铁路上的什么地方去工作。就这样吧，羞愧、耻辱、堕落，要来就来吧，越坏越好——这就是我当时的选择。种种幽暗的记忆与维亚泽姆斯基大院，填满了我接下来三年的生活。一年半之前，我的教母，一位有钱的老妇人，在莫斯科去世了，有些意外的是，在她的遗嘱中有三千卢布是留给我的。经过一番考虑，我做出了改变自己命运的决定。我打算开一家当铺，这并不需要别人的理解：等赚够了钱，我会去找一个能安身的角落，开始新的生活，远离从前的记忆——这就是我的计划。然而，那段黑暗的往事和永远洗刷不清的羞辱却在时时刻刻折磨着我。后来我结婚了，这是不是偶然的事情——我也不知道。但娶她进家门时，我想，我是给自己找了一位朋友，我太需要朋友了。但我也清楚，朋友间是需要磨合的，甚至是需要征服的。我能立刻向这位对我抱有成见的十六岁姑娘解释清楚所有事情吗？比如说，如果没有那次可怕的“左轮枪事件”，我能使她相信，我并非懦夫，被军队除名也是不公正的吗？但这件事来得是多么及时啊！在经受住了左轮枪的考验后，我彻底洗刷掉了那段屈辱与黑暗的历史。虽然不会有人知道这些故事，但只要她能明白就够了，这对我来说就是一切，因为她对于我来说就是一切，是我理想中未来的全部希望所在。她是我唯一想要的人，不需要别人了——她应该是都懂了，至少她清楚，投奔我的敌人对我来说是不公平的。这种想法让我无比欣慰。她现在可能还会觉得我是个怪人，但起码不会再认为我是个卑鄙下流之徒了。而且，经历了这一切之后，我更加认同：性格古怪并不是缺点；相反，有时候它更能打动女性的心。总之，我是把这件事暂时放下了，并不急于去解决。我感觉自己非常平静，对于我的理想来说，有太多的图景和素材可以利用。我是个幻想家，但这也是我的问题所在：我总是在幻想自己的未来，但对她呢，再等等吧。

整个冬天就在某种期待中过去了。我喜欢悄悄地看着她坐在桌边的样子。她会做一些针线活儿，缝缝补补，晚上有时会从我柜子里拿一本书读读。我的藏书基本上可以证明我的品位和兴趣。她几乎哪也不去。每天午饭后或黄昏前，我会带她出去散步，做些户外运动，我们也不像从前那样互不说话了。我尽量做出我们相处和睦的样子，但正如我前面说过的，我们俩都不会让自己和对方过于亲近。我是有意这样做的，而她呢，我想，还是应该再“给她些时间吧”。让我感到奇怪的是，我自己竟然从来都没仔细想过这种情况。整个冬天里，我一直喜欢悄悄地看她，但直到冬天结束，她都没看过我一眼！我只是认为，她还是太羞怯了，而且病后的虚弱无力让她看上去更加腼腆温顺。不，最好还是再等等吧——“说不定她会突然自己走过来……”

这个想法总是让我兴奋不已。再补充一句：有时我好像是故意让自己这么激动，这似乎也让我完全受制于她。就这样又过了一段时间。我对她的怨恨并没有越积越深，也没有在心底根深蒂固。我自己感觉这就像一场游戏。不错，那个时候我是解除了婚姻关系，给她买了床和屏风，但我从来没把她当成一个有罪之人来看待啊。这并不是因为我对她的过错认识肤浅，而是因为从第一天起，甚至在买床之前，我就决定要宽恕她。这听起来确实有点儿奇怪，因为无论如何，在道德要求上，我是个很严格的人。然而，在我眼中，她已经被征服了，受到了应有的惩罚，精神彻底崩溃，虽然有时候我对她充满怜悯，但有时候也对这种结果感到非常满意。我很喜欢我们之间这种不平等的感觉……

这个冬天里，我有意做了几件善事。我免去了两笔应收的债务，还在没有任何抵押物的情况下，放了一些钱给一个贫穷的女人。我没把这些事告诉我妻子，我这么做也不是为了让她知道；但那个女人自己上门来道谢，就差没给我跪下了。这事传了出去，我想，她也应该很高兴我这么做吧。

春天马上就到了，已经是四月中旬了，双层窗户已经被拿掉，明媚的阳光照进了我们安静的房间。似乎曾有一块障眼布挡在我的眼前，蒙蔽了我的头脑。这致命又可怕的障眼布啊！但不知为什么，我眼前的遮蔽物突然落下了，瞬间一切都变得明朗起来，我恍然大悟！这一天的到来是偶然的吗，是注定的吗，是太阳的光芒让我愚钝的头脑瞬间开悟的吗？不，并不存在什么顿悟，而是那根筋脉，那根已经僵死了的筋脉突然间又跳动了起来，它摇晃着我沉寂的心灵和骇人的高傲，它们复活了，它们又放射出了光芒。我突然感觉到像是从地上跳起来一样。是的，它来得太突然，太出人意料。事情发生在那天下午五点钟，临近傍晚……

2.障眼布突然落下了

在这之前，我先交代两句。早在一个月之前，我就发现她经常莫名其妙地陷入沉思之中，注意，是沉思，不是沉默。我也是突然发现的。我看她的时候，她总是坐在那里低头缝纫，看也不看我一眼。有时她坐在那里的样子会突然让我感到惊讶，纤细、瘦弱、面色苍白，嘴唇也毫无血色，如果再加上她若有所思的神情，那可真是一幅让人震撼的画面。在这之前，我就常常在夜里听到她小声干咳。有一次，我又听到她在咳嗽，我没和她打招呼，马上起床去请施罗德医生过来。

施罗德是第二天来我家的。她惊讶地看了看医生，又看了看我。

她随即面无表情地冷笑着说：“我没生病。”

施罗德没有太仔细检查病情（这种医生总是端着架子，有时看病马马虎虎），只是把我叫到另一个房间，对我说，她这是大病初愈后的常见情况，春天时最好能去海边疗养一下，如果不行的话，去乡间休息一段时间也可以。总之，他也没说出什么来，就是告诉我，她现在身体虚弱，需要休息之类的。施罗德走后，她非常严肃地看着我，还是说：

“我真的一点儿病都没有。”

但说着说着，突然脸红了起来，很明显，她觉得很惭愧。不说我也明白：她之所以觉得惭愧，是因为她知道，我还是她的丈夫，仍然像个真正的丈夫那样在关心她。但当时我没能彻底看清的是，她脸上那一抹红晕可绝不是温顺与谦卑的象征。（那就是一块障眼布！）

就这样，一个月之后，在四月一个阳光明媚的下午，我在当铺里结账，她在房间里干着活儿。当时已经五点多了，我突然听见我们的房间里传出了歌声……是她，她在那儿轻声地唱了起来。这是我第一次听到她唱歌，以至于那歌声给我留下的深刻印象，到现在我都无法完全理解。在那之后我几乎没有听到她唱过歌了，除了她刚嫁到我家的时候，我们还有说有笑，有时候我们会用左轮枪去打靶。那个时候，她的声音还很响亮、清脆，虽然有时忽高忽低，但非常悦耳，而且气力十足。但现在她的歌声是那样的微弱，虽然听上去并不忧郁（她唱的是首抒情歌曲），但她的嗓子就好像被撕裂、折断了一样，似乎不太适合用来歌唱，给人的感觉就像那首歌也生病了一样。她轻轻地唱着，唱到高音时，那虚弱的声音就会挣扎着断开，然后咳嗽一下，继续轻轻地往下唱……

有些人可能会嘲笑我太激动了，但可能永远都不会有人理解，我为什么要那么动情！不，我并不只是为她感到惋惜，除此之外，还有其他原因。起码在刚听到她的歌声时，我觉得有点儿莫名其妙，进而是惊讶不已，感到既可怕又怪异，到最后几乎是一种病态的报复心理：她在唱歌，居然在我面前唱歌！难道她忘了我的存在吗？

我浑身发抖地坐在那里，然后猛地站了起来，不假思索地拿上帽子准备出门，但我根本不知道要去哪里，要做什么。卢克里娅帮我穿好了大衣。

“她在唱歌？”我随口对卢克里娅说。但她没明白我的意思，看了看我，还是没搞懂；我这话说得的确有点儿含糊不清。

“这是她第一次唱歌吗？”

“不，您不在的时候，她偶尔会唱。”卢克里娅回答。

我明白了。我走下楼梯，上了街，开始漫无目的地游荡。我走到一处拐角，站下来想一想我要去哪儿。那里人来人往，不时会有人撞到我，但我毫无感觉。我叫下了一个马车夫，让他带我去“警察大桥”，我也不知道为什么要去那里。可不一会儿我就放弃了这个想法，并塞给他二十戈比。

“打扰了，这些钱你拿着吧。”我冲他茫然地笑了笑，但心里却突然开始一阵狂喜。

我加快脚步，转身回了家。那个颤抖、虚弱、撕裂的歌声又突然在我脑海里响起，几乎让我窒息。障眼布终于落了下来！假如她还能在我面前唱歌的话，那么说明她已经不在乎我了——这一点是很明确的，同时又很可怕。我能感受得到。但我心中的狂喜战胜了恐惧。

这真是命运对我的捉弄！要知道整个冬天我的心里全是这种喜悦的感觉，根本容不下其他任何东西，可我自己在哪里呢？我和我的心灵是融为一体了吗？我匆匆忙忙地跑上楼梯，我不知道，我进门的时候是不是看上去怯生生的。我只记得，地板仿佛波浪一样起起伏伏，而我则像是在水面上漂浮。我走进房间，她还是坐在原来的地方，低头做着针线活，但没有唱歌。她有意无意地朝我这边看了一眼，但目光并没有落在我身上，只是做了个动作而已，平淡又冷漠，无论谁来她都是这个样子。

我直接走了过去，坐在紧挨着她的椅子上。可能是我的举动有点儿反常，她似乎是被吓了一跳，飞快地看了我一眼。我握住她的手，但忘记了和她说的是什么，因为我当时已经完全语无伦次了。我已经控制不住我的声音了，我不知道我说了什么，只记得当时快要窒息了。

“我们聊聊吧……你知道……随便说点儿什么都行！”我好像是说了一些蠢话，可这时候又怎么能仔细思考呢？她哆嗦了一下，立刻把手抽了回去。她吓得不轻地看着我，但眼神中却满是严肃的惊讶神情。没错，惊讶又严肃的神情，它立刻将我击得粉碎。虽然她没有开口，但眼神却在突然发问：“爱情？你也想要爱情？”我能读懂她的眼神，我能读出她眼中的一切。这一切都让我激动不已，我扑倒在了她的脚边。是的，我在她面前崩溃了。她一下子跳了起来，但我用尽全力握住了她的双手。

我完全记得我当时绝望的感觉，对，完全记得！但你们相信吗，也正是在那个时候，我的心中翻滚沸腾，感受到了难以抑制的狂喜，我想，我快要死了。我如痴如醉地亲吻着她的双脚，沉浸在无边无际的幸福之中。没错，这难以言表的幸福就出现在彻底的绝望面前。我一边哭泣，一边想要说些什么，但根本说不出话来。她刚才那惊恐的神情突然变成了一副忧虑的样子，她看我的眼神有些怪异，甚至带有一丝野性，她似乎有一个非同寻常的问题，但很快又把它想清楚了，继而微微一笑。我继续亲吻着她的双脚，她羞涩地把脚移开，我便亲吻她脚下的地板。她看着眼前发生的这一幕，突然笑了（你们也见过羞涩的笑吧）。她笑得越来越厉害，甚至近乎歇斯底里，我看见她的双手在颤抖，但这些我都毫不在意，只是在那不停地对她低语，说我爱她，说我愿意永远匍匐在她面前，“让我吻你的裙子吧……我一辈子都会这样对你顶礼膜拜……”她突然开始号啕大哭，浑身不停地抽搐，犹如陷入可怕的癫狂中一般。是我把她吓到了。

我把她抱到床上。过了一会儿，她逐渐冷静下来，但神色却十分憔悴。她坐在床边，拉着我的手，请求我一定要冷静：“够了，您不要再折磨自己，冷静一点儿吧！”——说完，她又哭了起来。那天晚上我一直陪在她身边，寸步不离。我一直在和她说话，说我要带她去布洛涅[11]，去洗海水浴，马上出发，再过两星期就走；说我听到她的声音还像不久前那样虚弱；说我要关了当铺，把它卖给多布龙拉沃夫；还说要开始新的生活，这是最重要的，要去布洛涅，去布洛涅！她听了我讲的这些，觉得有些害怕，而且越来越害怕。但我并没有太在意她的感受，对于我来说，更重要的是，我发疯似的想要再跪倒在她的脚边，再亲吻她的双脚，亲吻她脚下的地板，膜拜她，我不停地对她说：“我再也不会向你索要什么了，不要回应我，不要在乎我，完全不要，我只请求你允许我在一个角落里默默地看着你，把我当成你的一件东西就好，把我当成一条狗……”她又哭了。

“我还以为您不会再理我了。”她脱口而出，说得那么突然，那么不经意，仿佛她自己都没有意识到她说了什么。但对于我来说，这是那天晚上最重要的一句话，无比清晰，正中要害，让我心如刀绞。这句话让我彻底醒悟了，只有她在我身边，在我眼前，我才能对未来充满渴望，我才能感到无比的幸福。啊，那天晚上我让她筋疲力尽，我能理解，但我也不断在想，我要马上做出改变。最后，她终于撑不住了，我劝她休息，她倒头便睡。夜里，我不停地起来，穿上鞋走到她床边，静静地看着她。和我想象的一样，她有时会在梦中低声呓语。我一边搓着手，一边看着她，看着这个躺在我花三卢布买来的小铁床上的病人。我跪了下来，但没有亲吻她的脚。（会弄醒她的！）我祈祷了一会儿，然后站了起来。这时，卢克里娅从厨房走了出来，看到了我。我走到她跟前，告诉她可以去睡觉了，从明天开始，就是“另一番光景”了。

我对这一点坚信不疑，甚至到了迷狂的程度。虽然我的眼前不再有任何障碍遮挡我的视线，但当时我正沉浸在那种无边无际的喜悦之中，久久不能平静下来，以至于完全不去理会灾祸降临的某种征兆。我只期待明天马上到来，对，就是明天！要知道，那个时候她还活着，她就在那里，就在我的眼前，就像我在她的眼前一样，一想到这些，我如何能平静得下来呢？“等她明天醒来，我要把这一切都告诉她，她会理解的。”这就是我当时的想法，简单而又明确，我为此狂喜不已！更重要的是去布洛涅的旅行。不知为什么，我总是想着布洛涅，似乎那就是一切，似乎在布洛涅会有某种终极存在的东西。“到布洛涅去，到布洛涅去！……”我狂躁地等待着明天。

3.我了解得太清楚了

这件事的的确确就发生在几天前，五天，总共只过去了五天，就在上星期二。不、不，如果她能再多等一会儿，用不了多长时间，我就可以驱散阴霾了！难道她的心还没有平静下来吗？第二天她听我说话时，虽然看上去有些心神不定，但脸上已经挂着微笑了……但在过去的整整五天里，她时而心神不宁，时而羞愧难当。她仍然感到害怕，非常害怕。我不会去争辩，也不想反驳，我没有丧失理智，她感到恐惧是可以理解的，她怎么能不害怕呢？要知道，我们彼此早已是陌生人了，相互生疏，形同陌路，但却突然发生了这一切……我并没有注意到她的恐惧，我只看到了美好的新生活！……的确，千真万确，我犯了一个错误。也可能是很多错误。第二天一觉醒来（已是星期三了），一大早我就犯了个错误：我竟然把她当成了自己的一位朋友。我向她坦白了我的过去，甚至连一生中自己都不想直面的事也没有隐瞒，虽然这是有必要的，但我过于着急了——这哪里只是坦白啊！我直接对她说，在这整整一个冬天里，我始终坚信她是爱我的。我向她解释，我当时开这个当铺只是由于意志和心灵的颓废，它既是对我个人意志的鞭挞，也是一种自我夸耀。我还向她承认，当初在茶点部时，我的确是害怕了，这是我的性格所致，我的神经过于脆弱：当时的氛围让我惶恐不安，连茶点部也让我惊慌失措，我甚至在纠结，我要不要赶紧离开，我是不是表现得很愚蠢？我害怕的不是决斗本身，而是在这一过程中被人嘲笑……后来我也一直不愿承认，我是在折磨所有人，我也因此在折磨她，我娶她就是想让她为此感到痛苦。我发疯似的跟她说了这些话。她抓住我的手，哀求我不要再说了：“您这说的什么话……您不要再折磨自己了。”说完，又开始号啕大哭，差点再次歇斯底里！她不停地求我什么都别说了，不要再想这些事了。

我没太理会她的请求，继续和她说着关于春天，关于布洛涅的事。那里有太阳，那里有我们的新太阳，这就是我要说的！我要关了当铺，把它转让给多布龙拉沃夫。我又突然向她提议，把我们所有的财产都分发给穷人，只留下我从教母那里继承的三千卢布，我们用这笔钱去布洛涅，等回来后再靠我们的双手开始新的生活。事情就这么定了，她没有反对，因为她什么也没说……只是笑了笑。她的笑似乎更像是出于安慰，只是为了不让我伤心。我看得出来，我让她很为难，你们别以为我又愚蠢又自私，什么都不懂。其实我什么都明白，我比谁都看得透，我已经处在彻底绝望的边缘了！

我把所有事都和她讲了，关于我的、关于她的，乃至关于卢克里娅的。我告诉她，我也哭过……唉，我当然不会多说关于我哭的事，而且有些事情我也是尽量不去提及。我记得，有那么一两次，她和我交谈时也表现得兴致勃勃，对，我记得！你们怎么可以说我什么都不在意呢？如果这件事没有发生的话，那一切都将大不一样。要知道，两天前她还笑着和我讲这个冬天她读过的书，讲吉尔·布拉斯和格林纳达大主教的片段[12]。那是多么纯真、可爱的笑容啊，和她还是我未婚妻的时候一模一样。（时间真是过得飞快！）看到这笑容我是多么高兴啊！不过，她在讲到大主教时的那种状态倒是让我很惊讶：很显然，她在冬天里读那本文学经典的时候获得了内心的宁静和幸福，以至于让她面露笑容。难道她那时真的已经心如死灰，完全确信我将抛弃她吗？因为她星期二的时候还说过：“我还以为您会抛弃我呢！”唉，这可真是十岁小女孩的想法！实际上，她那时的确完全相信，未来的一切事情都会是像她想的那样：我们两个人各自坐在自己的桌子旁，就这么一直坐下去，直到六十岁。但突然有一天，我走到她面前，我是她的丈夫，一个需要爱的丈夫！这是多么深的误解啊，我是多么糊涂啊！

我欣喜若狂地看着她，但这样做不太好，可能会把她吓到，我应该再克制一点。其实我已经很克制了，我控制住自己没再去亲吻她的脚。我从来没表现出过那种样子……就是……我作为一个丈夫的样子——我脑子里从来就没想过那应该是什么样子，我只想膜拜她！但我已经无法再沉默下去了，让我一言不发是完全不可能的。我突然对她说，和她交谈是一种愉悦的享受，我认为她的教养和见识都要远远超过我。她的脸涨得通红，慌忙说，我这是言过其实了。但处在狂喜中的我犯了一个愚蠢的错误，我情不自禁地和她提起了当初躲在门后，听她和那个无耻之徒论战的事，那次清白的论战。而且我还告诉她，我是多么地欣赏她的智慧、机敏和孩童般的纯真。她听了我的话，身体微微颤抖了一下，依然说我言过其实了，但这次声音更轻，而且脸色一下子阴沉了下来，随后便用双手捂着脸失声痛哭……这下我再也控制不住自己了：我又跪倒在她身边，亲吻她的双脚，最后又是以一阵歇斯底里般的发作收场，那场景和星期二时一模一样。这是昨天晚上的事，但到了第二天早上……

第二天早上？！天啊，那不就是今天早上吗，就在不久前，就是刚才！

你们仔细想想：就在我们刚才一起喝茶的时候（就是在昨天的那阵发疯后），她还对我说，她冬天时让我惊讶的那种平静心态是真实的！而我却整夜在为昨天的事担惊受怕。但她突然走到我面前，双手紧紧握在一起，（就在刚才！）对我说，她知道，她是有罪之人，整个冬天她的罪孽都在折磨着她，而且现在也没有停止……她说她非常敬佩我高尚的情操和坦荡的胸襟……“我要做您忠诚的妻子，我会一直尊敬您……”我一下子跳了起来，发疯似的抱住了她！我亲吻着她，吻她的脸颊，吻她的嘴唇，就像一位久别归家的丈夫一样。可我刚才为什么要出门，我就离开了两个小时……我去办理我们的出国护照……哦，我的天啊！我要是早回来五分钟，就那五分钟！……我回来时一群人围在大门口，那些人盯着我，那些目光……啊，主啊！

卢克里娅说（我现在无论如何也不能让卢克里娅走，她了解所有细节，整个冬天她都在，她会把一切都告诉我），大约在我回来前的二十分钟左右，她走进房间去问我妻子一件事，我记不起来是什么事了。她当时看到，圣像（就是前面提到过的圣母像）已被取了出来，就放在桌子上，好像我妻子刚刚祈祷过。“您怎么了，太太？”“没什么事，卢克里娅，你去吧……等等，卢克里娅。”我妻子走到她跟前，吻了她一下。“您现在觉得开心吗，太太？”“是的，卢克里娅。”“先生早就该向您道歉，太太……感谢上帝，你们终于和好了。”“好，卢克里娅，你去吧。”她笑了笑，但看上去有些怪异，怪异到卢克里娅总觉得有什么地方不对劲，十分钟后又返回房间去看她，“她当时站在墙边，离窗户很近，一只手贴着墙，头贴在手上，好像在想着什么事情。她想得太出神了，都没注意到我在门外看她。我看见，她好像在笑，站在那儿一边笑，一边想心事。我站了一会儿，就悄悄走开了，我正在纳闷儿的时候，突然听见窗户被打开的声音。我急忙走回去说，‘外面冷，太太，您可别着凉了’，就在这时我突然看到，她站到了窗台上，窗户开着，她背对着我站在窗户中间，手里握着圣像。我的心扑通一下，赶紧喊‘太太，太太’，她听见了，我以为她会转过身来看看我，但她没有，而是把圣像按在胸前，向前跨了一步，跳了下去！”

我只记得，我刚走进大门时，她还有体温。主要是他们都在看我。一开始他们还在吵吵嚷嚷，但一看到我立刻安静了下来，给我让出了一条路，我看见……她躺在那里，抱着圣像。我记得，当时感觉周围一团漆黑，我默默地走过去，站在那儿看了好久，大家围在我身边，好像在对我说着什么。卢克里娅当时也在，但我没看见她。听别人说，她还和我说话了。我记得，有一个人一直在冲我嚷嚷：“从嘴里流出一小摊血，就一小摊，一小摊！”他还指给我看地面上的血。我的一根手指好像沾到了血，有些弄脏了，我看了看我的手指（这个我记得），而那个人就一直在旁边对我说：“一小摊，一小摊！”

“什么‘一小摊’，你是什么意思？”我用尽全力冲他喊（据说是），然后抡起拳头朝他扑了过去……

啊，荒唐，荒唐！这是个误会！这不正常！这怎么可能！

4.只晚了五分钟

难道不是这样吗？难道这会是真的吗？难道你们觉得这是有可能的吗？为了什么，究竟是什么原因让这个女人选择了死亡？

你们要相信，我是知道原因的；但她为了什么而死——仍然是个谜。她对我的爱感到恐惧，她一定是认真地问过自己：是否应该接受这种爱？既然回答不了这个问题，那就只好选择死亡。我知道，我知道，其实这没有什么值得伤脑筋的地方：她对自己做了太多的承诺，她害怕无法兑现——就是这样。但有些情况是非常可怕的。

现在我仍然弄不明白的是，她是为了什么目的而死的？这个问题一直在我脑子里挥之不去。实际上，无论她想要过怎样的生活，我都会让她得偿所愿。但她不相信我会那样做，这就是问题所在！不、不，我在撒谎，完全不是这么回事。原因其实很简单，和我在一起就应该坦诚相待：她选择爱我，就会全心全意地爱，而不是像她爱那个杂货店老板那样敷衍行事。她是那么纯洁，那么真诚，她无法接受那位老板想要的那种爱情。她不想欺骗我，她不想用二分之一、四分之一的爱来装模作样地骗我。她就是这样的诚实，就是这样，先生们！那个时候我还想让她更加豁达一些，你们记得吗？多么奇怪的想法。

有些问题我非常想知道答案：她尊敬我吗？我不知道。她鄙视我吗？我不认为她会鄙视我。但奇怪的是，为什么我从来没想过这个问题，整个冬天我都从来没考虑过，她是不是在鄙视我。在她用那种严肃而又惊讶的目光看我之前，我一直都坚信她不会鄙视我。没错，严肃。正是那份严肃让我彻底明白，她鄙视我。但现在为时已晚，一切都无法重来了！啊，让她鄙视我吧，哪怕鄙视一辈子都没关系，只要她活着！刚才她还能走路，还能说话呢。我真想不通，她是怎么从窗户跳下去的！我哪曾想到，这事就发生在五分钟前。我叫来卢克里娅。我现在决不能让卢克里娅走，决不能！

我们还有很多事要商量呢。我们只是在这个冬天才开始彼此疏远的，难道就不能重归于好吗？为什么，为什么我们不能在一起重新开始新的生活呢？我是个坦荡又豁达的人，她也是——这不就是我们之间的契合点吗？我们只要再谈一谈，不需要多久，也许再过两天她就能彻底理解我了。

最让人无法接受的就是这样的事——简单、野蛮、愚昧，让人无法预料。这多么遗憾啊！五分钟，我就晚来了五分钟！我要是能提前回来五分钟，这事就不会发生了，她脑子里也再不会出现这样的念头了。到最后，她一定会理解我所做的一切。可现在，房间又变得空空荡荡，又只有我一个人了。钟摆还在那里嘀嗒作响，它无所牵挂，也没有遗憾。我身边一个人都没有——这就是我的不幸！

我一直在房间里走来走去。我知道，我知道，你们不用提醒我：我抱怨这件不可预料的事，我还抱怨那五分钟，你们觉得可笑吗？但你们要知道，这是很明显的。你们想想：出现这种情况时，一般人都会留一张字条，写着“我的死和任何人无关”，但她什么都没留下。难道她没想过，有的人可能会怀疑到卢克里娅吗？人们会说：“当时只有你和她在一起，一定是你把她推下去的。”如果不是当时有四个人在院子里和厢房窗户中看到她怀抱圣像，自己跳下去的话，那卢克里娅即便无罪，至少也要受一些刁难了。但其他人不也是偶然看到她跳下去的吗？是的，这一瞬间发生的事，完全就是无意识的本能冲动。这就是一场意外，这是毫无理性的行为！但你们会问，她在这之前不是还对着圣像祈祷来着吗？但这并不代表她做的就是死前祈祷。很有可能她就是在十分钟前才做出这种决定的——就在她站在墙边，头靠在手上，面带微笑时。那一刻一定有某种想法钻进了她的脑子，让她神魂颠倒，最终屈服。

你们的想法都存在明显的误解。她是可以和我一起生活的。就算她贫血又怎样呢？难道这是贫血或生命力枯竭所致吗？她从冬天开始就已经很虚弱了，就是这么回事……

我来晚了！

躺在棺材里的她是那样的纤细，连她的小鼻子都变得尖瘦了！她的睫毛像平放着的箭一样。她坠落地面后，哪里都没有摔破，哪里都没有折断！只有那“一小摊血”，一个勺子那么多。她是内脏破裂。我又冒出一个奇怪的想法：如果她不下葬会怎样？因为如果她被抬走，那么……不，她几乎不可能被抬走！我当然知道，她应该被抬走，我没疯，也没说胡话，相反，我现在比任何时候都要清醒——只不过家里又要冷冷清清了，又只剩那两个房间，又只有我一个人和那些抵押物在一起了。胡话、胡话，这就是在说胡话！我让她痛苦不堪，就是这样！

走到这一步，你们的那些法律对我来说算得了什么？你们的习俗、你们的文化、你们的生活、你们的国家、你们的信仰对我来说又算得了什么？把我送上法庭吧，让你们的法庭来公开审判我吧，我要说，我没什么好招认的。法官会冲我大喊：“肃静，军官！”我也会回应他：“你有什么权力让我服从你？为什么阴暗的守旧势力要打碎这世上最珍贵的东西？你们的法律为什么要这样对待我？我已经和那些条条框框一刀两断了。”我现在什么都不怕了！

盲目，她太盲目了！她死了，听不到我说话了！她不会知道，我把她置身在怎样的天国之中。天国就在我心里，但愿她已经身在其中！她不会再爱我了——好吧，不过那又怎样呢？万物本该如此，也终将如此。她本可以把我当成一个朋友——那样我们都会快乐，我们会看着对方开心大笑。我们本应这样去生活。如果她爱上了别人——好吧，去爱吧，去爱吧！她会和他走在一起开心地笑，而我会在街角望着他们……啊，不管什么都可以，只要她睁开眼睛，哪怕一次也好！睁开一会儿吧，就一会儿！看看我，就像刚才一样，像她站在我面前发誓要做一个忠诚的妻子那样！只要看一眼她就会全明白了！

旧势力啊！这世界啊！人类孤零零地活在这世界中——这就是不幸！俄罗斯的勇士们在呼喊：“有人活着吗？”我不是勇士，我也这么呼喊，可是无人应答。人们说，太阳赋予万物生命。太阳升起来了，你们看看它，难道它有生命吗？一切都没有生命，到处是一片死气沉沉。只有人是活着的，可他们周围却是一片沉寂——这就是我们的世界！“人们啊，彼此相爱吧！”——这是谁说的？这是谁的训诫？钟摆还在那里漠然地嘀嗒作响，令人厌恶。现在已经夜里两点了。她的靴子还立在床边，仿佛在等着她……不，说正经的，明天她就要被抬走了，我该怎么办？

[11]全称为“滨海布洛涅”，法国西北部港口城市，临加莱海峡，拥有海滨浴场。

[12]出自法国作家阿兰·勒内·勒萨日（1668—1747）的长篇小说《吉尔·布拉斯》。

Chapter 1

I. WHO I WAS AND WHO SHE WAS

... Now as long as she’s here - everything is still all right：I’m constantly going over and looking at her; but tomorrow they’ll take her away and - how will I ever stay behind all on my own? Now she’s on the table in the sitting room, on two card tables that were put together, and the coffin will come tomorrow, a white one, with white gros de Naples, how-ever, that’s not i ... I keep pacing and want to make sense of it for myself. Now it’s six hours that I’ve been trying to make sense of it and I still can’t collect my thoughts to a T. The fact of the matter is that I keep pacing, pacing, pacin ... Here’s how it was. I’ll simply tell it in order. （Order!） Gen-tlemen, I’m far from being a literary man, as you’ll see, well, so be it, but I’ll tell it as I myself understand it. That’s the horror of it for me, that I understand everything!

If you want to know, that is, if we take it from the very beginning, then quite simply she used to come to me to pawn things in order to pay for advertising in the Voice, say-ing, well, that there’s a governess, willing to travel and give lessons in the home and so forth and so on. That was in the very beginning and of course I didn’t single her out from the others：she came like all the others and so forth. But afterwards I began to single her out. She was so thin, fair, a bit taller than average; with me she was always awkward, as if she were embarrassed （I think that she was exactly the same with all strangers, and, it goes without saying, I was no different than anyone else, that is, if taken not as a pawn-broker but as a man）. As soon as she received her money she would immediately turn around and leave. And all in silence. Others argue, beg, haggle to be given more; but not this one, whatever she was give ... It seems to me that I keep getting muddle ... Yes; first of all, I was struck by her things：silver gilt earrings, a worthless little locket - things worth twenty kopecks. She herself knew that they were worth all of ten kopecks, but I could see from her face that for her they were objects of great value - and indeed, as I learned later, this was all that she had left from her papa and mama. Only once did I permit myself to smile at her things. That is, you see, I never permit myself that, I maintain a gentlemanly tone with the public：a few words said respectfully and sternly.‘Sternly, sternly and sternly.’ But she suddenly permitted herself to bring the remnants （quite literally, that is） of an old rabbit-skin jacket - and I couldn’t resist and suddenly said something to her in the way of a witticism, as it were. Goodness gracious, how she flared up! Her eyes were blue, large, thoughtful, but how they blazed! But she didn’t let drop a single word, she picked up her ‘remnants’and left. That was the first time that I noticed her particularly and thought something of that sort about her, that is, precisely something of that particular sort. Yes; I recall yet another impression, that is, if you wish, the main impression, the synthesis of everything：namely, that she was terribly young, so young, as if she were fourteen years old. Wereas she was then three months shy of sixteen. However, that wasn’t what I wanted to say, that wasn’t the synthesis at all. She came again the next day. I later learned that she had been to Dobronravov and Mozer with that jacket, but they don’t take anything except gold and didn’t even bother to talk to her. I, on the other hand, had once taken a cameo from her （a worthless little thing） - and when I gave it some thought later on I was surprised：I also don’t buy anything except gold and silver and yet I had taken a cameo. That was my second thought about her then, I remember that.

This time, that is, after going to Mozer, she brought an amber cigar holder - a so-so little piece, for the connoisseur, but something of no worth to us, because we deal only in gold. Since she had come after yesterday’s rebellion, I greeted her sternly. Sternness for me means dryness. However, as I was giving her the two roubles, I couldn’t resist and said with some irritation, as it were：‘I’m doing this only for you, Mozer wouldn’t take a thing like this from you.’I particu-larly emphasized the words ‘for you’, and precisely with a certain insinuation. I was angry. Once again she flared up, upon hearing that ‘for you’, but she held her tongue, didn’t throw down the money, took it - that’s what poverty is! But how she flared up! I understood that I had wounded her. But when she had gone, I suddenly asked myself：So is this triumph over her really worth two roubles? Hee-hee-hee! I remember that I asked precisely that very question twice：‘Is it worth it? Is it worth it?’ And, laughing, I answered this question to myself in the affirmative. Then I really cheered up. But this wasn’t a nasty feeling：I had a plan, a purpose; I wanted to test her, because suddenly I began to have some thoughts about her. That was my third particular thought about her.

...Well, it was from that time that it all started. It goes without saying, I immediately tried to find out all her cir-cumstances indirectly and waited for her arrival with particular impatience. You see, I had a feeling that she would come soon. Wen she came, I launched into an amiable conversation with unusual politeness. You see, I wasn’t badly brought up and have manners. Hmm. That was when I guessed that she was kind and meek. The kind and meek don’t resist for long, and although they are by no means very open, they don’t at all know how to avoid a conversation：they answer grudgingly, but they answer and the longer it goes on, the more they answer; but if this is what you want, you can’t let yourself get tired. It goes without saying that she didn’t explain anything to me then. It was later that I learned about the Voice and about everything else. She was then mustering every last bit she had to advertise - at first, it goes without saying, presumptuously：‘Governess, willing to travel, send terms by post’; but later：‘Willing to do any-thing, tutor, be a companion, housekeeping, care for the sick, can sew’and so forth and so on. The usual! It goes without saying that all this was added to the advertisement at different stages, and towards the end, when despair had set it, there was even ‘without salary, for board’. No, she didn’t find a position! I made up my mind then to test her for the last time：I suddenly picked up today’s Voice and showed her an advertisement：‘Young female, orphan, seeks position as governess of small children, preferably with an elderly widower. Willing to do light housework.’

‘There, you see, this was published this morning and by evening she’s sure to have found a job. That’s the way to advertise!’

Again she flared up, again her eyes blazed; she turned around and immediately walked out. I was very pleased. However, by then I was already sure of everything and had no fears：nobody would take her cigar holders. Besides, she had already run out of cigar holders. And so it was, two days later she comes, such a pale, agitated little thing - I under-stood that something had happened at home, and indeed something had happened. I’ll explain straight away what happened, but now I merely wish to recall how I suddenly did something chic and rose in her eyes. A plan suddenly occurred to me. The fact of the matter is that she brought this icon （she had steeled herself to bring it）... Oh, listen! Listen! This is where it began, but I keep getting muddle ... The fact of the matter is that I now want to recall everything, every trifle, every little detail. I still want to collect my thoughts to a T and - I can’t, and now there are these little details, these little detail ...

An icon of the Mother of God. The Mother of God with Child, a family heirloom, an antique, with a silver gilt frame - worth - well, worth about six roubles. I see that the icon is dear to her, and she’s pawning the whole icon, with-out removing the mounting. I tell her that it would be better if she removed the mounting and took the icon with her, because after all it’s an icon.

‘Surely you’re not forbidden?’

‘No, it’s not that it’s forbidden, but just that, perhaps, you yoursel ... ’

‘Well, remove it.’

‘You know what, I won’t remove it, but I’ll put it over there in the icon case,’ I said, after giving it some thought, ‘with the other icons, under the lamp.’（I’ve always had the lamp burning ever since I opened my shop.）‘And I’ll give you ten roubles - it’s as simple as that.’

‘I don’t need ten, give me five; I’ll redeem it without fail.’

‘But don’t you want ten? The icon is worth it,’ I added, after observing that her little eyes had flashed once again. She held her tongue. I brought her five roubles.

‘Don’t despise anybody - I’ve been in tight squeezes myself, and even a bit worse, and if you now see me in such an occupatio ... well, you see, after all that I’ve endure ... ’

‘You’re taking revenge on society? Is that it?’she suddenly interrupted me with a rather sarcastic gibe, in which, how-ever, there was a good deal of innocence （that is, of a general sort, because she certainly did not single me out from the others then, so it was said almost inoffensively）. ‘Aha!’ I thought, ‘so that’s what you’re like, your character is show-ing itself, you belong to the new movement.’

‘You see,’ I immediately observed, half-jokingly, half-mysteriously.‘I - I am part of that part of the whole that desires to do evil, but creates goo ... ’

She looked at me quickly and with great curiosity, in which, however, there was a great deal of childishness：

‘Wait a momen ... Wat’s that saying? Were’s it from? I’ve heard it somewher ... ’

‘Don’t rack your brains：Mephistopheles recommends him-self to Faust in those words. Have you read Faust?’

‘N ... not carefully.’

‘That is, you haven’t read it at all. You should read it. However, once again I see a sardonic grin on your lips. Please, don’t suppose that I have so little taste that I wished to paint over my role as a pawnbroker by recommending myself to you as Mephistopheles. Once a pawnbroker, always a pawnbroker. We know that, miss.’

‘You’re such a strange perso ... I didn’t in the least want to say anything of the kin ... ’

She wanted to say：I didn’t expect that you were an edu-cated man, but she didn’t say it, though I knew that she had thought it; I had pleased her terribly much.

‘You see,’ I observed, ‘one can do good in any walk of life. Of course, I’m not speaking of myself; let’s suppose that I do nothing but bad thing ... ’

‘Of course, one can do good in any position,’ she said, looking at me with a quick and penetrating glance. ‘Precisely in any position,’ she added suddenly.

Oh, I remember, I remember all those moments! And I also want to add that when these young people, these dear young people, want to say something intelligent and pene-trating, then their faces suddenly show you all too sincerely and naively：‘Here I am, I’m telling you something intelli-gent and penetrating.’And it’s not at all from vanity, as is the case with the likes of us, but you see that she herself sets great store on all this terribly, and she believes, and respects and thinks that you, too, respect all this just as she does. Oh, sincerity! That’s what they win you over with! And it was so charming in her!

I remember, I have forgotten nothing! Wen she left, I made up my mind at once. That same day I made my final enquiries and learned absolutely everything else there was to know about her present particulars; all the particulars of her past I already knew from Lukerya, who was then their servant and whom I had bribed several days earlier. These circumstances were so horrible that I don’t understand how it had been possible for her to laugh, as she had that day, and be curious about Mephistopheles’words, when she her-self was faced with such horrors. But-youth! That’s precisely what I thought about her then with pride and joy, because, you see, there was also magnanimity about it, as if she were to say：the great works of Goethe shine even on the brink of ruin. Youth is always magnanimous, if only ever so slightly and ever so distortedly. That is, I’m speaking of her, you see, her alone. And the main thing, I then looked upon her as mine and did not doubt my power. You know, that’s a most voluptuous thought, when you no longer have any doubt.

But what’s wrong with me? If I keep going on like this, then when will I collect everything to a T? Quickly, quickly-this isn’t the point at all, oh God!

II. A MARRIAGE PROPOSAL

The ‘particulars’I learned about her I can set forth in a few words：her father and mother had died a long time ago, three years previously, and she had been left with her disreputable aunts. That is, it’s saying too little to call them disreputable. One aunt was a widow with a large family, six children, each one smaller than the next; the other was a spinster, old and nasty. Both of them were nasty. Her father had been a gov-ernment official, but only a clerk, and a non-hereditary nobleman-in a word：everything played into my hands. I appeared as if from some higher world：after all, I was a retired staffcaptain of a brilliant regiment, a nobleman by birth, independent and so on, and as far as the pawnshop went, the aunts could only look at it with respect. She had been slaving for her aunts for three years, but nevertheless she had passed an examination somewhere-she had man-aged to pass it, snatched a free minute to pass it, despite relentless work day in and day out - and that meant some-thing about aspirations for the noble and the sublime on her part. After all, why did I want to get married? But who cares about me, we’ll save that for late ... As if that were the point! She taught her aunt’s children, she sewed their under-clothes, and towards the end she washed not only these underclothes, but she, with her bad chest, also washed the floors. To put it bluntly, they even beat her, reproaching her for every crumb. It ended with them intending to sell her. Ugh! I’ll omit the dirty details. Later she told me everything in detail. A neighbour, a fat shopkeeper, had been observing all this for a whole year, and he wasn’t just an ordinary shop-keeper, but the owner of two grocery stores. He had already beat two wives to death and was looking for a third, and had cast his eye on her：‘She’s a quiet one,’ he thought, ‘she grew up in poverty and I’m marrying for the sake of my orphans.’Indeed, he did have orphans. He began to seek her hand, started negotiations with the aunts, and on top of that-he’s fifty years old; she’s horri fied. And that’s when she started coming to me to get money for advertisements in the Voice. In the end, she began asking the aunts to give her just the littlest bit of time to think it over. They gave her that little bit, but only one, they didn’t give her another; they badgered her：‘We don’t know where we’ll get our next meal, even without an extra mouth to feed.’ I already knew all this, and on that same day, after her visit in the morning, I made up my mind. That evening the merchant came, he had brought from the shop a pound of candies worth fifty kopecks; she’s sitting with him, and I summon Lukerya from the kitchen and tell her to go to her and whisper that I’m standing by the gate and wish to tell her something most urgently. I remained pleased with myself. And in general I was terribly pleased with myself that entire day.

Right there at the gate, already dumbfounded that I had summoned her, I explained to her, in Lukerya’s presence, that I would consider myself happy and honoure ... Sec-ondly, she was not surprised by my manner or by the fact that this was taking place by the gate：‘I am a straightforward man,’ I said, ‘and have studied the circumstances of the mat-ter.’And I wasn’t lying that I’m straightforward. Well, to hell with it. I spoke not only decently, that is, by showing myself to be a person of good breeding, but originally as well, and that’s the main thing. Wat, is it a sin to acknowledge this? I want to judge myself and am doing so. I must speak both pro and contra, and I am doing so. I recalled it with delight afterwards, even though it was stupid：I announced straight out then, without any embarrassment, that, in the first place, I wasn’t particularly talented, not particularly intelligent, and perhaps not even particularly kind, that I was a rather cheap egoist （I remember this expression, I had composed it on my way there and remained pleased with it） and that-very, very likely - there was much that was unpleasant about me in other respects as well. All this was said with a particu-lar kind of pride - we know how these sorts of things are said. Of course, I had sufficient good taste, after nobly declaring my deficiencies, not to launch into a declaration of my virtues：‘But to make up for this, I have this, that and the other.’ I could see that she was still terribly afraid, but I didn’t soften anything; instead, seeing that she was afraid I deliberately intensified it：I said straight out that she wouldn’t go hungry, but as for fancy clothes, the theatre and balls-there would be none of that, though perhaps later, when I had achieved my goal. I was definitely carried away by this stern tone. I added, and as casually as possible, that if I had taken up such an occupation, that is, keeping this pawnshop, it was for one purpose only - that is, there was a certain circumstance, so to spea ... But you see I had a right to speak like that：I really did have such a purpose and such a circumstance. Wait a moment, gentlemen, all my life I have been the first to hate this pawnbroking business, but in essence, you see, even though it’s ridiculous to talk to oneself in mysterious phrases, I was ‘taking revenge on soci-ety’, you see, I really, really, really was! Therefore, her joke about the fact that I was ‘taking revenge’was unfair. That is, you see, if I had said to her straight out in so many words：‘Yes, I’m taking revenge on society’, and she had burst out laughing, the way she did that morning, it would indeed have come out ridiculous. But with an indirect hint and by dropping a mysterious phrase it turned out that it was pos-sible to engage her imagination. Moreover, I wasn’t afraid of anything then：you see, I knew that in any event the fat shopkeeper was more repulsive than I and that I, standing by the gate, was her liberator. I understood that, you see. Oh, man understands baseness particularly well! But was it baseness? How is one to judge a man in a case like this? Didn’t I love her already even then?

Wait a moment：it goes without saying that I didn’t say a word to her about doing a good deed：on the contrary, oh, on the contrary：‘It is I,’ I said, ‘who am being done the favour, and not you.’ So that I even expressed this in words, I couldn’t help myself, and perhaps it came out stupidly, because I noticed a fleeting grin on her face. But on the whole I had definitely won. Wait a moment, if I’m going to recall all this filth, then I’ll recall this final bit of swinishness：I was standing there and this is what was going through my head：You’re tall, fit, educated and - and finally, to speak without any boasting, you’re not bad looking. That’s what was running through my head. It goes without saying, she said ‘yes’there and then by the gate. Bu ... but I should add：she thought it over for a long time, right there and then by the gate, before she said ‘yes’. She was so deep in thought, so deep in thought that I was on the verge of asking, ‘Well, what is it going to be?’ - and I couldn’t even help myself from asking with a certain sense of chic：‘Well, what is it going to be, Miss?’ - adding the ‘Miss’for good measure.

‘Wait, I’m thinking.’

And her little face was so serious, so serious - that even then I might have read it! But instead I was offended：‘Is she really,’ I thought to myself, ‘choosing between me and the merchant?’ Oh, I still didn’t understand then! I still didn’t understand anything, anything then! I didn’t under-stand until today! I remember Lukerya ran after me when I was already walking away, stopped me in the street and said, catching her breath：‘God will reward you, sir, for taking our dear young lady - only don’t say anything about it to her, she’s proud.’

Well now, proud! I like them proud, I said to myself. The proud ones are particularly nice, whe ... well, when you no longer harbour any doubts about your power over them. Eh? Oh, base, awkward man! Oh, how pleased I was! Do you know, while she was standing there by the gate deep in thought about whether to say ‘yes’to me, and I was sur-prised, do you know, that she might even have been thinking：‘If it’s to be misfortune either way, isn’t it better to choose the worst straight away, that is, the fat shopkeeper; let him get drunk, the sooner the better, and beat me to death!’ Eh? Wat do you think, could that have been what she was thinking?

And even now I don’t understand, even now I don’t under-stand anything! I just now said that she might have been thinking that she should choose the worse of the two mis-fortunes, that is, the merchant. But who was worse for her then - the merchant or I? The merchant or the pawnbroker who quotes Goethe? That’s still a question! Wat question? You don’t understand even that：the answer is lying on the table, and you say ‘what question’! But to hell with me! I’m not the point here at al ... And at the same time, what do I care now - whether I’m the point or not? That’s something I’m utterly incapable of deciding. I’d better go to bed. I have a headach ...

III. THE NOBLEST OF MEN, BUT I DON’T BELIEVE IT MYSELF

I didn’t fall asleep. And how could I with that pulse ham-mering away in my head. I want to absorb all this, all this filth. Oh, the filth! Oh, the filth I dragged her out of then! She should have realized that, you know, she should have appreciated my deed! I was pleased, too, by various thoughts, for example, that I was forty-one years old and that she was only sixteen. That fascinated me, this sense of inequality, it was very sweet, very sweet.

I, for example, wanted to have the wedding à l’anglaise, that is, just the two of us, perhaps with two witnesses, one of whom would be Lukerya, and then at once to the train, for example, if only to Moscow （it so happened that I had business there）, to a hotel for a fortnight or so. She was against it, she wouldn’t have it and I was forced to visit her aunts and pay my respects to them as the relatives from whom I was taking her. I gave in, and the aunts were ren-dered their due. I even made a present of a hundred roubles each to those creatures and promised more, of course, with-out saying a word to her, so as not to distress her with the baseness of the situation. The aunts at once became as soft as silk. There was an argument about the trousseau as well：she didn’t have anything, almost literally, but she didn’t want anything either. However, I managed to convince her that it wasn’t possible to have absolutely nothing, and so I arranged for the trousseau myself, because who else would do any-thing for her? Well, but to hell with me! Various ideas of mine, however, I nevertheless did manage to convey to her then, so that she would at least know. Perhaps I was even too hasty. The main thing is that from the very beginning, however much she tried to hold out, she would throw herself at me with her love; she would meet me when I came home in the evening with rapture, she would tell me in her prattle （the charming prattle of innocence!） all about her child-hood, youth, about her parental home, about her father and mother. But I immediately threw cold water on all these ecstasies right then and there. That was the whole point of my idea. I answered her raptures with silence, gracious, of cours ... but she nevertheless quickly saw that we were different and that I was - a riddle. And the main thing is that I had set my sights on this riddle! You see, it was in order to pose this riddle perhaps that I committed all this foolishness! First of all, sternness - it was with sternness that I took her into my house. In a word, even though I was quite pleased with things as they were, I began to create a complete system. Oh, it took shape on its own, without any effort. And it couldn’t have been otherwise, I had to create this system on account of one incontrovertible circumstance - really, what is this? I’m slandering myself! The system was genuine. No, listen, if you’re going to judge a person, then you should judge him knowing the cas ... Listen.

How should I begin this, because it’s very difficult. Wen you begin justifying yourself - that’s when it gets difficult. You see：young people despise money, for example - I ham-mered away about money; I pressed home about money. And I hammered away so that she began to fall silent more and more. She would open her big eyes, listen, look and fall silent. You see：young people are magnanimous, that is, the good ones are magnanimous and impetuous, but they have little tolerance, as soon as something’s not quite right - you get their contempt. But I wanted breadth, I wanted to instil breadth right into her heart, to instil it into her heart’s vista, isn’t that so? I’ll take a trivial example：How could I explain, for example, my pawnshop to a person like that? It goes without saying that I didn’t bring it up directly, or it would have looked like I was asking her forgiveness for the pawn-shop; instead I acted, so to speak, with pride - I spoke almost silently. And I’m a master of speaking silently - all my life I’ve spoken silently and I’ve lived through entire tragedies in silence. Oh, and I too have been unhappy! I was cast aside by everyone, cast aside and forgotten, and no one, no one knows it! And suddenly this sixteen-year-old girl got hold of details about me afterwards from vile people and thought that she knew everything, but meanwhile the secret remained only in this man’s breast! I went on being silent, and I was particularly, particularly silent with her until just yesterday - why was I silent? Because I’m a proud man. I wanted her to find out on her own, without me, but not from stories told by scoundrels, but that she should guess herself about this man and comprehend him! Wen I received her into my house, I wanted her complete respect. I wanted her to stand before me beseechingly, on account of my suffering - and I was worthy of that. Oh, I’ve always been proud, I’ve always wanted all or nothing! And that’s precisely why I’m not for half-measures in happiness, but wanted everything - and that’s precisely why I was forced to act as I did then, as if to say：‘Figure it out for yourself and appreciate me!’ Because, you must agree, if I had begun by explaining and prompting, being evasive and asking for respect - then, you see, it would have been as if I were asking for charit ... Howeve ... However, why am I talking about this!

Stupid, stupid, stupid, stupid! I straight away and ruth-lessly （and I want to emphasize that it was ruthlessly） explained to her then, in a few words, that the magnanimity of young people was lovely, but not worth a brass button. Wy not? Because it comes cheap, they get it without having lived; it’s all, so to speak, the ‘first impressions of existence’, but let’s see you do some work! Cheap magnanimity is always easy, and even to give your life-even that’s easy, because that’s just a matter of the blood boiling and an over-abundance of energy, one passionately longs for beauty! No, take an act of magnanimity that is difficult, quiet, muted, without splendour, where you’re slandered, where there’s much sacrifice and not a drop of glory - where you, a shining man, are brought forward before everyone as a scoundrel, when you are the most honest man in the world - come on, try your hand at that sort of deed, no, sir, you’ll give it up! Wile I - all I’ve done my whole life is to shoulder that sort of deed. In the beginning she would argue - and how! But then she began to fall silent, completely and totally, she would just open her eyes terribly wide as she listened, such big, big eyes, and so attentive. An ... and besides that I suddenly saw a smile, a mistrustful, silent, bad smile. It was with that smile that I brought her into my house. And it’s also true that she had nowhere else to g ...

IV. PLANS AND MORE PLANS

Wich of us was the first to begin then?

Neither. It began on its own from the very first. I have said that I had brought her into my house with sternness; how-ever, I softened it from the very first. Wen she was still my fiancée it had been explained to her that she would assist in taking in the pledges and paying out the money, and she didn’t say anything then （note that）. And what’s more, she even took to the business with zeal. Well, of course, the apartment, the furniture - everything remained the same as before. The apartment has two rooms：one is a large room in which the shop is partitioned off from the rest, and the other one is also a large room in which we have our sitting room and bedroom. My furniture isn’t much; even her aunts had better. My icon-stand with the lamp is in the room with the shop; in the other room I have my bookcase with some books and a trunk to which I have the keys; and there’s a bed, tables, chairs. Wen she was still my fiancée I told her that one rouble a day and no more was allotted for our board, that is, food, for me, her and Lukerya, whom I had enticed away：‘I need 30，000 in three years,’ I told her, ‘otherwise I won’t be able to save up enough money.’She didn’t stand in the way, but I myself added to our board by thirty kopecks. It was the same thing with the theatre. Wen she was still my fiancée I told her that there wouldn’t be any theatre; however, I decided that we should go to the theatre once a month, and decently at that, in the orchestra. We went together, three times, and saw In Pursuit of Happiness and Songbirds, I think.（Oh, to hell with it, to hell with it!） We went in silence and returned in silence. Wy, why did we from the very beginning choose to be silent? After all, there weren’t any quarrels in the beginning, but there was silence then, too. As I recall, she somehow kept looking at me then on the sly; when I noticed that I increased my silence. True, I was the one who insisted upon silence, and not she. On her part there were outbursts once or twice, when she would rush to embrace me; but since these out-bursts were unhealthy and hysterical, and what I required was steadfast happiness, together with her respect, I received them coldly. And I was right to do so：each time the outburst was followed the next day by a quarrel.

That is, there weren’t any quarrels, but there was silence and - and on her part a more and more insolent look.‘Rebel-lion and independence’ - that’s what it was, only she didn’t know how. Yes, that meek face was becoming more and more insolent. Can you believe it? I was becoming repulsive to her - I came to understand that. And there could be no doubt about these outbursts that came over her. For example, after leaving behind such filth and beggary, after scrubbing floors, how could she suddenly begin to grumble about our poverty! You see, gentlemen：it wasn’t poverty, it was econ-omy, and where necessary there was some luxury, when it came to linens and cleanliness, for example. I had always dreamed before that cleanliness in a husband attracts a wife. However, it wasn’t poverty, but my supposed miserly econ-omy that bothered her：‘He has goals, he’s showing his firm character.’ She suddenly declined to go to the theatre. And there was more and more of that sardonic gri ... Wile I intensified my silence, I intensified my silence.

Surely there was no need to justify my actions? The main thing here was the pawnshop. Come now, sirs：I knew that a woman, especially one who was sixteen years old, couldn’t help but submit completely to a man. Women have no ori-ginality, that’s-that’s an axiom, even now it’s an axiom for me! Never mind what’s lying there in the front room：truth is truth, and even Mill himself can’t do anything about it! But a loving woman, oh, a loving woman idolizes even the vices, even the villainy of her beloved being. He would not seek such justifications for his villainy as she will find for him. That’s magnanimous but not original. It is this lack of originality alone that has been the undoing of women. And what, I repeat, what are you pointing to there on the table? Is there really anything original about what’s there on the table? Oh-h-h!

Listen：I was certain of her love then. You see, she would throw herself on my neck then. That meant she loved me, or rather - she wished to love me. Yes, that’s what it was：she wished to love, she sought to love. But the main thing, you see, is that there weren’t any villainies for which she needed to find justifications. You say a ‘pawnbroker’and that’s what everyone says. But what if I am a pawnbroker? That means there are reasons, if the most magnanimous of men became a pawnbroker. You see, gentlemen, there are idea ... that is, you see, when some ideas are said out loud, put into words, they come out terribly stupid. They come out so that you’re ashamed of them yourself. But why? For no reason at all. Because we’re all good-for-nothings and can’t bear the truth, or I don’t know why else. I said just now ‘the most magnanimous of men’. That’s ridiculous, you see, and yet that’s how it was. You see, it’s the truth, that is, it’s the most truthful truth of all! Yes, I had the right then to want to pro-vide for myself and open this shop：‘You, that is, you people, have spurned me, you have driven me away with your con-temptuous silence. You have answered my outbursts of passion with an insult that I will feel for the rest of my life. Consequently, I now am within my rights to protect myself from you with a wall, to amass those 30，000 roubles and end my days somewhere in the Crimea, on the southern shore, amidst mountains and vineyards, on my own estate pur-chased with that 30，000, and the main thing, far away from you all, but without malice towards you, with an ideal in my soul, with my beloved woman at my heart, with a family if God should send one, and - helping out the neighbouring peasants.’It goes without saying that it’s good that I’m tell-ing this to myself now, but what could have been more stupid than if I had described all this out loud to her then? That was the reason behind my proud silence, and that was the reason we sat in silence. Because what would she have understood? Just sixteen years old, so very young - what could she have understood of my justifications, of my suf-fering? I was dealing with straightforwardness, ignorance of life, cheap, youthful convictions, the blindness of ‘beautiful hearts’, and the main thing, the pawnshop and-basta!（But was I a scoundrel in the pawnshop, didn’t she see how I conducted myself and did I charge more than I should?） Oh, how terrible is truth on this earth! This charming one, this meek one, this heaven - she was a tyrant, the unbearable tyrant of my soul and my tormentor! I’d be slandering myself, you see, if I didn’t say that! You think I didn’t love her? Wo can say that I didn’t love her? You see：there was irony here, the malicious irony of fate and nature! We are accursed, the life of people in general is accursed! （And mine in particular!） I understand now, you see, that I made some mistake here! Something didn’t come out the way it was supposed to. Everything was clear, my plan was as clear as the sky：‘Severe, proud, requires no moral consolation, suf-fers in silence.’ That’s how it was, I wasn’t lying, I wasn’t lying! ‘She’ll see for herself later on that there was magna-nimity here, but she just wasn’t able to see it now-and when she does fathom it some day, she’ll appreciate it ten times more and will fall down in the dust with her hands folded in supplication.’ That was the plan. But I forgot something here or failed to take it into account. I wasn’t able to do something here. But enough, enough. And of whom can I ask forgiveness now? Wat’s done is done. Take courage, man, and be proud! It’s not you who are to blame!...

Now then, I’ll tell the truth, I won’t be afraid to stand face to face with the truth：she is to blame, she is to blame!...

V. THE MEEK ONE REBELS

The quarrels began when she suddenly took it into her head to pay out money as she saw fit, to appraise things for more than they were worth, and a couple of times she even thought fit to enter into an argument with me on the subject. I didn’t agree. But then this captain’s widow turned up.

An old lady, the widow of a captain, came with a locket - a present from her late husband, well, you know, a keepsake. I gave thirty roubles. She started to whine plaintively, begging me to keep the thing for her; it goes without saying that we keep it. Well, in a word, suddenly she comes five days later to exchange it for a bracelet that’s not worth even eight roubles; it goes without saying that I refused. She must have guessed then something from my wife’s eyes, but in any case she came when I wasn’t there, and my wife exchanged the locket.

Wen I learned about it that very same day, I began by speaking meekly, but firmly and reasonably. She was sitting on the bed, looking at the floor, tapping the rug with the toe of her right shoe （her gesture）; an unpleasant smile played on her lips. Then without raising my voice at all I announced calmly that the money was mine, that I had the right to look at life with my own eyes and that when I invited her into my house I had not concealed anything from her.

She suddenly jumped up, suddenly began trembling all over and-what do you think-she suddenly began stamp-ing her feet at me; this was a wild animal, this was a fit, this was a wild animal having a fit. I froze in astonishment：I had never expected such an outburst. But I didn’t become flus-tered, I didn’t even move a muscle, and once again in the same calm voice I declared plainly that from that time for-ward I refused to let her take part in my affairs. She laughed in my face and walked out of the apartment.

The fact of the matter is that she had no right to leave the apartment. Nowhere without me, that was the agreement we made when she was still my fiancée. She returned towards evening; I didn’t say a word.

The next day, too, she went out in the morning, and it was the same thing the following day. I locked up the shop and set off to see her aunts. I had broken off relations with them from the day of the wedding - I hadn’t invited them to visit me, we didn’t visit them. Now it turned out that she wasn’t with them. They heard me out with curiosity and laughed in my face.‘Serves you right,’ they said. But I had expected their laughter. I then and there bribed the younger aunt, the spinster, with a hundred roubles, and gave her twenty-five in advance. Two days later she comes to me：‘An officer,’ she says, ‘a Lieutenant Yefimovich, a former comrade of yours from the regiment, is mixed up in this.’ I was quite aston-ished. This Yefimovich had done me more harm than anyone else in the regiment, and a month ago he stopped by my shop a couple of times, and being the shameless fellow that he is, under the pretence of pawning something, I remember, he began laughing with my wife. I went up to him then and told him that, considering our relations, he should not pre-sume to visit me; but no idea of anything like that crossed my mind, I simply thought that he was an insolent fellow. But now suddenly her auntie informs me that she had made an appointment to see him and that this whole affair is being handled by a certain former acquaintance of the aunts, Yuliya Samsonovna, a widow, and a colonel’s widow at that- ‘It’s her that your spouse goes to visit now,’ she says.

I’ll cut this story short. This business cost me almost 300 roubles, but in two days it was arranged that I would stand in the adjoining room, behind closed doors, and listen to my wife’s first rendezvous alone with Yefimovich. Mean-while, the previous evening a brief but for me very significant scene between myself and my wife took place.

She returned towards evening, sat down on the bed, looked at me mockingly and thumped the rug with her foot. Suddenly, as I was looking at her, the idea flew into my head then that all this past month, or, rather, for the past two weeks, she had not been herself at all - one could even say that she had been exactly the opposite：a wild, aggressive being had made its appearance; I can’t say shameless, but disorderly and looking for trouble. Asking for trouble. Meekness, however, held her back. Wen a girl like that starts creating an uproar, even if she does cross the line, it’s nevertheless plain to see that she’s only hurting herself, that she’s egging herself on and that she will be the first who is unable to cope with her feelings of modesty and shame. That’s why girls like that sometimes go too far, so that you don’t believe your own eyes when you witness it. A soul accustomed to debauchery, on the contrary, always softens it, making it more vile, but in a guise of decorum and decency that claims to be superior to you.

‘And is it true that you were driven out of your regiment, because you were too cowardly to fight a duel?’she asked suddenly, out of the blue, and her eyes flashed.

‘It’s true; the officers rendered the verdict that I was to be asked to leave the regiment, although I had in any case already tendered my resignation.’

‘You were driven out as a coward?’

‘Yes, they judged me a coward. But I refused to duel not because I was a coward, but because I didn’t wish to submit to their tyrannical verdict and issue a challenge to a duel when I did not consider myself to be insulted. You should know,’ I couldn’t restrain myself here, ‘that flying in the face of such tyranny through my actions and accepting all the consequences took far more courage than any duel would have done.’

I couldn’t contain myself, with this phrase I launched into self-justifications, as it were, and that was all she needed, a fresh instance of my humiliation. She burst out in malicious laughter.

‘And is it true that for the next three years you wandered the streets of Petersburg like a tramp, and begged for kopecks, and slept under billiard tables?’

‘I even spent some nights in the Vyazemsky House on Haymarket Square. Yes, it’s true; in my life after leaving the regiment there was much shame and degradation, but not moral degradation, because I was the first to loathe my actions even then. It was merely the degradation of my will and mind, and it was brought about only by the desperation of my situation. But this passe ...’

‘Oh, now you’re an important person - a financier!’

That is, a hint at my pawnshop. But I had already man-aged to hold myself in check. I saw that she thirsted for explanations that would be humiliating for me and - I didn’t give them. Fortunately, a client rang the bell just then and I went to see him in the front room. Afterwards, an hour later, when she had suddenly dressed to go out, she stopped in front of me and said：

‘You didn’t tell me anything about this before the wed-ding, however.’

I didn’t answer, and she left.

And so, the next day I stood in this room behind the door and listened to my fate being decided, and in my pocket there was a revolver. She was dressed up, sitting at the table, and Yefimovich was putting on airs. And what do you know：it turned out （I say this to my credit）, it turned out exactly as I had foreseen and supposed, though without realizing that I had foreseen and supposed this. I don’t know whether I’m expressing myself clearly.

This is what happened. I listened for a whole hour and for that hour I witnessed a duel between the most noble and lofty woman and a worldly, depraved, dim-witted creature with a grovelling soul. And how, I thought to myself in amazement, how does this naive, this meek, this reserved girl know all this? The cleverest author of a high-society comedy could not have created this scene of ridicule, the most naive laughter and the holy contempt of virtue for vice. And such brilliance in her words and little turns of speech; what wit in her quick replies, what truth in her censure! And at the same time what almost girlish ingenuousness. She laughed in his face at his declarations of love, at his gestures, at his proposals. Coming straight to the matter with a crude assault and not foreseeing any opposition, all of a sudden he had the wind taken out of his sails. at first I might have thought that it was simply coquetry on her part - the ‘coquetry of a clever though depraved creature in order to show herself more lavishly’. But no, the truth shone through like the sun and it was impossible to have any doubts. It was only out of hatred for me, affected and impetuous though it was, that she, inexperienced as she was, could have decided to undertake this meeting, but as soon as it had become reality - her eyes were opened at once. Here was a creature who was simply flailing about so as to insult me no matter what, but once she had decided on such filth she couldn’t bear the disorder. And could she, blameless and pure, with ideals, have been attracted to Yefimovich or any of those other high-society brutes? On the contrary, he aroused only laughter. The whole truth rose up from her soul, and indig-nation called forth sarcasm from her heart. I repeat, towards the end this fool was utterly dazed and sat scowling, barely responding, so that I even began to fear that he would ven-ture to insult her out of mean-spirited revenge. And I repeat once again：to my credit I heard this scene out almost with-out astonishment. It was as though I had encountered something familiar. It was as though I had gone in order to encounter it. I had gone, believing nothing, no accusation, although I did put a revolver in my pocket-that’s the truth! And could I have really imagined her otherwise? Wasn’t that why I loved her, wasn’t that why I cherished her, wasn’t that why I had married her? Oh, of course, I was all too con-vinced that she hated me then, but I was also convinced of her purity. I brought the scene swiftly to a close by opening the door. Yefimovich jumped to his feet, I took her by the hand and invited her to leave with me. Yefimovich found his bearings and suddenly burst out in resounding peals of laughter.

‘Oh, I have no objections to sacred conjugal rights, take her away, take her away! And you know,’ he shouted after me, ‘even though a respectable person can’t fight you, yet out of respect for your lady, I am at your servic ... If you, however, want to risk i ... ’

‘Do you hear that!’ I stopped her for a second on the threshold.

Then not a word all the way home. I led her by the hand, and she didn’t resist. On the contrary, she was utterly dumb-founded, but only until we got home. On our arrival, she sat down on a chair and fastened her gaze on me. She was extraordinarily pale; though her lips had at once formed a mocking smile, she was already regarding me with a solemn and severe challenge, and, I believe, she was seriously con-vinced those first few moments that I was going to kill her with the revolver. But I took the revolver out of my pocket in silence and laid it on the table. She looked at me and at the revolver.（Note：she was already familiar with this revolver. I had acquired it and kept it loaded ever since open-ing the shop. Wen I was getting ready to open the shop I had decided not to keep hulking dogs or a burly lackey like Mozer did, for example. The cook opens the door for my visitors. But people who engage in my trade cannot deprive themselves of self-defence, just in case, and I kept a loaded revolver. During those first days when she had come to live in my house she showed a lot of interest in this revolver, she asked a lot of questions, and I even explained the mechanism and how it worked; moreover, I persuaded her once to shoot at a target. Note all that.）Paying no notice of her frightened look, I lay down on the bed half-undressed. I was very tired; it was already almost eleven o’clock. She went on sitting in the same place, without moving, for almost another hour, then she put out the candle and lay down, also dressed, on the sofa by the wall. It was the first time that she didn’t come to bed with me - note that as wel ...

VI. A TERRIBLE MEMORY

Now, this terrible memor ...

I woke up in the morning, between seven and eight, I think, and it was already almost completely light in the room. I woke up all at once fully conscious and suddenly opened my eyes. She was standing by the table, holding the revolver. She didn’t see that I was awake and watching. And suddenly I saw that she had started to move towards me, holding the revolver. I quickly shut my eyes and pretended to be fast asleep.

She came up to the bed and stood over me. I heard every-thing; although a dead silence had fallen, I heard even that silence. Then there came a convulsive movement - and I suddenly, uncontrollably, opened my eyes against my will. She was looking me right in the eyes, and the revolver was already by my temple. Our eyes met. But we looked at each other for no more than a moment. I forced myself to shut my eyes again and at the same moment I resolved with every fibre of my being that I would not stir or open my eyes, no matter what awaited me.

In fact, it does happen sometimes that a person who is sound asleep suddenly opens his eyes, even raises his head for a second and looks about the room, then, a moment later, he lays his head on the pillow again and falls asleep without remembering a thing. Wen, after meeting her gaze and feeling the revolver at my temple, I suddenly shut my eyes again and didn’t stir, like someone sound asleep, she cer-tainly could have supposed that I indeed was asleep and that I hadn’t seen anything, particularly since it was altogether incredible that having seen what I saw I would shut my eyes again at such a moment.

Yes, incredible. But she still might have guessed the truth - that was what suddenly flashed through my mind, at that very same moment. Oh, what a whirlwind of thoughts, sensations raced through my mind in less than a moment; long live the electricity of human thought! In that case （I felt）, if she had guessed the truth and knew that I wasn’t sleeping, then I had already crushed her with my readiness to accept death and her hand might now falter. Her former resolve might be shattered by this new extraordinary impres-sion. They say that people standing on a height are drawn downwards, as it were, of their own accord, to the abyss. I think that a lot of suicides and murders have been committed merely because the revolver was already in hand. There’s an abyss here as well, there’s a forty-five-degree slope down which you can’t help but slide and something relentlessly challenges you to pull the trigger. But the awareness that I had seen everything, that I knew everything and that I was awaiting my death from her in silence-might hold her back from that slope.

The silence continued, and suddenly I felt on my temple, at my hairline, the cold touch of iron. You will ask：did I firmly hope that I would be saved? I will answer you as if I were before God himself：I had no hope whatsoever, except perhaps one chance in a hundred. Wy, then, did I accept death? But I will ask：Wat need would I have of life after the revolver was raised against me by the being whom I adored? Moreover, I knew with all the force of my being that a struggle was going on between us at that very moment, a terrible duel for life and death, a duel of that same coward of yesterday, driven out by his comrades. I knew it, and she knew it, if only she had guessed the truth that I wasn’t sleeping.

Perhaps it wasn’t like that, perhaps I didn’t think that then, but still it must have been like that, even without thought, because all I’ve done since is think about it every hour of my life.

But you’ll ask me the question again：why didn’t I save her then from this treachery? Oh, I have asked myself that question a thousand times since-each time when, with a shiver down my spine, I recalled that second. But my soul then was plunged in dark despair：I was lost, I myself was lost, so whom could I have saved? And how do you know whether I still wanted to save somebody then? How can you know what I might have been feeling then?

My consciousness, however, was seething; the seconds passed, there was dead silence; she was still standing over me - and then suddenly I shuddered with hope! I quickly opened my eyes. She was no longer in the room. I got up from the bed：I had defeated her-and she was forever defeated!

I went out to the samovar. We always had the samovar brought to the outer room and she was always the one to pour the tea. I sat down at the table in silence and took a glass of tea from her. About five minutes later I glanced at her. She was terribly pale, even paler than yesterday, and she was looking at me. And suddenly - and suddenly, seeing that I was looking at her, she gave a pale smile with her pale lips, a timid question in her eyes.‘That means that she still has doubts and is asking herself：does he know or not, did he see or didn’t he?’ I indifferently turned my eyes away. After tea I locked up the shop, went to the market and bought an iron bed and a screen. Wen I returned home, I had the bed installed in the front room with the screen around it. This bed was for her, but I didn’t say a word to her. Even without words she understood from this bed alone that I ‘had seen everything and knew everything’and that there was no longer any doubt about this. I left the revolver on the table for the night as always. At night she silently got into her new bed：the marriage was dissolved, ‘she had been defeated but not forgiven’. During the night she became delirious, and by morning she had a fever. She was confined to bed for six weeks.

Chapter 2

I. A DREAM OF PRIDE

Lukerya just announced that she won’t stay with me and that she’ll leave as soon as the mistress is buried. I prayed on my knees for five minutes, and I had wanted to pray for an hour, but I keep thinking, and thinking, and they’re all such aching thoughts and my head aches - what’s the use of praying - it’s nothing but a sin! It’s also strange that I don’t want to sleep：in great, in such great sorrow, after the first violent outbursts, one always wants to sleep. They say that people who are condemned to death sleep extremely soundly on their last night. As they should, it’s only natural, other-wise they wouldn’t have the strength to endure i ... I lay down on the sofa, but I didn’t fall aslee ...

...For the six weeks of her illness we took care of her day and night-Lukerya and I and a trained nurse from the hos-pital, whom I had hired. I didn’t begrudge the money, and even wanted to spend money on her. I called in Dr Schroeder and paid him ten roubles a visit. Wen she regained con-sciousness, I started to show myself less often. But why am I describing this? Wen she was completely on her feet again, she sat quietly and silently in my room at a special table, which I had also bought for her at the tim ... Yes, it’s true, we were perfectly silent; that is, we began to talk later on, but only about the usual things. Of course, I delib-erately refrained from becoming expansive, but I could see very well that she also was happy not to say a word more than was necessary. This seemed perfectly natural on her part：‘She is too shaken and too defeated,’ I thought, ‘and of course she needs time to forget and get used to things.’And so it was that we were silent, but every minute I was secretly preparing myself for the future. I thought that she was doing the same as well, and it was terribly entertaining for me to guess：Exactly what is she thinking about now?

I’ll say one more thing：Oh, of course, nobody knows what I endured as I grieved over her during her illness. But I kept my grief to myself and kept the grieving in my heart even from Lukerya. I couldn’t imagine, I couldn’t even suppose that she would die without learning everything. Wen she was out of danger and her health started to return, I remem-ber this, I quickly calmed down and very much so. Wat’s more, I decided to postpone our future for as long as possible, and for the present to leave everything as it was now. Yes, then something happened to me that was strange and pecu-liar, I don’t know what else to call it：I had triumphed and this thought alone proved to be quite sufficient for me. And that’s how the whole winter passed. Oh, I was pleased as I had never been before, and that for the whole winter.

You see：in my life there had been one terrible external circumstance, which until then, that is, until the catastrophe with my wife, weighed heavily on me every day and every hour, namely, the loss of my reputation and leaving the regi-ment. To put it in a nutshell：this had been a tyrannical injustice against me. True, my comrades disliked me on account of my difficult and, perhaps, ridiculous character, although it often happens that what you find sublime, what you hold dear and esteem, for some reason at the same time makes a group of your comrades laugh. Oh, I was never liked, even in school. I’ve never been liked anywhere. Even Lukerya cannot like me. The incident in the regiment, though a consequence of this dislike for me, without a doubt bore an accidental character. I mention this because there’s nothing more exasperating and intolerable than to be ruined by an incident that might or might not have happened, by an unfortunate chain of circumstances that might have passed over, like a cloud. It’s humiliating for an educated man. The incident was as follows.

During the intermission at the theatre I went to the bar. Hussar A—v came in suddenly and began talking loudly with two of his fellow hussars in the presence of all the offi-cers and public gathered there about how Bezumtsev, the captain of our regiment, had just caused a scandal in the corridor ‘and he seems to be drunk’. The conversation moved on to other things; besides, there had been a mistake, because Captain Bezumtsev wasn’t drunk, and there hadn’t really been a scandal. The hussars began talking about some-thing else, and that was the end of it, but the next day the story made its way to our regiment, and at once they began saying how I was the only person at the bar from our regi-ment and that when Hussar A—v spoke insolently of Captain Bezumtsev I had not gone over to A—v and put a stop to it by reprimanding him. But why on earth should I have done that? If he had it in for Bezumtsev, then it was their personal affair, and why should I get involved? Meanwhile, the offi-cers began to take the position that the affair was not personal but concerned the regiment, and that since I was the only officer of our regiment present, I had proved by my conduct to all the officers at the bar as well as the public that there might be officers in our regiment who were not overly scrupulous concerning their honour and the regiment’s. I could not agree with this verdict. I was given to understand that I might still set everything right even now, belatedly, if I should wish to demand a formal explanation from A—v. I did not wish to do so and since I was annoyed, I refused with pride. I then at once resigned my commission - and that’s the whole story. I left proud, but with my spirit crushed. My mind and will both foundered. It was just then that my sis-ter’s husband squandered our little fortune and my portion of it, a tiny portion, so I was left on the street without a kopeck. I could have found employment in a private busi-ness, but I didn’t：after wearing my splendid regimental uniform I couldn’t go work on some railroad. And so - if it’s shame, let it be shame, if it’s disgrace, let it be disgrace, if it’s degradation, let it be degradation, and the worse, the better - that’s what I chose. There followed three years of gloomy memories, even of the Vyazemsky House. A year and a half ago a rich old lady, my godmother, died in Moscow and among other bequests unexpectedly left me 3，000 in her will. I gave it some thought and then decided my fate. I set-tled on the pawnshop, with no apologies to anyone：money, then a corner and - a new life far away from my former memories - that was the plan. Nevertheless, my gloomy past and the reputation of my honour, forever ruined, tormented me every hour, every minute. But then I married. By chance or not - I don’t know. But when I brought her into my house, I thought that I was bringing a friend, I greatly needed a friend. But I saw clearly that my friend had to be prepared, given the finishing touches, and even defeated. And could I have explained anything straight off like that to this sixteen-year-old girl with her prejudices? For example, how could I, without the accidental assistance of the terrible catastrophe with the revolver, have convinced her that I wasn’t a coward and that I had been unjustly accused by the regiment of being a coward? But the catastrophe arrived just at the right moment. Having stood up to the revolver, I had avenged all of my gloomy past. And even though nobody knew about it, she knew about it, and that was everything for me, because she was everything to me, all my hopes for the future in my dreams! She was the only person whom I was preparing for myself, and I didn’t need another-and now she knew everything; at least she knew that she had unjustly hurried to join my enemies. This thought delighted me. In her eyes I could no longer be a scoundrel, but merely a peculiar person, and even this thought, after everything that had happened, did not at all displease me：peculiarity is not a vice; on the contrary, it sometimes attracts the fem-inine character. In a word, I deliberately postponed the finale：what had taken place was more than sufficient, for the time being, for my peace of mind and contained more than enough pictures and material for my dreams. That’s the nasty thing about this-I’m a dreamer：I had enough material; as for her, I thought that she would wait.

And so the whole winter passed in some sort of expectation of something. I liked to steal looks at her, when she happened to be sitting at her little table. She would be busy with her needlework, with the linen, and in the evenings she would sometimes read books which she would take from my book-case. The choice of books in the bookcase should also have spoken in my favour. She hardly ever went out. Every day after dinner, before dusk, I would take her for a walk and we would go for our constitutional, but not completely in silence, as before. I precisely tried to make it look as though we weren’t being silent and were speaking harmoniously, but as I’ve already said we both avoided getting carried away talking. I was doing this on purpose, while she, I thought, needed to be ‘given time’. Of course, it’s strange that it did not once occur to me until almost the very end of the winter that though I liked to look at her on the sly, I never once caught her looking at me that whole winter! I thought that it was timidity on her part. Moreover, she had an air about her of such timid meek-ness, such weakness after her illness. No, better to bide one’s time and-‘and she will suddenly come to you on her ow ... ’

That thought delighted me irresistibly. I will add one thing：sometimes it was as if I had deliberately inflamed myself and really brought my heart and mind to the point that I would feel that I had been wronged by her. And so it continued for some time. But my hatred could never ripen and take root in my soul. And I even felt that it was only some sort of game. And even then, although I had dissolved our marriage by buying the bed and screen, never, never could I see her as a criminal. And not because I judged her crime lightly, but because it made sense to forgive her com-pletely, from the very first day, even before I bought the bed. In a word, this was a strange move on my part, for I am morally stern. On the contrary, in my eyes she was so defeated, so humiliated, so crushed that I sometimes felt tormenting pity for her, even though at the same time I sometimes definitely found the idea of her humiliation pleas-ing. The idea of our inequality pleased m ...

That winter it so happened that I deliberately performed several good deeds. I forgave two debts, I gave money to one poor woman without any pledge. And I didn’t tell my wife about this, and I hadn’t done this so that she would find out; but the woman came to thank me herself, she was prac-tically on her knees. And that was how it became known; it seemed to me that she was truly pleased to find out about the woman.

But spring was approaching, it was already the middle of April, the storm windows had been taken down, and the sun began to light up our silent rooms with its bright pencils of light. But scales hung before my eyes and blinded my reason. Fateful, terrible scales! How did it come about that they suddenly fell from my eyes and that I suddenly could see clearly and understand everything! Was it chance, was it that the appointed day had come, was it a ray of sunshine that had kindled the thought and conjecture in my benumbed mind? No, it wasn’t a matter of a thought but rather a nerve began to play up, a nerve that had grown numb began to quiver and came to life and illuminated my entire benumbed soul and my demonic pride. It was as if I had suddenly jumped up from my seat then. And it happened suddenly and unexpectedly. It happened towards evening, at about five o’clock, after dinne ...

II. THE SCALES SUDDENLY FALL

A couple of words first. A month earlier I had noticed a strange pensiveness in her, not just silence, but pensiveness. I had also noticed this suddenly. She was sitting at her work at the time, her head bent over her sewing, and she didn’t see that I was looking at her. And suddenly I was struck by how delicate and thin she had become, that her face was pale, her lips were drained of colour - all this as a whole, taken together with her pensiveness, shocked me all at once in the extreme. I had already heard earlier a little dry cough, particularly at night. I got up at once and set off to ask Schroeder to pay us a visit, without saying anything to her.

Schroeder came the following day. She was very surprised and looked first at Schroeder and then at me.

‘But I’m fine,’ she said with an uncertain smile.

Schroeder didn’t examine her very thoroughly （these med-ical men sometimes are condescendingly off hand）, and merely told me in the other room that it was the remnants of her illness and that come spring it wouldn’t be a bad idea to take a trip somewhere to the sea or if that were not possible, then simply to find a place in the country. In a word, he didn’t say anything other than that there was some weakness or something of the sort. Wen Schroeder had gone, she suddenly said to me again, looking at me terribly seriously：

‘I’m really, really fine.’

But after saying this, she then and there suddenly flushed, apparently from shame. Apparently, it was shame. Oh, now I understand：She was ashamed that I was still her husband, that I was taking care of her as if I were still her real hus-band. But I didn’t understand then and ascribed her blush to humility. （The scales!）

And then, a month later, between five and six o’clock, in April, on a bright sunny day I was sitting in the shop and doing the accounts. Suddenly I heard her in our room, at her table, over her work, singing ever so softl ... This new development made a tremendous impression on me, and to this day I don’t understand it. Until then I had almost never heard her sing, except perhaps in the very first days when I brought her into my house and we could still have some fun, target shooting with the revolver. Then her voice was still rather strong, ringing, though a bit off -key, but terribly pleasant and healthy. But now her little song sounded so feeble - oh, not that it was doleful （it was some romance）, but it was as if there was something cracked, broken, in her voice, as if the little voice couldn’t cope, as if the song itself were ailing. She was singing under her breath, and suddenly, after rising, the voice broke - such a poor little voice, it broke so pitifully; she cleared her throat and started singing again, ever so softly, you could barely hear he ...

My agitation may be laughable, but no one will ever understand why I had become so agitated! No, I didn’t feel sorry for her yet; it was still something altogether different. At the beginning, for the first moments at least, I suddenly felt bewilderment and terrible surprise, terrible and strange, painful and almost vindictive：‘She is singing and in my presence!Has she forgotten about me, is that it?’

Completely shaken, I stayed where I was, then I suddenly rose, took my hat and left, without thinking it through, as it were. At least I didn’t know why or where I was going. Lukerya started helping me on with my coat.

‘She sings?’I said to Lukerya unintentionally. She didn’t understand and looked at me, still not understanding; but I really had been incomprehensible.

‘Is this the first time that she’s been singing?’

‘No, she sometimes sings when you’re not here,’ Lukerya replied.

I remember everything. I walked down the stairs, went out into the street and set off for nowhere in particular. I walked as far as the corner and began to stare off into the distance. People passed by me, jostled me, but I didn’t feel it. I hailed a cab and told him to take me to the Police Bridge, I don’t know why. But then I suddenly changed my mind and gave him a twenty-kopeck piece.

‘That’s for your trouble,’ I said, laughing senselessly, but some sort of rapture had suddenly begun to fill my heart.

I turned around and went home, quickening my step. The cracked, poor, broken little note suddenly rang out in my heart again. It took my breath away. The scales were falling, falling from my eyes! If she’d started singing in my presence, then she had forgotten about me - that’s what was clear and terrible. My heart sensed this. But rapture shone in my soul and overcame my fear.

Oh, the irony of fate! You see, there had been nothing else and there could not have been anything else in my soul all winter except this very rapture, but where had I myself been all winter long? Had I been there with my soul? I ran up the stairs in a great hurry, I don’t know whether I walked in timidly or not. I remember only that the entire floor seemed to be rippling and it was as if I were floating down a river. I walked into the room, she was sitting in the same place, sewing, with her head bent, but no longer singing. She threw me a fleeting and incurious glance, but it wasn’t even a glance, merely the usual, indifferent gesture one makes when somebody enters a room.

I walked straight up to her and sat down on a chair right beside her, like a madman. She gave me a quick look, as though she were frightened：I took her by the hand and I don’t remember what I said to her, that is, what I wanted to say, because I couldn’t even speak properly. My voice kept breaking and wouldn’t obey me. And I didn’t know what to say, I just kept gasping for breath.

‘Let’s tal ... you kno ... say something!’ I suddenly babbled something stupid-oh, but was I capable of making sense? She flinched again and recoiled, badly frightened, looking at my face, but suddenly - stern surprise appeared in her eyes. Yes, surprise, and stern. She was looking at me wide-eyed. This sternness, this stern surprise came crashing down on me all at once：‘So you still want love? Love?’that surprise seemed to ask suddenly, although she was silent as well. But I could read it all, all of it. My whole being was shaken and I simply fell to the ground at her feet. Yes, I collapsed at her feet. She quickly jumped up, but I restrained her by taking hold of both her hands with extraordinary force.

And I fully understood my despair, oh, I understood! But would you believe it, rapture was seething in my heart so irrepressibly that I thought I would die. I kissed her feet in ecstasy and happiness. Yes, in happiness, immeasurable and infinite, yet understanding nonetheless all my hopeless despair! I wept, said something, but couldn’t speak. Her fright and surprise suddenly gave way to some anxious thought, some extreme question, and she looked at me strangely, wildly even-she wanted to understand something quickly, and she smiled. She was terribly ashamed that I was kissing her feet, and she kept moving back, but I would at once kiss the spot on the floor where she had been standing. She saw this and suddenly began to laugh from shame （you know how people laugh from shame）. Hysterics weren’t far off, I saw that, her hands quivered - I didn’t give it a thought and kept muttering that I loved her, that I wouldn’t get up, ‘...let me kiss your dres ... I’ll worship you like this for as long as you liv...’ I don’t know, I don’t remember - and suddenly she burst out into sobs and started trembling; a terrible fit of hysteria had set in. I had frightened her.

I carried her over to the bed. Wen the fit had passed, she sat up on the bed and with a terribly distraught look, seized me by the hands and pleaded with me to calm myself：‘Enough, don’t torment yourself, calm yourself!’ and she began to weep again. I didn’t leave her side all that evening. I kept telling her that I’d take her to Boulogne to bathe in the sea, now, right away, in two weeks, that she had such a cracked little voice, I had heard it earlier that day, that I would close the pawnshop, sell it to Dobronravov, that every-thing would begin afresh, and the main thing, to Boulogne, to Boulogne! She listened and was still afraid. She was more and more afraid. But that wasn’t the main thing for me, but rather that I more and more irrepressibly wanted to lie down again at her feet, and once again, to kiss, to kiss the ground on which her feet stood, and to idolize her and - ‘I’ll ask nothing more of you, nothing,’ I kept repeating every min-ute.‘Don’t answer me anything, don’t take any notice of me at all, and only let me look at you from the corner, turn me into your thing, into your little do ... ’ She wept.

‘But I thought that you were going to leave me like that,’ suddenly burst forth from her involuntarily, so involuntarily that perhaps she didn’t notice at all how she had said it, and yet - oh, it was the most important, her most fateful word and the most comprehensible for me that evening, and it was as if it had slashed my heart like a knife. It explained every-thing to me, everything, but as long as she was there beside me, before my eyes, I went on hoping irrepressibly and was terribly happy. Oh, I wore her out terribly that evening and I understood that, but I kept thinking that I would change everything at once. Finally, towards nightfall, she broke down completely; I persuaded her to go to sleep, and she immediately fell sound asleep. I expected delirium, and there was delirium, but it was very mild. I got up during the night every few minutes, and would quietly go in my slippers to look at her. I wrung my hands over her, as I looked at this sick being lying on that pathetic little cot, the iron bedstead that I had bought for her then for three roubles. I got down on my knees but I didn’t dare kiss her feet while she was sleeping （against her wishes!）. I would start praying to God, and then jump up again. Lukerya watched me closely and kept coming out of the kitchen. I went to her and told her to go to bed and that tomorrow ‘something quite different’would begin.

And I believed that blindly, madly, terribly. Oh, I was surging with rapture, rapture. I couldn’t wait for tomorrow. The main thing, I didn’t believe in any misfortune, despite the symptoms. My powers of understanding had not yet fully returned, even though the scales had fallen, and for a long, long time would not return - oh, not until today, not until this very day! And how, how could my understanding have returned then：you see, she was still alive then, you see, she was right there before me, and I before her. ‘She’ll wake up tomorrow, and I’ll tell her all this, and she’ll see it all.’ That was my reasoning then, clear and simple, hence the rapture! The main thing was this trip to Boulogne. For some reason I thought that Boulogne was everything, that there was something final about Boulogne.‘To Boulogne, to Boulogne!...’ I waited for morning in a state of madness.

III. I UNDERSTAND ALL TOO WELL

But this was only a few days ago, you see, five days, only five days ago, just last Tuesday! No, no, if only there had been a little more time, if only she had waited just a little bit longer and - and I would have dispelled the darkness! And hadn’t she calmed down? The very next day she listened to me with a smile even, despite her confusion. The main thing was that during all this time, all five days, she was either confused or ashame ... She was also afraid, very afraid. I don’t dispute it, I won’t deny it, like some madman：there was fear, but then how could she not be afraid? You see, we’d been strangers to each other for so long, we had grown so far apart from one another, and suddenly all thi ... But I didn’t pay attention to her fear - something new was shin-ing!... Yes, it’s undoubtedly true that I’d made a mistake. And perhaps even many mistakes. And as soon as we woke up the next day, when it was still morning （this was on Wed-nesday）, I suddenly made a mistake right away：I suddenly made her my friend. I was in a hurry, much too much of a hurry, but a confession was necessary, essential - and much more than a confession! I didn’t even conceal that which I had concealed from myself all my life. I told her straight out that I had done nothing all winter long but be certain of her love. I explained to her that the pawnshop had been merely the degradation of my will and mind, my personal idea of self-flagellation and self-exaltation. I explained to her that I had indeed turned coward that time at the bar, and that it was owing to my character, my touchiness：I was struck by the surroundings, I was struck by the bar; I was struck by how I would end up looking in all this and wouldn’t it end up looking stupid? I didn’t turn coward on account of the duel, but because it would end up looking stupi ... And then later I didn’t want to admit it, and tormented everyone, and tormented her for it as well, and then I married her so that I could torment her on account of it. In general, for the most part I spoke as though I were in a fever. She herself took me by the hands and begged me to stop：‘You’re exag-geratin ... you’re tormenting yourself’, and the tears would begin again, and again there’d almost be a fit of hysteria. She kept pleading with me not to say or remember any of this.

I paid little or no attention to her pleas：spring, Boulogne! There was the sun, there was our new sun, that was all I talked about! I locked up the shop, handed over the busi-ness to Dobronravov. I suddenly suggested to her that we give away everything to the poor, except for the initial 3，000 I had received from my godmother, which we would use to travel to Boulogne, and then we’d come back and begin our new working life. And so it was decided, because she didn’t say anythin ... she merely smiled. And I believe she smiled more out of a sense of delicacy, so as not to upset me. Of course, I saw that I was a burden to her, don’t think that I was so stupid or such an egoist that I didn’t see that. I saw everything, everything, right down to the last detail, I saw and knew better than anyone else; my despair was there for all to see!

I told her everything about myself and about her. And about Lukerya. I told her that I had wep ... Oh, I’d change the subject, you see, I was also trying not to remind her of certain things at all. And, you see, she even livened up once or twice, you see, I remember, I remember! Wy do you say that I looked and saw nothing? And if only this had not hap-pened, everything would have been resurrected. You see, it was she who told me the day before yesterday, when the conversation turned to reading and what she had read that winter - you see, it was she who told me and laughed, when she recalled that scene between Gil Blas and the Archbishop of Granada. And what a childish laugh, sweet, just like when she was still my fiancée （an instant! an instant!）; I was so happy! I was terribly struck, however, by the archbishop：you see, that meant she had found enough peace of mind and happiness to laugh at that masterpiece while she sat there that winter. That means that she had already begun to find herself wholly at peace, that she had already begun to be wholly persuaded that I would leave her like that. ‘I thought that you were going to leave me like that’ - that’s what she had said then on Tuesday! Oh, the thought of a ten-year-old girl! And you see, she believed, believed that everything would in fact remain like that：she at her table, I at mine, and that’s how it would be for both of us until we were sixty. And suddenly - here I come forward, her husband, and her husband needs love! Oh, the incompre-hensibility, oh, my blindness!

It was also a mistake to look at her with rapture; I should have exercised restraint, because the rapture frightened her. But you see, I did exercise restraint, I didn’t kiss her feet anymore. Not once did I make a show of the fac ... well, that I was her husband - oh, and it didn’t even cross my mind, I only worshipped her! But you see, I couldn’t be completely silent, I couldn’t say nothing at all, you see! I suddenly told her that I enjoyed her conversation and that I considered her incomparably, incomparably more educated and developed than I. Embarrassed, she blushed bright red and said that I was exaggerating. At this point, unable to contain myself, I foolishly told her what rapture I’d felt when I stood behind the door and listened to her duel, a duel of innocence with that beast, and how I had taken pleasure in her intelligence, her sparkling wit, combined with such childlike simple-heartedness. She seemed to shudder all over, murmured again that I was exaggerating, but suddenly her whole face darkened, she covered it with her hands and burst into sob ... Here I was unable to hold myself back：I again fell down before her, I again started to kiss her feet and again it ended in a fit, just as it had on Tuesday. That was yesterday evening, but the next mornin ...

Next morning?! Madman, but that morning was today, just now, only just now!

Listen and consider carefully：you see, when we met just now （this was after yesterday’s attack）, she even struck me with her calmness, that’s how it was! Wile all night long I had been trembling with fear over what had happened yes-terday. But suddenly she comes up to me, stands before me and with her arms folded （just now, just now!）, began by telling me that she’s a criminal, that she knows this, that the crime has tormented her all winter long, and is tormenting her no ... that she values my magnanimity all too muc ... ‘I’ll be your true wife, I’ll respect yo ... ’ Here I jumped up and embraced her like a madman! I kissed her, I kissed her face, her lips, like a husband, for the first time after a long separation. But why did I go out just now, for only two hour ... our foreign passport ... Oh, God! If only I had returned five minutes earlier, just five minutes!...And now there’s this crowd at our gate, these eyes fixed on m ... Oh, Lord!

Lukerya says （oh, I won’t let Lukerya go now for anything, she knows everything, she was here all winter, she’ll tell me everything）, she says that after I left the house and only some twenty minutes before my return-she suddenly went into our room to see the mistress to ask her something, I don’t remember what, and she saw that her icon （the same icon of the Mother of God） had been taken down and was on the table before her, and that her mistress seemed to have been praying before it.‘Wat’s wrong, mistress?’‘Nothing, Luk-erya, you may g ... Wait, Lukerya,’ she walked up to her and kissed her.‘Are you happy, mistress?’ I ask.‘Yes, Luk-erya.’ ‘The master should have come to ask your forgiveness long ag ... Thank God, you’ve made up.’ ‘All right, Luk-erya,’ she says, ‘leave me, Lukerya.’ And she smiled, but so strangely. So strangely that ten minutes later Lukerya sud-denly went back to look in on her：‘She was standing by the wall, right by the window, she had placed her hand on the wall, and laid her head on her hand, she was standing like that and thinking. And she was so lost in thought standing there that she didn’t hear me standing there and watching her from the other room. I saw that she was smiling, as it were, standing, thinking and smiling. I looked at her, turned around ever so quietly and walked out, thinking to myself, only suddenly I hear the window being opened. I at once went to say that“it’s fresh, mistress, you’ll catch cold” - and suddenly I see that she’s climbed up on to the window and is already standing there upright, in the open window, with her back towards me and holding the icon. My heart just sank then and I cried out：“Mistress, mistress!” She heard, made a move as if to turn around towards me, but didn’t, instead she took a step, clutched the icon to her breast-and threw herself out the window!’

I only remember that when I entered the gates she was still warm. The main thing is that they’re all looking at me. at first they were shouting, but then they suddenly fell silent and they all make way for me an ... and she’s lying there with the icon. I remember, though darkly, that I walked over in silence and looked for a long time, and they all gathered round and are saying something to me. Lukerya was there, but I didn’t see her. She says that she spoke with me. I remember only that tradesman：he kept shouting at me ‘only a handful of blood came out of her mouth, a handful, a handful!’ and pointing to the blood on a stone. I think I touched the blood with my finger, smeared some on my finger, looked at my finger （I remember that）, and he kept saying to me：‘A handful, a handful!’

‘And what do you mean“a handful”?’ I wailed, they say, with all my might, I raised my arms and threw myself at hi ...

Oh, it’s absurd, absurd! Incomprehensibility! Improbabil-ity! Impossibility!

IV. ONLY FIVE MINUTES TOO LATE

But is it really? Is it really probable? Can one really say that it was possible? Wy, for what reason did this woman die?

Oh, believe me, I understand; but why she died is still a question. She was frightened of my love, she asked herself seriously whether she should accept it or not, and she couldn’t bear the question and it was better to die. I know, I know, there’s no use in racking my brains over it：she had made too many promises, got frightened that she couldn’t keep them-that’s clear. There are a number of circum-stances here that are quite terrible.

Because why did she die? The question persists, all the same. The question hammers, hammers away in my brain. I would even have left her like that if she had wished to be left like that. She didn’t believe it, that’s what! No, no, I’m lying, that’s not it at all. It was simply because with me it had to be honest：to love meant to love completely, and not like she would have loved the merchant. And since she was too chaste, too pure to agree to a love like a merchant needs, she didn’t want to deceive me. She didn’t want to deceive me with half a love or a quarter of a love under the guise of love. She was much too honest, that’s what it is, gentlemen! I wanted to cultivate breadth of heart then, do you remember? A strange thought.

I’m terribly curious：did she respect me? I don’t know. Did she despise me or not? I don’t think she did. It’s terribly strange：why didn’t it occur to me all winter long that she despised me? I was utterly convinced of the contrary right until the moment when she looked at me then with stern surprise. Precisely, stern. It was then that I understood at once that she despised me. I understood irrevocably and forever! Ah, let her, let her despise me, for her whole life even, but let her live, live! Just now she was still walking, talking. I don’t at all understand how she could throw herself out the window! And how could I have supposed that even five minutes earlier? I summoned Lukerya. I won’t let Lukerya go now for anything, not for anything!

Oh, we could still have come to an understanding. It’s just that we had grown so terribly unused to each other during the winter, but couldn’t we have become accustomed to one another again? Wy, why couldn’t we have come together and begun a new life again? I’m magnanimous, and so is she-that’s the point of connection! Just a few words more, two days, no more, and she would have understood everything.

The main thing, it’s a pity that it all comes down to chance - simple, barbaric inertia, chance. That’s the pity of it! All of five minutes, I was only five minutes late! If I had arrived five minutes earlier - the moment would have passed by, like a cloud, and it would never have occurred to her again. And it would have ended by her understanding every-thing. But now the rooms stand empty again and I’m alone once again. There’s the pendulum ticking, it doesn’t care, it doesn’t feel sorry for anyone. There’s no one - that’s the awful thing!

I pace, I keep pacing. I know, I know, don’t try to put words in my mouth：you think it’s ridiculous that I complain about chance and the five minutes? But it’s obvious, you see. Consider one thing：she didn’t even leave a note saying, ‘Don’t blame anyone for my death’, like everyone does. Could she really not have considered that even Lukerya might get into trouble? They might say, ‘You were alone with her, so you must have pushed her.’In any event, she would have been dragged away, innocent though she was, if four people in the courtyard hadn’t seen from the windows of the wing and the courtyard how she stood there holding the icon and hurled herself down. But, you see, that’s chance as well that people were standing and saw it. No, this was all a moment, just one inexplicable moment. Suddenness and fan-tasy! So what if she was praying before the icon? That doesn’t mean that this was before death. The entire moment lasted, perhaps, all of some ten minutes, the entire decision-precisely when she was standing by the wall, with her head resting on her arm, and smiling. The thought flew into her head, her head started spinning and-and she couldn’t withstand it.

It was a clear misunderstanding, say what you will. She could still have lived with me. But what if it was anaemia? Simply on account of anaemia, the exhaustion of vital energy? She had grown tired during the winter, that’s what it wa ...

I was late!

How very thin she is in the coffin, how sharp her little nose has become! Her eyelashes lie like arrows. And she fell, you see - without smashing or breaking anything! Just this one ‘handful of blood’. A dessertspoon, that is. Internal concus-sion. A strange thought：Wat if it were possible not to bury her? Because if they take her away, the ... Oh, no, it’s almost impossible that she’ll be taken away! Oh, of course, I know that she must be taken away, I’m not a madman and I’m not the least bit delirious; on the contrary, my mind has never been so lucid - but how can it be that again there’ll be no one in the house, again the two rooms, and again I’m alone with the pledges. Delirium, delirium, that’s where the delirium lies! I tormented her - that’s what it was!

Wat are your laws to me now? Wat do I need with your customs, your ways, your life, your government, your faith? Let your judges judge me, let them take me to court, to your public court, and I will say that I acknowledge nothing. The judge will shout：‘Silence, officer!’ And I will cry out to him：‘Wat power do you now possess that I should obey you? Wy has dark inertia shattered that which was dearest of all? Wat need have I now of your laws? I part company with you.’Oh, it’s all the same to me!

Blind, she’s blind! Dead, she doesn’t hear! You don’t know with what paradise I would have surrounded you. The para-dise was in my soul; I would have planted it all round you! Well, you wouldn’t have loved me - so be it, what of it? Everything would have been like that, everything would have stayed like that. You would have talked to me only as a friend - and we would have rejoiced and laughed with joy, as we looked into each other’s eyes. That’s how we would have lived. And if you had fallen in love with somebody else - well, so be it, so be it! You would have walked with him and laughed, while I looked on from the other side of the stree ... Oh, let it be anything, anything, if only she would open her eyes just once! For one moment, just one! If she would look at me as she did just now, when she stood before me and swore to be my faithful wife! Oh, she would have understood it all in one glance!

Inertia! Oh, nature! People are alone on this earth-that’s the problem! ‘Is there a man alive on the field?’ the Russian bogatyr cries out. And I cry out as well, though I am not a bogatyr, and no one answers. They say that the sun gives life to the universe. The sun will rise and - look at it, isn’t it dead? Everything is dead, the dead are everywhere. There are only people, and all around them is silence - that’s the earth.‘People, love one another’ - who said that? Wose commandment is that? The pendulum ticks insensibly, dis-gustingly. It’s two o’clock in the morning. Her little shoes are by the bed, as if they were waiting for he ... No, ser-iously, when they take her away tomorrow, what will become of me?

1876

The Fox and the Goat

A Fox one day fell into a deep well and could find no means of escape. A Goat, overcome with thirst, came to the same well, and seeing the Fox, inquired if the water was good.

Concealing his sad plight under a merry guise, the Fox indulged in a lavish praise of the water, saying it was excel-lent beyond measure, and encouraging him to descend. The Goat, mindful only of his thirst, thoughtlessly jumped down, but just as he drank, the Fox informed him of the difficulty they were both in and suggested a scheme for their common escape. ‘If,’ said he, ‘you will place your forefeet upon the wall and bend your head, I will run up your back and escape, and will help you out afterwards.’

The Goat readily assented and the Fox leapt upon his back. Steadying himself with the Goat’s horns, he safely reached the mouth of the well and made off as fast as he could. When the Goat upbraided him for breaking his prom-ise, he turned around and cried out, ‘You foolish old fellow! If you had as many brains in your head as you have hairs in your beard, you would never have gone down before you had inspected the way up, nor have exposed yourself to dan-gers from which you had no means of escape.’

Look before you leap.

The Frogs Asking for a King

The Frogs, grieved at having no established Ruler, sent ambassadors to Jupiter entreating for a King.

Perceiving their simplicity, he cast down a huge log into the lake. The Frogs were terrified at the splash occasioned by its fall and hid themselves in the depths of the pool. But as soon as they realised that the huge log was motionless, they swam again to the top of the water, dismissed their fears, climbed up, and began squatting on it in contempt.

After some time they began to think themselves ill-treated in the appointment of so inert a Ruler, and sent a second deputation to Jupiter to pray that he would set over them another sovereign. He then gave them an Eel to govern them. When the Frogs discovered his easy good nature, they sent yet a third time to Jupiter to beg him to choose for them still another King.

Jupiter, displeased with all their complaints, sent a Heron, who preyed upon the Frogs day by day till there were none left to croak upon the lake.

The Stag at the Pool

A Stag overpowered by heat came to a spring to drink. See-ing his own shadow reflected in the water, he greatly admired the size and variety of his horns, but felt angry with himself for having such slender and weak feet.

While he was thus contemplating himself, a Lion appeared at the pool and crouched to spring upon him. The Stag immediately took to flight, and exerting his utmost speed, as long as the plain was smooth and open kept himself easily at a safe distance from the Lion. But entering a wood he became entangled by his horns, and the Lion quickly came up to him and caught him.

When too late, he thus reproached himself：‘Woe is me! How I have deceived myself! These feet which would have saved me I despised, and I gloried in these antlers which have proved my destruction.’

What is most truly valuable is often underrated.

The Town Mouse and the Country Mouse

A Country Mouse invited a Town Mouse, an intimate friend, to pay him a visit and partake of his country fare.

As they were on the bare plowlands, eating their wheat-stocks and roots pulled up from the hedgerow, the Town Mouse said to his friend, ‘You live here the life of the ants, while in my house is the horn of plenty. I am surrounded by every luxury, and if you will come with me, as I wish you would, you shall have an ample share of my dainties.’The Country Mouse was easily persuaded, and returned to town with his friend.

On his arrival, the Town Mouse placed before him bread, barley, beans, dried figs, honey, raisins, and, last of all, brought a dainty piece of cheese from a basket. The Country Mouse, being much delighted at the sight of such good cheer, expressed his satisfaction in warm terms and lamented his own hard fate.

Just as they were beginning to eat, someone opened the door, and they both ran off squeaking, as fast as they could, to a hole so narrow that two could only find room in it by squeezing. They had scarcely begun their repast again when someone else entered to take something out of a cupboard, whereupon the two Mice, more frightened than before, ran away and hid themselves.

At last the Country Mouse, almost famished, said to his friend：‘Although you have prepared for me so dainty a feast, Thnbsp; I must leave you to enjoy it by yourself. It is surrounded by too many dangers to please me. I prefer my bare plowlands and roots from the hedgerow, where I can live in safety, and without fear.’

Mercury and the Workmen

A Workman, felling wood by the side of a river, let his axe drop-by accident into a deep pool. Being thus deprived of the means of his livelihood, he sat down on the bank and lamented his hard fate.

Mercury appeared and demanded the cause of his tears. After he told him his misfortune, Mercury plunged into the stream, and, bringing up a golden axe, inquired if that were the one he had lost. On his saying that it was not his, Mer-cury disappeared beneath the water a second time, returned with a silver axe in his hand, and again asked the Workman if it were his. When the Workman said it was not, he dived into the pool for the third time and brought up the axe that had been lost. The Workman claimed it and expressed his joy at its recovery. Mercury, pleased with his honesty, gave him the gold and silver axes in addition to his own.

The Workman, on his return to his house, related to his companions all that had happened. One of them at once resolved to try and secure the same good fortune for himself. He ran to the river and threw his axe on purpose into the pool at the same place, and sat down on the bank to weep.

Mercury appeared to him just as he hoped he would; and having learned the cause of his grief, plunged into the stream and brought up a golden axe, inquiring if he had lost it. The Workman seized it greedily, and declared that truly it was the very same axe that he had lost. Mercury, displeased at his knavery, not only took away the golden axe, but refused to recover for him the axe he had thrown into the pool.

The Ass and the Lapdog

A man had an Ass, and a Maltese Lapdog, a very great beauty.

The Ass was left in a stable and had plenty of oats and hay to eat, just as any other Ass would. The Lapdog knew many tricks and was a great favourite with his master, who often fondled him and seldom went out to dine without bringing him home some tidbit to eat. The Ass, on the contrary, had much work to do in grinding the corn-mill and in carrying wood from the forest or burdens from the farm.

He often lamented his own hard fate and contrasted it with the luxury and idleness of the Lapdog, till at last one day he broke his cords and halter, and galloped into his master’s house, kicking up his heels without measure, and frisking and fawning as well as he could. He next tried to jump about his master as he had seen the Lapdog do, but he broke the table and smashed all the dishes upon it to atoms. He then attempted to lick his master, and jumped upon his back. The servants, hearing the strange hubbub and perceiving the danger of their master, quickly relieved him, and drove out the Ass to his stable with kicks and clubs and cuffs.

The Ass, as he returned to his stall beaten nearly to death, thus lamented：‘I have brought it all on myself! Why could I not have been contented to labour with my companions, and not wish to be idle all the day like that useless little Lapdog!’

黄昏之读

一，二，三，四，五。五个人。

在瑞士大圣伯纳德山口之巅，五个向导坐在修道院门外的长凳上。他们朝远处高山望去，那边巍峨的山峰浸染着落日的颜色，仿佛是谁失手泼洒了大量的红葡萄酒，色彩在山顶表面恣意流淌，好像还没来得及渗入下层白雪似的。

这可不是我的比喻，是那个最壮实的德国向导说的。不过其他向导对这番优美言辞倒没有多在意，就像他们也不在意我一样。此刻，我就坐在修道院门口另一边的长凳上，和他们一样抽着雪茄——也和他们一样——望着远处余晖染红的积雪。我们旁边是一间孤零零的小棚屋，里面放着不少旅行者的尸体，他们因大雪封山被困，从积雪下被挖出来，如今只能躺在地上慢慢干枯萎缩，毕竟这么冷，倒是不会腐烂。

我们就这样看着山顶的红酒一点点渗进雪中，山又恢复了洁白，天空泛着深蓝，风的呼啸声渐大，周遭空气寒冷刺骨。那五个向导扣紧了身上粗毛的大外套。在这里，向导做什么，你就跟着做什么，这样才最安全，于是我也赶忙扣紧了大衣。

先前夕阳映照下的山景打断了五个人的谈话，因为那实在雄伟壮丽，值得静静欣赏。现在太阳落山，他们又继续着之前的谈话。我之前没有听他们说，因为当时还在和一位美国绅士闲聊。他坐在修道院专门接待旅行者的客厅里，面朝壁炉，说要给我讲一个大骗子怎么靠着次次招摇撞骗，混成我们国家首富的故事。

“我的天！”瑞士向导冒出了一句法语。我不敢（像其他作者那样）说这个词可以完全表达出他的本意，但力求用英语写出来不像脏话吧。“如果谈起鬼魂——”

“但我说的不是鬼魂。”德国人说。

“那你要说什么？”瑞士人问。

“我要是知道，”德国人说，“那我懂的可就不止这些了。”

好答案，我心想，一下子就勾起了我的好奇心。因此，我挪到离他们较近的长凳的另一端，背靠着修道院墙，不用参与谈话，也能够听得十分清楚。

“电闪雷鸣！”德国人兴冲冲地说，“当一个人突然想要来看你，而他自己却毫无意识地把这个想法植入你的脑海，整日盘旋，仿佛是遣了某个看不见的信差，你怎么称呼这种现象？当你走在熙熙攘攘的街道——在法兰克福、米兰、伦敦、巴黎——想着身边走过的某个陌生人酷似你的朋友海因里希，另一个擦肩而过的路人也像海因里希，由此产生了一种奇怪的预感——不一会儿你就要见到他了——你还真就见到他了，虽然你一直以为他远在的里雅斯特[1]。你又把这个叫什么呢？”

“这都不是什么稀罕事啊。”瑞士人和其他三个人小声说。

“这很不平常！”德国人说，“平常是什么？平常是黑森林里的樱桃，那不勒斯的通心面。说起那不勒斯倒提醒了我！老侯爵夫人苏珊尼姆在基艾亚[2]的纸牌宴会上尖叫来着——我就在现场，因为当时我服侍的巴伐利亚一家也去了——哎呀，那侯爵夫人往牌桌前一坐，嘴唇煞白，惊呼道：‘我那在西班牙的妹妹死了！我刚刚感觉到她冰凉的手在摸我的背。’而她的妹妹恰恰就是在那一刻走的，这个你怎么看？”

“还有神职人员祷告后圣热内罗的血液就会溶解[3]——整个世界都知道，每年发生一次，就在我的家乡，”那不勒斯向导停顿了一会儿，带着戏谑的表情说，“您又怎么称呼这个呢？”

“那个！”德国人大声说，“对！我想有个名称可以。”

“神迹？”那不勒斯人依然神色狡黠。

德国人只是抽了口烟，放声大笑，其他人也一起抽烟大笑。

“呸！”过了片刻，德国人啐了一口，“我说的这些都是实在发生的。我要是想看招魂，怎么不找个专业的，钱就值回来了。有些怪事根本和鬼魂无关。说到鬼魂！乔万尼·巴普蒂斯塔，讲讲你那个英国新娘的事吧，里面没有鬼，可就是很诡异。谁来说？”

一时间大家陷入沉默。我朝旁边瞥了瞥，猜那个重新点了支雪茄的人就是巴普蒂斯塔。果然片刻后他接过了话茬，听口音是热那亚人。

“英国新娘？”他说，“够了！这点小破事谈不上什么故事。不过，也算是吧，是真的。竖起耳朵听好了，各位，绝无半句虚言。发光的不一定都是金子，可我接下来要说的一定是真的。”

接着，他又强调了一遍。

十年前，我带着自己的履历去找一位英国绅士。他住在伦敦邦德街的长龙酒店，正打算旅行一两年。他对我的履历很满意，对我印象也不错。问了价格后，对价钱也相当满意。于是他决定雇我六个月，给我的薪酬待遇也不错。

这位绅士年轻英俊，乐观潇洒，倾心一位貌美的英国富家小姐。他们就要结婚了，接下来的旅行算是度蜜月。为了在炎热的三个月中（当时已是初夏）能够充分休憩，他在里维埃拉[4]租了一栋老宅。从我所在的城市热那亚过去，非常方便，前往尼斯也需路过此地。我知不知道那栋宅子？当然。我告诉他，自己很了解那里。老宅带着大花园，有点昏暗阴森，周围树木环绕。不过宅子面积倒是不小，它伫立在海岸边，古老而庄严。他表示自己先前也听人这样讲过，很高兴我能有所了解。虽然里面家具是少了点，但别的地方也都这样。虽然房子阴森了点，但主要是看中了大花园，打算和女主人在树荫下避暑度日。

“所以没问题吧，巴普蒂斯塔？”他问。

“完全没有，先生。非常好。”

我们乘的是崭新的特制双轮马车，无论从哪方面来说都很完美。可以说是万事俱备，别无他求了。之后他们举办了婚礼，非常幸福。我也很高兴，因为生活是如此明快，一切都恰到好处，我又回到了自己长大的城市，还可以胡乱教女仆拉贝拉·卡罗琳娜说一些家乡话。她是一个活泼开朗的年轻女孩，时常被我逗得放声大笑。

时间就这样一天天过去，但我发现——听着，高潮来了！（说到这里向导压低了嗓音）——我发现女主人有的时候会陷入沉思，而且是以非常奇怪、可怕甚至悲伤的方式，脸上愁容惨淡，还有些飘忽不定的惊恐。开始注意到这个，是因为我正走着上坡，跟在马车边，主人早到前面去了。不管怎么说，到法国南部时，那天晚上发生的一些事让我更加确定了。当时女主人唤我把主人叫过来，于是主人又回头，陪着她走了很长的路，一直温柔地安慰她，鼓励她。他把手搭在打开的马车窗边，而女主人坐在车里，把手放在窗户内沿。主人时不时地开怀大笑，仿佛是为了驱散她心中的忧虑。不久之后，她也放声大笑，一切就又好起来了。

这件事有点古怪，我向漂亮的小女仆拉贝拉·卡罗琳娜打听。女主人有哪里不舒服吗？没有。精神不振？没有。担心路况或者强盗土匪？没有。更神秘的是，卡罗琳娜回答问题时不愿意看着我，只是望向远处的风景。

不过，有一天她把秘密告诉了我。

“如果，你真想知道的话，”卡罗琳娜说，“我发现，根据我听到的情况来看，女主人是被鬼缠上了。”

“怎么缠上的？”

“因为一个梦。”

“什么梦？”

“一个有着一张脸的梦。结婚前有三个晚上，她都梦到了一张脸——同一个面孔，只有一个。”

“那张脸恐怖吗？”

“不，是一个相貌非凡、面色黝黑的男人的脸。他一身黑衣，黑头发，还有灰色的小胡子——相当帅气，不过又冷淡又神秘。女主人压根就没见过这张脸，连长得像的都没有。梦里，他只是从黑暗深处静静地凝视着她，什么也不做。”

“后来女主人又做过同样的梦吗？”

“再也没有。但只要想起这个梦境，她心中就充满了不安。”

“为什么会困扰她呢？”

卡罗琳娜摇了摇头。

“这也是主人的疑惑，”卡罗琳娜说，“她不知道，自己也弄不明白。我只听到昨天晚上，她跟主人说如果在意大利的房子里发现那张脸的画像（她担心她会），那就真要崩溃了。”

说实话，这之后我就开始担心（热那亚向导说），等我们到了那座豪华的旧宫殿，真会看到某幅类似的倒霉画像，毕竟那里这种画像还真不少。随着离目的地越来越近，我心中恨不得把整个宅子的画廊都扔到维苏威火山口去。然而好像事情还不够糟一样，偏巧我们到里维埃拉的那晚风狂雨骤，天色阴沉，还打着雷。由于热那亚周围高山环绕，雷声在其间回荡时，显得震耳欲聋。蜥蜴仿佛受了雷鸣的惊吓，在花园颓圮的石墙缝隙间蹿来蹿去。青蛙一直扯着嗓子呱呱大叫。海风咆哮着卷进来，湿透的树木滴着雨水，还有闪电——把圣劳伦斯教堂都照得通亮！

我们都知道一栋热那亚风格的老式宫殿会是什么样——时间和海风会怎样将它玷染，外墙的纹案图饰会怎样像石膏一样片片斑驳脱落，低层的窗框会怎样慢慢生锈发黑，院子里会怎样杂草丛生、日渐荒芜，外围的建筑会怎样颓圮失修，整栋建筑会怎样无人问津、逐渐破败。我们租下的这栋宫殿就是活生生的例子。它大门紧闭已经几个月了。几个月？——不对，应该是好多年！房子里有一种土味，像墓室一样；同时外面露台上的橘子树味，墙边烂熟柠檬的果味，以及破裂的喷泉周围疯长的灌木丛的草味，不知怎的都跑进来，闷在这里面发酵。每个房间都隐约弥漫着一种陈年的腐朽气息，充斥着橱柜和抽屉。到了两个大房间之间用作流通的小间里，这种味道就变得更加令人窒息。如果你想挪动一幅画——说回到画来——是根本就动不了的，因为它们像蝙蝠一样牢牢粘在墙上。

房子里所有的格状百叶窗都紧闭着，只有两个头发灰白的老女仆在照看。其中一人拿着纺锤，站在门口缠卷着，咕哝着，估摸着她随时就能像放进空气一样把坏人放进来。主人、女主人、拉贝拉·卡罗琳娜和我一道穿过宫殿。虽然名字排在最后，但其实我走在最前面，打开了窗玻璃和网格百叶窗，结果自己淋到了几点雨，身上落了些石灰皮，还时不时有打盹的蚊子或热那亚当地带有斑点的大蜘蛛掉下来。

月光照进房间，主人们和拉贝拉·卡罗琳娜才进来。接着，大家查看了四周的画像，我则走进了另一间房。女主人打心底里恐惧，生怕见到和那张脸类似的任何东西——其实我们都怕，不过这没有发生。圣母圣婴、圣弗朗西斯科、圣塞巴斯蒂安、维纳斯、圣卡塔林纳、天使、强盗、修士、落日映照的神殿、战争、白马、森林、使徒和共和国[5]总督，画上尽是平凡无奇的常规题材——确实如此。那个身着黑衣、黑头发灰胡子、带着冷淡神秘气质、从黑暗中凝视女主人的帅气男子则毫无踪影。

最后我们走遍了所有房间，看过了所有画像，来到了花园。这里租给一个园丁后，维护得相当不错，面积很大，树木成荫。其中有一处简陋的露天小剧场，绿草覆盖的斜坡是主舞台：侧面一边三个入口，布景则是缀满叶子、散发着草木清香的绿幕。女主人明亮的大眼睛飞快转动着，即便在这儿，她仍然害怕那张脸会突然冒出来：还好一切正常。

“好了，克拉拉，”主人轻声说，“你看到了，什么都没有，开心点。”

女主人很受鼓舞，之后不久就适应了这个阴沉的宫殿，整天唱歌、弹竖琴，临摹古画，或者和男主人在绿树下或葡萄藤下散步。她光彩照人，他也心情畅快。男主人经常大笑着吩咐我备马，他要在中午热起来前骑马溜达一圈：

“一切都顺利，巴普蒂斯塔！”

“是的先生，谢天谢地，非常好！”

他不需要我陪伴，于是我就带着拉贝拉去看看大教堂、托雷安农齐亚塔[6]、咖啡馆、歌剧院、村庄庆典活动、公园、日间剧场、牵线木偶表演。所有这些都能让漂亮的小拉贝拉着迷。她还学会了意大利语——天哪！奇迹啊！我有时会问她，女主人是不是快忘记那个梦了？差不多吧，卡罗琳娜说——基本上是，她在慢慢淡忘。

一天，主人收到了一封信，把我叫过去。

“巴普蒂斯塔！”

“先生。”

“一位别人介绍我认识的绅士说今天要来这里共进晚餐。他叫德尔欧布拉。准备一下，别让我丢脸。”

真是奇怪的名字，我没听说过，不过当时也有很多贵族绅士因为在奥地利受到政治猜忌，然后改名的。可能是其中一位吧。管他呢！德尔欧布拉这个名字对我来说和任何名字一样，没什么不好。

晚餐时间，德尔欧布拉先生来了（说到这里，热那亚向导再一次压低了声音），我把他带到会客室，也就是老宫殿的大厅。主人热情真诚地接待了他，并转身向女主人介绍。而女主人站起身，脸色唰地一变，尖叫一声就晕过去了，直接栽倒在大理石地面上。

接着，我立马看向德尔欧布拉先生，只见他一身黑衣，表情冷淡而神秘，面色黝黑，相貌非凡，还蓄着黑头发和灰色小胡子。

主人把女主人抱回到她的房间，我赶紧让拉贝拉跟过去服侍。后来她告诉我，女主人吓得大半条命没了，整晚脑子里都是之前那个梦。

主人既恼怒又焦躁不安——几近愤怒，心中又很担心。这位德尔欧布拉先生是一位谦和儒雅的绅士，对女主人的病况表示了关心和同情。他说，来自非洲的风已经吹了好些时日（这是他听马耳他十字架酒店的人说的，他住在那里），妖风经常伤人。他还祝愿美丽的夫人能够早日康复。接着便要请辞离开，说自己可以等女主人康复后再行登门。不过主人没有同意，认真挽留他坐下来进餐，最后他们俩一起吃了饭。

德尔欧布拉先生当晚早早走了，第二天又来敲门，骑在马上，问女主人是否安好。一周内他来了那么两三次。

根据我的观察，加上拉贝拉·卡罗琳娜的消息，显然主人正在努力安慰女主人，让她克服胡思乱想的恐惧。他非常温柔体贴，但也理智坚定，慢慢分析给她听，告诉她任何空想都不过是庸人自扰，如果能安定心神，就什么事都没有了。如果她能克服自己奇怪的弱点，成功像英国淑女招待客人那样接纳德尔欧布拉先生，那就永远不会再出事了。最终，德尔欧布拉先生再次到访，女主人招待了他，没有表露出什么明显的痛苦（尽管仍有些局促和忧虑），当晚平静地度过了。主人对这种变化感到十分欣喜，为了急于确认她已好转，于是德尔欧布拉先生成了我们的常客。他的画艺和乐理都十分精湛，还博览群书，这种社交伙伴，在任何沉闷的意大利宫殿，都是相当受欢迎的。

我时常能注意到，女主人并没有真正恢复。在德尔欧布拉先生面前，她会垂下眼睑，低着头，要不就是以害怕又着迷的眼神飞快地瞥他一眼，好像他在这儿就会对她造成什么不好的影响或施加什么邪恶力量。我又看看德尔欧布拉先生，之前在荫蔽的花园或半明半暗的宽敞起居室里，我常常能看到他“从黑暗中凝视着她”，老实说，我并没有忘记拉贝拉·卡罗琳娜对梦中那张脸的描述。

德尔欧布拉先生第二次来访结束后，我听到主人说：

“亲爱的克拉拉，你看，都结束了！德尔欧布拉来了又走，你的忧虑已经完全没有啦。”

“他还——还会再来吗？”女主人问。

“再来？为什么不！当然，他会来很多次的！怎么了，你是不是冷？”（女主人打了个哆嗦。）

“不，亲爱的——但是——我真的害怕他：你确定真的还要他来吗？”

“克拉拉，这是毫无疑问的！”主人愉快地答道。

不过，他对女主人的完全康复倒抱有极大希望，并且这种期冀与日俱增。女主人优雅美丽，他也心情畅快。

“一切都顺利吧，巴普蒂斯塔？”他又对我说一遍。

“是的先生，感谢老天。非常好。”

有一天（热那亚向导微微抬高了嗓门儿），我们都在罗马参加狂欢节。我有个西西里岛的朋友，他也是向导，当时陪同一个英国家庭。我和他出去玩了一整天，晚上回酒店的时候，碰到小卡罗琳娜。她从来不单独离开家，那天却沿着大道狂奔，显得心烦意乱。

“卡罗琳娜！怎么了？”

“哦，巴普蒂斯塔！哦，老天啊！女主人到底去哪儿了？”

“女主人？”

“人家说她不见了。今天早上，因为她前一晚没休息好（太痛苦的缘故），主人出门就没有叫她。本来她应该在床上躺到天黑，再精神抖擞地起来活动。结果现在她不见了，不见了！主人回来了，撞开了门，发现她不见了！美丽大方又善良的女主人！”

娇小漂亮的卡罗琳娜在我面前大喊着，咆哮着，甚至拉扯自己的头发，要不是她最后像中枪一样晕倒在我怀里，我几乎就快控制不住她了。这时主人出现了——我从来没见过他这副模样，仪态、脸色，甚至嗓音都变了。他叫上我（我把小卡罗琳娜抱回她的床上，让内侍女仆陪着她），驾着马车气冲冲地闯进夜色里，横穿荒无人烟的原野。天亮时我们赶到一家破败驿站，可惜所有马匹在十二个小时前已全被租用，分别去往不同的方向。听着！都是德尔欧布拉先生订的，驿站的人说他曾驾车来过这里，还带着一位害怕得蜷缩在角落的英国女士。

打那以后（热那亚向导说着长长地舒了一口气）我再也没有听过她的消息。我所知道的就是，女主人和梦中见过的那张可怖的脸一起消失了，从此湮没在离奇骇人的故事里。

“你怎么解释这种事呢？”德国向导得意扬扬地说，“鬼！那里根本就没有鬼！接下来我要告诉你的事，看看又如何理解呢？鬼嘛！这个故事里也没有鬼！”

我曾经（德国向导继续说道）跟着一位英国绅士干活，他上了年纪，又是单身，当时要去我的祖国德国旅行。这位绅士是做德国进出口贸易的商人，所以懂德语，他在小时候去过德国，但长大成人以后没再去过——据我判断，那大概是六十年前的事了。

他叫詹姆斯，有个双胞胎哥哥叫约翰，也是单身汉。兄弟俩感情深厚，一起在古德曼广场打拼生意，但是并不同住。詹姆斯先生住波兰街，伦敦牛津街的外面，而约翰先生住在埃平森林旁边。

詹姆斯先生和我准备在一周内启程去德国，具体日子看生意安排。约翰先生来到波兰街（当时我就在房子里），准备和詹姆斯先生共度那一周。但是第二天，他却说：“詹姆斯，我有点不舒服。应该问题不大，是痛风的毛病。我想回家，因为老管家很了解我，能好好照顾我。如果好一点了，我就回来，在你走之前看看你。如果我撑不住了回不来，你启程前能不能去看看我呢？”当然，詹姆斯先生答应了。他们握了手——双手交叉互握，一贯如此——然后约翰先生命令双轮马车出发，坐在车里摇摇晃晃地回去了。

第二天晚上——也就是那周的第四天——穿着法兰绒睡袍的詹姆斯先生举着一盏蜡烛走进我的房间，我从熟睡中醒过来。他坐在我床沿，看着我，说：

“威廉，我有理由相信自己得了某种怪病。”

我立即察觉到他的神情非同寻常。

“威廉，”他说，“有些事我不怕告诉你，也不觉得羞耻，但我不愿意告诉其他人。因为你来自一个理智的国度，在那里，这么多年来，疑神疑鬼的事总会有人关心，人们却不会轻易地下结论，也不会不分青红皂白地表示鄙夷。我刚刚看到了哥哥的幽灵。”

我承认（德国向导说）听到这里，我浑身打了个激灵。

“就在刚刚看到的，”詹姆斯先生直视着我重复了一遍，好让我看出他很镇定也很清醒，“哥哥约翰的幽灵。我正坐在床上，毫无困意，突然他就进来了，穿着白袍，严肃地和我打了招呼。然后飘到房间的另一端，扫了眼写字台上的纸，又转过来像刚才一样认真凝望着我，随后出门离去。听着，我根本没有疯，也不想用任何自己以外的客观存在来解释那个幽灵，只是觉得这说明我生病了，现在最好放点血清醒一下。”

我赶紧下床（德国向导说），一边穿衣，一边让他不要慌，我会去请医生过来。正要出门，这时大门外传来巨大的敲门声，有人还按了门铃。我的房间是后院的阁楼，詹姆斯先生的卧室在前院二层，于是我们去到他的房间，打开窗子，看看外面什么情况。

“是詹姆斯先生家吗？”底下一个男人，退回到路对面抬头问。

“是，”詹姆斯先生说，“我认得你，我哥哥的男仆罗伯特。”

“是的先生。很遗憾地告诉您，约翰先生病了，非常严重，可以说是在鬼门关了。他想见您，所以我驾了马车来接您，请不要耽搁了，快跟我走吧。”

詹姆斯先生和我对视了一眼。“威廉，”他说，“太奇怪了。你跟我一起去吧！”我立即服侍他更衣，其实一半衣服都是在车上穿的。马儿跑得飞快，从波兰街到森林这一路不知踩死了多少小草。

这时，听好了！（德国向导说）我和詹姆斯先生一起来到了他哥哥的房间，以下都是我亲眼所见，亲耳所闻。

他哥哥躺在那间狭长卧室里头的床上，老管家站在旁边，还有几个人也在；估计这三四个人从下午就来陪他了。约翰先生一身白色，像幽灵一样，因为他正穿着睡袍。不过他脸色也像幽灵，一看到自己弟弟进来，眼神就直勾勾地盯着他。

不过，当弟弟来到床边时，哥哥支着身子坐起来，眼睛睁得老大，望着他说：“詹姆斯，你见过我的，今晚——你知道的！”

然后就咽气了！

德国向导讲完这个诡异的故事后，我静静等着，还想听他谈谈自己的看法。空气却陷入了沉默。我环顾四周，骇然发现五个向导都不见了：周围如此静谧，仿佛幽幽大山已将他们吞噬，埋入亘古的积雪。此时，寒冷的空气再度侵袭，我一点儿都不想独自待在这可怕的环境中——或者老实说，是压根儿不想一个人。因此，我起身走回修道院的大厅，发现那位美国绅士还很愿意讲那个了不起的骗子的故事，于是我又听了一通。

[1]的里雅斯特，意大利东北部港口城市。（说明：书中脚注均为编者注。）

[2]基艾亚是那不勒斯的一个区。

[3]那不勒斯每年有圣热内罗节，举行弥撒仪式，祈祷装在两个小玻璃瓶中的圣热内罗的血溶解。圣热内罗是公元四世纪的殉道者，他的血液至今存放在那不勒斯教堂的一个玻璃瓶中。

[4]意属里维埃拉即利古里亚海岸地区，该海岸以热那亚为中心分界点。

[5]这里指（前）威尼斯和热那亚共和国。

[6]意大利南部坎帕尼亚大区那不勒斯省的一个城市，坐落于维苏威火山下。

信号员

“喂！下面的！”

听到有人叫他时，他正站在岗亭前，手里拿着一面卷起的小旗。鉴于我们的相对位置，你可能会觉得他绝不会弄错声音的方向。但是，他不仅没有抬头看上方陡峭岩峰处站着的我，反而转身向铁路远处望去。这一举动里有一些耐人寻味的东西，虽然我可能一辈子也搞不明白到底是什么。但我知道，我已经被吸引了，即使对于站在高处的我来说，他的身影在沟槽底部，显得又矮又暗。而我浑身浸染在晃眼的落日余晖里，只有用手挡住刺眼的光晕才能看清他。

“喂！下面的！”

他把目光从铁路上收回，转过身来抬了抬眼，看到了高处的我。

“这附近有路吗？我可以下去和你说说话。”

他看着我，没有答话，我也低头看了看他，没有再问，不想强迫他回答我无聊的问题。就在这时，地面和四周开始轻微地震颤，并很快演变成了剧烈的震动，一股迎面而来的急流迫使我开始后退，力量之大好像可以把我拖拽下去。从飞驰的火车中涌出的蒸汽升至和我一样的高度，飘过我身旁，渐渐散开。我再次向下望去，看到他正在卷火车经过时挥舞起来的小旗。

我又问了他一遍。他沉默了一阵，似乎是在定睛观察，然后用卷起的小旗指了指和我在同一高度的一个点，距我两三百码[7]远。我冲着下面喊了一句“好的”，随后开始朝着那个点走去。到达后我仔细地环顾了一下四周，发现岩壁上有一条曲曲折折的小道——我就是顺着这条道下去的。

岩壁上的这条路凿得很深，异常的陡峭，开在一块黏湿的巨石上，而且越往下走，石体就愈加湿软。因此，我走得十分缓慢，中途还想起了他最初给我指路时表现出的那种奇怪的不情愿，好像被谁胁迫了一样。

当我顺着这条曲折的下坡路走到能看到他的地方时，他正站在火车刚才经过的轨道中间，一副好像正等着我的样子。他的左手扶着下巴，右手则横在胸前托着左肘。他这种期待又警惕的态度让我停下来想了一会儿。

我继续往下走着，来到铁路旁，朝着他的方向走去。眼前的他是一个面色蜡黄的男人，胡须黑森森，眉毛浓密。他工作的地方是我见过的最孤立最凄凉的地方。两旁渗水的粗糙石墙遮蔽了所有的光线，只留下一道缝隙得以窥见天空。往一边望去，这个地牢一般的空间弯弯曲曲不见尽头。而在另一侧，很快就能看到不远处昏暗的红色信号灯和更为昏暗的入口，后者通往一条漆黑的隧道，而这个庞然大物里还弥漫着粗野、压抑和令人生畏的气息。由于能照到这里的阳光少得可怜，四周氤氲着一股令人难以忍受的泥土气息。而且穿堂的冷风一阵接着一阵，吹得我直打颤，我觉得自己已经被冻死了。

在他还纹丝未动时，我就走到了能碰到他的位置。可还没把眼神从我身上移开，他就后退了一步，抬起了手。

这是一个孤独的岗位（我说过），我当时从那边的高处往下看时就完全被它吸引了。我想，来这里的人应该算是稀客了，希望我这个稀客不会让人讨厌。在他眼里，我只是一个终其一生都局限于狭窄的范围内毫无突破的人，一个终获自由后对这些伟大的工作萌发兴趣的人。带着这样的想法，我对他开了口。但是我对自己的用词根本毫无把握，因为除了我本人不喜欢引出话题外，这个人身上有一种令我生畏的东西。

他用一种非常好奇的目光望向隧道口附近的红灯，并仔细地打量了一番，好像那里少了什么东西，然后他才看向我。

那个灯也归他管吗？还是不归？

他低声答道：“你难道不知道它吗？”

我打量着他一直盯着我的眼睛和有点阴郁的脸，脑海中产生了一个可怕的念头，这是一个灵魂，不是人类。此后我就一直怀疑他脑子是不是坏了。

这次轮到我了，我往后退了几步。但在退的时候，我察觉到他眼中有一丝潜在的对我的恐惧。这让那个可怕的念头一扫而空。

“你看我的时候，”我说，强挤出一个笑脸，“感觉你在怕我。”

“我在想，”他答道，“我之前是不是见过你。”

“在哪儿？”

他指了指之前一直看的红灯。

“在那儿吗？”我反问道。

他立刻对我警觉起来，（无声地）说了一声“是”。

“老兄，我去那儿干吗啊？但就算有可能，我也根本没去过，你可以肯定。”

“或许可以，”他接着说道，“是的，我可以。”

他的举止开始放松起来，像我一样。不仅回答爽快利落，用词还很恰当。他的工作很多吗？是的。也就是说，他要承担很多责任。但是他的岗位要求他保持精准和机警，几乎没有什么体力活。变换信号、修理灯具和把这个铁把手拉来推去[8]就是他所有的职责。那些我似乎过于看重的漫长寂寞时光，对他来说，只是被生活中的例行常规填充成现在的模样，他也慢慢习惯了这样的生活。在下边的这段日子他还自学了一门语言——如果看得懂、对发音有一些粗略理解可以算是学会一门语言的话。他还学了分数和小数，以及一点代数。但他还是像小时候一样，算数非常糟糕。当班的时候他就必须一直待在充斥着潮湿空气的隧道中吗？他永远都不能从那两堵高石墙中走出来感受阳光吗？哎呀，这还要看时机和情境。某些情况下在铁路上的时间确实显得比其他情形下的时间长，在一天之中也有某些时段情况如此。天气晴朗的时候，他确实也会走出阴影，往高处去。但是，由于随时都要注意聆听电铃，而且这种情况下更要加倍小心，他大概并没有我想的那么轻松。

他带我进了岗亭，屋里生着火，桌子上放着一本工作手册——他必须在上边做一些记录，一个带有拨号盘和指针的电报设备，还有他之前提到的小铃铛。他曾说自己受过良好教育——大概是要高于火车站工作人员受教育的水平（希望这么说没有冒犯之意）。我本以为他会对这样的说法感到难为情，但他说大多数人都会撒这样的小谎，并不稀奇。在救济院、警署，甚至是最让人绝望的地方——军队里，他都听过这样的吹嘘。而且他知道不管是干什么的铁路工，或多或少都会这样标榜一下。他年轻的时候曾经（如果说坐在那个小屋里的我还能相信，他自己都不信了）研究过自然哲学[9]，还受过正规的教育。但当时年少轻狂，不肯好好把握机会，堕落至此，再也没有回头的一天了。他对此倒并无半句怨言，铺好了床，然后躺了上去，看样子也不打算另铺一张了。

所有我现在简洁复述的内容，从他口中说出时都相当平静。那时的他，显得严肃忧郁，一会儿看看我，一会儿又凝视火苗。他时不时会冒出一句“先生”，尤其是在讲述自己年少时光的时候：仿佛是在让我明白，我看到的他就是全部的他。中途有几次谈话被小电铃打断了，他不得不停下来，去读取信息并立即回复。有一次甚至不得不站到门外去，在火车经过的时候挥舞小旗，和司机说几句话。我发现他在履行职责时精准又机敏，一个词都没说完就开始了工作，而且在完成之前会一直保持沉默。

总之，我应该会把这个人列为该岗位上最可靠的人之一，但是他在对我说话时，会突然停下，沉着脸去看并没有发出任何声响的小电铃，而且还会打开小屋的门（之前因为要隔绝有害气体一直关闭着），伸出头去看隧道口附近的红灯。这种情况发生了两次，每次他回到火炉旁，脸上都挂着令人费解的神情，我们当时坐得很远，我说不太清。

起身准备走时，我说了一句：“我差点就以为你活得很惬意。”

（恐怕我必须要承认，我说这话的意思是想让他接的。）

“我觉得我之前是，”他用一开始的低沉嗓音答道，“但是我有麻烦了，先生，我被麻烦缠身了。”

只要愿意，他完全可以收回所说的话。但他还是说了，于是我很快接了上去。

“什么麻烦？你的麻烦是什么？”

“这个很难说清楚，先生。真的很难很难开口。如果你还来的话，我会试着告诉你的。”

“但是我是明确打算再来拜访你的。那么，什么时候呢？”

“我凌晨下班，先生，明天晚上十点再上班。”

“那我十一点过来。”

他谢过我，把我送到了门外。“先生，我会一直亮着白灯的，”他用自己独特的低音说道，“一直到你找到上去的路为止。找到之后，别叫！到了山顶，也别叫！”

他这么说，不禁让我觉得寒意更甚，但我只回了一句：“好的。”

“你明晚下来的时候，不要叫！让我问你最后一个问题。是什么让你今晚喊出那句‘喂！下面的’？”

“谁知道呢，”我说，“我就是喊出那个意思的——”

“别那个意思，先生。它们是具有特殊意义的词。我非常了解它们。”

“我承认它们有特殊意义。我的确那么叫了，因为看到了你就在下面啊。”

“没有其他的原因？”

“还能有什么原因！”

“你没觉得它们是通过某种非自然的方式传递给你的吗？”

“没有。”

他说了声“晚安”后，举起了灯。我沿着下行铁路的边缘走着（有一种火车就要从身后开过来的不适感），最后找到了路。上去要比下来容易些，我非常顺利地回到了自己的旅社。

第二天晚上，我准时赴约，在远方传来十一点钟声的时候，踏上了曲折小路的第一块石板。他在底下等着我，手里的白灯亮着。“我没有喊叫，”靠近后我说了这么一句，“我现在可以说话了吗？”“当然可以，先生。”“那么晚上好。”他伸出了手。“晚上好先生。”我也伸出了我的。随后我们并肩向他的岗亭走去，进来后关上门，在炉火边坐了下来。

“我决定了，先生，”刚一坐下他就探着身子说道，声音只比耳语大一点，“你不用再问我麻烦是什么了。昨晚我把你认作了别人。那就是我的麻烦。”

“认错人吗？”

“不。是那个‘别人’。”

“谁？”

“我不认识。”

“像我吗？”

“不知道。我从来没见过正脸。他的左臂挡在脸前，右臂在挥舞，挥舞得很厉害。就像这样。”

我注视着他的行为，那是一种非常激动与愤怒的姿势——“老天啊，把路让开！”

“那是一个月光皎洁的夜晚，”他说，“我当时正坐在这里，突然听到一声‘喂！下面的！’于是我起身站在门口向外看，那个‘别人’就站在隧道附近的红灯旁，像我刚才那样挥着胳膊。他的声音似乎已经因为喊叫沙哑了，他叫道，‘小心啊！小心！’然后又叫，‘喂！下边的！小心！’我拿起灯，把它调成了红光后向着那个人影边跑边叫，‘怎么了？发生什么事了？在哪里？’他就站在隧道的阴影外。我走到近处时，发现他一直用袖子遮住自己的眼睛，感到非常奇怪。所以我径直走过去，伸出手试图拉掉他的袖子，就在那个时候他消失了。”

“进隧道了。”我说道。

“不。我跑进了隧道，足足跑了五百码。我停下来把灯举过头顶，看到了测距的标记数字，当时潮湿的污渍从壁上缓缓流淌下来，还有些直接从拱顶滴落。我又跑出去，速度比之前还要快（因为我极度厌恶眼前这地方），路上我还用手中的红灯照了照隧道的红信号灯，查看周边情况，并且爬上铁梯去了顶部的走廊，之后又爬下来，跑回了这里。我给两边都拍了电报：‘收到警报，一切可好？’两边的回电都是‘一切正常’。”

我感到一根冰凉的手指正慢慢划过后脊背，我努力克制住自己，告诉他这个人影一定是出现的幻觉，是视觉神经过于脆弱才出了问题，很多病人都曾这样，其中一些已经意识到了这种痛苦的本质，甚至通过医学实验证明了这种认识。“至于那个想象中的喊叫声，”我说，“我们小声说话的时候，你可以听一听这个怪异山谷的风声，听听它们吹过电报线时的诡异尖叫！”

“你说的也有道理。”在我们坐着听了一会儿后，他如是说道。他对大风和电线应该是熟悉的，毕竟他在那里度过了那么多冬夜，经常一个人默默看着这一切。但他跟我说，事情并没有完。

我对打断他的话表示了歉意，于是他慢慢把手搭在我胳膊上，一字一句地说了下面这段话：

“在这个‘现象’出现的六小时后，这条铁路线上最重大的事故发生了，十小时后，伤亡者被抬出隧道，恰好就经过了那个人影曾经站过的地方。”

我竭力克制住浑身的战栗，回答说，这巧合确实是太过出人意料了，仿佛是人为精心设计出来，好叫他永远难忘的。然而，毫无疑问的是，惊人的巧合确实一直都有，谈起类似的话题也必须考虑到这一点。尽管必须承认，我补充道（因为我认为我看出他准备对这番话提出异议），但凡有点常识的人都不会让事故成为日常轨迹的一部分。

他又一次请求继续说下去。

我再次为自己不知不觉打断他的话道了歉。

“这件事，”他说着，再次把手放在我胳膊上，空洞的眼神向后瞟去，“就发生在一年前。六七个月后，我已经从当时的震惊错愕中恢复了过来，有一天破晓时分，我就站在那个门前，朝着红灯的方向看，又看到了那个幽灵。”他停下来，直直地盯着我。

“它叫出声了吗？”

“没有。它很安静。”

“它挥手示警了吗？”

“没有。它倚着灯柱，双手都放在脸前。就像这样。”

我再次看向他。那是哀悼的姿势。我曾在坟墓上的石像上见过这种姿势。

“你过去了吗？”

“我进屋坐了下来，一方面是想理一下思绪，另一方面是因为它让我感到有点晕眩。等我再出门时，太阳已经升得很高了，那个鬼魂也不见了。”

“没有后续了？这之后没有发生什么？”

他一边用食指轻轻戳了我的胳膊两三下，一边极为勉强地点点头：

“就在那一天，当一列火车驶出隧道时，我注意到在我这边的一个车厢窗户边有一些头和手，很混乱，有什么东西在挥舞。我又看到了它，立即给司机示意，停车！司机迅速关火踩刹车，但是火车还是往前走了一百五十码，甚至更多。我在后边追着跑，路上就听到了可怕的尖叫声和哭喊声。一个隔间里的漂亮小姐当场死亡，她被抬进了这里，就放在我们俩中间这片地板上。”

我看着他指的那片地方，不由自主地把自己的椅子向后推了推。

“真的，先生。千真万确。事实就是这样，和我告诉您的一样。”

我不知道该说些什么，也不知道怎么说，我的嘴巴非常干燥。风声和电线共同发出一声长长的哀叹，将故事接了下去。

他继续说道：“现在，先生，记住这个，帮我判断一下我脑子到底怎么了。那个灵魂一周前又回来了。从那之后，它就会时不时地出现在那里，断断续续地。”

“在灯光下？”

“在危险信号灯下。”

“它看上去想要干什么？”

他把之前“老天啊，把路让开”的动作又重复了一遍，似乎是带着更多的激情与愤怒。

然后，他继续说道：“我为了这事日夜不得安宁。它用一种痛苦的语调对我喊道‘下面的！小心！小心啊！’，持续的时间加起来有好几分钟，它就站在那里冲我挥手，敲我的小电铃……”

我突然想到了什么。“昨天晚上我在这里的时候是因为它敲你的铃，你才出门看的吗？”

“两次。”

“哎，你看吧，”我说，“你的想象欺骗了你。我的眼睛是盯着铃铛的，我的耳朵也是听着铃声的，所以如果我是一个活人，我就敢说它在那些时刻并没有响。不，在其他时候也没有响，除非是在火车开过，司机和你交流的时候它响了。”

他摇了摇头：“迄今为止我在那方面从没弄错过，先生。我从来没有把铃声和人声弄混过。鬼魂的铃声是电铃的一种奇怪震动，毫无来由，而且我还没有说，那个电铃就在我的眼前晃动。您没有听到它我并不奇怪。但是我确实听到了。”

“那你往外看时，那个灵魂还在吗？”

“在。”

“两次都是？”

他坚定地重复了一遍：“两次都是。”

“现在你能和我一起到门前去看看它吗？”

他咬了咬自己的下嘴唇，似乎不太情愿，但最终还是站了起来。我打开门，站在台阶上，他则站在门口。向远处望去，那边有危险信号灯，有阴森的隧道口，有凿壁湿漉漉的高墙，有头顶的一片星空。

“你看到它了吗？”我边问边特意看了看他的脸。他的双眼突出，满是紧张的神色，但是当我认真地看向同样的地点时，我的双眼可能更突出，神色更紧张。

“不，”他答道，“它不在那里。”

“同意。”我说道。

我们再次进去，关上了门，坐回原先的位置上。我开始考虑如何才能更好地发挥这个优势——如果他这样肯定的回答能够被称为一种优势的话，他是如此肯定事实的不可争辩，以至于我处在了一个最无力的位置上。

“这次你就彻底明白了吧，先生，”他说，“让我这么抓狂的，是一个问题，那个灵魂到底是什么意思？”

我告诉他，我也不确定，但我充分理解他。

“它让我们警惕什么？”他注视着火苗，沉思着，时不时往我这里看一眼。“危险是什么？危险又在哪里？有危险马上就要来临，就在铁路线上的某处。可怕的灾难就要发生。经历了前两次事故后，这一次不能再犹豫了。但是这对我来说确实太残酷，阴魂不散的。我能做什么呢！”

他扯出自己的手帕，擦了擦热得冒汗的额头。

“如果我发出危险两字，不管是发往其中一边，还是两边都发，我都没办法解释。”他一边继续说着，一边擦拭着手掌心，“我会陷入麻烦，于事无补。他们会觉得我疯了。情况就会是这样——信息：‘危险！当心！’回复：‘什么危险？地点？’信息：‘不知。但务必当心！’他们会辞退我的。要不然还能怎么办呢？”

他的痛苦不禁让人心生怜悯。那是一个意识清醒的人在遭受精神上的折磨，他一直默默背负着某种关乎生命的难以理解的责任，压力已经到了极限。“当它第一次站在危险信号灯下的时候，”他一边继续说着，一边把额前的黑发拢到了脑后，伸手揉着两边的太阳穴，看上去极度悲痛，“为什么不告诉我事故发生的地点——如果它注定要发生？为什么不告诉我规避的方法——如果可以规避？它第二次来的时候遮住了自己的脸，为什么不直接告诉我‘那个女士就要死了，让他们把她留在家里吧’？如果它来的前两次，只是为了告诉我它的警报是正确的，从而让我为第三次做好准备，为什么现在不明白地警告我呢？而且我，老天帮帮我吧！我就是这个冷清车站里一个可怜的信号员而已！为什么不去找一个大家都相信的人呢，或者有能力做出改变的人！”

看到他这样，我意识到为了这个可怜人，也为了公共安全，必须立即平复他的情绪。因此，暂时撇开我们之间所有有关现实和非现实的争论，我告诉他任何一个被赋予职责的人都应该认真履行，虽然他不明白这些莫名其妙的现象到底是什么意思，但至少他明白自己的职责所在，这也是能够让他感到欣慰的地方了。相比于让他放弃自己想法的劝说，我的安慰要成功得多。他镇静了下来，随着夜色越来越深，他的工作对注意力的要求也越来越高。我是在凌晨两点离开的。我提出要过夜，可是他连听都不想听。

我在沿着小路往上走时不止一次地回头看那盏红灯，我并不喜欢那个灯，如果我的床在它下面，我应该已经睡着了，只不过会很不舒服。我没有理由隐瞒这些想法。而且我不喜欢那两场事故和死去的女孩。我也知道没有理由去隐瞒这些。

但是，我想得最多的还是应该怎么做。毕竟我已经知道了这个秘密。我已经证实了这个人聪明、机警、隐忍和严谨。然而他能维持这种状态多久呢？虽然他的职位不高，但做这份工作需要被充分信任，我（举个例子）愿意拿自己的生命做赌注去相信他会一如既往地精准吗？

如果我把他跟我说的这些话告诉公司领导，那就出卖了他。但我实在不愿意背叛他，也不想一开始真诚相待，随后又提出折中方案，于是最终决定陪他（要不然就暂时保守他的秘密）去看这一带最好的医生，照医生说的办。明天晚上就是换班时间，他告诉我，日出后的一两个小时下班，等日落后就赶回来上班。我也相应地做了往返安排。

第二天傍晚天色很好，我早早地就出了门。穿过岩顶凿壁附近的田野小道时太阳还没有下山。我心里盘算再漫步一小时就差不多了，半小时去，半小时回，然后就该去岗亭找信号员了。

继续散步前，我往崖边走了走，机械性地往下看了看，就站在我第一次看见他的地方。这时，我看见一个人影站在隧道口的不远处，左袖遮住了眼睛，正在拼命地挥舞右臂。一种无法形容的恐惧袭上心头。

不过只一瞬间，这种无名恐惧就消失了。我发现那个人影的的确确是一个人，而且不远处还站着另外一小撮人，他似乎正对着这群人排练这个姿势。危险信号灯还没有亮起来。灯柱旁出现了一个我完全没见过的矮小棚屋，由一些木质的支架和防水帆布搭建而成，看上去还没有一张床大。

一种不好的感觉袭上心头——自责带来的恐惧一闪而过，我把那个人留在那里，没让人去注意或纠正他的行为，导致了这一出致命的恶作剧——我以最快的速度从小路冲了下去。

“怎么了？”我问其中一个男人。

“信号员今天早上死了，先生。”

“不是那个岗亭里的人吧？”

“就是他，先生。”

“不是我认识的那个人吧？”

“你会认出他的，先生，如果你认识的话，”那个人说着郑重地脱下帽子，掀起了防水帆布的一角，“因为他的脸非常完好。”

“啊！怎么会这样呢，怎么会这样呢？”随着帆布再次盖上，我挨个问了好几个人。

“他是被火车头撞倒的，先生。在英格兰没有人比他更熟悉这份工作了，但是不知道怎么回事，他没从外轨中出去。当时天已大亮，他打开了信号灯，手里还拿着他的提灯。火车头出隧道的时候，他正背朝着火车，就被撞倒了。那就是开火车的人，正在演示当时的过程。给这位绅士讲一下，汤姆。”

那个穿着粗布深色裙子的男人往后退了几步，站到了之前所在的隧道口：

“当时正在隧道的弯道附近，先生，”他解释道，“我看见了尽头处的他，好像是用望远镜看到的。当时没有时间去检查车速，而且我也知道他会当心的。由于他好像并没有注意到汽笛声，火车冲过去时我就把它关了，靠近的时候拼了命地大声喊他。”

“你喊了什么？”

“我喊的是：‘下面的！小心！小心啊！老天啊，把路让开！’”

我吃了一惊。

“啊！简直是噩梦，先生。我从来都用不着喊他的。这次我只能把胳膊挡在自己眼前，不去看，然后一直挥舞着胳膊，但是都没用。”

我不再继续赘述这几个相较于其他故事来说格外奇特的事件了。在文章结尾，我想说明，火车驾驶员发出警告的巧合，不仅仅是不幸的信号员反复说给我听的那些阴魂不散的话语，而且还有我自己——不是他——看到他模仿的姿势时，只在心里想过的话。

[7]英制长度单位。1码约等于91.44厘米。

[8]旧铁路线上需要推拉把手以变换铁路路线。

[9]从前用以指自然科学，特别是物理学。

谋杀案审判

我发现，即便是智慧超群、学识卓越的人，如果要让他们吐露一下自己奇奇怪怪的心理活动，大家都会变得胆小谨慎。几乎所有人都会担心自己的一番讲述无法引起听众内心世界的共鸣，可能受到质疑或嘲笑。对于一个敢于说实话的旅行者来说，即便是见过（传说中）海蛇怪一般的神奇生物，他也会毫不害怕地说出自己的经历。但是，如果他已有某种奇特的不祥预感、内心冲动、奇思妙想、（所谓的）憧憬展望、梦境，抑或其他特别的心理印象，就会在最终承认前反复犹豫纠结，难以开口。在我看来，大部分以上那些不可言明的因素导致了这种缄默。习惯上，我们不会像谈论客观事物一样去沟通主观的感受。带来的后果就是，这方面的经历常常显得非同寻常，就其不幸与缺憾而言，的确如此。

接下来我要说的，既不是为了讲什么道理，也不是要反驳或声援什么理论。我了解柏林书商[10]的过去，也经戴维·布鲁斯特爵士介绍研究过一位已逝皇家天文学家妻子的案件。此外，我还深入研究过密友们身上发生的鬼魅幻影案。关于最后一点我有必要声明一下，受害人（一位女士）本人和我关系疏远，甚至可以说是毫无瓜葛。那件事的错误假设为我自己的案件提供了部分解释——不过只是部分——因为整件事是完全没有根据的，不能说明我天生就具有某种超能力，况且之前和之后也从没有经历过类似事情。

同时这也没有影射那桩英格兰谋杀案的意思，不记得是很多年还是好几年前了，总之当时那件案子可谓举世关注。这些年我们相继听过不少臭名昭著的谋杀犯，但如果可以，我想彻底埋葬关于那个暴徒的记忆，就像他的身躯被埋进新门监狱[11]地下一样。接下来的讲述中，我会尽量避免透露有关罪犯身份的直接线索。

谋杀案刚发现的时候，还没有人怀疑他——我不能说得太详细，应该说——这名后来入狱的犯人身上还没有任何公开的嫌疑。当时，由于各大报纸并没有对其进行报道，很显然，人们不可能从报纸上读到任何有关他的描述。记住这一点很关键。

我一边吃着早餐，一边翻看晨报，上面对这个谋杀案进行了首次曝光。我饶有兴致地细细读了两三遍。尸体是在卧室发现的，读到这里我放下报纸，突然眼前闪过——划过——流过——不知道应该叫什么，暂时还没找到恰当的词，总之就是我似乎看到那个卧室正穿过自己的房子，就像是画在流水上的一幅画。虽然是一闪而过，但是清晰可见，甚至在我清楚地看到床上没有尸体后，心里还有一丝庆幸。

这种奇妙感觉不是在什么温柔乡产生的，而是在皮卡迪利大街的套间里，紧邻着圣詹姆斯街道的拐角。对此时窝在安乐椅里的我来说，这个案子相当新奇，除了奇妙外还伴有一丝古怪的战栗，让椅子都晃起来。（不过有必要说明椅子下面本来就很滑。）我走到一扇窗旁（房间在二层，有两扇窗），俯视皮卡迪利大街上的车水马龙，放松眼睛。明亮的秋日上午，大街在阳光照耀下熠熠生光，一切都显得愉悦惬意。秋风正劲，从邻近公园裹挟来大量落叶，一阵疾吹之下，只见叶子打着旋儿翻飞上升，形成小圆柱。恍然间，柱子又轰然倒塌，叶片四散。这时我看见马路对面有两个人，一前一后自西向东走去。前面的人时不时扭头往后看，后面的人跟他隔了约三十步，气势汹汹地举着右手。首先，在人来人往的大道上，这持续的怪异举动本身就吸引了我。接着我发现，如此不同寻常的情况，竟然没有任何人注意到。他们在行人间穿梭自如，丝毫不像走在人行道上。目之所及，没有一个人给他们让路、碰到他们或者多看他们一眼。从我窗前走过时，他们还都抬头凝视着我。我也认清了这两张脸，估计到哪儿都不会忘了，他们脸上倒没什么突出特征值得注意，只不过前面那个人一脸苦相，后面那位则面色蜡黄，一脸阴沉。

我是个单身汉，身边只有一名贴身男仆和他妻子跟着。我目前在一所银行分行工作，作为部门主管，我本希望这个职位和人们想的一样轻松。那个秋天，上面安排我待在城里，以防有任何变动。我没有生病，但也不算健康。本篇中，读者将会最大程度地感受到我的厌倦情绪，体会到我对单调乏味生活的失望，甚至还“有点消化不良[12]”。给我看病的那位名医说，我的身体没什么大毛病，在我的要求之下，他写了一份纸质说明给我，我在这里只是引用他的原话。

随着谋杀案的调查逐渐展开，案情日益披露，公众也越来越关心。不过我尽量不去管这些事，不让自己陷入普遍的兴奋情绪。但据我所知，目前已经断定这是一场蓄意谋杀，并且嫌疑犯也已被押送至新门监狱，等候审判。我还知道，由于惯常的偏见和准备辩护所需的时间不够，定于伦敦中央刑事法院的审判被推迟了数个会期。我基本已经猜出，案件会具体推到什么时候开庭，但又觉得自己不知道。

我的客厅、卧室和更衣室都在同一层，更衣室只能从卧室过去。以前更衣室里确实有扇小门通向楼梯，不过多年前浴室重修，就把那里堵上了。当时装修工还顺手把门钉牢，盖上了帆布。

有天深夜，我正站在卧室里，趁仆人睡前吩咐他一些事情。我的脸正对着通向更衣室唯一的那扇门，当时门紧闭着，仆人背对着听我说话。就在此时，我看见门突然开了，一个男人探头朝这边看，还向我招手，表情严肃而神秘。这个人正是在皮卡迪利大街上后面走着的那位，面色蜡黄，一脸阴沉。

打完招呼后他就退回去，关上了门。我略微怔住，赶紧穿过卧室，打开更衣室房门朝里看。我手上举着点燃的蜡烛，心里倒也不指望真能在更衣室看见那个身形。果然，最后什么也没看到。

想起来仆人还震惊在原地，我转身说：“德里克，你相信吗，我刚才十分清醒地看到了一个——”我刚把手放到他胸膛上，他突然猛烈颤抖起来，说：“噢，天哪，是的，先生！一个死人在招手！”

此时我意识到，眼前这个忠心耿耿跟了我二十多年的约翰·德里克，在我触碰到他之前，其实什么都没有看见，也什么都不知道。他身上的变化实在太过剧烈，我们接触时，我明显感觉到他通过某种神秘的方式，在一瞬间吸取了我的意识，从而得出现在的结论。

我让德里克去取白兰地酒来，给他和自己都倒了点，对于之前发生的事却只字未提。后来我细细回想了一番，可以肯定的是，除了在皮卡迪利大街，自己与这个人从未谋面。对比他在门边招手和在街上抬头凝视时的神情，我明白了：第一次他是要在我脑中留下印象，第二次他是想确认我能够迅速地记住他。

那晚，尽管有一种难以解释的确切预感——知道他不会再回来，我仍然睡得不安稳，天亮时才陷入沉沉睡梦。后来我是被约翰·德里克叫醒的，他来到床边，手里攥着一张纸。

依稀中正是因为这张纸，来者和仆人在门口好一顿争吵。这是一张传票，传唤我去老贝利街参加中央刑事法院的近期开庭。约翰·德里克很清楚我以前从未参加过陪审团，也认为——我不清楚是现在推理得出的还是什么其他方式——陪审团成员的身份通常要比我低，所以一开始婉拒了。传票人却态度倨傲，公事公办，说我去还是不去对他都没有影响，传票就在这里，怎么处理后果自负，与他无关。

一两天过去了，我还没想好到底是回复传票，还是直接无视。我自问心中不存丝毫的奇怪偏见，也没受到什么影响或诱惑，不会偏向于哪一方。说出这样的话，我问心无愧，和自己在这里说的每一句话一样肯定。不过最终我还是决定前去，就当是乏味生活里的一点调剂好了。

约定的那天到来的时候已是十一月，上午出门，天气阴冷。皮卡迪利大街雾气浓重，雾色由棕转黑，在圣殿关[13]附近显得格外压抑。而在法院大楼内，煤气灯照得过道和楼梯灯火通明，整个法院也显得亮堂堂的。我觉得，在我跟着引导官员进入法院见到满堂听众前，我根本不知道那个谋杀犯是今天受审。我觉得，要不是他们费了老大劲才带我挤进这里，估计我也不会知道拿着这张传票到底应该进哪个门。但是我说这话也不十分肯定，因为当时我对大脑所做的这个判断并不是很满意。

我在陪审团的预备席落座，尽力环顾四周，让视线穿过雾气和人们呼出气体的浓密混合物质。我看到巨大窗玻璃外的黑雾像是积满灰尘的窗帘，听到车轮压过稻草发出闷响，又或是鞣料渣洒落街道的窸窣，同时伴有人群逐渐聚拢的嗡嗡声，刺耳的哨音或响亮的歌声、喊声偶尔也会突兀地划过耳畔。不久，两位大法官进来坐下，法庭内原先的嗡嗡耳语迅速消寂，众人目光都集中在被带上来的谋杀犯身上。他出现在被告席栅栏后的一刹那，我就认出来了：他是走在皮卡迪利大街上的前者。

如果当时就点名，我可能会惊愕到说不出话。不过好在陪审团里我坐在大概第六、第八的位置，等轮到我时已经缓过来了。“到！”现在，注意了。囚犯之前一直密切却冷漠地注视着每一位陪审员，而就在我踏进陪审席时，他突然变得非常激动，还朝自己的律师打手势，针对我的意思再明显不过了。他强烈反对我就任陪审，闹得不得不暂时休庭。休庭时，辩护律师一只手搭在被告席上与他小声交谈，还不断摇头。后来我向这位绅士打听，他说客户的第一句话就吓到他了。“不惜任何代价，反对那个人！”不过，由于囚犯本人不愿意做任何解释，也承认在我被叫到之前，他从来没有听说过我，所以最终他还是没有如愿以偿。

我不希望唤起任何关于谋杀犯的不快记忆，这一点已经说过，再加上详细说明他的漫长审判过程之于整体叙述而言又并非不可或缺，因此，我准备根据极不寻常的个人经历，谈谈陪审团成员共同度过的十天十夜。这些事估计要比谋杀犯更吸引读者，希望大家关注它们，而不只是《新门记事》[14]上那一纸故事。

我被选为陪审团团长。审判的第二天，取证就花了两小时（我亲耳听见教堂的钟敲了两次）。不经意间，我瞥了瞥陪审团的同人们，发现很难数清他们的人数。我来来回回点了好几遍，始终有一种说不清道不明的困难，简而言之，总觉得多了一个人。

我拍拍邻座的同事，悄声说：“帮我点点人数。”听到这个请求他有些惊讶，但是很快扭头开始清点。“为什么，”他突然说，“一共十三——，但是不，不可能。不会，我们一共十二人啊。”

根据我当天的清点，具体到每个人都没有问题，但是总的来看时又显得多了一个。那时还什么都没有发生——也没有任何人物出现——来解答我内心的困惑，但是我有预感，有东西一定会来。

陪审团都住在伦敦酒馆的一间大客房里，有各自的床位，始终受人看护，并且被监视着，尽管那个官员发誓他只是来保障我们安全的。他聪明机警，很有礼貌，乐于助人，同时（我很高兴听说）他在伦敦城也是颇受尊敬的人物，不仅相貌堂堂，眼睛炯炯有神，还有着令人艳羡的黑络腮胡，甚至连嗓音也洪亮悦耳。我觉得这里倒没有必要隐去他的姓名，他叫哈克。

晚上，当我们各自回到床上时，哈克先生的床就会被拉过来横在门口。第二天夜里，我尚无困意，看到哈克先生坐在他的床边，就过去也坐下来，递了一口鼻烟。就在从我手里接过鼻烟盒开始吸烟时，他突然诡异地哆嗦了一下，说：“那是谁！”

我顺着他的目光望去，视线越过房间，看见意料之中的那个人——皮卡迪利大街上的后者。我嗖地站起来，向前跑了好几步，接着停下来，回头看向哈克先生。只见他一脸漫不经心，哈哈大笑，愉快地说：“有一瞬间我还以为出现第十三位没有床的陪审员了，定睛一看只是月光而已呀。”

我没有和哈克先生解释，只是邀请他一起走到房间那头，并且始终注视着眼前的那个身影。他在其他十一位成员床边枕头的位置分别伫立了一会儿，每次都是到床的右边，走到下一张床的床尾时总会闪一下。从他头的位置来看，好像他只是忧郁地看着每个躺下休息的陪审员，根本没注意到我和我的床，尽管我的床离哈克先生最近。接着，他从月光照进来的位置飘然出去，穿过高大的窗玻璃，仿佛踏上了空中步梯一般离开。

次日早餐时，我才知道，昨夜大家好像都不约而同地梦到了被谋杀的死者，除了我和哈克先生。

到此时我已经确信，走在皮卡迪利大街上的第二个人（应该）就是死者，他身体力行的证词已经深深扎根在我的脑海。不过在此之后，还是发生了让我不知所措的一些事。

审判的第五天，当检方陈述接近尾声，一个死者的袖珍画像作为证据被呈上来。这个画像本应在死者的床头，但是在案发现场却不见了踪影，之后它又出现在另一个据目击者称是谋杀犯埋尸的隐秘地点。目击者检查确认后，这项证物上呈给法官，继而交由陪审团。当一位穿着黑袍的官员拿着袖珍像朝我走来时，皮卡迪利大街上第二个人的身影突然自人群中冲出，他从官员手里夺走袖珍像，亲自交到我手上。因为画像在小盒子里，我还没看到画像，就听见他低沉空洞的声音飘来——“我当时还很年轻，脸上也没这么煞白。”这声音在我传给下一个陪审员的时候又出现了，等他传给他身边的另一位时再次响起，就这样每传到下一个人，这话就响起一遍，直到最后，画像又回到了我手里。而其他所有人好像对此都毫无察觉。

陪审团用餐通常都在一处，由哈克先生监管。打第一天开始，我们就会很自然地在饭桌上讨论起当日案情进展。到第五天时，原告方的案情陈述已经结束，陪审团已经从这一角度了解到事件全貌，讨论自然更加热烈，也更为严肃[15]。陪审团中有一位教区代表——我所见过的最愚蠢的白痴——他以非常荒谬的理由否决了最简单确凿的证据，还有两个优柔寡断的教区跟屁虫也支持他。他们三人都是从一个区被选进来的，那个区的治安简直一团糟，我敢说光他们那里的谋杀案审判估计就不下五百起。就在这些笨蛋家伙愈吵愈凶时，我又看到了那个死者，当时已临近午夜，我们中一些人已准备休息了。他阴森森地站在他们身后，朝我挥手。我一走到陪审员中间加入讨论，他就消失了。打那以后，他便时常出现，在我们被关着的这个大房间里来回飘荡。每当同事们把脑袋凑到一起商议时，我就看见他的脑袋也从中间冒出来。每当他们比较分析的内容于他不利时，他就会情不自禁地向我招手，表情一脸严肃。

不过你们要记住，直到审判的第五天，那个袖珍画像出现之前，他可从未在法庭显形。随着案件进入到辩护阶段，有三点变化出现了。我先说其中两点吧。首先，死者的身影如今频频出现在法庭上，再也不对着我，而总是向着正在发言的人。比如，死者的喉咙曾被人切断，辩方一开始就指出他很有可能是自己割喉而亡。这时，死者飘到说话人肘边，打开他恐怖的断喉部位（之前藏起来了），任凭支气管在空中交叉晃动，左右手还交替比画，奋力向律师展示，不论哪只手都不可能造成这种伤口。还有一次，有位女性作为品德证人出庭，宣誓说嫌犯是这世上最亲切友善的人。死者立即抵在她的面前，凑上去死命瞪她，还伸出手臂，用手指着犯人阴邪的面孔。

接下来要说的第三点变化给我印象最深刻，也最为震惊。我不想解释分析，只打算准确地描述事实，交由你们来判断。尽管被靠近的对象毫无察觉，但死者的靠近还是会让他们感到些许惊恐与不安。在我看来，好像有一种未知的力量在限制他完全暴露自己，但同时也使得他能够无形无声地侵入别人的大脑。当首席辩护律师提及自杀的假设时，那身形就会闪现在这位博学的绅士旁，扯开自己被割断的喉咙，露出令人毛骨悚然的伤口。不可否认的是，辩护律师在之后的演讲中竟变得结结巴巴，甚至卡顿了几秒钟，忘记了精心准备的说辞，还脸色煞白，不断用手帕擦拭前额。当品德证人面对死者的显形时，我几乎可以肯定她确实按照死者手指的方向看去了，十分犹豫和苦恼地盯着嫌犯。这两个补充例子已经足够说明问题。在审判的第八天，每日午后的照例小憩和茶歇结束，我和陪审员们一起回到法庭，法官还没回来。我站在位子上四处张望，没看见死者，还以为他不在，结果不经意间抬头扫了一眼廊台，发现他身子前倾，正靠在一位优雅的女士身上，似乎是在确定法官们有没有归位。那位女士立即尖叫一声晕了过去，然后被人抬走了。主持审判的大法官是位经验丰富、睿智又耐心的人，他也跟了出去，等到料理好一切，才回来坐好，稳住自己，开始宣读总结陈词。这时死者从法官走进来的门飘入，直接到他桌旁，站在他身后急切地看笔录。法官大人正要翻页，突然脸色陡变，手也僵住，只见熟悉的一阵战栗传遍全身。他结结巴巴地说：“抱歉各位请稍等，不知怎的我被这污浊的空气弄魔怔了。”他端起杯子喝下一整杯水，才缓过来。

没有尽头的十天期限已经挨过了单调枯燥的六天——同样的法官坐在席位上，同一个谋杀犯坐在被告席，同样的律师坐在桌边，同样语气的问答声飘散在法庭上空，同样的沙沙作响声自法官笔下传出，同一批接待员进进出出引导，没有自然光时，同样的灯会在同样的时间亮起，雾天里蒙在巨幅玻璃外窗帘一般的同样的浓雾，雨天里吧嗒吧嗒打下的同样的雨滴，狱吏和囚犯日复一日在同样的地面上留下的同样的脚印，开关重重大门时转动的同样的钥匙——所有这些乏味的反复都让我有一种错觉，好像把这个陪审团团长当到天荒地老了，外面皮卡迪利大街还是当初和巴比伦都城一同繁华起来的。不过那个死者的一举一动我都不曾错过，他太过特别，实在难以忽略。实际上，就我所见，显灵的死者从来没有看向过谋杀犯。我一遍又一遍地想，为什么呢？真的一次都没有。

自打袖珍画像出现直到结案，死者再也没有看我一眼。陪审团在深夜十点还差七分钟的时候，退庭回去商议。由于教区代表和他的两个跟班太过蠢笨，又添了不少麻烦，以至于我们两次回法庭请求重读法官的部分笔录。我们九个人认为这些笔录一点儿问题都没有，随便从法庭上拽一个人估计他都会这么觉得。可那白痴三人组什么都不懂，就知道添乱，一直怀疑反对。我们争论了好久，才说服他们，于是陪审团在十二点十分重返法庭。

此时，死者站在陪审团坐席的正对面，法庭的另一边。待我入座，他十分刻意地盯着我看，然后似乎还比较满意，悠悠地拿起搭在手臂上的灰色大面纱——此前他从来没有戴过——盖住自己的头和整个身子。我宣读裁定时，讲到“判定有罪”，那纱巾一下掉在了地上，里面什么都没有了，他原先所在之处此时空空如也。

依照惯例，法官询问谋杀犯在宣布死刑之前他还有没有话要说，犯人含糊地嘟囔了一番。第二天，各大主要报纸都对此进行了报道，并形容这番话为“有点冗长混乱、不合逻辑、含糊不清的话，显然是为了抱怨自己受到不公，因为觉得陪审团团长早就对他心存偏见”。实际上，他那番不同寻常的说辞如下：“大人，我一看到陪审团团长就座，就知道自己完蛋了。法官阁下，他一定不会放过我的，因为我还没被抓的时候，有一天晚上，他就不知道怎的来到床边，把我叫醒，还要拿绳子勒死我。”

[10]柏林书商，指阿道弗斯·亚瑟（1800——1853），当时他的书店是伦敦文人名流聚会之所。

[11]新门监狱，位于伦敦西门的著名监狱。

[12]英文中，单词dyspeptic一语双关，既指“消化不良”，也指“（因消化不良而变得）阴郁悲观或暴躁牢骚”。

[13]圣殿关，地处商业中心伦敦和政治中心西敏之间的关卡。在狄更斯时代，即1878年之前，这里矗立着克里斯托夫·雷恩设计的石制门坊，即圣殿闩。

[14]《新门记事》，18世纪至19世纪英国家喻户晓的通俗月刊，讲述新门监狱里执行死刑的故事。

[15]英美司法体系中，对于刑事案件，陪审团会分别听取原告被告双方陈述和证据陈列后，再进行封闭式讨论，得出有罪或无罪的判定。

银勺

在维也纳有一位军官，他盘算着：“我怎么着也得去红牛[1]吃顿午饭。”

如同其他地方一样，酒店里充斥着各色人等：既有熟客，也有生人；既有社会名流，也有无名鼠辈；既有坦荡君子，也有江湖骗子。人们在这里吃吃喝喝，有人吃得多，有人吃得少。人们在这里聊天闲扯，从摩拉维亚[2]最近为什么会天降陨石雨，一直聊到法国有个叫玛钦的家伙打败了大恶狼。总有某人向自己的听众们吹嘘：自己比其他人提前一年从相好的那里洞悉了不可告人的天机。

在午餐快要结束的时候，总有一两个家伙举着还剩下半升匈牙利葡萄酒的杯子开怀畅饮，另一个家伙就像药剂师生产药丸那样把软面包搓成一个个的球，第三个家伙则耍起了刀子、叉子或者银勺子。军官注意到：一个穿着绿色上衣的家伙正玩着银勺子，忽然勺子滑进了他的衣袖里，再也没有出现。

如果换作别人，可能会想：“这关我什么事儿？”然后就视而不见，或者干脆跟着一块儿胡闹。军官却想：“我不知道那个偷勺子的绿衣服家伙是谁，这可能会引起误会。所以在老板过来结账之前，我得保持沉默。”

当老板过来结账的时候，军官拿起一把银勺子，插进了自己上衣的两个扣眼之间——一个扣眼进，另一个扣眼出，就像士兵们在战场上携带勺子那样，只是没有汤。在军官买单的时候，老板盯着他的外套，心中暗想：“这位先生佩戴的勋章真是别具一格啊，莫非他是曾经与一碗龙虾汤英勇战斗，因此才获得了一把银勺子？或者这把勺子就是属于我的？”

在买完单之后，军官故意板着脸说：“这把勺子是送的，对不对？账单已经够贵的了。”老板回答：“我们这儿可没这规矩！如果您家里没有勺子使，我可以送您一把钢的，但我这把还请您留下！”

这时候军官站了起来，拍着老板的肩膀笑了。“我和那边那位穿绿色外套的先生，我们俩这是跟您开玩笑呢，”他说，“那位绿衣服的先生，如果您能把您的勺子从袖子里拿出来，我也把我的勺子交出来。”偷勺子的贼人意识到：他双手不诚实的举动已经落入了一双诚实的眼睛里。他想：最好还是假装开玩笑，把勺子还给店主吧。

就这样，老板的财产终于物归原主，偷勺子的贼也笑了——然而他并没能得意多久。目睹了事件经过的其他顾客们齐心协力追打辱骂着行径暴露的贼人，将他轰出了酒店。老板也让佣人在贼人身后撒上了满满一把没有燃尽的炉灰[3]。这位好样儿的军官因为他正直的行为获得了一瓶匈牙利葡萄酒作为奖赏。

注意：不应该偷银勺子！

注意：正义从来不会缺席！

（1810年）

[1]红牛酒店（Gasthaus Roter Ochsen）是维也纳一家历史悠久的豪华酒店。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2]今捷克共和国东南部地区的旧称，当时属于奥地利帝国领土。

[3]基督教风俗，有让罪人悔改之意。

廉价午餐

有一句古老的谚语：自己挖坑埋自己。在某个小镇有家狮子客栈，这里发生的故事，恰好就说明了这句话的含义。

有一位衣冠楚楚的客人，他声称要点一份上等的肉汤、一块牛排和一份蔬菜。

客栈老板小心翼翼地问他：“您是否还想来一杯葡萄酒？”

“当然了，”客人回答，“只要对得起我兜里这钱。”

在把这些食物都一扫而光之后，客人掏出一枚磨损的五芬尼[4]硬币放到桌上，对客栈老板说：“老板先生，这是我的钱。”

客栈老板大怒：“这叫什么玩意儿？难道这顿饭不值一塔勒[5]吗？”

客人回答道：“我可没有说要点一顿价值一塔勒的饭菜，我说的是要点一顿对得起我兜里这钱的饭菜。我的钱就搁在这儿了，再多也没有了。是您饭菜给多了，这是您的错儿。”

很显然，客栈老板因为自己的傲慢和大意被顾客耍弄了，事情本应该到此为止的。然而，故事到这里并没有结束。

“您是个狡猾的流氓，”客栈老板说，“我本该好好收拾您一顿，然而这顿午饭算我白请，我再送给您二十四枚十字币[6]，请您再去到隔壁的大熊客栈，对他们重复一遍刚才的把戏。”

客栈老板之所以这么说，是因为他和隔壁大熊客栈的同行一直是竞争关系，双方彼此仇视，经常赌咒发誓，Thnbsp；不共戴天。然而狡猾的客人一把攥紧了客栈老板给的钱币，小心地看了一眼门外，对客栈老板道了一声晚安，最后笑着说：“我之前已经去过隔壁的大熊客栈了，是他们家老板让我上您这儿来的。”

鹬蚌相争，渔翁得利。然而如果这两位客栈老板能够有所领悟，并且彼此和解的话，他们还是应该好好感谢这位狡猾的客人。所谓和则两利，斗则两伤。

（1804年）

[4]芬尼（Pfennig）是德国历史上最小的货币单位之一。

[5]塔勒（Taler）是德国及中欧地区古代通行的大银币，每枚价值相当于360芬尼。

[6]十字币（Kreuzerstück）是德国南部及奥地利古代通行的银质辅币，因钱币上有十字架图案而得名，每枚价值相当于4芬尼。

户外午餐

人们常常抱怨：与某些人打交道是多么不容易。这么说当然没问题。然而在这些难打交道的人当中，很多人并不是坏人，只是脾气古怪而已。一旦别人正确理解了他们的思想和行为，并且用适当的方法对待他们，既不固持己见，也不一味附和，就会发现和他们相处其实是非常轻松愉快的。

从前有一位仆人对他的主人就是这么做的。这位仆人时常做错事，有时候也因为不是自己犯下的错误而受到责难。有一天，主人怒气冲冲地回到家里，坐下开始吃午餐。可能是因为汤太烫了，太凉了，或者不冷不热了，总而言之，主人怒了。他抄起盛汤的碗，从敞开的窗户将碗连同里面的汤汤水水一起扔到了外面的庭院里。

这时候仆人是怎么做的呢？他毫不犹豫地拿起本来要上到餐桌上的肉，将它像汤那样扔到了庭院里，随后他又把面包、葡萄酒以及包括桌布在内桌上的所有东西一股脑儿都扔了出去。

“你这冒失鬼想要干吗？”主人从沙发上暴跳起来，怒气冲冲地问道。仆人不慌不忙地回答：“如果我错误理解了您的意思的话，还请您原谅我。我没想别的，只是以为您今天想去庭院里吃饭。空气是多么新鲜，天空是多么湛蓝，开花的苹果树是多么可爱，蜜蜂都在花间愉快地享用它们的午餐。”

——这一次汤被扔出了窗外，但以后再也不会了。主人认识到了自己的错误，他欣赏着窗外美妙的春光，为仆人机智的反应会心一笑，并且在心中暗自感谢仆人给他上的这一课。

（1805年）

机智的法官

我们曾经听说过：并不是所有在东方国家发生的事情都是不公平的。下面这件事情就发生在那里。

有一位财主因为疏忽大意遗失了被他缝在布袋里的一大笔钱。当他发现把钱弄丢了以后，他顺理成章地悬赏一百塔勒来奖励那个找到钱的诚实的发现者。

不久就来了一个诚实的好人。“您的钱我找到了。分文不少！如数奉还！”当好人说这番话的时候，他坦荡的目光中透着诚实和善良，真是好样儿的。可是财主只在财产失而复得的瞬间露出了笑容。他不诚实的品性很快就会展现在我们面前。财主一边数着钱，一边暗中盘算：按照我之前的承诺，我将要付给这位发现者一大笔赏金。

“好伙计，”财主说，“布袋里原来一共有八百塔勒，但是现在只剩七百了，我猜您一定从缝隙里拿走了一百塔勒作为赏金，谢谢您。”

这真是太坏了。然而我们的故事并没有结束。诚实永垂不朽，而制造不公平的人却总是搬起石头砸自己的脚。这位诚实的发现者努力捍卫自己的清白正直，他保证自己将捡到的布袋原封不动还给了失主。

最后他们一起来到了法官面前。这两人各执一词，一位声称布袋里原本就有八百塔勒，另一位则坚持自己并没有从布袋里拿走一分一毫。两人唇枪舌剑好一番。

然而这位机智的法官早已看出了这两人一个胸怀磊落，一个心怀鬼胎，于是他眉头一皱，计上心来。他表示相信当事双方的陈述都是真实可靠的，并且做出了如下的判决：“照这么说，你们两人一个遗失了有八百塔勒的布袋，另一个捡到了有七百塔勒的布袋，所以你捡到的这个布袋很显然不是他遗失的那个。你，诚实的发现者，把你捡到的这笔钱先拿回去，直到遗失了七百塔勒的那人过来找你。至于你嘛，我也没有什么好说的，你应该耐心等着那个捡到八百塔勒的人来找你。”这就是法官的判决，并且是终审判决。

（1805年）

狡猾的轻骑兵

有一位参加最后一战[7]的轻骑兵，在街道上遇到向他迎面走来的一位庄稼汉。他得知这位庄稼汉刚刚由于出售干草而获得了一百古尔登[8]，正打算带着这笔钱回家。因此他打算向庄稼汉要点儿钱去买烟打酒。谁知道他会不会因为讨到几个子儿而满足呢？

然而那位庄稼汉却指天咒地地说：他的最后一枚十字币已经在隔壁的村庄花光了，现在他已经是一文不名。

“这地方离我们驻地不远，”轻骑兵说，“所以我们应该都能找到一些援助；但因为你啥都没有，我也啥都没有，所以我们得先走到圣阿方索[9]面前，如果他今天给咱俩恩赐的话，咱俩就像兄弟一样平分。”

所谓的圣阿方索，其实不过是立在乡村小路旁一座古老而人迹罕至的小教堂里的石头雕像。

起初，庄稼汉对徒步朝圣并没有什么兴趣，然而轻骑兵却不由分说，生拉硬拽着他一块儿上了路，还向他强调：圣阿方索从没有让他陷入过困境。这让农夫心中也燃起了一丝希望。

或许在小教堂里有一位轻骑兵的战友或者伙伴在等着他们？才没有呢！那儿只有一座圣阿方索的雕像，他俩在雕像前跪了下来，轻骑兵开始假装虔诚地祈祷。

“现在，”轻骑兵对他的伙伴耳语，“圣人在召唤我了。”他站起身，将自己的耳朵贴在石像的嘴唇上，然后面露喜色地回到他的同伴那里。

“圣人送给我一枚古尔登，就在我的衣兜里。”轻骑兵当着庄稼汉的面从衣兜里掏出一枚他事先藏好的古尔登，然后他俩就如同事先所约定的那样，像兄弟般平分了这笔钱。

庄稼汉觉得这很合理，他催促轻骑兵如法炮制再试一次。轻骑兵依样画葫芦又表演了一通，然后又欣喜若狂地从圣人那里回来了。“这一次好心的圣阿方索给了咱们一百古尔登，就在你的衣兜里。”

当庄稼汉听到这番话的时候，他的面色变得惨白起来，他再三保证，自己连一枚十字币都没剩下。然而轻骑兵告诉庄稼汉：他应该相信圣人，圣阿方索是不会骗他的。无论结果如何，他都应该把衣兜翻出来清空。

当一百枚古尔登出现在两人面前的时候，庄稼汉也只有打落门牙肚里吞，像轻骑兵之前和他平分自己的一枚古尔登那样，和轻骑兵平分了他这一百枚古尔登。

这件事儿办得机智而巧妙，然而这么做是不对的，尤其是在教堂里。

（1807年）

[7]指19世纪初由欧洲各国封建君主组成的“反法同盟”围攻拿破仑指挥下的法国军队的战争。

[8]原文中的Florin在当代西方语言中通常指代英国自1849年开始通行的面值2先令银币，但作者成书距此尚有近半个世纪之久。经译者考据，Florin另有一个含义是17世纪至19世纪德意志神圣罗马帝国境内通行的古尔登（Gulden）银币，其价值约为1/2塔勒，即180芬尼，此译法也与下面原文中将要提到的古尔登相吻合。

[9]圣阿方索（St. Alphonsus，1696—1787），出生于意大利那不勒斯，著名天主教神父，著有多部神学著作，死后由教皇庇护九世册封为圣人。

牙医

有两个懒汉，在一起东游西荡已经有些日子了。他俩懒得去赚那点儿打工的小钱，又身无长技，找不到快速致富的门道，最后变得穷困潦倒，走投无路。

于是他俩想到一个主意：挨家挨户去乞讨，不是为了填饱肚子，而是为了坑蒙拐骗。他俩把讨来的面包又揉又捏，做成小药片和药丸的形状，再混上被虫蛀过的烂木头的碎屑，看起来和药剂师那里的黄色药丸一模一样。

随后他俩从书籍装订商那里花几个巴岑[10]买来了一些红色的纸张（漂亮的颜色对每一种骗局都有所帮助）。他们把纸裁开，每张包上六到八颗“药丸”。

现在其中一人来到了镇上的年集，走进了一家红狮酒馆，希望能多招徕一些客人。他要了一杯葡萄酒，然而并不喝，而是坐在角落里，双手托腮露出一副痛苦的表情，不断发出低声的呻吟。

酒馆里纯朴的农民和镇上的人，都认定这个可怜人应该是患上了严重的牙疼。然而怎么办呢？人们同情他，安慰他说这一切很快就会过去，喝完了杯中的葡萄酒，又回到各自的工作中去了。

这时候另一个懒汉出现了。这两个混蛋看起来就好像这辈子从来不认识对方一样。他们并没有彼此注视对方，直到第二个家伙好像被坐在角落里的第一个家伙的呻吟声所吸引。“好伙计，”他说，“您看上去好像犯了牙疼？”然后他缓缓迈着大步走到了对方跟前。

“我是特拉法尔加[11]的施瑙齐乌斯·拉朋齐乌斯医生。”他接着说。这样一个奇特而响亮的名字就如同醒目的颜色一样，有助于实施诈骗。“如果您服下我的牙疼药丸的话，”他接着说，“即使是如此严重的症状，只需要一颗，最多两颗就可以药到病除。”

“看在上帝的分儿上。”另一个骗子回答。于是这位冒牌的拉朋齐乌斯医生从口袋里掏出红色的纸包，从里面取出一颗药丸，命令病人把药丸放在那颗坏牙上，完全嚼碎。顾客们一个接一个从桌边探过头来，围观这奇迹般的治愈。

接下来发生的事情您可想而知。病人不想从第一颗药丸开始就吹嘘它神奇的功效，于是他发出了一声尖利的号叫。这让医生感到非常满意。“您的疼痛，”他说，“已经开始被打破了。”说着他迅速拿出了第二颗药丸，用同样的方式让病人服下。

所有的疼痛立刻消失了。病人欢快地一跃而起，擦去额头上由于紧张而冒出的汗珠，尽管他手中其实空空如也，他还是假装对救命恩人千恩万谢，并掏出一笔貌似可观的报酬放到对方手中表示感谢。

这种伎俩看起来非常高明，而且的确行之有效。每一个在场的人现在都想要拥有这种神奇的药丸。“医生”对每包药丸开价二十四个十字币，在几分钟之内药丸就被一抢而空。

这两个骗子一前一后分别离开了，当他俩再次相聚的时候，他们为人们的单纯以及他们因此骗来的钱财而放声大笑。

这些“面包”可真是价值不菲啊。损失二十四枚十字币这笔小钱并不能让人陷入贫困，然而这对受骗的人们来说还不是最糟糕的。软面包球随着时间的流逝会变得像石子儿一样坚硬。在一年半载之后，当一位可怜的受骗者牙疼发作，他自信满满地一颗接一颗用他的坏牙咬碎坚硬的药丸，然而并没有被治愈，而是感到撕心裂肺的疼痛。而这种疼痛就是用他当初从自己兜里掏出去的那二十四枚十字币换来的！

由此我们可以看到，人们是多么容易被四处游荡的流浪汉的伪装所欺骗，这些骗子他们今生前所未见，今后也不会再见。有些读者看到这里可能会想：“我是如此的单纯，曾经也上过类似的当。”

记住：那些知道如何从其他地方骗钱的家伙，当他们来到村庄或者年集上的时候，可不会穿着有破洞的袜子，或者在右脚和左脚的鞋上分别安上白色和黄色的鞋扣。

（1807年）

[10]巴岑（Batzen），瑞士古代通行的银质辅币，价值相当于1/15古尔登。

[11]西班牙西南部的海角地区。

一份特殊的酒馆账单

一个恶作剧的念头有时候会成功，有时候却需要付出外套甚至是皮肤作为代价。这一次仅仅是外套。

从前有三个浪荡的大学生，他们在旅途中一路风流快活，衣兜里连一个赫勒[12]都没剩下。像往常那样，他们又走进了一家小酒馆，盘算着白吃白喝一顿然后悄悄从后门溜走。

天遂人愿，当时酒馆里只有年轻柔弱的老板娘一个人。他们仨一边胡吃海喝，一边高深莫测地对话，诸如：这个世界已经存在了几千年之久，将来还会存在这么久，Thnbsp；直到某一天的某一个时辰，每一年、每一天、每一小时都会像六千年前那样从头开始。

“是的。”他们中的一位终于发声了，他对坐在窗户旁，手里一边做着针线活儿，一边认真倾听的老板娘说道，“这是我们从学过的书籍里知道的。”

另一位则厚颜无耻地声称：他依稀记得他们在六千年前曾经来过这个地方，他还能清楚地认出老板娘那张美丽而友善的脸庞。

这样的对话持续了好长一段时间，老板娘看起来越是相信他们说的一切，这几个年轻的浪荡子弟越是卖力地享用着葡萄酒、烤肉和纽结面包。最后他们账单上的数字一路攀升到了五古尔登外加十六枚十字币。当他们吃饱喝足之后，哥仨打算按照之前计划的那样逃之夭夭。

“老板娘女士，”其中一位说，“这回哥几个手头有点儿紧。这条街上有很多酒馆，我们有幸找到了您这位聪明的女士，我们希望这次您作为老朋友能让我们赊账。如果您不介意的话，当六千年后哥几个再回来的时候，咱们新账旧账一块儿算。”

聪明的老板娘并没有面露愠色，而是显得十分愉快。她表示：几位先生如此满意，这让她也十分高兴。随后她不声不响地站在了酒馆的门口，要求这几位先生立刻把六千年前欠下的五古尔登外加十六枚十字币的账付了。因为按照他们所说，今天所发生的一切，从前已经原封不动地发生过一遍了。

不幸的是，这时村里的警长正领着几个精壮的汉子，走进酒馆想要为他们的荣誉喝上一杯。这对这几位瓮中之鳖来说可不是什么好事儿。很快警长就做出了判决：“欠账六千年可不是件光荣的事情，这几位先生要么立刻把债还清，要么就把身上崭新的上衣脱下来抵债。”

哥仨不得不选择了第二个选项，而老板娘也保证：如果六千年后他们几个带着钱回来的话，她会把衣服一件一件全部还给他们。

这个故事就发生在1805年4月17日泽灵根[13]的酒馆里。

（1808年）

[12]赫勒（Heller）是德国古代通行的铜质辅币，1赫勒价值相当于1/2芬尼。

[13]泽灵根（Segringen），今德国南部巴符州一小镇。

意外的重逢

五十多年前，在瑞典的法伦有一位年轻的矿工，他亲吻着美丽的未婚妻，对她说：“在圣露西亚节[14]我们的爱情将会在牧师手中得到祝福，我们将成为夫妻，共同建筑爱巢。”

“那里面将充满了宁静和爱，”美丽的未婚妻带着甜蜜的微笑说，“你是我的唯一和全部，离开你，我除了坟墓哪里也不想去。”

然而，他俩还没来得及站在圣露西亚面前，牧师还没有机会说：“如果有谁反对这两位新人结成婚姻的，请站出来陈述理由。”——死亡就站出来了。

有一天早上，小伙子穿着他乌黑的矿工制服从姑娘的房前经过——矿工总是穿着他自己的寿衣——他又一次敲响了她的窗户，对她说早安，然而他却没能对她说晚安。他再也没能从矿井里回来。

那天早上，姑娘因为无聊系上了她为婚礼准备的带着红边的黑色围巾。当得知未婚夫的噩耗之后，她把围巾扯了下来，为他哭泣，念念不忘。

与此同时，葡萄牙的里斯本城被地震摧毁[15]，七年战争[16]结束了，弗兰茨一世皇帝[17]去世了，耶稣会[18]被解散，波兰被瓜分[19]95年波兰被俄、普、奥三国最终瓜分。[20]去世，施特林泽[21]被处决，美国宣告独立，法国和西班牙联军没能攻破直布罗陀[22]。土耳其人将斯坦因将军关进了匈牙利的“老兵山洞”[23]，约瑟夫皇帝[24]也去世了。瑞典的古斯塔夫国王7从俄罗斯手里夺取了芬兰，法国大革命引发了长期的战争，利奥波德二世皇帝[25]也进了坟墓。拿破仑征服了普鲁士[26]，英国人炮轰哥本哈根[27]。农民们播种又收割，磨坊主磨面，铁匠们敲打，矿工们在地下工场中挖掘金属矿脉。然而，在1809年圣约翰节◆◆◆圣约翰节（Johannistag），基督教节日，为纪念施洗者约翰——为耶稣洗礼的基督教先知而设立，时间通常在每年6月24日。◆◆◆前后，法伦的矿工们想要在两条竖井之间打开一条通道，在距离地面三百多腕尺[28]的碎石和酸水中，他们挖出了一具年轻男子的尸体。他在绿矾水的保护下，毫发未损，栩栩如生。人们可以清晰地辨认出他的容貌和年龄，仿佛他在一小时之前刚刚死去，或者正在工作间隙打盹儿。

当人们把尸体抬出矿井的那天，他的父母双亲、好友故知都早已离世，没有人能够认出这个长眠的小伙子，或者述说他不幸的遭遇。直到矿工的未婚妻认出了那张某一天从她面前消逝、一去不返的面庞。

她苍白的脸上已布满皱纹，拄着一根拐棍来到广场上辨认她的未婚夫。她跪倒在爱人的尸体前，心中的喜悦胜过了忧伤。她内心波澜起伏，久久才平静下来。“他是我的未婚夫，”她终于说道，“五十年来我一直牵挂着他，如今在上帝的安排之下，我终于在离世之前再次见到了他。在我们婚礼之前八天他下了矿井，从此一去不返。”

那位昔日的未婚妻，无情的时光已经在她脸上刻满了皱纹，而她的未婚夫，面容却依然像年轻时候那样英俊。好像在五十年后，她胸中年轻时爱的火焰又被重新点燃了，然而他却再也不能发出笑声，眼睛再也不能睁开了。围观的人们都被这悲伤的情景感动得热泪盈眶。

最后她让矿工们把他的尸体抬进了她的小屋，就仿佛她是他所拥有的唯一东西，而他也拥有这样的权利，直到在教堂墓地里他的墓穴被挖好。

第二天，墓穴已经挖好了，矿工们抬着尸体走向教堂墓地。她从一个小箱子里拿出那条带着红边的黑色围巾系上，穿上她最好的衣服，陪伴着他走上她每周日去教堂的必经之路，就仿佛这是他俩的婚礼，而不是他的葬礼。

当人们把他的尸体放进教堂墓地的墓穴，她说：“安息吧，在冰冷的婚床上再待上几天，不要感到时光漫长。我还有一点儿事情要处理，重逢的日子不远了。——大地已经将你还给了我，它不会再次将你夺走的。”她一步三回头地离开了。

（1811年）

[14]圣露西亚节（Sankt Luciä）是北欧国家通行的基督教节日，为纪念罗马帝国时期的女圣人圣露西亚（Sankt Luciä，283—304）而设立，时间通常在每年的12月13日。

[15]1755年11月1日，里斯本发生了迄今为止欧洲发生过的最大地震，地震引发了30米高的海啸，整个城市被摧毁，6～10万人遇难，占当时里斯本人口的1/4至1/5。

[16]1756年至1763年欧洲各国之间围绕着王位继承权和殖民地利益而爆发的一系列战争，最后以英国、普鲁士等一方胜利，法国、奥地利、俄罗斯等一方失败告终。

[17]欧洲历史上有多位名叫弗兰茨一世（Franz der Erste）的君主，此处应为哈布斯堡王朝的弗兰茨·史蒂芬（Franz I. Stephan，1708—1765）。

[18]1534年成立于法国的天主教修会，1773年被教皇敕令解散。

[19]1★★★此处应为古斯塔夫三世（Gustav Ⅲ，1746—1792）。

[20]，玛丽亚·特利莎女皇★★★玛丽亚·特利莎（Maria Theresia），奥地利女君主（1717—1780）。

[21]约翰·弗里德里希·施特林泽（Johann Friedrich Struensee，1737—1772），德国人，丹麦和挪威国王克里斯蒂安七世（Christian Ⅶ，1749—1808）的御医，因篡夺权位以及与王后私通被斩首分尸。

[22]直布罗陀（Gibraltar），西班牙伊比利亚半岛最南端的海岬，1704年在西班牙王位继承战争中被英军占领，此后西班牙多次设法收复，至今未果。

[23]此事应发生在1787年至1792年第六次俄土战争期间，当时奥地利帝国参与了俄罗斯一方。

[24]约瑟夫二世（Joseph Ⅱ，1741—1790），奥地利帝国皇帝，特利莎女皇之子。

[25]利奥波德二世[Leopold Ⅱ.（HRR），1747—1792]，神圣罗马帝国皇帝波西米亚、克罗地亚及匈牙利国王。

[26]1806年普鲁士军队在第四次反法同盟中被法军彻底击败，被迫于次年签订了割地赔款的季利济特条约。

[27]1807年，由于害怕中立国丹麦-挪威王国与拿破仑领导下的法国结盟，英国军队在不宣而战的情况下对该国首都哥本哈根进行了为期三天的炮击，造成了大量人员财产伤亡损失。

[28]腕尺（Ellen），德国古代长度单位，1腕尺相当于现代公制的45～56厘米。

狡猾的朝圣者

几年前，有一个四处游荡的流浪汉，他把自己打扮成虔诚的朝圣者的样子，声称自己来自帕德伯恩[29]，正走在朝拜耶路撒冷神圣墓地[30]的路上。

在米尔海姆[31]的驿站，他曾经向人打听：“这儿离耶路撒冷还有多远？”

别人告诉他：“需要七百个小时，但如果你从毛兴[32]的小路走的话，就可以省下一刻钟的时间[33]。”

这听上去还不赖，所谓不积跬步，无以至千里嘛。毕竟节省或者赚到一个巴岑的机会，要比获得一个古尔登的机会多得多。

然而十五个巴岑毕竟就相当于一个古尔登。所以在七百个小时的旅程中，每五小时里就能省下一刻钟的话，谁知道一共能够省下多少时间呢。

但是这位冒牌的朝圣者可不是这么想的，他就是一门心思东游西荡，蹭吃蹭喝。

一个乞丐永远不应该忘记一句古老的谚语：不要去一个贫穷的村庄乞讨，因为讨来的东西还抵不上一路上鞋底的磨损，尤其是光着脚的时候更不要去。朝圣者也是这么想的，所以他很快就回到了大路上，这里有富人们的房屋和丰盛的食物。

这个无赖并不满足于作为一个普通朝圣者从一双双充满同情而虔诚的手中获取的寻常食物，他除了“营养丰富”的卵石汤[34]以外，什么都不想喝。

只要在路旁看到上好的酒馆，比如说克罗琴根[35]的驿站，或者施林根[36]的巴塞尔酒吧，他就装出一副极其谦卑和饥饿的样子，向别人乞讨一碗由清水和卵石煮成的汤，看在上帝的份儿上，钱自然是不付的。

当好心的老板娘对他说“虔诚的朝圣者，鹅卵石太硬了，在胃里没法儿消化！”的时候，他回答道：“所以我才要吃它！去耶路撒冷的路这么远，这玩意儿吃下去比面包顶饿！当然如果您能送我一杯葡萄酒的话，肯定会有助于我的消化。”

这时候老板娘会说：“然而，虔诚的朝圣者，这样的一碗汤没法儿给您提供足够的能量啊。”

朝圣者这样回答：“如果您能把清水换成肉汁的话，肯定会更有营养的。”

现在老板娘给他端来了这样一碗汤，并且说：“底料还没煮得那么软。”朝圣者回答道：“是啊，而且肉汁看上去也太稀了。您能不能往汤里再添上满满几勺蔬菜或者一块肉，或者二者都添上？”

当好心的老板娘把蔬菜和肉加进汤碗里之后，朝圣者说道：“上帝保佑您！现在请把面包给我，我要喝汤了。”

于是朝圣者扔下他的手杖，挽起衣袖，坐下了。他满心欢喜地端起他的杰作，将最后一粒面包屑，最后一根肉丝，最后一滴葡萄酒和肉汁都吃喝得干干净净。然后用餐巾或者袖口擦了擦嘴，或者根本不擦嘴，说道：“老板娘女士，您的汤把我撑得太饱了，所以我无法勉为其难吃下这些美丽的鹅卵石了。太可惜了！但还是请您把它们收好。当我回来的时候，我会送给您一枚来自亚实基伦[37]的神圣贝壳或者一朵来自杰里科[38]的玫瑰。”

（1808年）

[29]帕德博恩（Paderborn），德国中西部城市。

[30]此处指位于耶路撒冷的耶稣墓地。

[31]米尔海姆（Müllheim），德国西南部城市。

[32]毛兴（Mauchen），米尔海姆附近一小镇。

[33]考虑到作者成书的年代距今已有两个世纪，德语原文中的“七百小时”其实是路人的信口开河，只是大概虚数；而“一巴岑”与“一刻钟”则分别是流浪汉作为缺乏教育的社会底层人物所能理解的最小货币和时间单位，因此用二者来做类比，虽然与“一古尔登”和“五小时”在比例上并不准确，但非常符合其思维逻辑。

[34]卵石汤（Kieselstein suppen）源自一个古老的欧洲民间传说：一群饥饿的旅人谎称用清水煮石头可以做出人间美味，以此骗村民们将自己的食物投入锅中与其分享，也被称为“斧头汤”或者“纽扣汤”，其含义与中文的“空手套白狼”有相似之处。

[35]克罗琴根（Krotzingen），德国西南部小城。

[36]施林根（Schliengen），德国西南部小城。

[37]亚实基伦（Ashkelon），以色列南部古城，临近地中海东岸。

[38]杰里科（Jericho），以色列中部古城，位于死海北岸河谷中，因盛产玫瑰而著称。

司令官和轻装步兵在赫斯菲尔德

在上一次与普鲁士-俄罗斯联军的战役中[39]，法国军队和一大部分联盟[40]军队都驻扎在波兰和普鲁士境内，其中有一支来自巴登[41]的轻装步兵队伍在黑森[42]的赫斯菲尔德[43]担任警戒任务。此地在战端初起之时，就已经被皇帝[44]派兵占领，据为己有了。

相比旧的统治者而言，经常为非作歹的占领军显然不受当地居民的待见，因此他们在赫斯菲尔德也遇到了许多反抗，其中一起是一位法国军官被杀害了。

法国皇帝正在前线与不计其数的敌军鏖战，他可不允许敌人在他身后捣乱，造成这样的事情发生，因为即使是一点星星之火，也可能卷起燎原的烈焰。

赫斯菲尔德可怜的居民们，很快就被要求为自己鲁莽的行为承担后果。按照法国皇帝的命令，赫斯菲尔德市必须遭到劫掠，然后四处纵火，被烧成灰烬。

赫斯菲尔德是一个居民富足，有着许多工厂和美丽建筑的地方。当这样一个坏消息传来的时候，这些可怜的父老乡亲是一种什么样的心情，大家可想而知。穷人们仅有的身家将被人一把夺走，而富人们的财产则将被人用一辆辆马车运走。广场旁的豪宅和角落里的寒舍将化成同样的灰烬，就如同教堂墓地也是富人和穷人共同的归宿。

然而，最坏的情况并没有发生。在法国驻卡塞尔[45]和赫斯菲尔德司令官的求情下，惩罚明显减轻了：只有四座房屋被烧毁，损失有限；然而劫掠还将照旧执行，这依然是非常严厉的惩罚。

当不幸的居民们听到最终判决的时候，他们恐惧万分，魂飞魄散。他们对在仁慈的司令官面前进行徒劳无益的抱怨和请求已经不抱任何希望，只想争分夺秒在劫掠开始前将自己最重要的财物抢救出来。

恐怖的时刻终于来临了，鼓声在不幸的人们的号啕大哭声中响起。士兵们匆匆忙忙穿过恐惧、奔逃、绝望的人群，来到了他们的集合点。

于是这位正直的司令官站在他的轻装步兵队列前面，他首先声情并茂地向他们描述了居民们的悲惨遭遇，随后说道：“士兵们！劫掠的许可从现在开始生效。谁有兴趣参加的，请出列。”

没有人站出来，一个都没有！司令官又重复了一遍命令，依然没有人迈步。司令官表示：如果没有人想要参与劫掠，那他就只好自己去了。然而依然没有人愿意服从。于是显而易见，这次任务就被放弃了。

当居民们知道这件事情的时候，他们的心情就仿佛刚刚从一场噩梦中醒来一样。他们的快乐简直无法形容。他们立刻派出一位代表去见司令官，向他的宽宏大量表示感谢，并且送给他一份丰厚的礼物作为报答。谁知道如果没有他将会发生什么！

然而司令官却拒绝了礼物，他说，自己做好事不是为了钱财。

这个故事于1807年发生在赫斯菲尔德，这座小城至今依然屹立。

（1808年）

[39]此处应指1806年至1807年的第四次反法同盟。

[40]此处指1806年至1813年由法国扶植德意志地区众邦国组建的“莱茵联盟”（Rheinbund）。

[41]巴登（Baden），当时为“莱茵联盟”境内公国，领土包括今日德国西南部巴符州南部地区。

[42]黑森（Hessen），当时亦为“莱茵联盟”境内公国，领土包括今日德国中部黑森州大部分地区。

[43]赫斯菲尔德（Hersfeld），黑森公国境内城市。

[44]此处指拿破仑一世。

[45]卡塞尔（Kassel），德国中部城市，当时为黑森公国首都。

坏的奖赏

在上一次与普鲁士的战争中，法国人攻入了普鲁士国王[46]所在的城市柏林[47]，许多属于王室的财产被夺走，它们被人占有，或者被变卖。因为战争从不会带来任何东西，它只会掠夺东西。

人们发现了许多精心藏匿的财宝，作为战利品的一部分，但王室财产并没有全都被找到。有大量属于王室的木质建材尚未被发现，保存完好。

在国王的侍从中有一个无赖，他想着借此好好赚上一笔。他跑到法国司令官那里，挤眉弄眼地告诉他：在某某地方有一批质量上乘的橡木和杉木，价值数千古尔登。

然而这位正直的司令官婉言谢绝了这种背叛行为，他说：“就让那些上乘的木料待在它们原来的地方吧，不应该对敌人赶尽杀绝。”

当国王回国之后，他命令用这些木材给这位“忠诚”的侍从建起了一座崭新的绞刑架，以此作为对他“忠诚”的报答。

在莱茵兰[48]的朋友如果欣赏这个故事的话，可以试着在自家的森林里挖一挖，或许能找到一些当时被遗忘的木材呢。

（1809年）

[46]此处指腓特烈·威廉三世（Frederick William Ⅲ，1770—1840）。

[47]1806年10月，法军在与第四次反法同盟的战争中大败普军，占领了包括柏林在内的普鲁士大部分地区，腓特烈·威廉三世被迫逃亡到位于东部的柯尼希堡（Königsberg）。

[48]莱茵兰（Rhineland），今属德国西部的莱法州，当时为普鲁士王国领土。

奇怪的鬼故事

去年秋天，有一位陌生的绅士来到了施林根这个美好的地方。在登山的时候，他放弃骑马，选择了步行。在途中，他向一位克罗伊茨纳赫[49]人讲述了一个他亲身经历的故事。

半年前，这位绅士在丹麦旅行，一天深夜他来到了一座村庄，村庄不远处的山丘上有一座整洁的小城堡，他决定就在村里过夜了。

客栈老板告诉他，当天晚上已经没有足够的床位了，而明天早上将有一场行刑，他将和三个刽子手一起过夜。于是这位绅士回答说：“我要去那座小城堡，那里的领主或者主人会让我进去，并且给我提供一张空床铺。”

老板说：“那里有许多挂着丝绸床幔的美丽的床，就在居高临下的房间里，而我负责保管城堡的钥匙。然而我不建议您去那里。三个月之前，城堡仁慈的主人和他的妻子儿女一起出了远门，打那以后，这座小城堡就被鬼魂占据了。城堡的看守和仆人们都待不下去了，其他去过小城堡的人就没有再去第二次的。”

这位陌生的绅士笑了。他是一个勇敢的人，对鬼魂毫不惧怕。他说：“我想去试试。”

尽管客栈老板对此表示反对，他还是从老板手里拿到了钥匙。随后他准备好了拜访鬼魂所需要的物品，与一直跟随他的仆人一起走进了城堡。

在城堡里，他衣不解带，睡意全无，一心等待着将要发生的事情。他把两盏点亮的灯放在桌上，旁边摆上两把上好膛的手枪，看着用细细的红丝带悬挂在镜框下面的金色纸片，欣赏着美丽的图画，回想着与莱茵兰发小儿共度的往日时光。很长时间过去了，可什么都没有发生。

然而到了午夜时分，教堂的屋顶开始闪烁，大钟敲响了十二点，一片乌云飘过来遮住了城堡，巨大的雨滴敲打着窗户，发出比敲打大门大三倍的响声。一个有着漆黑而空洞的眼睛、半肘长的鼻子、突出的牙齿和山羊胡子、全身长满了乱蓬蓬的毛发的身影开始在房间里游荡，并且发出可怕的鼻音：“我是梅菲斯特[50]，欢迎来到我的宫殿。你们要和你们的老婆孩子永别了！”

陌生的绅士感到一股冷气从大脚趾上升起，顺着后背一直蹿到了睡帽上。至于他可怜的仆人，就更不用想了。

然而有着恐怖鬼脸的梅菲斯特正向他走来，膝盖抬得高高的，就好像在火焰上漫步一样。可怜的绅士想：以上帝的名义，在此一举了。他勇敢地站起身，用枪指着那个鬼魂，喊道：“不许动！不然我就开枪了！”

在这种情况下，没有任何鬼怪会感到害怕，因为尽管人们想开枪，但要么枪打不响，要么子弹对鬼怪毫发无损，反而飞回来击中开枪自卫的那个人。

然而梅菲斯特却高高地举起他的大脚趾，慢慢转过身，像他来的时候那样迈着缓慢的步伐离开了。

当陌生人看到魔鬼在火药面前心生畏惧的时候，他想：现在没有危险了。他用另一只手拿起灯，蹑手蹑脚地慢慢跟在鬼魂的身后。而这位仆人，他用最快的速度蹿出城堡，回到了客栈，他宁可跟刽子手在一起过夜，也不要和鬼魂待在一起。

然而，在过道里，鬼魂忽然从大胆的跟踪者的眼前消失了，看起来就仿佛沉入了地底一样。

当绅士想要再往前走几步一探究竟的时候，他脚下的地板忽然消失了，他掉进了一个地洞里。他看到迎面而来的火光，相信自己马上就要一命归西了。然而当他的十个脚趾终于安全落地的时候，他才发现自己身在一个有着穹顶的地窖里，毫发无损地躺在一堆干草上。有六个外形奇特的家伙围着火堆站着，梅菲斯特也在其中。在他们周围摆放着各种各样稀奇古怪的装备，在两张桌子上堆满了闪闪发光的伪造塔勒，一张比一张更迷人。

这时候陌生人终于恍然大悟：原来他们是一个伪造钱币的秘密团伙，所有人都是有血有肉的活人。他们利用城堡主人不在的时机，将造币设备秘密运进了城堡，有一些熟悉城堡情况的内部人员或许也参与其中。为了保证他们的秘密行动不被打扰和发现，他们开始装神弄鬼，每个来到城堡里的人都惊恐万状，以至于下次再也不来了。

然而现在旅行者开始为他没有听从村里客栈老板的劝告而感到后悔了。因为他被塞进一个狭窄的洞穴里一处阴森的小屋，并且听到他们的“战争法庭”在讨论对自己的处治方案。

“最好还是把他宰了，然后把尸体埋起来。”有人说。

然而另一个人却说：“我们应该先审问一下他，他是谁，他叫什么名字，他从哪儿来。”

当他们听到他是一位贵族绅士，并且要去哥本哈根觐见国王的时候，他们面面相觑，瞪大了眼睛。在把他扔回阴森的储藏室之后，他们说：“这下大事不好了，一旦他失踪了，人们就会从客栈老板那里知道他进了城堡再也没有出来的事情。轻骑兵一夜之间就会来到这里，把我们揪出来。我们长期的苦心经营，就要毁于一旦了。”

他们表示愿意放过这位俘虏，前提是他发誓不把他们的秘密泄露出去。此外他们还威胁说，他们会在哥本哈根派人监视他。他们还要求他在誓词里把自己的住处说出来。

他说：“在野人左手附近有着绿色百叶窗的大房子。”

然后他们送给他一杯勃艮第葡萄酒作为起床饮料。在天亮之前他整晚看着他们如何铸造假塔勒。

当阳光穿过缝隙照进了地窖的时候，街上传来了啪啪的鞭子声和哞哞的牛叫声。陌生人告别了阴暗的地窖，向主人们的“友好招待”表示了感谢，带着欢快的神情回到了客栈，全然不顾他的怀表、烟斗和手枪还留在城堡里。

老板说：“谢天谢地，终于再见到您了，我整个晚上都没睡着。您那边怎么样？”

然而旅人却想：“一诺千金。虽然是为了保命而许下的誓言，然而也不应该将它泄露出来，否则就是对上帝的亵渎。”

所以他一言不发。这时钟声又敲响了，那些可怜的罪犯已经把现场清理干净，一切就这样过去了。

在哥本哈根，他也对这件事情守口如瓶，几乎都快想不起来了。

然而，在几个星期后，邮局给他送来了一个小箱子，里边装着一对儿崭新的带着银饰价值不菲的手枪，一块崭新的镶嵌着昂贵宝石的金质怀表，一个带着金链子和金线刺绣烟袋的土耳其烟斗，还有一封短信。

短信上写着：“我们给您送上这份礼物，以此表达对给您带来惊吓的补偿，以及对您站在我们一边、保持沉默的感谢。现在一切都过去了，如果您愿意的话，可以把这个故事讲出来了。”

这就是那位绅士之所以把这个故事讲给克罗伊茨纳赫人听的原因。当他在登山途中听到赫廷根正午时分的钟声，掏出来对时的，就是他说的那块金表。后来在巴塞尔的仙鹤旅馆[51]，有一位法国将军出价七十五枚崭新的杜布伦[52]。然而他没有答应。

（1809年）

[49]克罗伊茨纳赫（Krenzach），德国西部莱法州城市。

[50]梅菲斯特（Mephistopheles）是当时德国文学中常见的魔鬼形象，在同时代歌德的《浮士德》中亦有出现。

[51]仙鹤旅馆（Gasthof zum Storchen）是巴塞尔一家历史悠久的豪华酒店。

[52]杜布伦（Dublone），古代欧洲通行的金币，西班牙、法国、瑞士等均有铸造，1杜布伦价值约相当于3古尔登。

废话连篇

有一位富裕的施瓦本[53]绅士将他的儿子送到巴黎去学习法语和礼仪。过了一年多，这位父亲的仆人也来到了巴黎。

当年轻的绅士看到仆人的时候，他充满惊喜和友善地叫出了声：“嗨，汉斯！哪阵风把你吹来的？家里怎么样？有什么消息吗？”

“没啥消息，威廉先生，只是一年前牧场工人送给您的那只美丽的乌鸦在十天前死了。”

“可怜的动物，”这位威廉先生回答，“它怎么死的？”

“唉，您知道，当咱家美丽的马一匹接一匹地死去之后，它可能吞吃了太多的尸体。我就知道会这样。”

“什么？我父亲那四匹美丽的摩尔马[54]都死了？”威廉先生问道，“这是怎么回事？”

“当咱家的房子和农场着火的时候，它们因为运水而劳累过度，我们对此也无能为力。”

“天哪！”威廉先生惊叫，“咱家的房子烧了？这是什么时候的事儿？”

“那天晚上我们正在火化您父亲的尸体，有人一不留神，一颗小火星就把房子点着了。”

“多么不幸的消息！”威廉先生哀号着，“那我的妹妹还好吧？”

“您还没出嫁的妹妹生了个没有父亲的孩子，是个男孩。这就是令尊大人被活活气死的原因。除此以外就没有什么消息了。”他补充道。

（1809年）

[53]施瓦本（Schwabenland），今德国巴伐利亚州西南部地区，当时为公国。

[54]摩尔马（Mohren schimmel）指肤色类似摩尔人的棕黑色马种。

赔本买卖

在大都市伦敦及其周围地区，有许多极其愚蠢的傻瓜，他们对别人的金钱、怀表或者昂贵的戒指有着孩子般的喜好，不弄到一模一样的，誓不罢休。

他们常常通过诡计或者欺骗来达到自己的目的，更多时候则是通过明火执仗的抢劫，这样的抢劫有时就发生在光天化日之下开阔的公路上。其中有的成功了，有的则失败了。伦敦的狱卒或者刽子手可以讲述很多这样的故事。

有一天，一个奇特的故事就发生在一位高贵而富有的先生身上。

一个美丽的夏日，国王和许多贵族仕女聚集在一座巨大的王家花园中，那里有一条幽长曲折的道路，一直通往森林的深处。

有许多其他人等也聚集在那里，他们并没有兴趣花几个小时去小路上一探究竟，只要看到他们热爱的国王和王室成员就感到非常愉快和幸运了。

人们又吃又喝，歌舞嬉戏，成双成对或者独自一人在美丽的小路上或者茂密的玫瑰花丛中漫步。

一个衣冠楚楚的人，打扮得就好像众人中的一员，在外套下面掖着一把手枪，藏身在花园与森林交界处的一棵树后，等着有人路过。

说曹操，曹操就到。有一位绅士戴着闪闪发光的戒指、叮当作响的表链、钻石镶嵌的带扣、宽阔的绶带和金星，心无杂念地走进了凉爽的树荫里。

正在他心无杂念的时候，那个家伙从他面前的树林里走出来，给了这位好先生一个“谦卑的欢迎”。他从外套下面的马甲里掏出手枪，将枪口指着绅士的胸口，并且礼貌地要求他不要作声，因为他不想让别人听到他们之间的谈话。

当人站在枪口前面的时候，难免会感到恐惧，因为你也不知道枪里装着什么。

这位绅士理智地思考了一下：身体比钱财更有价值，而失去戒指总比失去手指要强。于是他同意保持沉默。

“尊贵的老爷，”这家伙开口了，“您能不能把您的两块金表出一个好价钱卖了呢？我们的校长每天都要找别人对表，而日晷上的刻度又非常模糊，我们总是不清楚准确的时间。”

不管这位富有的绅士是否情愿，他不得不以几个斯蒂博[55]的价格将怀表卖给了这个无赖，这点儿钱甚至都不够去喝上一杯四分之一升的酒。

就这样，这个无赖右手举着枪，左手拿着几个小钱，一件一件地从绅士那里买来了戒指、带扣和金星。

到最后绅士想：“终于完事儿了，谢天谢地！”可这时无赖却耍起了新的花招：“尊贵的老爷，鉴于咱俩之间相处得还是挺融洽的，您想不想从我这儿买点儿东西呢？”

绅士思考了一下这句话，觉得面对这桩糟糕买卖，还是应该有个好的表情，于是说道：“让我瞧瞧吧！”

于是无赖就从口袋里掏出了各种各样的小玩意儿，Thnbsp；这些都是他从“件件两巴岑”的杂货店里买来的，现在可算是找到一位不还价的买主了。那位好绅士不得不把所有的东西以高昂的价格一件一件从他手里买过来。

到最后，除了手枪无赖把所有东西都卖光了，而绅士的绿色丝绸钱包里还剩下一些迷人的杜布伦。无赖还在说着：“尊贵的老爷，您难道不想用手里剩下的钱，买下我这把手枪吗？它是由伦敦最好的工匠打造的，看在咱哥俩的情面上，两个杜布伦卖给你。”

绅士惊讶地想：“你这个蠢贼！”然后买下了手枪。

当他把手枪买下之后，他立刻掉转枪口喊道：“不许动，坏家伙，立刻给我往前走，我叫你去哪儿你就去哪儿，否则我就一枪毙了你。”

无赖一下蹿进了树林，嘴里喊着：“尽管开枪吧，尊贵的老爷，枪没上膛！”

绅士扣动了扳机，枪果然没有响。他把通条插进了枪管，里面一粒火药都没有。

这时那个贼人已经逃进了树林深处，这位高贵的英国人只好面红耳赤地回去了。今天这段可怕的经历，够他好好回味一阵子的。

（1809年）

[55]斯蒂博（Stüber）是古代荷兰发行的辅币，每枚价值相当于4芬尼。

秘密斩首

我不知道，在某一年6月17日的早晨，兰道[56]的刽子手是否曾经再三向我们在天上的父虔诚地祈祷。

但在他的祈祷中，他肯定没有祈求一封来自南锡[57]的短信在那一天到来。

在这封信上写着：“兰道的邻居！您必须带上砍头用的大剑，立刻到南锡来。在这儿您将被告知要执行的任务，并且得到丰厚的报酬。”——一辆旅行马车已经停在了他家门前。

刽子手想：“这是我的工作。”于是就坐进了马车。

在离南锡还有一小时车程的时候，太阳已经和血红色的晚霞一起落下，夜幕降临了。车夫悄悄把车停下，说了声：“明天又是个好天气。”

这时候路边来了三个全副武装的壮汉，上车坐在刽子手的身旁，他们向他保证不会伤害他，但他必须让他们把他的眼睛蒙住。当把刽子手的眼睛蒙好以后，他们说道：“车夫，走吧。”

车夫驾车继续向前。刽子手感觉足足过去了十二个小时，但却不知道自己身处何方。一路上他听到了午夜猫头鹰的叫声，听到了公鸡的打鸣声，听到了早晨的钟声。

马车终于再次停了下来，有人把刽子手带进了一所房子，给了他一杯饮料和一根上好的香肠。

当食物和饮料让他恢复了体力之后，有人领着他在房子里继续前行，进进出出穿过一道道门，上上下下走过一级级台阶，当他的蒙眼布被解开的时候，他发现自己身处一座巨大的大厅之中。大厅的四周被黑布遮蔽，桌上点着蜡烛。

在大厅中央的椅子上坐着一个人，她的脖子裸露着，脸上戴着面具，她的嘴好像被什么东西堵住了，因此不能说话，只能发出呜咽声。

在四周的墙边站着许多穿着黑色外衣，脸部蒙着黑色面纱的绅士，这样下次当他再遇见他们的时候，就完全认不出他们来了。其中的一个人命令刽子手举起剑，把坐在椅子上的那个人的头颅砍下来。

可怜的刽子手感觉心脏里好像被冰凉的水灌满了，他表示：他的剑是为了执行法律而铸造的，他不能用谋杀去亵渎它。

这时候其中一位绅士掏出一把手枪，从远处指着刽子手说：“您选吧！如果您不执行命令的话，那您再也见不到兰道的教堂钟楼了。”

刽子手想起了家中的老婆孩子。“既然别无选择的话，”他说，“愿我剑下这无辜之人的鲜血，流到你们的脖子上。”他一刀砍下去，那个可怜的人顿时身首异处。

行刑结束之后，这些绅士给了刽子手一个钱袋，里面装着二百杜布伦。有人把他的眼睛又蒙上了，领着他坐上了同一辆马车，还是同样那几个人陪着他一起返程。

当马车最后又停下来的时候，他被允许离开马车。解开蒙眼布，他发现自己又回到了那天晚上他遇见三个男人时距离南锡一小时车程的地方。然而这一次，马车匆匆掉头回去了。

这就是兰道的刽子手所经历的故事。这位好朋友非常遗憾自己无法说出是怎样一个可怜的灵魂通过这条血腥的道路去了天堂。

是啊，没有人知道她是谁，她犯了什么罪，也没有人知道她的坟墓在哪里。

（1810年）

[56]在德国和奥地利有多处以兰道（Landau）为名的城镇，根据上下文推断，此处应为今日德国西部莱法州境内的兰道（Landau in der Pfalz）。

[57]南锡（Nanzig），今法国东部洛林省首府，历史上曾数次在法德之间易主。

假宝石

在斯特拉斯堡[58]的梅齐格门A [59]前有一座美丽的花园，任何人只要有钱就可以进去参加一些有趣而公平的娱乐活动。这其中就有一个衣冠楚楚的男人，像别人一样，端着个小啤酒杯坐在那里。他的手指上还戴着一枚戒指，戒指上镶嵌着一枚价值昂贵的宝石，闪闪发光。

这时候来了一个犹太人。他说道：“我没有恶意，先生。您戒指上的宝石真漂亮。它闪闪发光的样子，难道不像祭司亚伦[60]胸牌上的乌灵与土明[61]吗？”

这个衣冠楚楚的陌生人简短而生硬地说：“这块宝石是假的。如果它是真的，可能就已经戴在别人的手指，而不是我的手指上了。”

犹太人请求陌生人把戒指给他看看。他把戒指拿在手里，翻来覆去，左看右看。“这块宝石难道不是真的吗？”他想着。随后他向陌生人出价两枚崭新的杜布伦购买这枚戒指。

那个陌生人不情愿地说：“我骗您干吗？您已经听到了，这块宝石是假的。”

犹太人请求把宝石给一位行家鉴定一下。这时候旁边坐着的一位开口了：“我可以为这个以色列人担保，这块宝石或许真像他所说的那样值点儿钱。”

陌生人说：“我不需要什么担保，这块宝石不是真的。”

在这座花园的另一张桌子上，有一位此间的常客正和他的狐朋狗友们一起进行着有趣而公平的金钱游戏。

其中一个人是精于此道的金匠。他曾经为一位在奥斯特利茨之战[62]失去了鼻子的士兵用银子打造了一个假鼻子，涂上肌肤的颜色，这个鼻子除了不能用来呼吸以外，看上去和真的毫无二致。

犹太人向那位金匠走过去。“先生，”他说，“这块宝石究竟是不是真的呢？所罗门王[63]的王冠上能不能有一块比它更漂亮的呢？”

那位金匠，也算是半个宝石专家，说道：“它就像天空中的毕宿五[64]一样闪亮，我愿意出九十杜布伦向您收购这枚戒指。如果您能够花言巧语把它买过来的话，那您就赚到了。”

犹太人转身回到陌生人跟前说：“不管真的假的，我给您六个杜布伦。”说着，他数出几枚崭新的钱币放在桌上。

陌生人把戒指又戴回了手指上，并且说：“这玩意儿我不卖。这块假宝石的做工太逼真了，如果您把它当成真的买了，我心里会过意不去的。”说着，他把手插进了口袋里，这样贪心的以色列人就看不见那块宝石了。

“八杜布伦。”

“不行。”

“十杜布伦。”

“不行。”

“十二——十四——十五杜布伦。”

“这样的话，”陌生人终于说道，“如果您不肯让我安静一下，坚持要买的话，当着在场所有先生的面，我得跟您说好了：这块宝石是假的，我从来没有说过它是真的。我不想引起任何误会。这枚戒指现在是您的了。”

犹太人欢天喜地地把这枚戒指拿到金匠面前，说：“明天我来找您拿钱吧。”

然而这位从未被人蒙骗过的金匠，却吃惊地瞪大了双眼说道：“好伙计，这不是您两分钟以前拿给我看的那枚戒指。看在咱哥们儿的情面上，这块宝石最多就值二十枚十字币。它是圣布拉辛[65]的玻璃工厂制造的。”

原来这个陌生人早就把一枚和在他手指上闪闪发光的真戒指看上去一模一样的假戒指藏在了口袋里，当犹太人和他交易的时候，他把手插进口袋里，用拇指把真戒指从手指上撸下来，再戴上假戒指，拿出来交给了犹太人。

受骗者怒气冲天地回到了陌生人那里，喊着：“天哪，天哪！我上当了！我真倒霉！这块宝石是假的！”

然而这个陌生人却十分沉着冷静地回答道：“我卖给您的就是假的，在场的先生们都能见证。”

（1810年）

[58]斯特拉斯堡（Straßburg），今法国东部阿尔萨斯省首府，历史上曾多次在法德之间易主。

[59]梅齐格门（Metzgertor），斯特拉斯堡地标性建筑之一，位于市中心的奥斯特里茨广场。

[60]亚伦（Aaron），《圣经》中犹太人领袖摩西（Moses）的兄长。

[61]乌灵与土明（Urim und Thummim），古代犹太教祭司置于胸牌中，用于占卜神意的两件法器，通常被认为是黑白两色的两枚宝石。

[62]在1805年12月，法国军队与奥地利-俄罗斯联军在当时奥地利帝国境内的奥斯特利茨（Austerlitz，今属捷克）进行决战，史称奥斯特利茨之战（Schlacht von Austerlitz）或“三皇会战”（Dritter Koalitionskrieg），此役以法军完胜告终，第三次反法同盟也随之瓦解。

[63]所罗门王（König Salomon，公元前971——前931），以色列国王，以其财富和智慧而著称。

[64]毕宿五（Aldebaran）是位于金牛座中的双星，是天空中最闪亮的星星之一。

[65]圣布拉辛（Sankt Blasien）是德国西南部莱法州小城。

一个可怕的故事是如何被一条普通的屠夫的狗公之于众的

两个屠夫一同来到郊外的一个村庄，他们在天鹅客栈门前分手，一个向左走，一个向右走，说：“我们在天鹅客栈里再见。”然而他俩再也没能重逢。

他们中的一人随着一位农夫走进了畜栏，农夫的妻子尽管正在厨房洗碗，也跟着一同走了进去，农夫的孩子也在后面跟着。

这时候魔鬼推了一下这个女人的胳膊：“看上去这个屠夫好像在他的围裙下面藏着一大笔钱！”

女人对她的男人使了个眼色，男人也给她回了个眼色。他俩一起砸死了那个可怜的屠夫，然后迅速把他的尸体用稻草掩盖了起来。

魔鬼又推了一下女人的胳膊：“瞧，谁正在看着。”

女人环顾四周，看到了自己的孩子。

于是他们一行人惊魂未定地回到了家中，紧锁房门，如临大敌。

这个心如蛇蝎的女人说道：“孩子，看看你把自己弄成什么样了，到厨房来，我给你洗洗。”

在厨房里，她把孩子的脑袋按进滚烫的肥皂水里，活活烫死了。

现在她感觉一切终于清静了，然而她却没有想到被谋杀的屠夫的那只狗。

被谋杀的屠夫的狗，和它的同伴们在一起旅行已经有些日子了。在孩子被烫死，并被迅速扔进火炉的时候，它就已经嗅到了味道。它顺着畜栏门外主人熟悉的味道一路嗅了过来，它扒着农舍的门，意识到这里发生了一些非同寻常的事情。它猛然蹿回村庄，寻找它的同伴。很快，它拉扯着另一个屠夫的上衣，呜咽哀号着，那个屠夫也意识到了什么。所以他和狗一同回到了农舍，他立刻判断出这里曾经发生过一些可怕的事情，于是挥手招来了两个从远处路过的男人。

当那两个杀人凶手听到了狗的哀鸣声和屠夫的呼喊声，他们的眼前仿佛出现了刑场的情景，心脏也仿佛掉进了地狱。

那个男人想要从后窗跳出去逃跑，女人却拉住他的外套说：“留下来吧！”

男人说：“跟我走吧！”

女人回答：“我走不动，我的双脚好像灌了铅一样。你没看见窗前那个可怕的身影吗？它有着闪亮的眼神和炽热的呼吸。”

这时候房门被撞开了，人们很快找到了被谋杀者的尸体。这两名罪犯被双手反绑送到了法官面前。

六个星期之后，他俩被执行了车轮刑[66]。他们丑陋的尸体支离破碎地挂在车轮上，这时候乌鸦们说道：“这堆肉的味道不错！”

（1810年）

[66]车轮刑（Rädern或Radebrechen）是古代欧洲通行的一种酷刑，因使用车轮作为行刑工具而得名。具体执行方式为将犯人绑在车轮侧面用铁棒打断四肢然后任其自然死亡，或直接将犯人用车轮砸死或者碾压致死。

最轻的死刑判决

有人可能认为这是断头台，然而并不是！[75]

有个男人，尽管他为祖国做出了许多贡献，并且受到了亲王的明文表彰，但还是因为一次由激情驱使的犯罪行为，被判处了死刑。

常言道：“如果乞求得不到的，祈祷也得不到。”然而由于他曾经受过亲王的明文表彰，他还是被获准选择自己最喜欢的死法，这意味着他可以选择用任意一种方式死去。

于是高等书记官来塔楼[76]拜访他，说道：“公爵想要向您展现他的仁慈。如果您想要被执行车轮刑，那么您将被执行车轮刑。如果您想要被执行绞刑，那么您将被执行绞刑。绞刑架上已经挂着两个人了，然而众所周知还有第三个位置。如果您想要吞耗子药的话，药剂师那儿有的是。公爵说了，无论您选择哪一种死法，都悉听尊便。然而您必须死，这您应该明白。”

于是这位罪犯说道：“如果我必须去死的话，车轮刑是一种非常憋屈的死法。而绞刑呢，尤其是在有风的时候，晃来晃去太难受了。然而您可能没有正确理解这个判决。依我来说，我一直相信，由于衰老而导致的死亡是最温和的。既然公爵让我选择死法，这就是我的选择，没人能够改变。”于是他就活了下来，没有被处决。

因此，这个男人得以重获自由，并且继续活着直到老死。公爵说：“一言既出，驷马难追。”

这个小故事来自我的岳母，如果她能够救别人的生命，她绝不会袖手旁观。

（1811年）

[75]在古代欧洲有许多类似于前文中车轮刑的酷刑，斩首和绞刑被认为是死刑中最轻的刑罚。

[76]古代欧洲统治者常常将塔楼用作囚禁贵族囚犯的监狱，例如著名的伦敦塔。

被欺骗的杂货商

在俄罗斯，一卢布就是一枚银质硬币，价值相当于二十七巴岑；而一帝国币[77]则是一枚价值十卢布的金币。

人们当然可以用一帝国币换来一卢布，比方说在牌桌上输了九卢布的时候，然而却不可能用一卢布换来一帝国币。

然而在莫斯科有一个狡猾的士兵却说：“明天我要去年集上，用一卢布做诱饵，赚上两帝国币。”

第二天，年集上的货摊已经排成了一条长龙，在每个摊位前都站着人，人们或夸耀或贬损着商品，讨价还价。人群忽而聚集忽而散开，小伙子们向姑娘们打着招呼。这时候士兵手拿一卢布来到了这里。

“这枚印着皇帝头像的卢布是谁的？是您的吗？”他向每一个摊位前站着的每一位摊主询问。

其中有位摊主其实并没有丢钱，他观察了一阵，最后想：要是你觉得这钱在你手里烧得慌，还不如拿过来给我呢。他喊道：“这边来，步兵！这个卢布是我的。”

步兵说：“如果您不喊我的话，我在人群中还真不容易找到您呢。”说着就把卢布给了摊主。

这位商人拿着这枚卢布左看右看，想从声音上确定它是否是真的。直到确定是真的之后，才把它放进了口袋。

“要是没问题的话，现在请把我的帝国币还给我。”那位步兵说道。

商人回答：“我没有拿过您的帝国币，所以我也不欠您的钱。如果您只是想开个玩笑的话，您可以把您的那一枚卢布拿回去。”

然而步兵却说：“我的一枚两帝国币已经给您了，我不是在跟您开玩笑，我要去找市场保安和警察了。”

于是他俩你一言我一语地争吵了起来，从宽容说到固执，从固执说到卑鄙，在摊位前聚集的人越来越多，就好像蜂箱上聚集的一群蜜蜂一样。

突然，有个身影像鼹鼠一样穿过了人群。

“这儿发生什么事情了？”这位警官带着手下一边穿过人群，一边问道。

“发生什么了？问我吗？”这位杂货商不善言辞，偏偏步兵却是个能言善辩的家伙。

步兵声称，在一刻钟之前，他在杂货商那里买了价值一卢布的商品，然而当他付钱的时候，翻遍了所有的口袋，只找到爷爷临终之前留给他的一枚价值两帝国币的金币。所以他只好把帝国币作为押金留下，去取卢布。当他拿着一卢布回来的时候，却找不到刚才那个货摊了，他只好在所有的摊位前询问：“我欠谁一卢布？”眼前这位商人承认自己就是刚才卖货给他的那一位，并且收下了那一卢布，然而他却拒绝承认关于帝国币的事情。

警官询问摊位周围的人，他们说道：“这位步兵确实曾经向每个货摊询问过这枚卢布是属于谁的，当这位杂货商听到步兵的声音，他承认这枚卢布是属于他的。他收下了卢布，并且通过听声音辨别了真伪。”

当警长听到这里，他立刻做出了裁决：“既然您已经收下了那枚卢布，那么就把士兵的帝国币还给他，否则我就让人用长钉子把您的摊位封起来，您将在属于自己的木板之间过上与世隔绝的生活，于是您将长时间忍饥挨饿，这样您就可以健康长寿了。”

这就是警察局长所说的。于是商人就这样以一帝国币的代价从步兵手里换来了一卢布。[78]

注意：就像新雪会使旧雪融化一样。贪恋陌生人的财物，难免殃及自身。

（1811年）

[77]帝国币（Imperial），18世纪至19世纪俄罗斯发行的金质硬币。

[78]此处与上文中提到“两帝国币”似有冲突，疑为泛指，同时与本文开头呼应。

好耐性

一个法国人骑马路过一座桥梁，这座位于河流之上的桥非常狭窄，以至于两名骑马的人都无法同时通过。

一个英国人也从另一端骑马上了桥，他俩在桥的中间狭路相逢了，双方谁都不愿意给对方让路。

“一个英格兰人是不会给一个法国人让路的。”那个英格兰人说道。

“上帝啊”[79]，法国人回答，“我的马也是英格兰马[80]，所以您如果想要我掉头，给您看看它的秃尾巴的话，门儿都没有。要不还是让您骑着的这匹英格兰马给我骑着的这匹英格兰马让路吧。您这匹看起来比我这匹要年轻一些，我这匹可是在路易十四[81]时代的公元1702年就参加过卡法奥泽战役[82]的。”

英格兰人自然对这种冒犯感到些许不快，然而他说道：“我可以等。我现在有了一个绝好的机会来读读今天的报纸。我可以一直等到您愿意给我让路为止。”说着，他就像英格兰人通常那样，非常冷漠地从口袋里掏出一张报纸，像叠手绢那样把它折了起来，骑着马在桥上看了整整一小时。

然而太阳却并不愿意长时间地注视这两个笨蛋，它飞快地朝着山头落了下去。

一小时之后，英格兰人终于看完了报纸，他把报纸重新收好，盯着法国人，说道：“好了吧？”[83]

然而法国人却不肯点头，他回答道：“英格兰人，把您的报纸给我看一会儿吧，我可以看看它，直到您愿意让路为止。”

当英格兰人终于见识到了对手的耐性的时候，他说道：“你猜怎么着，法国人？过来吧，我给你让路。”

于是英格兰人给法国人让了路。

（1812年）

[79]此处原文为法语Par Dieu。

[80]原文中的“英格兰人”和“英格兰马”都是德语“Engländer”，此处法国人显然有羞辱英格兰人之意。

[81]路易十四（Louis Ⅹ　Ⅳ，1638—1715），法国国王，自称“太阳王”（le Roi Solei），在位七十二年间曾发动多次对外战争，法国的版图及国际影响力均有所扩大。

[82]在1702年期间英法两国的确为西班牙王位继承战争的交战双方，但历史文献中从未有“卡法奥泽”（Käferolse）这一地名出现，更遑论相关战役。此处显然系法国人信口开河。

[83]此处原文为法语“Eh bien”。

天气操纵者

就如同一位筛子工匠或者一位补锅工匠那样，作为手艺人，当他居住在一个小地方的时候，他的同乡们不能给他提供全年的工作以及给养，所以他就需要在周边地区四处奔走，打工赚钱。

这位五金工匠像其他手艺人那样勤奋地在周边地区奔走，只不过他兜售的不是五金小玩意儿，而是欺骗和谎言。他就靠着蛊惑人心在客栈里骗吃骗喝。

有一天他来到了上埃欣根[96]，径直去了镇长那儿。

“镇长先生，”他说道，“您难道不想换个天气吗？刚才我从您的田地上经过，土地深处已经吸收了太多雨水，这对庄稼的生长可不好。”

镇长表示，说起来倒是轻巧，要做起来可就需要本事了。

“嗯，”这位“五金工匠”回答，“在这一趟旅行中我就做到了。在意大利波隆纳改变天气的人不就是我吗？那里种着酸橙和柠檬，所有的天气都按照安排好的那样出现了。这方面你们德国人已经落后了。”

这位镇长是个正直的好人，他属于那种想快速致富，而不是缓慢积累的人。所以他接受了这位“五金工匠”的提议，然而还是希望保持一些谨慎。

“明天早上就给我来个晴天试试吧，”他说，“天空中还要有一些淡淡的白云，这样一整天一缕缕闪亮的阳光就可以从其间温和地投射下来。在中午时分您可以放飞第一只黄色的蝴蝶，在傍晚时分天气又重新变得凉爽。”

“五金工匠”回答：“我可不接只有一天的活儿，镇长先生。这对我来说不合算。我从来都只接为期一年的活儿，到那时候您就要为找不到足够的地方存放您的粮食和新酿的葡萄酒而发愁了。”

关于镇长先生提出的关于操纵一年天气所需要的费用问题，他表示：一切准备就绪至少需要三天时间，在此期间他除了每天一枚古尔登以及免费的酒水以外，别无所求。

“打那以后，您在每一桶[97]葡萄酒上都能收获更多，”他说道，“比最好的年份还要多四分之一。每一马尔脱[98]粮食都能多收一赛斯特[99]。”

“这好像不多啊。”镇长说。

在当地，人们说“多”的时候，通常是用“veil”，而不是“viel”。为了表示对“五金工匠”的尊敬，镇长特地用了标准德语。

正当他从柜子里取出纸笔，想要让“五金工匠”把未来的天气按月份写下来的时候，“五金工匠”提出了新的意见：“这可不行，镇长先生！如果这样的话，您就得听听公民们的意见。毕竟天气是一件公共事务，您不能指望所有人都赞同您对天气的安排。”

镇长说道：“您说得对！您真是个明白事理的人。”

聪明的读者可能已经识破了“五金工匠”的伎俩，正如同他之前估计的那样，公民们不可能就这个问题达成一致。第一次镇民大会没有任何结果，第七次也没有。在第八次大会上，在经过一系列严肃的演讲之后，有位聪明的律师提出的意见终于获得了镇民们的一致认可：最好把钱付给这位天气操纵者，把他送走。

于是镇长告诉天气操纵者：“这是您的九古尔登，麻烦制造者，请您务必要离开，把谋杀和凶杀从镇上带走。”

“五金工匠”并不需要第二遍催促。他拿上这笔钱，留下了大约二十大壶[100]葡萄酒的酒馆账单，天气也一如既往没有发生任何改变。

总之，这位“五金工匠”真是一位有教育意义的人物啊。

注意：迄今为止，那位至高的统治者已经按照他自己的意志将天气安排妥当。即使我们的日历制定者、日月星辰和各界贤达[101]，也不会轻易去问及这方面的问题，Thnbsp；更遑论改变岁月静好的日子了。所以如果有人提起这事儿，还是洗洗睡吧。

（1819年）

[96]上埃欣根（Obernehingen），今德国西南部巴符州境内小镇。

[97]原文的量词“Saum”是奥地利南部及瑞士德语区方言，意思是容量为130～180公升的大酒桶。

[98]马尔脱（Malter），德国古代计量单位，1马尔脱约相当于110公升。

[99]赛斯特（Sester），德国古代谷物计量单位，1赛斯特相当于15～17公升。

[100]原文的量词“Maß”在奥地利南部及瑞士德语区方言中意为装酒的大壶。

[101]此处德语原文“Landstànde”意为中世纪时期由社会各界贤达人士组成的地方仪会代表。

The Silver Spoon

An officer in Vienna was thinking, ‘Just for once I’ll dine at the Red Ox,’ and into the Red Ox he went. There were regulars there and strangers, important and unimportant people, honest men and rascals such as you’ll find any-where. They were eating and drinking, some a great deal, others little. They talked and argued about this and that, about how it had rained rocks at Stannern in Moravia, for instance, or about Machin who fought the great wolf in France. When the meal was almost over one or two were drinking a small jug of Tokay to round things off, one man was making little balls from bread crumbs as if he were an apothecary making pills, another was fiddling with his knife or his fork or his silver spoon. It was then the officer happened to notice how a fellow in a green huntsman’s coat was playing with a silver spoon when it suddenly disappeared up his sleeve and stayed there.

Someone else might have thought, ‘It’s no business of mine,’ and said nothing, or have made a great fuss. The officer thought, ‘I don’t know who this green spoon-hunter is and what I might let myself in for,’ and he kept as quiet as a mouse, until the landlord came to collect his money. But when the landlord came to collect his money the officer, too, picked up a silver spoon, and tucked it through two button holes in his coat, in one and out the other as soldiers sometimes do in war when they take their spoons with them, but no soup. As the officer was paying his bill the landlord was looking at his coat and thinking, ‘That’s a funny medal this gentleman’s wearing! He must have distinguished himself battling with a bowl of cray-fish soup to have got a silver spoon as a medal! Or could it just be one of mine?’ But when the officer had paid the landlord he said, without a sign of a smile on his face, ‘The spoon’s included, I take it? The bill seems enough to cover it.’ The landlord said, ‘Nobody’s tried that one on me before If you don’t have a spoon at home I’ll give you a tin one, but you can’t have one of my silver spoons!’ Then the officer stood up, slapped the landlord on the shoulder and laughed. ‘It was only a joke we were hav-ing,’ he said, ‘that gentleman over there in the green jacket and me! - My green friend, if you give back that spoon you have up your sleeve I’ll give mine back too.’ When the spoon-hunter saw that he had been caught in the act and that an honest eye had observed his dishonest hand, he thought, ‘Better pretend it was a joke,’ and gave back his spoon. So the landlord got his property back, and the spoon thief smiled too - but not for long. For when the other customers saw what had happened they set about him with curses and hounded him out of the Holy of Holies and the landlord sent the boots after him with a big stick. But he stood the worthy officer a bottle of Tokay to toast the health of all honest men.

Remember：You must not steal silver spoons!

Remember：Someone will always stand up for what is right.

The Cheap Meal

There is an old saying：The biter is sometimes bit. But the landlord at the Lion in a certain little town was bitten first. He received a well-dressed customer who curtly demanded a good bowl of broth, the best his money would buy. Then he ordered beef and vegetables too for his money. The landlord asked him, all politeness, if he wouldn’t like a glass of wine with it. ‘Indeed I would,’ his guest replied, ‘if I can have a good one for my money.’ When he had finished, and he enjoyed it all, he took a worn six-kreuzer piece from his pocket and said, ‘Here you are, landlord, there’s my money!’ The landlord said, ‘What’s this? You owe me a thaler!’ The customer answered, ‘I didn’t ask for a meal for a thaler, but for my money. Here it is. It’s all I have. If you gave me too much for it then that’s your fault!’ It wasn’t really such a clever trick. It called only for cheek and a devil-may-care view of the consequences. But the best is yet to come.

‘You’re an utter villain,’ said the landlord, ‘and don’t deserve this. But you can have the meal for nothing and take this twenty-four kreuzer bit as well. Just keep quiet about it and go over to my neighbour who keeps the Bear and try the same trick on him!’ He said this because he had had a quarrel with his neighbour and resented his success and each was keen to do the other down.

But the artful customer smiled as he took the money he was offered in his one hand and reached carefully for the door with the other, wished the innkeeper good after-noon, and said, ‘I went to the Bear first, it was the landlord there who sent me over here!’

So really both of the innkeepers had been tricked; the cunning customer took advantage of their quarrel. Yet he might have also earned a further reward, grateful thanks from both of them, if they had learnt the right lesson from it and had made things up between them. For peace pays, whereas quarrels have to be paid for.

Dinner Outside

We often complain how difficult or impossible it is to get on with certain people. That may of course be true. But many such people are not bad but only strange, and if you got to know them well with all their ins and outs and learnt to deal with them properly, neither too wilfully nor too indulgently, then many of them might easily be brought to their senses. After all, one servant did manage to do that with his master. Sometimes he could do noth-ing right by him and, as often happens in such situations, was blamed for many things that were not his fault. Thus one day his master came home in a very bad mood and sat down to dinner. The soup was too hot or too cold for him, or neither; no matter, he was in a bad mood! So he picked up the dish and threw it and its contents out of the open window into the yard below. So what do you think the servant did? He didn’t hesitate, he threw the meat he was bringing to table down into the yard after the soup, then the bread, the wine, and finally the table-cloth and everything on it, all down into the yard too. ‘What the devil do you think you’re doing?’ said his mas-ter angrily and rose threateningly to his feet. But the servant replied quietly and calmly, ‘Pardon me if I mis-understood your wishes. I thought you wanted to eat outside today. The air’s warm, the sky’s blue, and look how lovely the apple blossom is and how happy the bees are sipping at the flowers!’ Never again would the soup go out through the window! His master saw he was wrong, cheered up at the sight of the beautiful spring day, smiled to himself at his man’s quick thinking, and in his heart he was grateful to him for teaching him a lesson.

The Clever Judge

Not everything that happens in the East is so wrong. We are told the following event took place there. A rich man had been careless and lost a large sum of money sewn up in a cloth. He made his loss known, and in the usual way offered a reward for its return, in this case a hundred thalers. Soon a good honest man came to see him. ‘I have found your money,’ he said. ‘This must be yours.’ He had the open look of an upright fellow with a clear conscience, and that was good. The rich man looked happy too, but only at seeing his precious money again. As for his hon-esty, that we shall see! He counted the money and worked out quickly how he could cheat this man of the promised reward.‘My friend,’ he said, ‘there were in fact eight hun-dred thalers sewn up in this cloth. But I can find only seven hundred. So I take it you must have cut open a corner and taken your one hundred thalers’reward. You acted quite properly. I thank you!’ That was not good. But we haven’t got to the end yet. Honesty is the best policy, and wrongdoing never proves right. The honest man who had found the money and who was less con-cerned for his reward than for his blameless name protested that he had found the packet just as he handed it over, and had handed over exactly what he had found. In the end they appeared in court. Both of them stuck to their stories, one that eight hundred thalers were sewn up in the cloth, the other that he had left the packet just as he found it and had taken nothing from it. It was hard to know what to do. But the clever judge, who seemed from the outset to recognize the honesty of the one and the bad faith of the other, approached the problem as follows. He had both swear their statements on solemn oath, and then passed the following judgement：‘Since one of you lost eight hundred thalers and the other found a packet containing only seven hundred, the package found by that second party cannot be the one to which the first party has just claim. You, my honest friend, take back the money you found and put it into safe keeping until the person who lost only seven hundred thalers makes himself known. And you I can only advise to be patient until someone says he has found your eight hun-dred thalers.’ That was his judgement, and that was final.

The Artful Hussar

A hussar in the last war knew that the farmer he met on the road had just sold his hay for a hundred guilders and was on his way home with the money. So he asked him for something to buy tobacco and brandy. Who knows, he might have been happy with a few coppers. But the farmer swore black and blue he had spent his last kreuzer in the nearby village and had nothing left. ‘If we weren’t so far from my quarters,’ said the hussar, ‘we could both be helped out of this difficulty; but you have nothing, and neither have I; so we’ll just have to go to Saint Alphonsus! We’ll share what he gives us like brothers.’ This Saint Alphonsus stood carved from stone in an old, little frequented chapel in the fields. At first the farmer was not too keen to make the pilgrimage. But the hussar allowed no objection, and on the way he was so vigorous in his assurances that Saint Alphonsus had never let him down when in need that the farmer began to cherish hopes himself. So you think the hussar’s comrade and accomplice was hiding in the deserted chapel, do you? Not a bit of it! No one was there, only the stone figure of Alphonsus, and they knelt before him, and the hussar appeared to be praying fervently.‘This is it!’ he whispered to the farmer, ‘the saint has just beckoned to me.’ He got to his feet and went to put his ear to the lips of stone and came back delighted. ‘He’s given me a guilder, he says it’s in my purse!’ And indeed to the other’s amazement the hussar took out a guilder, but one that he had had there all the time, and shared it like a brother as promised. That made sense to the farmer and he agreed that the hussar should try again. All went just as before. This time the hussar was even happier when he came back to the farmer. ‘Now Saint Alphonsus has given us a hundred guilders all in one go! They’re in your purse.’ The farmer turned deadly white when he heard this and repeated his protests that he had no money at all. But the hussar persuaded him he must trust Saint Alphonsus and just take a look; Alphonsus had never deceived him! So whether he liked it or not he had to turn his pockets inside out and empty them. Then the hundred guilders appeared all right, and since he had taken half of the hussar’s guilder it was no use pleading and imploring, he had to share his hundred.

That was all very artful and cunning, but that doesn’t make it right, especially in a chapel.

The Dentist

Two loafers who had been roaming around the country together for some time because they were too lazy to work or had learnt no trade finally got into a tight corner because they had no money left, and they saw no quick way of getting any. Then they had this idea：they went begging at doors for bread which they intended to use, not to fill their stomachs, but to stage a trick. For they kneaded and rolled it into little balls and coated them with the dust from old, rotten worm-eaten wood so that they looked just like yellow pills from the chemist. Then for a couple of pence they bought some sheets of red paper at the bookbinder’s （for a pretty colour often helps take people in）. Next they cut up the paper and wrapped the pills in it, six or eight to a little packet. Then one of them went on ahead to a village where there was a fair and into the Red Lion where he hoped to find a good crowd. He ordered a glass of wine, but he didn’t drink it but sat sadly in a corner holding his face in his hand, moaning under his breath and fidgeting and turning this way and that. The good farmers and townsfolk in the inn thought the poor fellow must have terrible toothache. Yet what could they do? They pitied him, they consoled him, saying it would soon go away, then went back to their drinks and their market-day affairs. Meanwhile the other idler came in. The two scoundrels pretended they had never seen each other in their lives before. They didn’t look at each other until the one seemed to react to the other’s moans in the corner.‘My friend,’ he said, ‘have you got toothache?’ and he strode slowly over to him.‘I am Dr Schnauzius Rapunzius from Trafalgar,’ he con-tinued. Such resounding foreign names help take people in too, you know, like pretty colours. ‘If you take my tooth pills,’ he went on, ‘I can easily get rid of the pain, one of them will do the trick, at most two.’ ‘Please God you’re right!’ said the other rogue. So now the fine doctor Rapunzius took one of the red packets from his pocket and prescribed one pill, to be placed on the tongue and bitten on firmly. The customers at the other tables now craned their necks and one by one they came over to observe the miracle cure. You can imagine what hap-pened! But no, the first bite seemed to do the patient no good at all, he gave a terrible scream. The doctor was pleased! They had, he said, got the better of the pain, and quickly he gave him the second pill to be taken likewise. Now suddenly the pain had all gone. The patient jumped for joy, wiped the sweat from his brow, though there was none there, and pretended to show his thanks by pressing more than a trifling sum into his saviour’s hand. The trick was artfully done and had its desired effect. For all those present now wanted some of these excellent pills too. The doctor offered them at twenty-four kreuzers a packet, and they were all sold in a few minutes. Of course the two scoundrels now left separately one after the other, met up to laugh at the people’s stupidity, and had a good time on their money.

The fools had paid dear for a few crumbs of bread！ Even in times of famine you never got so little for twenty-four kreuzers. But the waste of money was not the worst part of it. For in time the pellets of breadcrumbs naturally became as hard as stone. So when a year later a poor dupe had toothache and confidently bit on a pill with the offending tooth, once and then again, just imagine the awful pain that he had got himself for twenty-four kreuzers instead of a cure!

From this we can learn how easy it is to be tricked if you believe what is told you by any vagrant whom you meet for the first time in your life, have never seen before and will never see again. Some of you who read this will perhaps be thinking：‘I was once silly like that too and brought suffering on myself!’

Remember：Those who can, earn their money elsewhere and don’t go around villages and fairs with holes in their stockings, or a white buckle on one shoe and a yellow one on the other.

Strange Reckoning at the Inn

Sometimes a cheeky trick comes off, sometimes it costs you your coat, often your skin as well. But in this case it was only coats. One day, you see, three merry students on their travels didn’t have a brass farthing left between them, they had spent everything on a good time, but nevertheless they went into another inn intending to leave without sneaking out by the back door, and it suited them fine that they found only the landlord’s nice young wife inside. They ate and drank merrily and talked very learnedly about the world being many thousands of years old and how it would last as long again, and how each year, to the day and the hour, everything that happened came to pass as it had done on that day and at that hour six thousand years before. Eventually one of them turned to the landlady, who was sitting on one side by the win-dow knitting and listening attentively, and said, ‘That’s how it is, ma’am, we’ve had to learn that from our learned tomes.’And one had the impudence to assert that he just about remembered their being there six thousand years ago, and he remembered the landlady’s pretty friendly face very well indeed. They carried on talking for some time, and the more the landlady seemed to believe every-thing they said the more the young gadabouts tucked into the wine and the meat and a fistful of pretzels, and in the end their bill stood chalked up at five guilders and sixteen kreuzers. They had eaten and drunk their fill, and now they came out with the trick they had planned.

‘Ma’am,’ said one, ‘this time we are short of money, for there are so many inns on the road. But since we know you’re a clever woman we hope that as old friends we can have credit here, and if you agree, in six thousand years’time when we come again we’ll pay our old bill together with the new one.’ The sensible landlady was not upset by that, it was fine by her, she was delighted that the young gentlemen were well served. But before they had noticed her move she was standing in front of the door and was asking the gentlemen kindly just to settle now the bill of five guilders and sixteen kreuzers that they owed from six thousand years ago, since, as they said, everything that happened now was an exact repetition of what had taken place before. Unfortunately just at that moment the village mayor came in with a couple of sturdy men to enjoy a glass of wine together. That didn’t suit our gay young dogs at all! For now the official verdict was pronounced and carried out：you had to give it to some-one who had allowed credit for six thousand years! The gentlemen were therefore to pay their old debt immedi-ately or leave their newish overcoats as a pledge. They were obliged to take the second option, and the landlady promised to return their coats in six thousand years’time when they came again with a bit more money.

This took place in 1805 on the 17th of April in the inn at Segringen.

Unexpected Reunion

At Falun in Sweden, a good fifty years ago, a young miner kissed his pretty young bride-to-be and said, ‘On the feast of Saint Lucia the parson will bless our love and we shall be man and wife and start a home of our own.’ ‘And may peace and love dwell there with us,’ said his lovely bride, and smiled sweetly, ‘for you are everything to me, and without you I’d sooner be in the grave than anywhere else.’ When however, before the feast of Saint Lucia, the parson had called out their names in church for the second time：‘If any of you know cause, or just hindrance, why these two persons should not be joined together in holy Matrimony’ - Death paid a call. For the next day when the young man passed her house in his black miner’s suit（a miner is always dressed ready for his own funeral）, he tapped at the window as usual and wished her good morning all right, but he did not wish her good evening. He did not return from the mine, and in vain that same morning she sewed a red border on a black neckerchief for him to wear on their wedding day, and when he did not come back she put it away, and she wept for him, and never forgot him.

In the meantime the city of Lisbon in Portugal was destroyed by an earthquake, the Seven Years War came and went, the Emperor Francis I died, the Jesuits were dissolved, Poland was partitioned, the Empress MariaTheresa died, and Struensee was executed, and America became independent, and the combined French and Spanish force failed to take Gibraltar. The Turks cooped up General Stein in the Veterane Cave in Hungary, and the Emperor Joseph died too. King Gustavus of Sweden conquered Russian Finland, the French Revolution came and the long war began, and the Emperor Leopold II too was buried. Napoleon defeated Prussia, the English bom-barded Copenhagen, and the farmers sowed and reaped. The millers ground the corn, the blacksmiths wielded their hammers, and the miners dug for seams of metal in their workplace under the ground.

But in 1809, within a day or two of the feast of Saint John, when the miners at Falun were trying to open up a passage between two shafts, they dug out from the rubble and the vitriol water, a good three hundred yards below ground, the body of a young man soaked in ferrous vitriol but otherwise untouched by decay and unchanged, so that all his features and his age were still clearly recog-nizable, as if he had died only an hour before or had just nodded off at work. Yet when they brought him to the surface his father and mother and friends and acquaint-ances were all long since dead, and no one claimed to know the sleeping youth or to remember his misadven-ture, until the woman came who had once been promised to the miner who one day had gone below and had not returned. Grey and bent, she hobbled up on a crutch to where he lay and recognized her bridegroom; and, more in joyous rapture than in grief, she sank down over the beloved corpse, and it was some time before she had recovered from her fervent emotion.‘It is my betrothed,’ she said at last, ‘whom I have mourned these past fifty years, and now God grants that I see him once more before I die. A week before our wedding he went under ground and never came up again.’The hearts of all those there were moved to sadness and tears when they saw the former bride-to-be as an old woman whose beauty and strength had left her, and the groom still in the flower of his youth; and how the flame of young love was rekindled in her breast after fifty years, yet he did not open his mouth to smile, nor his eyes to recognize her; and how finally she, as the sole relative and the only person who had claim to him, had the miners carry him into her house until his grave was made ready for him in the churchyard.

The next day when the grave lay ready in the church-yard and the miners came to fetch him she opened a casket and put the black silk neckerchief with the red stripes on him, and then she went with him in her best Sunday dress, as if it were her wedding day, not the day of his burial. You see, as they lowered him into his grave in the churchyard she said, ‘Sleep well for another day or a week or so longer in your cold wedding bed, and don’t let time weigh heavy on you! I have only a few things left to do, and I shall join you soon, and soon the day will dawn.

‘What the earth has given back once it will not withhold again at the final call’, she said as she went away and looked back over her shoulder once more.

The Sly Pilgrim

A few years ago an idler roamed around the countryside pretending to be a pious pilgrim, saying he came from Paderborn and was making for the Holy Sepulchre in Jerusalem, and already at the Coach and Horses in Mül-heim he was asking, ‘How far is it to Jerusalem now?’They told him, ‘Seven hundred hours. But you’ll save a quarter of an hour if you take the path to Mauchen.’So he went by way of Mauchen to save himself a quarter of an hour on his long journey. That wasn’t such a bad idea. You must not scorn a small gain or a bigger one won’t come your way. You more often get a chance to save or make threepence than a florin. But eight threepennies make a florin, and if on a journey of seven hundred hours you can save a quarter of an hour every five hours, over the whole journey you will save - now, who can work that out? How many hours? But that wasn’t how our supposed pilgrim saw it! Since he was only after an easy life and a good meal he didn’t care which way he went. As the old saying goes, a beggar can never take the wrong turning, it’s a poor village indeed where he can’t collect more than the cost of the shoe leather he has worn out on the road, especially if he goes barefoot. Yet our pilgrim intended to get back as soon as he could to the main road where he’d find rich people’s houses and good cooking. For this rascal wasn’t content, as a true pilgrim should be, with common food given in compassion by a pious hand, he wanted nothing but nourishing pebble soup! You see, whenever he saw a nice inn by the road, for instance the Post House at Krozingen or the Basel Arms at Schliengen, he would go in and very humbly and hungrily ask for a nice soup made of pebbles and water, in God’s name, he had no money. And when the innkeeper’s wife took pity on him and said, ‘Pious pilgrim, pebbles are not easy to digest!’, he said, ‘That’s just it! Pebbles last longer than bread and it’s a long way to Jerusalem. But if you were to give me a little glass of wine too, in God’s name, it would help me digest them.’Now if she said, ‘But good pilgrim, a soup like that won’t give you any strength at all!’ then he replied, ‘Well, if you use broth instead of water then of course it would be more nourishing.’And when she brought him his broth and said, ‘The bits at the bottom are still a bit hard, I’m afraid,’ then he’d say, ‘You’re right, and the broth looks a little thin. Would you have a couple of spoonfuls of vegetables to add to it, or a scrap of meat, or maybe both?’If now the innkeeper’s wife still felt sorry for him and put some meat and vegeta-bles in the bowl, he said, ‘God bless you! Now just hand me a piece of bread and I’ll tuck into your soup!’ Then he would push back the sleeves of his pilgrim’s habit, sit down and set to work with relish, and when he had eaten the last crumb of bread, drained the wine, and finished the last morsel of meat and vegetables and the last drop of broth, he would wipe his mouth on the tablecloth or his sleeve, or perhaps he wouldn’t bother, and he’d say, ‘Missus, your soup has strengthened me as a good soup should, what a shame I can’t find room for the nice peb-bles now! But put them by, and when I come back I’ll bring you a holy conch from the seashore at Ascalon or a Jericho rose.’

The Commandant and the Light Infantry in Hersfeld

In the last campaign in Prussia and Russia when the French Army and a large part of the allied troops were in Poland and Prussia, a contingent of the Baden Light Infantry was in Hessen and stationed at Hersfeld. For the Emperor had taken that state at the beginning of the campaign and stationed troops there. The inhabitants who preferred the way things had been before defied the new order and there were several acts of lawlessness, par-ticularly in the town of Hersfeld. In one incident a French officer was killed. The French Emperor was engaged face to face with great numbers of the enemy and couldn’t allow hostilities behind his back or let a spark spread into a great fire. The unfortunate people of Hersfeld thus had cause to regret their rashness. For the Emperor ordered the town to be looted, set alight at each corner and burnt to the ground.

This town of Hersfeld has many factories and thus many rich inhabitants and fine buildings; and all of us with a heart can understand how its unfortunate people, those fathers and mothers with families, felt when they heard the dreadful news. The poor whose possessions could be carried off in one pair of arms were just as much affected as the rich whose goods couldn’t all be loaded on a train of wagons. Great houses on the town square and small dwellings in the alleyways are all the same when burnt to the ground, just like rich and poor in the graveyard.

But the worst didn’t happen. The French Commandant in Kassel and Hersfeld interceded and the punishment was reduced. Only four houses were to be burnt down, and that was lenient. But the plundering was to take place as ordered, and that was hard enough. The wretched townsfolk, hearing this latest decision, were so cowed and robbed of all presence of mind that the benevolent Com-mandant himself had to urge them, instead of weeping and pleading in vain, to remove their most precious pos-sessions in the short time that was left. The dreadful hour arrived, the drums sounded over the wails of anguish. The soldiers hurried to their place of assembly through the crowds fleeing in despair. Then the stalwart Com-mandant of Hersfeld stood before the ranks of the infantry, and first he painted a vivid picture of the sad fate of the townspeople, then he said, ‘Men, you now have permission to loot! Those who wish to take part, fall out!’ Not one man moved. Not a single one! The order was repeated. Not one pair of boots stirred, and if the Com-mandant had intended the town to be plundered he would have had to do it himself. But no one was more pleased than he was that things turned out as they did, that is easy to tell. When the townsfolk learnt this, it was as if they woke from a bad dream. No one can describe their joy. They sent a delegation to the Commandant to thank him for his kindness and magnanimity, and offered him a handsome gift to mark their gratitude. Who knows what they might not have done! But the Commandant refused and said he wouldn’t be paid for a good deed.

This happened in Hersfeld in the year 1807, and the town is still standing.

A Poor Reward

When in the last Prussian war the French came to Berlin where the King of Prussia resides, a great deal of the royal property as well as other people’s was taken and carried off or sold. For war brings nothing, it only takes. Much was claimed as booty, however well it was hidden they found it, but not everything. A large store of royal building timber remained undiscovered and untouched for some time. But eventually a rascal among the king’s own sub-jects thought, there’s a fair penny to be made here, and with a smirk and a wink he went to tell the French com-mandant what a lovely stack of oak and pine logs was still at such and such a place, and it was worth a few thousand guilders. But the French commandant paid him badly for this betrayal and said, ‘Just you leave those fine logs where they are! There’s no call to deprive the enemy of his most basic needs. For when your king returns he will need tim-ber for new gallows for trusty subjects like you!’

Your Family Friend can only applaud that, and he would make a present of a few logs from his own coppice if they were needed.

A Curious Ghost Story

Last autumn a gentleman was travelling through Schlien-gen, a nice little place. And as he was walking up the hill to spare the horses he told a man from Grenzach the following story of what had happened to him.

Six months earlier this gentleman was on his way to Denmark, and late one evening he arrived in a village with a fine mansion on a hill outside, and he wanted to stay the night. But the innkeeper said he had no room, there was a hanging the next day and three hangmen were staying with him. So the gentleman replied, ‘Then I’ll ask up there in the big house. The owner, the governor or whoever he is, will take me in and find a spare bed for me.’ The innkeeper said, ‘There are plenty of fine beds with silk hangings up there all ready made up, and I’m in charge of the keys. But I wouldn’t advise you to go there! Three months ago the lord and the lady and the young master went away on a long journey, and since then the mansion house has been haunted by ghosts. The steward and the servants had to leave, and all the others who have been to the house never went back a second time.’ Our stranger smiled. For he was a plucky man who wasn’t afraid of ghosts, and he said, ‘I’ll risk it!’ Despite all the innkeeper’s objections he had to hand over the key, and after the traveller had put together what was needed to pay a visit on ghosts he went to the mansion with his servant who was travelling with him.

Once inside he didn’t undress or get ready for bed, but waited to see what happened. He put two lights to burn on the table and a pair of loaded pistols next to them, and to pass away the time he picked up the Rhinelanders’Family Friend, bound in gold paper, which was hanging by a red silk ribbon under the mirror in its frame on the wall, and looked at the nice pictures. For a long time nothing happened. But when midnight stirred in the church tower and the clock struck twelve, and a rainstorm was passing over the house and large drops were beating against the window, there were three loud knocks on the door and a ghastly apparition with black squinting eyes, a nose half a yard long, gnashing teeth, a beard like a goat and hair all over its body came into the room and said in a horrible growl：‘I am the lord Mephistopheles. Welcome to my palace! Have you said your goodbyes to your wife and children?’The visitor felt a cold shiver run up from his big toes over his back and up under his night-cap, and his poor servant was in a worse state still. But when this Mephistopheles came towards him, scowling dreadfully and stepping high as if he was crossing a floor of flames, the unfortunate gentleman thought：in God’s name, this is the test! And he stood up boldly and pointed his pistol at the monster and said, ‘Halt, or I’ll shoot!’ Not every ghost can be stopped like that, for even if you pull the trigger it doesn’t go off, or the bullet flies back and hits you instead of the target. But Mephistopheles raised his first finger in warning, turned slowly on his heels and strode away just as he had come. Now when our traveller saw that this devil had respect for gunpowder, he thought, ‘There’s no danger now!’, picked up a light in his free hand and followed the ghost cautiously along the passage; and his servant who was standing behind him ran for all he was worth out of this blessed place and down to the village, thinking he’d sooner spend the night with the hangmen than with spooks.

But suddenly in the passage the ghost disappeared from under the eyes of its plucky pursuer just as if it had gone through the floor. And when the gentleman went on another few paces to see where it had gone, all at once there was no floor under his feet and he fell down through a hole towards a flaming fire, and he himself thought he was on the way to hell. But after dropping about ten feet he found himself lying unharmed on a heap of hay in a cellar. And six weird fellows were standing around the fire, that Mephistopheles with them. All sorts of strange implements were piled up around them, and two tables stood heaped with shining thalers, each one more lovely than the other.

Now the stranger knew what was going on. For this was a secret band of forgers, all with blood running in their veins. They had taken advantage of the owner’s absence and set up their mint in his mansion, and some of them were probably servants of the house who knew their way about; and to make sure they were not disturbed and discovered they wailed like ghosts, and anyone who came to the house was so frightened he never came back to take a second look. Yet the plucky traveller now had cause to regret his lack of prudence in not listening to the innkeeper’s warnings. For he was pushed through a nar-row opening into a small dark room and could hear them deciding his fate：‘The best thing is to kill him!’ said one. But another said, ‘First we must question him, find out who he is and where he’s from.’When they then learnt he was a man of consequence and on his way to Copen-hagen to see the king they looked at each other wide-eyed. And when he was back in the dark storeroom they said, ‘This is a bad business. For if he’s missed and they find out from the innkeeper that he came here and didn’t leave, the hussars will come overnight and fetch us out, and there’s plenty of hemp in the fields this year, so hang-men’s nooses come cheap.’So they told their prisoner they would let him go if he swore an oath not to betray them, threatening they would have him watched in Copenhagen. And he had to tell them on oath where he lived. He told them, ‘Next to the Green Man, on the left in the big house with green shutters.’Then they poured him some Burgundy wine and he watched them coining their thalers until it was light.

When the morning light shone down through the grat-ings, and they heard the sound of whips on the road and the cowherd blowing his horn, the traveller took leave of his night-time companions, thanked them for having him and went gaily back to the inn, quite forgetting that he had left his watch and pipe and the pistols behind in the mansion. The innkeeper said, ‘Thank God you’re back, I didn’t get a wink of sleep! How did you get on?’ But the traveller thought, an oath is an oath, and you mustn’t take God’s name in vain to save your life. So he said nothing, and as the bell was ringing and the wretched malefactor was being led out everyone ran off to watch. He said nothing in Copenhagen either, and almost forgot the incident himself.

A few weeks later, however, he received a parcel by the post, and in it were a pair of expensive new pistols inlaid with silver, a new gold watch set with diamonds, a Turkish pipe with a gold chain and a silk tobacco-pouch embroi-dered with gold, and in the pouch was a note. It said, ‘We are sending you this to make up for the fright we gave you and to thank you for keeping quiet. It’s all over now, and you can tell anyone you like.’So the traveller told the man from Grenzach, and it was that same gold watch that he took out at the top of the hill to check that the clock at Hertingen was striking noon on time, and later on in the Stork in Basel a French general offered him seventy-five new doubloons for it. But he wouldn’t part with it.

One Word Leads to Another

A rich man in Swabia sent his son to Paris to learn French and a few manners. After a year or more his father’s farm-hand came to see him. The son was greatly surprised and cried out joyfully, ‘Hans, whatever are you doing here? How are things at home, what’s the news?’

‘Nothing much, Mr William, though your fine raven copped it two weeks ago, the one the gamekeeper gave you.’

‘Oh, the poor bird,’ replied Mr William. ‘What hap-pened to it?’

‘Well, you see, he ate too much carrion when our fine horses died one after the other. I said he would.’

‘What! My father’s four fine greys are dead?’Mr William asked.‘How did that happen?’

‘Well, you see, they were worked too hard hauling water when the house and the barns burned down, and it did no good.’

‘Oh no!’ exclaimed Mr William, horrified.‘Our house burnt down? When was that?’

‘Well, you see, nobody thought of a fire when your father lay in his coffin. He was buried at night with torches. A small spark soon spreads.’

‘That’s terrible news!’ exclaimed Mr William in his dis-tress.‘My father dead? And how is my sister?’

‘Well, you see, your late father died of grief when the young Miss had a child and no father for it. It’s a boy.

‘There’s nothing much else to tell,’ he added.

A Bad Bargain

In the great city of London and round about it there are an extraordinary number of silly fools who take a childish delight in other people’s money or fob watches or pre-cious rings and don’t rest until they have them for themselves. Sometimes they get them by cunning and trickery, but more often by fearless assault, sometimes in broad daylight on the open road. Some of them do well, others don’t. The London jailors and executioners can tell a few tales about that! One day, however, a strange thing happened to a certain rich and distinguished man. The King and many other great lords and their ladies were gathered on a lovely summer’s day in a royal park where the winding paths led to a wood in the distance. Crowds of other people were there too, they didn’t think their journey or their time wasted if they could see that their beloved King and his family were happy and well. There was food and drink, music and dancing. There were walks to be taken in pairs or alone along the inviting paths and between scented rose bushes. A man, well-dressed so that he appeared to be one of the company, took up his stand with a pistol under his coat by a tree at a secluded spot where the park bordered on the wood, waiting for some-one to come his way. And someone did come, a gentleman with a ring sparkling on his finger, a tinkling watch chain, diamonds in his buckles, and a ribbon and a star on his breast. He was strolling in the cool shade and thinking of nothing in particular. And while he was thinking of nothing in particular the fellow behind the tree stepped out, bowed low, pulled his pistol from under his coat, pointed it at the gentleman’s breast and asked him politely to keep quiet, no one need know about their conversa-tion! You can’t help feeling uneasy when a pistol is aimed at you, you can never be sure what’s in it! The gentleman very sensibly thought：better your money than your life, better lose a ring than a finger! and he promised to keep quiet.

‘Now, Your Honour,’ said this fellow, ‘would you part with your two gold watches for a good price? Our school-master adjusts the clock every day, so we can never be sure of the right time, and you can’t see the figures on the sundial.’ The gentleman had no choice, he was obliged to sell his watches to the scoundrel for a few pence, hardly the price of a glass of wine. In this way the rascal bought his ring and his buckles and the decorations off his breast, one after another and each for a paltry sum, with the pis-tol in his left hand all the time. When at last the gentleman thought, now he’ll let me go, thank God!, the rogue began again.

‘Your Honour, since we do business so easily, why don’t you buy some of my things from me?’ The gentleman thought, I must grin and bear it, that’s the expression, and said, ‘Show me what you have!’ The fellow took a collection of trinkets from his pocket, things he had bought at a tuppenny stall or filched from somewhere, and the gentleman had to buy them all from him, one after the other, none of them cheap. Eventually the rogue had nothing left but the pistol, but seeing that the gentle-man still had a couple of lovely doubloons in his green silk purse he said, ‘Sir, won’t you buy this pistol of mine with what’s left in your purse? It’s made by the best gun-maker in London and it’s worth two doubloons of anyone’s money!’ The gentleman was surprised. ‘This robber’s an idiot!’ he thought, and bought the pistol. When he had bought it from the robber he turned the tables on him and said：‘Hands up, my fine friend, and do as I tell you, keep walking in front of me or I’ll blow your brains out!’ But the rogue darted off into the wood. ‘Go ahead and shoot, Your Excellency,’ he said, ‘it’s not loaded!’ The gentleman pulled the trigger, and in fact it didn’t go off. He pushed the ramrod into the barrel, there was no trace of powder. By now the thief was well away into the wood; and the distinguished Englishman walked back, red in the face at being frightened by an empty threat, and he had something to think about now.

A Secret Beheading

Whether or not on that morning of 17 June that year the executioner at Landau said the Lord’s Prayer with proper devotion and its‘Lead us not into temptation but deliver us from evil’ - that I don’t know. But a delivery came, a note posted from Nancy, and if he hadn’t said his prayers, then it arrived on just the right day. The note said：‘Exe-cutioner at Landau, come to Nancy straight away and bring your big sword. You will be told what to do and paid well.’A coach was waiting outside. ‘It’s my job’, thought the executioner and got into the coach. When he was still one hour this side of Nancy, it was evening already and the sun was setting among blood-red clouds, the driver drew up, saying, ‘It will be fine again tomor-row’, when suddenly three strong armed men were standing by the road, climbed in beside the executioner and promised that he wouldn’t come to any harm, ‘But you must let us blindfold you!’ And when they had put the blindfold over his eyes they said, ‘Driver, drive on!’ The coachman drove on, and it seemed to the executioner that he was taken a good twelve hours further, and he had no way of telling where he was. He heard the mid-night owls; he heard the cocks crow; he heard the morning bells. Then without warning the coach stopped again. They took him into a house and gave him something to drink and a nice roll and sausage too. When he was strengthened by food and drink they led him on inside the same building, through several doors and up stairs and down, and then they removed his blindfold and he saw he was in a large room. It was hung all around with black drapes, and wax candles burnt on the tables. In the middle sat a woman on a chair with her neck bared and a mask over her face, and she must have been gagged, for she couldn’t speak, only sob. Round the walls stood a number of gentlemen dressed in black and with black crape over their faces so that the executioner could not have recognized them if he had met them again an hour later. And one of them handed him his sword and ordered him to cut off the head of the woman sitting on the chair. The poor executioner’s blood ran cold and he said they must excuse him：his sword was dedicated to the service of justice and he could not defile it with murder. But one of the gentlemen by the wall pointed a pistol at him and said, ‘Get on with it! Do as we tell you or you’ll never set eyes on the church tower at Landau again!’ The execu-tioner thought of his wife and children at home.‘If I’ve no choice,’ he said, ‘and I must shed innocent blood, then on your head be it!’ and with one blow he severed the poor woman’s head from her body.

When it was done one of the men gave him a purse with two hundred doubloons. They put the blindfold over his eyes again and took him back to the coach he had come in. The men who had brought him there escorted him again. And when at last the coach drew up and they let him get out and remove the blindfold he was left standing where the three men had joined the coach, one hour this side of Nancy on the Landau road, and it was night. The coach sped off back.

That is what happened to the executioner at Landau, and Your Family Friend is not sorry that he can’t say who that poor soul was who had to take such a bloody way to life everlasting. No, nobody found out who she was, what sin she had committed, and nobody knows where she is buried.

The Fake Gem

Outside the Butcher’s Gate at Strassburg there is a pleas-ant garden where anyone can go and spend his money on decent pleasure, and there sat a well-dressed man drinking his wine like everyone else, and he had a ring with a precious stone on his finger and held it so it spar-kled. So a Jew came up and said, ‘Sir, you have a lovely gem in that ring on your finger, I wouldn’t mind that myself! Doesn’t it glitter like the Urim andThummim in the breastplate of Aaron the priest?’ The well-dressed stranger answered very curtly, ‘The gem is a fake. If it weren’t, it would be on someone else’s finger, not mine!’ The Jew asked to take a closer look at it. He turned it this way and that in his hand and bent his head to look at it from every angle. ‘He says this stone is a fake?’ he thought, and offered the stranger two new doubloons for the ring. But the stranger said quite angrily, ‘Why do you think I’m lying? I told you, it’s a fake!’ The Jew asked permission to show it to an expert, and someone sitting close by said, ‘I’ll vouch for the Israelite, he’ll know what the jewel is worth!’ The stranger said, ‘I don’t need to consult anyone, the stone’s a fake.’

While this was happening Your Family Friend was sit-ting at another table in the same garden with good friends of his, happily spending money on decent pleasure, and one of the company was a goldsmith who knows all about gems. He fitted a soldier who lost his nose at the battle of Austerlitz with a silver one and painted it skin colour, and it was a good nose. The only thing he couldn’t do was breathe the breath of life into it. The Jew came over to this goldsmith. ‘Sir,’ he said, ‘would you say this is a fake stone? Can King Solomon have worn anything more splendid in his crown?’ The goldsmith, who was also something of a stargazer, said, ‘It shines like Aldebaran in the sky all right. I’ll get you ninety doubloons for this ring. If you come by it cheaper the profit is yours.’

The Jew went back to the stranger. ‘Fake or not, I’ll give you six doubloons!’ and he counted them out on the table, sparkling new from the mint. The stranger put the ring back on his finger and said, ‘I have no intention of parting with it. If it’s such a good fake that you think it’s real that doesn’t make it worth any less to me,’ and he put his hand in his pocket so that the eager Israelite could no longer see the stone. ‘Eight doubloons.’ ‘No.’ ‘Ten doubloons.’ ‘No.’ ‘Twelve - fourteen - fifteen doubloons.’ ‘Very well,’ said the stranger at last, ‘if you won’t leave me in peace and insist on being deceived at all costs! But I tell you, in front of all these gentlemen here, the stone is a fake, and I’ll not say it isn’t. For I don’t want any trouble. You can have the ring, it’s yours.’

Now the Jew took the ring joyfully over to the gold-smith.‘I’ll come for the money tomorrow.’But the goldsmith, who had never been taken in by anyone, opened his eyes wide in amazement.‘My friend, this isn’t the ring you showed me two minutes ago! This stone is worth twenty kreuzers at most. This is the sort they make in the glass works at Sankt Blasien!’ For actually the stranger had in his pocket a fake ring which looked as good as the one that had first sparkled on his finger, and while the Jew was bargaining with him and his hand was in his pocket, he pushed the genuine ring off his finger with his thumb and slipped his finger into the fake, and that was the one he had given the Jew. At once the dupe shot back to the stranger as if fired on a rocket：‘Oh, woe, woe unto me! I have been tricked, the stone is a fake!’ But the stranger said coldly and calmly, ‘I sold it to you for a fake. These gentlemen here are witnesses. It’s yours now. Did I talk you into buying it or did you talk me into selling it?’ All those present had to admit, ‘Yes, he told you the stone was a fake when he said you could have it!’ So the Jew had to keep the ring and no further fuss was made of the matter.

How a Ghastly Story was Brought to Light by a Common or Garden Butcher’s Dog

Two butchers out in their district buying in animals came to a village and split up, one went left past the Swan, the other right, and they said, ‘We’ll meet up again in the Swan.’But they never did meet up again. For one of them went with a farmer into his cowshed. The farmer’s wife went as well, though she was doing the washing in the kitchen, and their child decided to follow too. The devil gave the woman a nudge：‘Look at that belt full of money peeping out from under the butcher’s shirt!’ The woman gave her husband a wink, he gave her a nod, and they killed the poor butcher in the cowshed and hurriedly hid his body under some straw. The devil nudged the woman again：‘Look who’s watching!’ She looked round and saw the child. So, driven out of their minds by fear, they went back together into the house and locked the doors as if the enemy were near. Then the woman, whose heart was not just as black as sin but blacker and hotter than hell, said, ‘Child, just look at you again! Come into the kit-chen,’ she said, ‘I’ll clean you up.’In the kitchen she pushed her child’s head into the hot suds and scalded him to death. Now, she thought, there’s no one to tell on us - but she didn’t think of the murdered butcher’s dog.

The murdered butcher’s dog had run along a bit with the other butcher, and then, while the child was being boiled and then popped into the bread oven, the dog doubled back and picked up his master’s scent, sniffed at the cowshed door, scratched at the door to the house, and knew that something was wrong. Off he ran at once, back into the village, looking for the other butcher. Soon he was whinging and whining and pulling at this butcher’s coat, and the butcher, too, knew something was wrong. So he went with the dog back to the house, in no doubt that something dreadful had happened there. He beckoned over two men who were passing nearby. When the mur-derers heard the dog whining and the butcher shouting, they had nothing but the gallows before their eyes and the fear of hellfire in their hearts. The man tried to escape through the back window but his wife grabbed him by his coat and said, ‘Stay here with me!’ The man said, ‘Come with me!’ She answered, ‘I can’t, my legs won’t move! Can’t you see that ghastly figure outside the window, with its flaming eyes and fiery breath?’ Meanwhile the door had been broken open. They soon found the two corpses. The criminals were taken and brought to court. Six weeks later they were put to death, their villainous corpses bound to the wheel, and even now the crows are still say-ing, ‘That’s tasty meat, that is!’

The Cunning Styrian

It was in Styria during the last war and some way off the main road, and a rich farmer was thinking：‘How can I keep my thalers and my dear little ducats safe in these evil times? I’m ever so fond of the Empress MariaTheresa, God bless her, and the Emperor Joseph, God bless him, and the Emperor Francis, God give him long life and health! And just when you think you have these dear sovereigns ever so safe and out of harm’s way the enemy gets a whiff of them as soon as he sticks his nose into the village and takes them off prisoner to Lorraine or Cham-pagne! It’s enough to make a poor patriotic Austrian’s heart bleed!’ ‘I’ve got it!’ he said, ‘I know what I’ll do,’ and in the dark moonless night he took his money out into the kitchen garden.‘The Seven Sisters will not betray me,’ he said. Out in the garden he put the money straight down between the wallflowers and the sweet peas. Next to it he dug a hole in the path between the beds, threw all the soil on top of the coins and trampled on the beau-tiful flowers and the chard all around like someone treading down sauerkraut. The next Monday the Chas-seurs were scouting all round the district, and on the Tuesday a patrol entered the village and went straight to the mill, and then with white elbows from the mill to our farmer. And an Alsatian brandished his sword and bawled at him, ‘Out with your money, farmer, or say your last Our Father!’ The farmer said they were welcome in God’s name to take whatever they could find. He had nothing left, it had all gone yesterday and the day before that. ‘You’ll not find anything,’ he said, ‘you fine fellows!’ When they found nothing except for a couple of coppers and a gilded threepenny piece with the image of the Emp-ress MariaTheresa on it and a ring to hang it up by, the Alsatian said, ‘Farmer, you’ve buried your money! Show us here and now where you buried your money or you’ll leave for the hereafter without saying your last Our Father!’ ‘I can’t show you it here and now,’ said the farmer, ‘I’m sorry, but you’ll have to come with me out into the kitchen garden. I’ll show you where it was hidden there and what happened. Our lords and masters, the enemy, were here before you, yesterday and the day before, and they found it and took the lot.’The Chasseurs saw how things looked in the garden, found everything just as the man said, and not one of them thought the money might be lying under the pile of earth, but each of them gazed into the empty hole and thought：‘If only I’d been here earlier!’ ‘And if only they hadn’t ruined the wallflowers, and the chard as well!’ said the farmer, and so he fooled them and all those who came after them, and so it was that he saved the whole family of archdukes, the Emperor Francis, the Emperor Joseph, the Empress MariaTheresa, and Leopold the First, the Most Blessed of All, and kept them safe in their own country.

A Report from Turkey

There is justice in Turkey. A merchant’s man was over-taken on his journey by night and fatigue, tied his horse laden with precious goods to a tree not far from a guard-house, lay down under the shelter of the tree and went to sleep. Early next day he was woken by the morning air and the quails calling. He had slept well, but his horse had gone.

So he rushed off to the governor of the province, Prince Carosman Oglu he was called and he was staying nearby, and complained that he had been robbed. The prince cut the hearing short：‘So close to the guardhouse! Why didn’t you ride on another fifty yards, then you would have been safe! It’s your own stupid fault!’ But then the merchant’s man said, ‘O just prince, should I have feared to sleep in the open in a land where you rule?’ That pleased the Prince Carosman, and it annoyed him too. ‘Drink a little glass of Turkish brandy tonight,’ he said to the merchant’s man, ‘and sleep under the same tree again.’ The man did just as he was told. The next morning when he was woken by the morning air and the quails calling he had slept well again, for the horse was standing there tethered at his side together with all the precious goods, and in the tree hung a dead man, the thief, who never saw the sun rise again.

They do say there are trees enough in most parts, big ones and little ones.

The Lightest Death Sentence

People have said it’s the guillotine. But it isn’t, you know! A man who had done much for his country and was highly thought of by its ruler was sentenced to death for a crime he’d committed in a fit of passion. Petitions or prayers were no use. But since he was otherwise highly regarded by the ruler, he, the prince, let him choose how he would like to die：he was to die in whatever way he chose. So the chief secretary came to him in prison：‘The prince has determined to show you mercy. If you wish to be put to death on the wheel you shall be put on the wheel; if you wish to be hanged he will have you hanged-there are already two up on the gallows but everybody knows there’s room for three at a time. If, however, you would rather take rat poison there is some at the chemist’s. For whatever kind of death you choose the prince says it shall be yours. But, as you know, die you must!’ The criminal replied, ‘If I really must die, then death on the wheel can be bent to suit one’s taste, and hanging can be turned to suit one’s inclination if the wind lends a hand. But you haven’t got the point! For my part I have always thought that death from old age is the easiest way, and since the prince leaves the choice to me I’ll choose it and no other!’ And that was his final decision, he wouldn’t be talked out of it. So they had to let him go free and live on until he died of old age. For the prince said, ‘I gave my word and I’ll not break it.’

This little story comes from our mother-in-law who doesn’t like to let anyone die if she can possibly help it.

A Stallholder is Duped

A rouble is a silver coin in Russia, worth a bit less than two guilders, whereas an imperial is a gold coin and worth ten roubles. So you can get a rouble for an imperial, for instance if you lose nine roubles at cards, but you can’t get an imperial for a rouble. Yet a cunning soldier in Moscow said, ‘Want to bet? Tomorrow at the fair I’ll get me an imperial for a rouble.’The next day long rows of stalls were set out at the fair, the people were already standing at all the booths, admiring or finding fault, mak-ing bids and haggling, the crowd was walking up and down and the boys were saying hello to the girls, when up came the soldier with a rouble in his hand. ‘Whose is this rouble? Is it yours?’he asked all the stallkeepers in turn. One of them who wasn’t doing much business looked on for some time and then thought：if that mon-ey’s too hot for you to hold I can warm to it! ‘Over here, musketeer, it’s my rouble!’ The soldier said, ‘If you hadn’t shouted I would never have found you in the crowd,’ and he handed him the rouble. The trader turned it one way and the other and tested its ring; it was a good one all right, and he put it in his purse. ‘Now give me back my imperial, please!’ said the musketeer. The trader said, ‘I don’t have any imperial of yours, I owe you nothing. You can have this stupid rouble back if you’re playing a trick on me!’ But the musketeer said, ‘Hand over my imperial, this is no joke, I’m serious and can easily fetch a con-stable!’ One thing led to another, a polite word to a defiant one, defiance to insults, and a crowd gathered around the stall like bees round a honey pot. Then some-thing was burrowing its way through the throng. ‘What’s going on here?’ said the police sergeant who had pushed through the crowd with his men. ‘I said, what’s all this?’ The stallkeeper couldn’t say much, but the musketeer had a good story to tell.

Less than a quarter of an hour before, he said, he had bought this and that from this man for one rouble. But when it came to paying he could find only a double imper-ial, nothing smaller, one his godfather had given him when he was enlisted. So he gave him the imperial until he came back with a rouble. When he came back with the rouble he couldn’t find the right stall, so he asked at all the booths, ‘Who do I owe a rouble?’ And this man said it was him, and it was too, and he took the rouble but pretended he didn’t have his imperial. ‘Now will you agree to give it back?’ The police sergeant questioned those around and they said：Yes, the musketeer asked at all the stalls whose rouble it was and this man said it was his, and took it too, and tested it to see if it was genuine. When the police sergeant heard that, he settled the mat-ter：‘You’ve got your rouble, so give this soldier his imperial or we’ll close down your stall and nail it up with you inside and leave you to starve to death!’ Thus the police officer, and the trader it was who had to give the musketeer an imperial for a rouble.

Remember：Other people’s property can eat into your own just as fresh snow swallows up the old.

Patience Rewarded

One day a Frenchman rode up on to a bridge over a stream, and it was so narrow there was scarcely room for two horses at once. An Englishman was riding up from the other side, and when they met in the middle neither of them would give way. ‘An Englishman does not make way for a Frenchman!’ said the Englishman.‘Pardieu,’ said the Frenchman, ‘My horse has an English pedigree too! It’s a pity I can’t turn him round and let you have a good look at his backside in retreat! But you could at least let that English fellow you’re riding step aside for this English mount of mine. In any case yours seems to be the junior; mine served under Louis XIV in the battle of Kieferholz, 1702!’

But the Englishman was not greatly impressed. ‘I have all the time in the world!’ he said.‘This gives me a chance to read today’s paper until you are pleased to make way.’So with the coolness the English are famed for he took a newspaper from his pocket and opened it up and sat on his horse on the bridge and read for an hour, and the sun didn’t look as if it would shine on this pair of fools for ever, it was going down quickly towards the mountains. An hour later when he had finished reading and was about to fold up the newspaper again he looked at the Frenchman and said, ‘Eh bien?’ But the Frenchman had kept his head too and replied, ‘Englishman, kindly lend me your paper a while, so that I can read it too until you are pleased to make way.’ Now, when the Englishman saw that his adversary was a patient man, he said, ‘Do you know what, Frenchman? Come on, I’ll make way for you!’ So the Englishman made way for the Frenchman.

The Champion Swimmer

Before the war and all its afflictions when you could still cross freely from France to England and drink a glass or two in Dover or buy material for a waistcoat, a large mail boat sailed from Calais across the straits to Dover and back again twice a week. For the sea between those two countries is only a few miles wide at that point, you see. But you had to get there before the boat left if you wanted to sail on it. A Frenchman from Gascony seemed not to know that, for he came to Calais a quarter of an hour too late, just as they were shutting up the hens, and the sky was clouding over.‘Must I sit around here for a couple of days twiddling my thumbs? No,’ he thought, ‘I’d do better to pay a boatman a twelve-sous piece to go after the mail boat.’ For a small craft can sail faster than the heavy mail boat, you understand, and will catch up with it. But when he was sitting in the open boat the boatman said, ‘If I’d thought I’d have brought a tarpaulin!’ For it began to rain, and how! Very soon it poured down from the night sky as if a sea up above was emptying itself into the sea below. But the Gascon thought, ‘This is going to be fun!’ ‘Praise be,’ said the boatman at last, ‘I can see the mail boat.’ And he pulled up alongside and the Gas-con climbed aboard, and when he suddenly appeared through the narrow hatchway in the middle of the night and in the middle of the sea and joined the passengers on the ship they all wondered where he had sprung from, all on his own, so late and so wet. For on a ship like that it is like being in a cellar, you can’t hear what is going on outside over the talk of the passengers, the sailors’shouts, the noise of the wind, the flapping sails and the crashing waves, and nobody had any idea it was raining.‘You look as if you’ve been keelhauled,’ said one, ‘pulled right under the ship from one side to the other, I mean.’ ‘Is that what you’re thinking?’said the Gascon. ‘Do you imagine you can go swimming and stay dry? If you can tell me how to do that I’ll be glad to hear it, you see I’m the postman from Oléron and every Monday I swim over to the mainland with letters and messages, it’s quicker that way. But now I have a message to take to England. With your permission I’ll join you, since I was fortunate enough to meet up with you. Judging from the stars it can’t be far to Dover now.’ ‘You’re welcome, fellow country-man,’ said one（though he wasn’t a fellow Frenchman but an Englishman）and blew a cloud of tobacco smoke from his mouth. ‘If you have swum this far across the sea from Calais you must be a class above the black swimmer in London!’ ‘I’m not afraid of competition,’ said the Gas-con. ‘Will you take him on,’ replied the Englishman, ‘if I place a hundred louis d’or on you?’ The Gascon said, ‘You can bet I will!’ It’s the custom of rich Englishmen to bet with each other for large sums placed on men who excel at some physical activity. And so it was that this Englishman on the ship took the Gascon to London with him at his expense and had him eat and drink well so that he stayed fit and strong. ‘My lord,’ he said to a good friend of his in London, ‘I have brought with me a swim-mer I found at sea. I bet you a hundred guineas he can beat your Moor!’ His friend said, ‘You’re on!’

The next day they both appeared with their swimmers at an agreed spot on the riverThames, and hundreds of curious people had gathered there and they laid their bets too, some on the Moor, some on the Gascon, one shilling, or six shillings, one, two, five, twenty guineas, and the Moor didn’t give the Gascon much of a chance. But when they had both undressed the Gascon tied a little box to his body with a leather strap without saying why, as if that were quite normal. The Moor said, ‘What are you up to? Have you learnt that from the champion jumper who had to tie lead weights to his feet when he was set to catch a hare and was afraid he would jump right over it?’The Gascon opened his box and said, ‘I’ve only got a bottle of wine in here, a couple of saveloys and a small loaf of bread! I was going to ask you where you have your eats. For I shall swim straight down the riverThames into the North Sea and down the Channel into the Atlantic and on to Cadiz, and I suggest we don’t call in anywhere on the way, for I have to be back in Oléron by Monday, that’s the 16th. But tomorrow morning in Cadiz at the White Horse I’ll order a good dinner for you so it will be ready by the time you arrive.’ You, good reader, will hardly be imagining that he could escape that way! But the Moor was scared stiff. ‘I can’t compete against that amphibian!’ he told his master. ‘You can please yourself what you do!’ And he got dressed again.

So the bet was over, the Gascon was given a handsome reward by the Englishman who had brought him there and everyone scoffed at the Moor. For although they must have seen that the Frenchman was only shamming, they were all amused by his bravado and the unexpected out-come, and for a month after that he was treated in the inns and beerhouses by all those who had bet on him, and he admitted he had never been in the water in all his life.

The Weather Man

Just as a sieve-maker or a basket-weaver who lives in a small place cannot earn enough in his village or town to keep himself all year, but has to look for work and practise his craft in the countryside around, so our compasses-maker too does business away from home, and his trade is not in compasses but in knavish tricks that pay for a few drinks at the inn. Thus one day he appeared in Ober-ehingen and went straight to the mayor. ‘Mr Mayor,’ he said, ‘could you do with different weather? I’ve seen how things are hereabouts. There’s been too much rain on the bottom fields and the crops on the hill are behindhand.’ The mayor thought that was easy to say but difficult to put right. ‘Just so,’ replied the compasses-maker, ‘but that’s my line of business! Didn’t you know I’m the weather man from Bologna?’ In Italy, he said, where the oranges and lemons grow, all the weather was made to order. ‘You Germans are a bit behind in these matters.’ The mayor was a good and trusting fellow and one of those who would like to get rich sooner rather than later. So he was attracted by the offer. But he also thought cau-tion was called for! ‘As a test run,’ he said, ‘make it a clear sky tomorrow with just a few fluffy white clouds, sunshine all day with some streaks of vapour glistening in the air. Let the first yellow butterflies come out round midday, and it can be a nice cool evening!’ The compasses-maker replied, ‘I can’t commit myself just for one day, Mr Mayor! It wouldn’t cover my costs. I can only take on the job by the year. But then you’ll have problems finding room to store your crops and the new wine!’ When the mayor wanted to know how much he would charge for the year he was careful and didn’t ask for payment in advance, only a guilder a day and free drinks until the matter was properly in hand, that could take at least three days-‘But after that a pint from each gallon of wine over what you press in your best years, and a peck from every bushel of fruit.’ ‘That’s risnible,’ said the mayor. He stood in awe of the compasses-maker and was using refined language, and people in his part of the country think it’s refined to say‘risnible’for reasonable. But when he took pen and paper from the cupboard and was drawing up a schedule for the weather month by month the compasses-maker came up with a further complication：‘You can’t do that, Mr Mayor! You will have to consult the people. The weather is a community matter. You can’t expect every-one to accept your choice of weather.’ ‘You’re right!’ said the mayor. ‘You’re a sensible man.’

You, good reader, will have taken the measure of our compasses-maker and will have foreseen that the people could not agree on the matter. At their first meeting no decision was reached, nor even at the seventh, at the eighth hard words were spoken, and in the end a level-headed lawyer concluded that the best thing to do, to preserve peace and avoid strife in the community, was to pay the weather man off and send him packing. So the mayor summoned the compasses-maker. ‘Here are your nine guilders, you mischief-maker, now make sure you leave before there’s blood shed in the village!’ The compasses-maker didn’t have to be told twice. He took the money, left owing for about twelve pints of wine at the inn, and the weather stayed as it was.

Now then, as always the compasses-maker has much to teach us! In this case how good it is that up till now the supreme ruler of the world has always governed the weather according to his will alone. Even we calendar-makers, luminaries and the other estates of the realm are scarcely consulted and need lose no sleep on that score.

亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵的罪行

一

这是温德米尔夫人在复活节前的最后一场招待会，本廷克山庄比平日里更加热闹。六位内阁大臣直接从议长会议的现场赶来，身上还披挂着星章缎带；所有漂亮女人都穿上了她们最时髦的裙子。在画室尽头站着的，是卡尔斯鲁厄的索菲亚公主。她一副鞑靼人的面相，长着一对黑溜溜的小眼睛，佩戴着华美的翡翠首饰，尖声操着一口蹩脚的法语，无论谁对她说些什么，都报以夸张的大笑作回应。现场云集了各方各派的宾客：漂亮的贵族夫人们与狂热的激进派亲切地交谈，颇有声望的传教士与大名鼎鼎的无神论者擦肩而过，一群虔诚的主教追随着一位丰腴的歌剧首席女主唱穿堂过室，楼梯上站着几个皇家学院院士，假充成艺术家的样子。据说一时间，晚餐室里高朋满座，佳客云集。事实上，那真是温德米尔夫人最美好的一个夜晚，公主待到了快十一点半才离去。

公主刚一离开，温德米尔夫人就回到了画室，开始和佩斯利公爵夫人攀谈起来。画室里，一位著名的政治经济学家正表情严肃地向一位愤愤不平的匈牙利艺术大师解释音乐的科学原理。温德米尔夫人看上去明艳动人，她那秀颀的脖颈白皙如象牙，大大的眼睛仿佛幽蓝的勿忘我花，一头浓密的卷发闪烁着金色光华—绝不是当今篡夺纯金声名的那种浅淡的麦秸色，而是交织在璀璨阳光里或隐藏在珍稀琥珀中的那种金色。它们为她的脸庞镀上了一圈圣光，全然掩去了她罪人的魅惑。她是一个奇妙的心理学研究课题。年轻的时候，她就发现了一条重要的真理：越是放浪形骸，越是清纯可人。于是经由一系列鲁莽的出格行为—其中多半无伤大雅，她赢得了一位名流所享有的优遇。她换了不止一任丈夫。据《德布雷特英国贵族年鉴》记载，她曾有过三段婚姻。不过她从来没换过情人，于是坊间早就不再传播她的流言蜚语了。如今她四十年华，无儿女承欢膝下，只对寻欢作乐有着极度的热情，这也是她永葆青春的秘密。

她突然急切地环顾了一下房间，用她清晰而低沉的嗓音问：“我的手相师呢？”

“你的什么，格拉迪斯？”公爵夫人不由自主地高声问道。

“我的手相师，公爵夫人。我现在没他活不下去。”

“亲爱的格拉迪斯，你总是这么别出心裁！”公爵夫人边低声说着，边暗自琢磨手相师到底是什么，心想总不会和手足科医生差不多吧。

“他每周都会来给我看两次手相，”温德米尔夫人继续说道，“有趣极了。”

“我的老天！”公爵夫人自言自语道，“还真是一个手足科医生。太可怕了！我希望他无论如何至少是个外国人，那样的话还不算太糟糕。”

“我一定要把他介绍给您。”

“介绍给我？！”公爵夫人大喊一声，“你的意思是他就在这儿？”她开始四处张望，寻找她的玳瑁小扇子和一件破旧不堪的蕾丝披肩，以便做好准备，即刻离开。

“他当然在这儿。我怎么可能不邀请他来参加我的派对？他说我有一只通灵的手，要是我的拇指再短哪怕一丁点儿，我必定会是一个悲观主义者，会入修道院。”

“哦，我明白了！”公爵夫人如释重负，“他是个占吉卜卦的算命先生？”

“也卜算厄运。”温德米尔夫人答道，“吉凶祸福，前世今生。比如，明年我命里有灾，在陆地或海上都危险，所以我打算住在高空气球上，每天晚上用篮子把吃食拎上来。这些都写在我小手指上，也许是我的掌纹，我记不清是哪个了。”

“但你这必定是在违背天意，格拉迪斯。”

“我亲爱的公爵夫人，我坚信天意是禁得住这一回考验的。我认为每个人每月都应该看一次手相，好知道什么不该做。当然，有的人还是会去做，不过能被提前预警还是好的。现在，如果没有人赶紧去把波杰斯先生找来，我只好自己去了。”

“由我为您效劳吧，温德米尔夫人。”一个高大帅气的年轻男子说道。他一直微笑着站在旁边，饶有兴趣地聆听着她们的对话。

“太感谢了，亚瑟勋爵！可是我怕你不认识他。”

“如果他如您所说的那般出众，温德米尔夫人，我是不会认不出他的。跟我说说他什么样子，我会立刻把他带来。”

“嗯，他一点儿也不像是一个手相师。我的意思是，他并不是一副神秘莫测、深藏不露或不着边际的样子。他是一个矮壮的男人，滑稽的秃头，戴一副大大的金丝眼镜，形貌介于家庭医生和乡村律师之间。实在抱歉，可这并不是我的错—人们太讨厌了，我的钢琴师们都看起来和诗人一模一样，而我的诗人们又仿佛是一群钢琴家。我还记得上一季我邀请了一个曾经炸死过许多人的、极度可怕的阴谋家来吃晚饭，他以前总是穿一件锁子甲，袖子上别着一把匕首。可你知道吗，他来的时候看起来就像是一位和善的老牧师，整晚都在讲笑话。当然了，他非常有趣，可是我失望至极。当我问起他的锁子甲，他只是大笑着说：‘英格兰实在太冷了，没法穿。’啊，波杰斯先生来了！波杰斯先生，我想让你给佩斯利公爵夫人看看手相。公爵夫人，您得把手套脱了。不，不是左手，另一只。”

“亲爱的格拉迪斯，我认为这实在是不妥。”公爵夫人说着，轻轻地脱下了一只脏污的小山羊皮手套。

“但凡有趣的事情都不妥，”温德米尔夫人说，“世事如此。不过，我一定要介绍你们认识。公爵夫人，这是波杰斯先生，我钟爱的手相师。波杰斯先生，这是佩斯利公爵夫人，如果你敢说她手掌上的月亮山[1]比我的大，我就再也不会相信你了。”

“我确信，格拉迪斯，我手上没有那东西。”公爵夫人严肃地说。

“夫人说得没错，”波杰斯先生瞥了一眼那只手指短粗的小胖手，说道，“月亮山没有成形。不过，生命线极好。请您弯一下手腕。谢谢！手腕上三条醒目的主线！您会长命百岁的，公爵夫人，而且非常幸福。志向线—不好不坏。才智线不算突出，情感线—”

“您就直言不讳吧，波杰斯先生！”温德米尔夫人大声说道。

“倘若看出了公爵夫人经历过什么，我自然乐意直言，”波杰斯先生说着，鞠了一躬，“可是很遗憾，我只看到了伟大的情感，伴随着强烈的责任感。”

“请您继续，波杰斯先生。”公爵夫人说道，看上去颇为受用。

“理财是夫人您重要的美德。”波杰斯先生继续说。温德米尔夫人大笑着离开了。

“理财是件极好的事。”公爵夫人自鸣得意地说，“我嫁给佩斯利的时候，他有十一座城堡，可没有一所房子能住人。”

“如今，他有了十二所房子，可一座城堡也没有了。”温德米尔夫人大声说道。

“哦，亲爱的，”公爵夫人说，“我喜欢……”

“舒适，”波杰斯先生说道，“现代化设施，而且每一间卧室里都有热水。夫人您完全正确，舒适是我们的文明带给我们的唯一的东西。”

“你已经准确地讲出了公爵夫人的性格，波杰斯先生，现在你一定要给弗劳拉夫人看看手相。”女主人微笑着点头示意，一位淡褐色头发、削肩膀的高个儿女孩便从沙发后面笨手笨脚地走出来，伸出了一只瘦骨嶙峋的细长的手掌，手指像竹片儿一样。

“哈，一位钢琴师！”波杰斯先生说道，“我看是一位杰出的钢琴师，不过或许还称不上是音乐家。非常矜持，非常坦诚，而且非常爱动物。”

“太对了！”公爵夫人大声说着，转向温德米尔夫人，“完全正确！弗劳拉在麦克洛斯基养了二十四只柯利牧羊犬。如果她父亲允许的话，她会把我们城里的房子变成动物园。”

“哎呀，正巧每个星期四的晚上我也这么对待我的房子。”温德米尔夫人大笑着高声说道，“只不过比起柯利牧羊犬，我更喜欢狮子。”

“这是您的一桩错事，温德米尔夫人。”波杰斯先生说着，浮夸地鞠了一躬。

“如果一个女人不能令她所犯的错事楚楚动人，那她充其量也仅是一位女性罢了。”这是女主人的回答。“不过你一定要给我们多看几个手相。来，托马斯爵士，让波杰斯先生给您看看。”一位身穿白色西装马甲的亲切和蔼的老绅士走上前来，伸出一只厚实粗糙的手，中指尤其长。

“生性爱冒险。以往有过四次长途旅行，即将开启一段新旅程。遭遇过三次船难。不，两次，不过下次旅行会有遭遇海难的风险。一个坚定的保守派，非常守时，酷爱收藏奇珍异宝。在十六岁到十八岁之间生过一场重病，快三十岁的时候继承了一笔财富。对猫和激进派深恶痛绝。”

“太神奇了！”托马斯爵士惊呼道，“您一定得给我夫人也看看手相！”

“您的第二任夫人，”波杰斯先生依然握着托马斯爵士的手，轻声说道，“您第二任夫人的手。我荣幸之至！”可是马维尔夫人，一个棕色头发、连睫毛都伤感的忧郁女人，完全拒绝将她的过去或未来暴露出来。而温德米尔夫人费尽口舌也没能让俄国大使克洛夫先生脱下他的手套。事实上，似乎许多人都很害怕面对这个满脸一成不变的微笑、戴着金丝眼镜、眼睛贼亮的古怪的小个子男人。而且，当他当着所有人的面，对可怜的弗莫尔夫人说，她其实一点儿都不喜欢音乐，只是非常喜欢音乐家的时候，人们都觉察到，手相学真是一门最危险的科学，不应该受到鼓励，除非是两人私下交流。

然而，亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵全然不知弗莫尔夫人的不幸遭遇，他已经饶有兴致地看了波杰斯先生许久，迫不及待地希望他给自己看看手相，可是又不太好意思主动前去要求。于是他穿过房间走到了温德米尔夫人落座的地方，满脸绯红地询问，是否能请波杰斯先生给他瞧瞧。

“当然了，他会愿意的。”温德米尔夫人说，“那正是他来这儿的目的。亚瑟勋爵，我所有的狮子都是马戏团演员，无论何时，我一声令下，它们就得跳火圈。不过我得事先警告你，我会把一切都告诉西比尔的。她明天来和我共进午餐，聊聊帽子的事。如果波杰斯先生发现你脾气很坏，或者有痛风的征兆，或是在贝斯沃特金屋藏娇，我必定将一切如实奉告给西比尔。”

亚瑟勋爵微笑着摇了摇头。“我不担心，”他答道，“西比尔对我了如指掌，我对她也一样。”

“啊！你这么说倒令我感到一丝遗憾。婚姻是建立在彼此误解的基石之上的。我可一点儿都不愤世嫉俗，只是有些经验罢了，然而事实正是如此。波杰斯先生，亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵巴不得你快给他看看手相。你可别说出什么‘他和伦敦最漂亮的女孩儿订婚了’之类的话，这消息早在一个月以前就登过《晨报》了。”

“亲爱的温德米尔夫人，”杰德堡侯爵夫人大声说道，“千万让波杰斯先生多留会儿。他刚刚才告诉我，我应该登台表演，我对此颇有兴趣。”

“如果他真是这么说的，杰德堡夫人，我必定得把他带走了。快过来，波杰斯先生，给亚瑟勋爵看看手相。”

“好吧，”杰德堡夫人噘着嘴从沙发上站起身，“就算我当不成演员，至少能当个听众吧。”

“当然，我们大家都来做听众。”温德米尔夫人说，“现在，波杰斯先生，千万告诉我们点儿好话，亚瑟勋爵可是我特别钟爱的客人之一。”

可是，当波杰斯先生看到亚瑟勋爵的手掌，他竟一言不发，面色变得莫名地苍白。他似乎打了个寒战，粗重的眉毛以一种奇怪又恼人的方式扭曲着，正如每次他困惑不解时的样子。接着他的黄脑门上渗出豆大的汗珠，仿佛有毒的露水，他的粗手指也变得冰冷黏湿。

亚瑟勋爵自然注意到了这些令人不安的奇怪迹象，有生以来第一次，他感觉到了恐惧。他想冲出房间，可是他克制住了自己的冲动。最好能知道最坏的情况，不管是什么，也好过在骇人的未知中惶惶度日。

“愿闻其详，波杰斯先生。”他说道。

“我们都等着呢！”不耐烦的温德米尔夫人急切地大喊道。可是那位手相师偏偏缄口不言。

“我相信亚瑟勋爵也是要登台表演的。”杰德堡夫人说，“只不过刚才被你斥责一番，波杰斯先生就不敢再这样告诉他了。”

突然间，波杰斯先生松开了亚瑟勋爵的右手，抓起他的左手，低低地俯下身去，仔细查看，眼镜的金边都要蹭到手掌心了。霎时间，他的脸变得惨白，如同一副恐怖的面具，但他很快恢复了镇静。他抬起头看着温德米尔夫人，挤出一个微笑说：“这是一个迷人的年轻人的手。”

“当然了！”温德米尔夫人答道，“不过他会是一个可爱的丈夫吗？这才是我想知道的。”

“所有迷人的年轻人都会是可爱的丈夫。”波杰斯先生说道。

“我认为做丈夫的不应该太过迷人，”杰德堡夫人一脸忧思地低声说道，“那太危险了。”

“我亲爱的宝贝，他们永远都不会太过迷人的。”温德米尔夫人大声说，“不过我想知道细节，只有细节才是最有趣的。亚瑟勋爵会发生什么事？”

“哦，未来几个月之内，亚瑟勋爵将外出旅行……”

“没错，当然了，他要去度蜜月。”

“还会失去一位亲戚。”

“但愿可别是他妹妹？”杰德堡夫人用满是怜悯的语气问道。

“当然不是他妹妹，”波杰斯先生做了一个不以为然的手势，“只是个远房亲戚。”

“哦，我真是失望透顶，”温德米尔夫人说，“我明天没有一星半点儿的东西可以透露给西比尔。现如今可没人在乎什么远房亲戚，多少年前就过时了。不过，我想她最好备一块黑丝巾在身边，去教堂总会用得到。好了，我们去吃晚餐吧。他们肯定把什么都吃光了，我们没准儿还能找些热汤喝。弗朗索瓦以前会烹制极美味的鲜汤，可是他现在对政治狂热，我都有些搞不懂他了。我倒是希望布朗热将军能保持安静。公爵夫人，您肯定累了吧？”

“一点儿也不，亲爱的格拉迪斯，”公爵夫人边回答，边蹒跚着走向门口，“我过得非常愉快，那个手足科医生，我是说那个手相师，真是太有意思了。弗劳拉，我的玳瑁扇子在哪儿？哦，谢谢你，托马斯爵士，非常感谢！我的蕾丝披肩呢，弗劳拉？哦，谢谢你，托马斯爵士，你真是个好人！”然后，这位高贵的人物终于走下了楼，途中只把香水瓶弄掉了两次。

这期间，亚瑟·萨维尔勋爵一直站在壁炉旁，挥之不去的恐惧与对厄运将临的胆战心惊笼罩着他。妹妹挽着普利姆代尔勋爵的胳膊从他身边经过，身着粉色织锦，戴着粉色珍珠配饰，楚楚动人，而他只对着妹妹苦笑一番。他几乎没听到温德米尔夫人在招呼他跟上。他想着西比尔·默顿，想着他们之间可能会产生嫌隙，不禁泪湿了眼眶。

看着他，人们会说，复仇女神涅墨西斯已经偷走了帕拉斯[2]的盾牌，让他看到了蛇发女妖戈耳工的头。他似乎石化了，忧郁阴沉的脸像是大理石一般。他从出生以来就过着富家公子锦衣玉食的生活，无俗事挂心，度过了无忧无虑的美妙的少年时光。此刻，有生以来第一次，他意识到了世事无常、命运捉弄，感受到了在劫难逃的可怕。

这真是疯狂且荒谬至极！这些骇人的秘密罪孽、血红的犯罪征兆，都以一种他自己无法识读的字符，写在他的手掌上，而另一个人却可以破译？没有逃离厄运的可能吗？无论是荣耀还是耻辱，我们难道都如棋子一般，被一股无形的力量左右，如陶工手下的器皿一般任由人搓扁揉圆？他的理智对抗着它，同时他又感到灾难正纠缠着自己，他突然被要求去承担一个难以负荷的重任。演员们太幸运了，他们可以选择演绎悲剧或喜剧，品尝苦涩或欢愉，大笑或哭泣。可现实生活并非如此。大部分男人和女人都被迫扮演一些他们并不能胜任的角色。我们的吉尔登斯吞[3]为我们扮演着哈姆雷特，而我们的哈姆雷特不得不像哈尔王子[4]一样开着玩笑。世界是一个舞台，可是剧里的演员都配错了角色。

波杰斯先生突然走进房间。看到亚瑟勋爵时，他惊了一下，粗鄙肥胖的脸青黄不定。两人目光交错，一时间沉默无言。

“公爵夫人把一只手套落在这里了，亚瑟勋爵，让我给她拿过去。”波杰斯先生终于开口，“啊，在沙发上！晚安！”

“波杰斯先生，我要请教您一个问题，请您务必直言不讳。”

“下次吧，亚瑟勋爵，公爵夫人等着急了，我得赶紧走。”

“先别走，公爵夫人没什么急事。”

“不该让夫人们久等，亚瑟勋爵。”波杰斯先生说着，无力地笑了笑，“女士们很容易不耐烦的。”

亚瑟勋爵任性又轻蔑地撇了撇他轮廓鲜明的嘴唇。此刻，那位可怜的公爵夫人对他而言一点儿都不重要。他穿过房间，来到波杰斯先生身旁，伸出他的手。

“告诉我您看到了什么，”他说，“实话实说。我必须知道真相。我不是个小孩儿。”

金丝眼镜后面，波杰斯先生的眼睛眨了眨。他不安地交错着步子，手指紧张地把弄着一条闪闪发光的表链。

“您为什么会认为除了我告诉您的那些，我还在您手上看到了更多的东西呢，亚瑟勋爵？”

“我就是知道。你不说明白，我是不会罢休的。我可以付钱给你。我会给你一张一百英镑的支票。”

那对绿眼睛闪亮了片刻，紧接着又恢复了暗淡。

“基尼金币[5]？”最终，波杰斯先生低声说道。

“当然。我明天就把支票给您送去。您在哪个俱乐部？”

“我没有俱乐部。也就是说，目前还没有。我的地址是……还是请允许我奉上名片吧。”说着，波杰斯先生从马甲背心口袋里掏出一张镶金边的卡片，递给亚瑟勋爵，并向他深深鞠了一躬。卡片上写着：

塞普蒂默斯·R.波杰斯先生

—职业手相师—

西月街103a号

“我的工作时间是上午十点到下午四点。”波杰斯先生例行公事地小声说道，“全家一起来有折扣。”

“快点儿吧！”亚瑟勋爵的面色极度苍白，边高声催促，边伸出了他的手。

波杰斯先生紧张地环顾四周，拉上了厚重的门帘。

“要花点儿时间，亚瑟勋爵，您最好先坐下。”

“长话短说，先生！”亚瑟勋爵再次大声催促，在光可鉴人的地板上愤怒地跺着脚。

波杰斯先生笑了笑，从他胸前的口袋里掏出一面小放大镜，用手帕小心地擦拭着。

“我准备好了。”他说。

二

十分钟以后，大惊失色、悲痛欲绝的亚瑟勋爵从大条纹雨篷周遭站着的一群穿毛皮大衣的男仆们中间挤过去，冲出了本廷克山庄，似乎对一切视而不见、充耳不闻。那天晚上天寒地冻，广场四周的煤气灯闪烁在凛冽的寒风中。可是他的双手却热得发烫，他的额头如火烧火燎一般。他迈着醉汉似的步伐，走了又走。他经过一个警察的身边，警察好奇地打量他；一个乞丐懒散地从拱廊中走出来，乞求施舍，看眼前人的痛苦更甚于自己，反倒害怕起来。他一度在路灯下驻足，看看自己的双手。他仿佛能觉察到上面已沾满血污，颤抖的双唇间迸出一声微弱的呜咽。

谋杀！那手相师看出来的竟是一场谋杀！此刻的夜晚似乎也洞悉了一切，荒凉的风在他耳畔呼啸，漆黑的街角也满是这秘密，这秘密在房顶上对他咧着嘴笑。

他先是来到公园，那里阴暗的树林似乎对他有强烈的吸引力。精疲力竭的他倚靠在栏杆上，额头抵着湿冷的金属降温。他倾听着林木间令人战栗的寂静。“谋杀！谋杀！”他不断地重复着，仿佛反复的诉说可以减弱这个词的恐怖。他自己的声音令他胆战心惊，然而他又希望回声女神或许能听到他，把这座酣睡的城市从梦境中唤醒。他感到一种强烈的欲望，想要拦住随便哪个过往的行人，将一切说与他听。

而后，他游荡过牛津街，来到逼仄腌臜的小巷子。他经过的时候，两个浓妆艳抹的女人逗弄他。一个漆黑的院子里传来打骂声，紧接着是尖叫声，然后他看到了弯腰驼背挤成一团的穷人和老者，都蜷缩在门前潮湿的台阶上。一种莫名的怜悯之情涌上心头。罪恶与苦难注定是这些人的结局吗？就像他也有命定的归宿一样？难道他们也和他一样，仅仅是一场大秀中的提线木偶吗？

然而击溃他的不是个中谜题，而是受难的喜剧性。它的全然无用，它荒谬至极得毫无意义。一切看起来是多么不合逻辑！毫无和谐可言！他惊诧于白日浅薄的乐观主义与真实存在的事实之间的不协调。他还非常年轻。

片刻之后，他发现自己来到了马里波恩教堂前。安静的车道看起来像是一条长长的亮闪闪的银缎带，斑驳错落的光影仿佛深色的蔓藤花纹。远处弯弯曲曲一排明灭不定的煤气灯，一座带围墙的小房子外面孤零零地停放着一辆双轮马车，车夫正在里面睡觉。他急匆匆地向着波特兰广场的方向走去，还不时地四处张望，似乎在担心被人跟踪。在里奇街的街角站着两个男人，他们正读着公告牌上的一张小布告。一股莫名的好奇心驱使他凑上前去。他刚一走近，那两个黑字—“谋杀”就映入他的眼帘。他吓了一跳，两颊变得通红。那是一张悬赏公告，为了抓捕一个中等身材、年龄在三十岁到四十岁之间、头戴圆顶毡帽、身穿黑色大衣和格子裤子、右脸上有道疤的男人。他读了一遍又一遍，想着那个可怜的男人会不会被抓住，猜想他脸上的疤是怎么来的。或许，某一天，他自己的名字也会出现在伦敦街墙的布告栏上。或许，某一天，人们也会给他的人头开个悬赏捉拿价。

这想法令他毛骨悚然。他猛然转身，快步没入夜色之中。

他不清楚自己身在何处。他模模糊糊地记得自己游荡过一片迷宫一样的脏房子，在一大片纵横交错的幽暗的街道中迷了路。最后他发现自己走到了皮卡迪利广场，此时已是曙光初照，黎明破晓。他溜达着回家，向贝尔格雷夫广场走去，路上遇见了驶向科芬园的四轮运货大马车。马车夫们身穿白色罩衫，留着粗糙的卷发，晒伤的脸上满是欢愉。他们稳坐在马车上，马鞭子挥得噼啪作响，彼此间时不时地高喊几声。这支嘈杂的队伍中为首的是一匹大灰马，马背上坐着一个胖嘟嘟的男孩，他破旧的帽子里有一束报春花。他一路笑着，小手紧紧地抓着马鬃毛。堆得高高的蔬菜看上去就像是许多块翡翠直冲云霄，又像是美艳玫瑰的粉红花瓣上镶嵌的碧玉。亚瑟勋爵被莫名地感动，说不清是为什么。黎明时分的柔和美妙中有些东西似乎于他而言是无以言表的可悲，他想起所有那些初时晴好、晚时暴风雨侵袭的日子。还有这些庄稼人，他们粗粝又欢快的声音，他们满不在乎的举止，他们眼中的伦敦是多么不寻常啊！没有夜晚的罪行，没有白天的烟雾，伦敦，一个毫无生气的鬼魅般的城市，一座荒冢之城！他好奇他们如何看待它，他们是否了解它的壮丽与耻辱，它热烈的色彩斑斓的欢乐，它恐怖的饥荒，它从早到晚的创造与破坏。也许对他们而言，它只不过是一个可以卖水果的集市，是他们至多逗留几个小时的地方—他们离开时街道依然安静，房屋依然沉睡未醒。观察这些过往的行人成为他的一件乐事。粗野的人们穿着笨重的大头鞋，迈着笨拙的步子，散发着几分超然世外的感觉。他觉得这些人与大自然共生，而自然教会了他们平和。他羡慕他们对许多事都不知晓。

他走到贝尔格雷夫广场的时候，天空泛着微蓝，花园中的鸟儿开始叽叽喳喳。

三

亚瑟勋爵醒来的时候是十二点，正午的阳光透过象牙色丝绸窗帘照进他的房间。他起身望向窗外。这座伟大的城市被笼罩在热气蒸腾的朦胧的雾中，一所所房子的屋顶是暗银色。下面广场上一闪一闪的绿色中，一些孩子正像白色的蝴蝶一般飞舞着，人行道上满是去往公园的人。在他眼中，生命从未如此美妙，邪祟从未离他如此遥远。

他的贴身男仆用托盘给他送来一杯巧克力。他喝完巧克力，拨开厚重的桃红色长丝绒门帘，走进浴室。柔和的光从上方倾泻下来，穿过透明的缟玛瑙薄板，大理石水池里的水像块月长石一样闪闪发光。他急切地跳了进去，直到清凉的水波触到了脖子、头发，然后他把头沉下去，仿佛这样可以洗刷掉一些可耻的斑驳记忆。他迈步出来的时候，感到几乎平静了。此刻他敏锐的身体状况支配了他，正如许多本质精纯的事物一样，心智就像是烈火，既可用于提纯，亦可用于毁灭。

早餐之后，他瘫坐在沙发床上，点了根烟。壁炉架上，精致的旧织锦相框中，立着一幅西比尔·默顿的大照片。照片中的人一如他在诺埃尔夫人的舞会上初见时的模样。形状精致的小脑袋微微垂向一侧，就好像那个细长如芦苇似的脖子没法承担如此的美貌一般；双唇微启，仿佛专为甜美的音乐而生；一双满是好奇的梦幻的眼睛透出少女的清纯。她穿着柔软贴身的中国绉纱的裙子，手持大大的叶形团扇，看上去就像是一尊人们在塔纳格拉[6]附近的橄榄树丛中找到的那种精美的小陶俑。而她的仪态风度中确有些希腊风范。尽管她个子并不娇小，但她比例匀称完美—在那个大多数女人要么太魁梧，要么太微不足道的年纪，这可是件难得的事。

此刻亚瑟勋爵看着她，心中由爱而生出万般怜悯。他感到自己头上悬着谋杀的宿命，娶她为妻是一种堪比犹大的背叛，是连波吉亚家族[7]做梦也想不出的更恶劣的罪行。他可能在任何时刻受到感召，去实践那个写在他手上的罪大恶极的预言。如此，他们两个还有什么幸福可言呢？当命运依然掌握着这个可怕的天平，他们的生活会如何呢？无论如何，婚礼必须要推迟，对此他毅然决然。尽管他深爱着那个女孩，当他们坐在一起时，哪怕是手指轻触，也会令他全身上下每一个神经因无比的欢愉而震颤，然而他清楚地意识到自己的责任所在，也完全明白那个事实—在他完成这桩谋杀之前，他没有权利结婚。完成之后，他可以和西比尔·默顿站在圣坛前，把自己的一生交付于她的手上，不再惧怕有恶事发生；完成之后，他可以拥她入怀，知道她再也不用因为他而脸红，再也不用羞愧得抬不起头。可是，完成这桩谋杀必须是第一要务，对他们两个人而言，越快越好。

许多男人如果处于他的境遇，会优先选择寻欢作乐的鲜花小径，而非承担责任的悬崖峭壁。可亚瑟勋爵太过认真尽责，以至于无法将快乐建立在原则之上。他的爱可不是一时意乱情迷，西比尔对他来说就是一切美好高贵的象征。有那么一瞬间，他对于自己要去做的事情本能地产生强烈的厌恶，不过那感觉转瞬即逝。他的内心告诉他这不是罪行，而是牺牲；他的理智提醒他，没有其他出路。他必须在为自己而活还是为他人而活之间做出选择。尽管毫无疑问，加之于他身上的责任非常糟糕，可他知道不能让自私战胜爱。早晚我们都会面临同样的抉择，我们所有人都会被问同样的问题。亚瑟勋爵的问题来得早一些，他的本性还没有被中年斤斤计较的愤世嫉俗而腐坏，他的心还没有被我们这个时代流行的浅薄的自负而侵蚀，他毫不犹豫地选择承担自己的责任。对他而言同样幸运的是，他既不是空想家，也不是懒散的不学无术之徒。他如果是那样的人，就会犹豫踌躇，会像哈姆雷特一样，让优柔寡断毁了他的目标。可他本质上是一个务实主义者。对他来说，生命意味着行动，而非思考。他拥有最难能可贵的东西—直觉决断力。

前一晚狂乱混沌的感觉此刻已经完全褪去，回想自己走街串巷地疯狂游荡，回想起自己情感上经历的剧烈的苦痛挣扎，他甚至觉得有些羞愧。他那些锥心刻骨的痛苦现在似乎变得很不真实。他很纳闷，自己怎么会傻到对无可避免之事埋天怨地。唯一令他苦恼的问题是，他要杀死谁？他并没有无视那个事实—谋杀就像是异教世界的宗教信仰，除了要有一位祭司，还需要一名牺牲者。他不是天才，没有敌人，而且他确实感觉到，这次不是意气用事或满足个人好恶的时机，他卷入的任务是一件最重大、最严肃的事件。于是，他在一页纸上列出了他的亲友名单，经过一番深思熟虑，他最终选择了自己的远房表亲克莱门蒂娜·比彻姆夫人，一位住在可胜街的可爱的老妇人。他一直非常喜欢克莱姆[8]夫人—每个人都这么称呼她，而且他法定年龄一到就继承了拉格比勋爵的所有财产，自己非常富有，并不会从她的离世中获得什么钱物的好处。事实上，他越琢磨就越觉得她是最合适的人选，任何拖延都是对西比尔的不公，他决意即刻安排行事。

首先要搞定的当然是手相师。于是他在窗边的谢拉顿[9]小书桌前坐下来，开了一张一百零五英镑的支票，受款人为塞普蒂默斯·波杰斯先生。接着，他将支票装进信封，令他的贴身男仆送去西月街。而后他打电话给马厩，叫了一辆马车，自己穿戴好就出了门。离开房间之前，他回头看了看西比尔·默顿的照片，发誓无论如何，他绝不会让她知道自己为她做了什么，他要将自我牺牲的秘密永远深埋在心中。

在去往白金汉宫俱乐部的路上，他去了一趟花店，为西比尔递送了一篮水仙，俏丽的白色花瓣，鲜艳夺目的花蕊副冠，漂亮极了。他一到俱乐部，就径直走向图书馆，摇响服务铃，向侍者要一杯柠檬苏打水和一本毒物学的书。他心意已决，毒药是解决这件麻烦事的最佳方式。人与人之间任何形式的暴力行为都令他反感，况且，他非常担心杀死克莱姆夫人可能会引起大众关注。他很讨厌成为人们在温德米尔夫人家嘲讽戏弄的谈资，更不愿看到自己的名字出现在恶俗的社会新闻报道中。他还要考虑西比尔的父母，他们是非常传统守旧的人，倘若牵涉任何丑闻，他们很可能会反对这桩婚姻。尽管他也确信无疑，如果他将这件事情的来龙去脉告诉他们，他们会是最理解他行事动机的人。因此，无论怎么看，毒药都是最佳选择。安全、安静、万无一失，能避免出现任何痛苦的场面—像大多数英国人一样，他从骨子里拒绝一切痛苦的场面。

然而，他对毒物学一无所知，而且除了《拉夫入门指南》和《贝利杂志》，侍者在图书馆中也实在找不出什么东西。他亲自查看了书架，终于发现一册装帧精美的《药典》，还有一本由皇家医师学院院长马修·里德爵士编纂的厄斯金的《毒物学》。马修·里德爵士是白金汉宫最古老的成员之一，曾因为其他人被误选，那次令人窘困的意外事件大大激怒了委员会，以至于当真人出现的时候，他们全体一致投票反对他。亚瑟勋爵读不懂两本书中的专业术语，已经开始后悔当初在牛津大学没认真上古典文学课程了。不过他在《毒物学》第二卷中发现一个非常有趣的关于乌头碱性能的详细记录，是用简单易读的英文记述的，看起来正是他想要的毒药。毒发快—几乎是即刻生效，完全无痛，而且据马修爵士的建议，如果以胶囊的形态服用，丝毫不会难以下咽。他在衬衫袖口上记下足以致命的药剂量，将书放回原位，然后漫步到圣詹姆斯街的帕索-亨贝大药房。帕索先生常与贵族阶层打交道，对于亚瑟勋爵的需求，他感到十分惊讶，极其毕恭毕敬地低声说道，买这些药品必须要有诊断书的。亚瑟勋爵解释说是为了解决一只挪威巨獒，因为它出现了早期的狂犬病症状，已经咬了马车夫小腿肚子两次。帕索先生对这个理由非常满意，还恭维了亚瑟勋爵丰富的毒物学知识，并立刻配好了药。

亚瑟勋爵在邦德街一家商店的橱窗里发现一个漂亮的银质小糖果盒。他将胶囊装进糖果盒中，丢掉帕索-亨贝大药房的丑陋的药盒，然后立刻动身前往克莱姆夫人家。

“好啊，坏小子，”他一进屋，老夫人就大声说道，“怎么这么长时间没来看我？”

“我亲爱的克莱姆夫人，我实在无暇抽身。”亚瑟勋爵笑着说。

“我猜你的意思是你整日间都陪在西比尔·默顿小姐身边，买衣服、聊废话？我真是不理解人们为何对结婚这样小题大做。在我那个年代，我们从没想过在公共场合喁喁私语、卿卿我我，甚至私下也不曾。”

“向您保证，克莱姆夫人，我已经二十个小时没见过西比尔了。依我看，她是完全属于她的女帽商的。”

“当然了，要不是这样，你也不会来看望我这个丑老太婆。我很纳闷，你们男人怎么不引以为戒？我年轻的时候也有人为我痴狂，现如今变成一个风湿病缠身的可怜的老东西，一副假牙外加一副臭脾气。要不是亲爱的詹森夫人四处搜罗些蹩脚的法国小说给我送来，我估计都熬不过这一天。医生真是百无一用，就会向我收钱。他们连我烧心的毛病都治不好。”

“我给您带来了治疗烧心的药，克莱姆夫人，”亚瑟勋爵一脸严肃地说，“美国人研制的，药效奇佳。”

“我可不喜欢美国人的发明创造，亚瑟。我一点儿也不喜欢。我最近读了几部美国小说，全都不知所云。”

“哦，我这个可不是不知所云的东西，克莱姆夫人！我向您保证，药到病除。您一定要答应我试试看。”说着，亚瑟勋爵从口袋里拿出那个小盒子，递给她。

“嗯，这个盒子还挺精致的，亚瑟。真是给我的礼物吗？你真是太贴心了。这是那个灵丹妙药吗？看上去像一颗糖果。我现在就吃。”

“我的天啊！克莱门蒂娜夫人，”亚瑟勋爵大喊一声，抓住她的手，“现在可不行，它是顺势疗法[10]的药，如果在不烧心的时候吃，可能会后患无穷呢。等您难受的时候再吃，您会被药效吓一跳的。”

“那我现在就该吃。”克莱姆夫人说着，将小小的透明胶囊举到灯前，里面流动着液态乌头碱的泡沫。“我相信它一定很好吃。事实上，我虽然讨厌医生，却很喜欢药。不过，我还是等下次犯病时再吃吧。”

“那会是什么时候呢？”亚瑟勋爵急切地问道，“会很快吗？”

“但愿一个星期内不要再犯了。我昨天早上烧心，难受极了。不过，谁知道呢？”

“那么，克莱姆夫人，您肯定在这个月底之前还会再犯病？”

“怕是如此。不过，亚瑟，你今天真是有心啊！真的，西比尔让你变得更好了。你现在得离开了，我一会儿要和几个非常无聊的人吃晚饭，他们从来不聊八卦丑闻，我如果现在不睡一会儿，晚饭的时候是没法保持清醒的。再见，亚瑟！代我问候西比尔，还有谢谢你带来的美国药。”

“您可别忘了吃啊，克莱姆夫人。”亚瑟勋爵从座位上起身说道。

“我当然不会忘啊，傻孩子。你这样为我着想，真是太贴心了！我如果需要更多，会写信告诉你的。”

亚瑟勋爵兴高采烈地离开了，感到如释重负。

那天晚上他和西比尔·默顿碰了面。他告诉她，他突然被置于一个极其困难的境地，无论出于尊严还是责任，他都无法退缩；他告诉她婚礼必须推迟，因为直到他摆脱那个可怕的纠缠物，他才能恢复自由之身；他恳求她相信自己，请她对未来不要有任何怀疑，一切都会走上正轨，但必须要忍耐。

这场景发生在帕克巷默顿先生家的花房里，亚瑟勋爵平日里常来这儿吃晚饭。今夜的西比尔处于莫大的幸福之中，有那么一刻，亚瑟勋爵险些向心中懦弱的部分屈服，打算写信向克莱门蒂娜夫人要回药丸，让婚礼照常进行，假装这世上根本没有波杰斯先生这个人。然而，他良善的本性很快占了上风，甚至当西比尔埋在他怀中痛哭流涕时，他也没有犹疑。令他心旌荡漾的美丽也触动了他的良心。他觉得为了几个月的快乐而毁掉如此美好的一生，是大错特错的。

直到临近午夜，他一直陪着西比尔，两人彼此慰藉。第二天一早，他给默顿先生写了一封充满男子气概的意志坚决的信，言明婚礼不得不推迟，然后就动身前往威尼斯了。

四

在威尼斯，他见到了他的弟弟瑟比顿勋爵。瑟比顿正巧乘着他的游艇从科孚岛来，两个年轻人一起度过了愉快的两周。早上，他们在利多岛上骑马，或是乘着狭长的黑色贡多拉在绿色的水道中滑行；下午，他们通常在游艇上招待访客；晚上，他们在佛罗莱恩餐厅吃饭，在皮亚扎广场上没完没了地抽烟。但不知怎的，亚瑟勋爵并不开心。他每天都要读《泰晤士报》的讣告栏，希望能看到克莱门蒂娜夫人去世的消息，可每天都是失望。他开始担心是不是发生了什么意外。他经常后悔，当初她迫切地希望尝试药效的时候，自己阻止了她服下那枚乌头碱。尽管西比尔的信满是爱与信任以及温柔，却也总是语带哀伤。他常常在某些时候觉得自己与她永别了。

两周之后，瑟比顿勋爵厌倦了威尼斯，决定沿海岸南下，到拉文那去，因为他听说那里的松树园里有一些重要的射猎活动。一开始，亚瑟勋爵坚决拒绝同往，不过，他钟爱的瑟比顿最终说服了他，说他如果自己待在达涅利酒店，会闷死的。15号的早上，他们借着一阵强劲的东北风，在惊涛骇浪中出发了。那项运动十分精彩，而自由的户外生活也让亚瑟勋爵的脸上又焕发了生机。可是到了22号，他又开始担忧起克莱门蒂娜夫人的事，于是不顾瑟比顿的反对，乘坐火车回到了威尼斯。

他刚刚从贡多拉中迈步出来，踏上酒店的台阶，酒店老板就拿着一沓电报迎了上来。亚瑟勋爵从他手中一把夺过电报，把它们撕开。大功告成！克莱门蒂娜夫人于17号夜里突然离世！

他首先想到的是西比尔，于是发了一封电报告诉她自己即刻赶回伦敦。接着他让贴身男仆收拾行李，连夜赶车。他支付了贡多拉船夫五倍的船费，终于怀着轻松的心情、迈着轻快的步伐回到了家，直奔起居室。起居室里有三封给他的信。一封来自西比尔，满是同情与哀悼。另外两封分别来自他的母亲和克莱门蒂娜夫人的律师。似乎那天晚上老夫人先和公爵夫人吃了饭，席间相谈甚欢，可是因为烧心难受，提早离开了。第二天早上，她被发现死在了床上，很显然走得安详，没遭罪受苦。马修·里德爵士立刻被请来，当然也是于事无补，回天乏术。她将于22号被安葬在比彻姆-查克特。她去世前几天刚刚立了遗嘱，除了将袖珍画收藏品都留给了自己的姐妹玛格丽特·拉福德夫人，紫水晶项链留给了西比尔·默顿之外，她将自己可胜街的小房子、所有的家具、个人财物、藏画等等悉数留给了亚瑟勋爵。遗产倒是不值什么，可律师曼斯菲尔德先生急切地要亚瑟勋爵尽早赶回来，因为有许多账单要支付，克莱门蒂娜夫人生前从没有理财记账的习惯。

克莱门蒂娜夫人对亚瑟勋爵的善念让他动容，他觉得波杰斯先生要为此事负很大的责任。然而他对西比尔的爱支配了其他所有情感，他认为自己履行了应尽的职责，这让他平静安宁。当他抵达查令十字街时，他感到全然的幸福。

默顿一家亲切地招待了他，西比尔让他发誓再也不会有什么东西挡在两人之间。婚礼定在6月7日。他的生活又变得光明美好起来，往日的欢乐再次回到他身边。

这天，他在克莱门蒂娜夫人的律师和西比尔的陪同下，来到可胜街的那间房子。他们烧掉了一包包褪色的信件，收拾出一抽屉一抽屉的垃圾。突然，那个年轻的女孩兴奋地叫出了声。

“你发现了什么，西比尔？”亚瑟勋爵停下手中的活儿，抬起头微笑着问道。

“这个可爱的银质小糖果盒，亚瑟。你不觉得它古雅别致、有几分荷兰风格吗？把它给我吧！我知道八十岁以前我都用不上那条紫水晶项链的。”

是那个装了乌头碱的盒子。

亚瑟勋爵吓了一跳，两颊泛红。他几乎全然忘记了自己的所作所为。对他来说，这真是奇怪的巧合：西比尔，这个让他经历那一切烦忧的人，也最先让他想起 了它。

“你当然可以拥有它，西比尔。本就是我送给可怜的克莱姆夫人的。”

“哦！谢谢你，亚瑟。这颗糖也给我吗？我都不知道克莱门蒂娜夫人喜欢吃糖。我原以为她是理性行事的人。”

亚瑟勋爵面色惨白如纸，一个可怕的念头闪过他的脑海。

“糖？西比尔，你什么意思？”他用沙哑的声音缓慢地说。

“里面有一颗糖果，只有一颗，看上去很旧，沾满了灰尘，我可一点儿也不想吃它。怎么了，亚瑟？你脸色怎么这么差？”

亚瑟勋爵快步穿过房间，抓过那个盒子。里面正是带有毒性泡沫的琥珀色胶囊。原来克莱门蒂娜夫人是寿终正寝！

这个发现令他震惊不已！他将胶囊扔进火里，一屁股坐在沙发上，发出绝望的悲声。

五

第二次推迟婚礼让默顿先生忧心忡忡，而茱莉亚夫人已经订好了参加婚礼的礼服，因此她竭力劝说西比尔断了这段姻缘。西比尔虽深爱着自己的母亲，也同样将终身托付给了亚瑟勋爵，无论茱莉亚夫人说什么都动摇不了她的信念。亚瑟勋爵自己则用了好多天才平复了巨大的沮丧，有一段时间，他处于神经衰弱的状态。然而，他绝佳的直觉决断力很快占了上风，他强健务实的大脑并没有让他陷于长久的迟疑之中。毒药计划彻底失败了，炸药或爆炸物显然值得一试。

他再次检视了一遍亲友名单，经过一番慎重考虑，他决定炸死他的舅舅，奇切斯特教长。这位学识渊博的教长酷爱钟表，收藏了一批从十五世纪到当代的精美钟表。在亚瑟勋爵看来，这位好教长的这个嗜好恰恰为他实施计划提供了绝佳的机会。当然，去哪儿搞来一套爆炸装置，那得再做打算了。《伦敦通讯簿》在这方面没有提供任何信息，而且他觉得就算去苏格兰场[11]也探听不到什么，因为在爆炸之前，他们似乎从来也搞不清楚炸药的来龙去脉，甚至炸过之后，依然一无所知。

他突然想起了他的朋友鲁沃洛夫，一个极具革命主义倾向的年轻俄国人，冬天的时候，他们曾经在温德米尔夫人家碰过面。据说鲁沃洛夫伯爵正在撰写彼得大帝的传记，来到英国是为了调研这位沙皇在此当造船工人时期的相关资料。不过人们普遍怀疑他是一名虚无主义特工。毫无疑问，俄国大使馆十分不愿意看到他出现在伦敦。亚瑟勋爵觉得他正是那个能助自己一臂之力的人。于是，亚瑟在一天早上驱车前往鲁沃洛夫位于布鲁姆斯伯里的寓所，去寻求意见和协助。

“所以您当真要投身政治？”当亚瑟勋爵道出此行目的时，鲁沃洛夫伯爵如此问道。可亚瑟勋爵讨厌任何形式的招摇，觉得有必要承认自己对社会问题没有一星半点儿的兴趣，仅仅是需要一个爆炸装置来处理一件纯粹的家务事，而这件事只牵涉他自己，无关任何其他人。

鲁沃洛夫伯爵惊诧地看了他一会儿，发觉他十分认真，于是在纸上写下一个地址，签了名，递给桌子对面的他。

“苏格兰场可是不惜代价想得到这个地址，我亲爱的朋友。”

“他们不会知道的。”亚瑟勋爵大笑着高声说道。和这个年轻的俄国人热情地握手之后，他跑下楼，看了一眼纸条，让马车夫带他去苏荷广场。

到了那儿，他让马车夫先回去，自己则步行到希腊街，最终来到一个叫贝尔庭院的地方。他穿过拱廊，走进一个奇怪的死胡同。这里显然是一家法国洗衣店，晾衣绳在房屋之间纵横交错成一张完美的大网，亚麻布在清晨的空气中飘动着。他径直走到头儿，敲了敲一所绿色小房子的门。在等人应门的空当，院子里的每一扇窗户都映出一张张模糊的窥探的脸。开门的是一个长相极其粗鄙的外国人，用一口蹩脚的英语问他有什么事。亚瑟勋爵递上鲁沃洛夫伯爵写给他的纸条。那个男人看到纸条后，鞠了一躬，将亚瑟勋爵请进了房屋底层一间破败不堪的前厅。没多久，温克尔科夫先生—在英格兰人们都这样称呼他—急匆匆地走进房间，脖子上围着沾了红酒渍的餐巾，左手还拿着一把餐叉。

“鲁沃洛夫伯爵介绍我来找您。”亚瑟勋爵鞠躬说道，“我急需和您简单聊聊，谈笔买卖。我叫史密斯，罗伯特·史密斯先生，我希望您卖给我一只能爆炸的钟表。”

“很高兴见到您，亚瑟勋爵！”和蔼可亲的小个子德国人大笑着说道，“别紧张，我的职责就是认识每一个人，我记得某个夜晚在温德米尔夫人家见过您。我希望夫人她万安！您介意坐下来陪我吃完早餐吗？有一盘上乘的美味佳肴，我那些好心的朋友们都说我的莱茵葡萄酒比他们在德国大使馆喝到的还要好。”亚瑟勋爵还没从被认出的惊讶中缓过来，发现自己已经在里屋落座了。手持铭刻着皇家纹饰的浅黄色大酒杯，小口品着最美味的莱茵白葡萄酒，亚瑟勋爵十分友好地和这位著名的阴谋家交谈起来。

“爆炸钟表，”温克尔科夫先生说道，“可不是什么海外出口的好东西，就算成功通过了海关，可火车运输太不规律，经常还没运到目的地就爆炸了。不过，如果您是想家用，我倒是可以给您提供一件绝佳的物件，效果包您满意。我能问您是要给谁用吗？如果是针对警察，或者任何与苏格兰场有关的人，我恐怕没法帮您。英国警探们真是我们的好朋友，我发现仰仗他们的愚蠢，我们可以为所欲为。我可不想让他们任何一个遭殃。”

“我向您保证，”亚瑟勋爵说，“这件事和警察绝无半点牵连。其实，这钟表是给奇切斯特教长的。”

“哎呀！亚瑟勋爵，我都不知道您对宗教有如此强烈的态度。如今已经鲜少有年轻人如此了。”

“恐怕您抬举我了，温克尔科夫先生。”亚瑟勋爵红着脸说，“事实上，我对神学一无所知。”

“那么就是一件纯粹的私人恩怨了？”

“纯粹私事。”

温克尔科夫先生耸了耸肩，离开了房间。几分钟后回来的时候，他手里多了一小块一分钱硬币大小的圆形炸药，一只精美的法式钟表，顶端是一尊镀金的自由神像，脚踏象征独裁专政的九头蛇。

亚瑟勋爵一见到它不禁面露喜色。“正是我想要的。”他大喊道，“快告诉我怎么让它爆炸。”

“啊！那是我的秘密。”温克尔科夫先生回答道，他注视着自己的发明创造，满脸是无可厚非的自豪。“告诉我您希望它什么时间爆炸，我会把这个装置设定到那个时间。”

“那么，今天是星期二，如果您能马上把它送去……”

“那可不行。我现在要为莫斯科那边的朋友处理一些重要的事情。不过，我明天倒是可以送出去。”

“哦，那时间足够了！”亚瑟勋爵礼貌地说，“如果明晚或周四一早抵达。爆炸时间，定在周五正午时分如何？那时候，教长通常会在家里。”

“星期五，正午时分。”温克尔科夫先生重复着，在壁炉旁衣柜上放着的大账本上做了大致记录。

“那么现在，”亚瑟勋爵从座位上起身说道，“请告诉我该支付您多少钱。”

“小事一桩，亚瑟勋爵，我可没打算从中牟利。那个炸药七先令六便士，钟表三镑十先令，马车费大约五先令。能为鲁沃洛夫伯爵的朋友服务，我感到万分荣幸。”

“可是劳您费了工夫，温克尔科夫先生。”

“哦，那没什么！我很乐意效劳。我工作可不是为了钱，我完全是为了我的艺术而活。”

亚瑟勋爵在桌上放了四英镑二先令六便士，向友善的小个子德国人道了谢，拒绝了下周六在某个茶会上见一些无政府主义者的邀请，然后离开了那所房子，前往帕克巷。

接下来的两天，他都处于极度兴奋的状态中。周五中午十二点，他驱车前往白金汉宫等待消息。整个下午，呆头呆脑的门厅侍者贴出来自全国各地的电报，公布赛马结果、离婚案的陪审团裁决、天气报告，诸如此类；电报机上打出下议院整晚会议的乏味细节，以及证券交易所的一小场恐慌。四点钟，各类晚报来了。亚瑟勋爵拿着《帕摩尔街报》《圣詹姆斯报》《环球报》《回声报》一头扎进了图书馆。古德柴尔德上校对此义愤填膺，他想要阅读关于他上午在伦敦市长官邸发表的一篇演讲的报道，演讲主题是南非传教以及在各省设立黑人主教的建议。而出于种种原因，他对《晚间新闻报》抱有强烈的偏见。然而，所有报纸上都没有奇切斯特的任何消息，亚瑟勋爵猜想这次尝试肯定又失败了。这对他是一次沉重的打击，他一度感到万念俱灰。第二天他去见了温克尔科夫先生。温克尔科夫先生万分诚恳地道歉，主动提出为他免费提供另一块钟表，或者以成本价卖给他一套硝化甘油炸药装置。不过亚瑟勋爵已经对爆炸彻底死心，温克尔科夫先生自己也承认，现如今什么事都掺假，连炸药都不纯。这个小个子德国人承认那个装置一定是出了什么问题，可是那个钟表还是可能会爆炸的。他举例子说，他曾经给敖德萨的军政长官送去一个气压计装置，预设在十天之后爆炸，可是三个月过去了都没动静。后来它果真爆炸了，仅仅把女仆炸得粉碎，军政长官早在六个星期以前就出城了。不过这至少证明了，虽然时间总是不准，可一旦奏效，炸药的杀伤力还是威力无穷的。亚瑟勋爵听了这些才感到一丝丝欣慰，可是这点儿希望也最终破灭了，因为两天之后，他正准备上楼时，公爵夫人把他叫到自己的房间，给他看了一封她刚刚收到的从教区发来的信。

“简的信向来写得生动。”公爵夫人说道，“你一定要读一读最近这一封，完全像穆迪送来的那些小说一样好看。”

亚瑟勋爵从她手中接过信件。内容如下：

教区，奇切斯特

5月27日

我最亲爱的姑妈：

十分感谢您为多加会[12]送来法兰绒和方格布。我非常赞同您的观点，她们想要穿漂亮衣服，这真是太荒唐了。可现如今，每一个人都如此激进，如此反宗教，很难让她们明白她们不该穿得像上流社会。我不确定我们的未来将如何。正如爸爸经常在布道时所说的，我们生活在一个没有信仰的年代。

我们这儿最近发生了一件趣事。上周四，某个匿名仰慕者给爸爸送来一只钟表。它被装在一个木头盒子里，邮资已付，寄件地址是伦敦。爸爸认为一定是某个人读了他杰出的布道文《放纵即为自由吗？》，然后送来了这东西，因为在钟表的上面是一尊女像，爸爸说她头上的帽子代表自由。我觉得它并不好看，可是爸爸说它有年头了，所以我猜想它应该还不错。帕克拆开了盒子，爸爸把钟表放在了图书室的壁炉架上。星期五早上我们都坐在那里，当钟表指针指向十二点的时候，我们听到嗡嗡的一声，人像底座冒出一小股烟，自由女神掉了下来，撞上壁炉挡板，撞坏了鼻子！玛丽亚吓了一大跳，可是当时太可笑了，詹姆斯和我不禁大笑起来，甚至连爸爸都被逗乐了。我们上前检查，才发现它其实是一只闹钟，如果你把它设定在某一时刻，然后在一个小锤子下面放些火药和一个小火帽，它可以在你预设的时刻爆炸。爸爸说它会产生噪声，不能放在图书室，因此雷吉把它带去了讲堂。它一点儿用处都没有，就是成天到晚地小规模爆炸。你觉得亚瑟会想要一个作为结婚礼物吗？我觉得它们在伦敦算是时鲜的玩意儿。爸爸说它们其实寓意深远，表明自由不能长久，最终会坠落。爸爸还说自由是在法国大革命时期被发明出来的。真是糟透了！

我现在得去多加会了，去给她们朗读您启迪心灵的书信。亲爱的姑妈，您说得太对了，她们这个阶层就应该穿一些简朴的衣服。我必须说，她们愁穿戴这件事真是太荒唐了，毕竟在这个世界上，在未来的日子里，还有那么多更加重要的事情。我很高兴您那件印花底绸效果很好，蕾丝花边都没坏。我打算在星期三的主教学校穿您送给我的那件黄缎子，我想看上去一定很不错。您会佩戴蝴蝶结吗？詹宁斯说如今每个人都佩戴蝴蝶结，而且衬裙要有荷叶边。雷吉那边又爆炸了，爸爸命令他把钟表送去马厩。我觉得爸爸不像刚开始那么喜欢它了，尽管有人送来这么一件漂亮精巧的玩具还是令他颇为受用的，至少说明人们读了他的布道文，并从中受益。

爸爸让我问候您，还有詹姆斯、雷吉和玛丽亚都问您好。希望塞西尔姑父痛风的毛病好些了。相信我，亲爱的姑妈，永远爱您的侄女。

简·佩尔西

又及，记得回答我蝴蝶结的问题，詹宁斯非说这是现在的时尚。

公爵夫人因为这封信大笑不已，亚瑟勋爵对着它却面色凝重，十分不快。

“我亲爱的亚瑟，”她大声说道，“我再也不会给你看年轻女士的信了！可是对于那只钟表我真是无话可说。我想它是一件伟大的发明，我自己也应该拥有一只。”

“我可没什么兴趣。”亚瑟勋爵苦笑着说道。他亲吻了母亲，然后离开了房间。

上楼以后，他瘫坐在沙发上，满眼噙泪。他殚精竭虑地去完成这桩谋杀，可两次都失败了，而且错都不在他。他已经努力去履行自己的责任了，可命运女神似乎背叛了他。他因为良愿无法达成而烦忧，因为徒劳无功而烦忧。或许，彻底取消这场婚姻更好一些。西比尔会痛苦，没错，可是这痛苦并不会真的毁掉她高洁的本质。至于他自己，有什么关系呢？人终有一死，既然生无可恋，死亦无惧。就让命运主宰厄运吧，他也不费力去帮命运女神了。

七点半，他穿好衣服去俱乐部。瑟比顿正在那儿和年轻的人们开派对。他被迫留下来和他们共进晚餐。他们琐碎的闲谈和无聊的笑话实在提不起他的兴趣，上咖啡的时候，他谎称自己还有约会，先行离开了。他刚一走出俱乐部，侍者就递给他一封信。信来自温克尔科夫先生，邀请他第二天晚上屈尊前去看一个只要一打开就会爆炸的雨伞。这是最新的发明，刚刚从日内瓦运来。他把信撕得粉碎。他已经下定决心不再做任何尝试。然后他游逛到泰晤士河堤岸，在河边坐了几个小时。月亮从鬃毛一般的黄褐色的云团间透出头，仿佛是一只狮子的眼睛；空洞无边的苍穹中数不清的星光闪烁，仿佛在紫色的穹顶上撒满了金粉；偶尔，一只驳船摇荡着进入混浊的水流，随着起落的潮水漂远；铁路信号灯由绿变红，火车呼啸着驶过大桥。过了一会儿，威斯敏斯特高塔上发出十二点的低沉的钟声，每一声洪亮的钟声都仿佛让黑夜震颤。接着，火车信号灯熄灭了，一盏孤零零的路灯发出柔弱的光，就像是一根巨大的船桅杆上镶嵌着一颗硕大的红宝石。喧嚣的城市渐渐沉寂。

凌晨两点，他站起身，漫步去黑衣修士桥。一切看起来多么不真实！多像是一场奇怪的梦！河对岸的房子似乎建在黑暗中。人们会说银光黑影重新装点了这个世界。圣保罗教堂的大屋顶若隐若现，就像是朦胧天空中的一个气泡。

他走到克利奥帕特拉方尖碑[13]的附近，见一个男人正靠在矮墙上。等他再走近一些，那个男人抬起了头，煤气灯光照亮了他的整张脸。

是波杰斯先生，那个手相师！谁都不会认错那张松弛的胖脸，那副金丝眼镜，那个苍白无力的微笑，那张魅惑的巧嘴。

亚瑟勋爵停下脚步。一个机智的念头闪过他的脑海，他悄无声息地来到他的身后。说时迟，那时快，他一把抓住波杰斯先生的双腿，把他丢进了泰晤士河。一声粗俗的咒骂和一片重重的水花飞溅之后，一切归于平静。亚瑟勋爵紧张地观望，看不到那个手相师的踪迹，只有一顶高帽在月光照耀下的河水中随漩涡旋转着。过了一会儿，高帽也沉了，再寻不到波杰斯先生的任何踪迹。他一度以为大桥楼梯上一个身形高大的怪异的人看到了他，一股挫败的恐怖感笼罩了他。不过后来他发现那只是一个倒影，当月亮从云后面出来，它就消失不见了。终于，他似乎完成了命运的裁决。他长长地舒了一口气，如释重负，嘴边呢喃着西比尔的名字。

“您丢了什么东西吗，先生？”一个声音突然出现在他身后。

他转过身，看到一个手持牛眼灯的警察。

“没什么重要的，警察先生。”他微笑着回答。他招呼了一辆路过的马车，跳上去，让车夫驶往贝尔格雷夫广场。

接下来的几天，他在希望与恐惧之间煎熬。有时候，他期待波杰斯先生走进房间；有时候，他又觉得命运不该对他如此不公。他去了两次西月街手相师的住处，可是没勇气按响门铃。他希望得到确信，又害怕它。

它终于来了。他正坐在俱乐部的吸烟室喝茶，心不在焉地听着瑟比顿描述狂欢会上最后一首滑稽歌曲，侍者拿着晚报走进来。他拿起《圣詹姆斯报》，百无聊赖地翻看，一个奇怪的标题引起了他的注意：

一名手相师的自杀

他赶紧读起来，脸色因为兴奋而变得苍白。文章是这样写的：

昨天早上七点钟，著名手相师塞普蒂默斯·R.波杰斯先生的尸体被冲刷上了船坞酒店前的格林威治河岸。这位不幸的先生已经失踪数日，手相圈已经开始担心他的安危。据推测，他由于劳累过度，引发暂时性精神错乱，进而选择了自杀，今天下午验尸陪审团也证实了这一推断。波杰斯先生刚刚完成了一篇主题为“人类手相”的优秀论文，将于不久后发表，届时必将引发广泛关注。逝者六十五岁，似乎没有任何亲眷在世。

亚瑟勋爵拿着报纸冲出俱乐部，门厅侍者惊诧万分，企图拦住他，却是徒劳。他立刻乘车赶往帕克巷。西比尔透过窗户看到了他，感觉到他似乎带来了什么好消息。她跑下楼去迎接他，当她看到他的脸，她知道云开雾散了。

“我亲爱的西比尔，”亚瑟勋爵大喊道，“我们明天就结婚吧！”

“你这个傻瓜！急什么？蛋糕都没订呢！”西比尔说着，眼眶含泪，笑逐颜开。

六

大约三个星期之后，他们举行了婚礼，圣彼得教堂挤满了身着锦衣华服的人。奇切斯特教长极其郑重庄严地主持了婚礼仪式，所有人都承认他们从没见过比这对新人更漂亮的夫妻。然而，不只是漂亮，他们还非常幸福。亚瑟勋爵从未曾有一时半刻后悔他为西比尔所承受的一切苦楚，而她也给予了他一个女人可以给予男人的最好的东西—崇拜、温柔，还有爱。对于他们而言，现实没有扼杀情爱。他们一直感到年轻。

几年之后，他们有了两个漂亮的孩子。温德米尔夫人来到奥尔顿修道院探望他们。奥尔顿修道院是个可爱的老房子，是公爵送给儿子的结婚礼物。一天下午，她正和亚瑟夫人坐在花园里的酸橙树下，看着小男孩和小女孩像是跃动的阳光一般在玫瑰小径上蹦蹦跳跳。她突然握住女主人的手，问道：“你幸福吗，西比尔？”

“亲爱的温德米尔夫人，我当然幸福。您呢？”

“我没时间幸福，西比尔。我总会喜欢新结识的人。我一旦和谁变得熟识，就会对他们厌烦。”

“您的狮子们也无法取悦您吗，温德米尔夫人？”

“哦，当然不能！狮子的趣味超不过一季。一旦它们的狮鬃被剪掉，它们就变成了世界上最无聊的东西。而且，如果你对它们非常好，它们就得寸进尺起来。你记得那个讨人厌的波杰斯先生吗？他是个大骗子。当然，我全然不在意，甚至当他想向我借钱的时候，我都原谅了他，但我无法忍受他向我求爱。他让我打心底里厌恶手相学。我现在相信传心术。那可好玩儿多了！”

“您可别在这儿说任何手相学的不好，温德米尔夫人。这是唯一一个亚瑟不喜欢别人打趣的话题。我向您保证，他是很认真的。”

“你不会告诉我他信手相学吧，西比尔？”

“您自己问他，温德米尔夫人，他来了。”亚瑟勋爵手捧着一大束黄玫瑰出现在花园中，他的两个孩子绕着他嬉闹。

“亚瑟勋爵？”

“什么事，温德米尔夫人？”

“别告诉我你相信手相学？”

“我当然相信啊。”那个年轻的男子微笑着说。

“可是，为什么呢？”

“因为我毕生的幸福都多亏了手相学。”他低声说着，坐到柳条椅上。

“我亲爱的亚瑟勋爵，它给了你什么？”

“西比尔。”他边回答，边将那束玫瑰献给妻子，并深深凝望着她紫色的眼睛。

“胡说八道！”温德米尔夫人大声说道，“我这辈子都没听过这种胡话！”

[1]西方手相学术语，掌纹名称，被认为与人的想象、创造、本能等相关。（说明：文中脚注均为译者注。）

[2]帕拉斯即为雅典娜，古希腊神话中的战争与智慧女神。

[3]莎士比亚剧作《哈姆雷特》中的角色。

[4]莎士比亚剧作《亨利四世》中的角色。

[5]英国于1663年到1814年间铸造并发行的货币名称。

[6]古希腊维奥蒂亚城邦中雅典以北的一个城镇和自治区，距离底比斯不远，在古代因为以此地名命名的女像小陶俑而闻名。

[7]15世纪和16世纪欧洲极具影响力的西班牙裔意大利贵族，因为犯罪、通奸、贿赂、乱伦、谋杀等一系列丑闻而臭名昭著。

[8]克莱门蒂娜的简称。

[9]托马斯·谢拉顿（Thomas Sheraton，1751—1806）是18世纪英国最著名的家具设计师与家具生产商之一，此处指谢拉顿风格的家具。

[10]顺势疗法是德国医生塞缪尔·哈内曼（Samuel Hahnemann，1755—1843）于1796年创立的替代治疗方法，声称如果某些物质能够引发健康人身体的某种症状，那么这些物质就可以治疗产生同样症状的病人的疾病，类似我们俗称的“以毒攻毒”。

[11]伦敦地区警察机关的名称，多用于代指伦敦警察厅。

[12]由基督教教会发起的慈善团体，目的是向穷人提供衣物援助。

[13]位于伦敦地区威斯敏斯特市的方尖大石碑。1819年，埃及统治者为了纪念尼罗河战役和亚历山大战役的胜利，将其赠予英国。

伊凡·伊里奇之死

一

在法院大厦里，当梅尔文斯基案审讯暂停时，法官和检察官都聚集在伊凡·叶果罗维奇·谢贝克的办公室里，谈论着闹得满城风雨的克拉索夫案件。费多尔·瓦西里耶维奇情绪激动，认为此案不属本院审理范围；伊凡·叶果罗维奇坚持相反意见；彼得·伊凡内奇一开始就没加入争论，始终不过问此事，而是翻阅着刚送来的《公报》。

“诸位！”他说，“伊凡·伊里奇死了。”

“真的吗？”

“喏，您看吧！”他对费多尔·瓦西里耶维奇说，同时把那份散发出油墨味的刚出版的《公报》递给他。

公报上印着一则带黑框的讣告：“普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜·高洛文娜沉痛哀告亲友，先夫伊凡·伊里奇·高洛文法官于1882年2月4日逝世。兹定于礼拜五下午一时出殡。”

伊凡·伊里奇是在座几位先生的同事，大家都喜欢他。他病了几个礼拜，据说患的是不治之症。他生病以来职位还给他保留着，但大家早就推测过，他死后将由阿历克谢耶夫接替，而阿历克谢耶夫的位置则将由文尼科夫或施塔别尔接替。因此，一听到伊凡·伊里奇的死讯，办公室里在座的人首先想到的就是，他一死对他们本人和亲友在职位调动和升迁上会有什么影响。

“这下子我很可能弄到施塔别尔或文尼科夫的位置，”费多尔·瓦西里耶维奇想，“这个位置早就说好给我了，而这样一提升，我就可以在车马费之外每年净增加八百卢布收入。”

“这下子我可以申请把内弟从卡卢加调来。”彼得·伊凡内奇想，“妻子一定会很高兴的。如今她可不能再说我不关心她家的人了。”

“我早就想到，他这一病恐怕起不来了，”彼得·伊凡内奇说，“真可怜！”

“他究竟害的是什么病啊？”

“几个医生都说不准。或者说，各有各的说法。我最后一次看见他，还以为他会好起来呢。”

“自从过节以来我就没有去看过他，去是一直想去的。”

“那么，他有财产吗？”

“他妻子手里大概有一点，但很有限。”

“是啊，应该去看看她。他们住得太远。”

“从您那儿去是很远。您到什么地方去都很远。”

“嘿，我住在河对岸，他总是有意见。”彼得·伊凡内奇笑眯眯地瞧着谢贝克说道。大家又说了一通城市太大、市内各区距离太远之类的话，然后回到法庭上。

伊凡·伊里奇的死讯使每个人不由得推测，人事上会因此发生什么变动，同时照例使认识他的人都暗自庆幸：“还好，死的是他，不是我。”

“嘿，他死了，可我没有死。”人人都这样想，或者有这样的感觉。伊凡·伊里奇的知交，他的所谓朋友，都同时不由自主地想，这下子他们得遵循习俗，参加丧礼，慰问遗孀了。

费多尔·瓦西里耶维奇和彼得·伊凡内奇是伊凡·伊里奇最知心的朋友。

彼得·伊凡内奇跟伊凡·伊里奇在法学院时是同学，自认为受过伊凡·伊里奇的恩惠。

午饭时，彼得·伊凡内奇把伊凡·伊里奇的死讯告诉了妻子，同时讲了争取把内弟调到本区的想法。饭后他没休息，就穿上礼服，乘车到伊凡·伊里奇家里去了。

伊凡·伊里奇家门口停着一辆自备轿车和两辆出租马车。在前厅衣帽架旁的墙上，靠着带穗子和擦得闪闪发亮的金银饰带的棺盖。两位穿黑衣的太太在这里脱去皮外套。其中一位是伊凡·伊里奇的姐姐，彼得·伊凡内奇认识她；另一位没有见过面。彼得·伊凡内奇的同事施瓦尔茨从楼上下来，一看见他进门，就站住向他使了个眼色，仿佛在说：“伊凡·伊里奇真没出息，咱们可不至于如此。”

施瓦尔茨脸上留着英国式络腮胡子，瘦长的身体穿着礼服，照例表现出一种典雅庄重的气派，但这同他天生的顽皮性格不协调，因此显得很滑稽。彼得·伊凡内奇心里有这样的感觉。

彼得·伊凡内奇让太太们先走，自己则慢吞吞地跟着她们上楼。施瓦尔茨在楼梯顶上站住，没有下来。彼得·伊凡内奇懂得施瓦尔茨的用意：他想跟他约定，今晚到什么地方去打桥牌。太太们上楼向孀妇屋里走去；施瓦尔茨却一本正经地抿着厚嘴唇，眼睛里露出戏谑的神气，挤挤眉向彼得·伊凡内奇示意，死人在右边房间。

彼得·伊凡内奇进去时照例有点困惑，不知做什么好。但有一点他很清楚，凡是到这种场合，画十字总是不会错的。至于要不要同时鞠躬，他可没有把握，因此选择了个折中的办法：他走进屋里，动手画十字，同时微微点头，好像在鞠躬。在画十字和点头时，他向屋子里偷偷环顾了一下。有两个青年和一个中学生，大概是伊凡·伊里奇的侄儿们，正一面画十字，一面从屋子里出来。一个老妇人一动不动地站在那里。一个眉毛弯得出奇的女人在对她低声说话。诵经士身穿法衣，精神饱满，神态严峻，大声念着什么，脸上表现出神圣不可侵犯的样子，充当餐室侍仆的庄稼汉盖拉西姆蹑手蹑脚地从彼得·伊凡内奇面前走过，把什么东西撒在地板上。彼得·伊凡内奇一看见这情景，立刻闻到淡淡的腐尸臭。他上次探望伊凡·伊里奇时，在书房里看到过这个庄稼汉。当时他在护理伊凡·伊里奇，伊凡·伊里奇特别喜爱他。彼得·伊凡内奇一直画着十字，向棺材、诵经士和屋角桌上的圣像微微鞠躬。后来，他觉得十字已画得够了，就停下来打量死人。

死人躺在那里，也像一般死人那样，显得特别沉重，僵硬的四肢陷在棺材衬垫里，脑袋高高地靠在枕头上，蜡黄的前额高高隆起，半秃的两鬓凹进去，高耸的鼻子仿佛压迫着上唇。同彼得·伊凡内奇上次看见他时相比，他的模样大变了，身体更瘦了，但他的脸也像一般死人那样，比生前好看，显得端庄。脸上的神态似乎表示，他已尽了责任，而且尽得很周到。此外，那神态还好像在责备活人或者提醒他们什么事。彼得·伊凡内奇却觉得没有什么事需要提醒他，至少没有事跟他有关系。他心里有点不快，就又匆匆画了个十字——他自己也觉得这个十字画得太快，未免有点失礼——转身往门口走去。施瓦尔茨宽宽地叉开两腿站在穿堂里等他，双手在背后玩弄着大礼帽。彼得·伊凡内奇瞧了瞧服饰雅致、模样顽皮可笑的施瓦尔茨，顿时精神振作起来。他知道施瓦尔茨性格开朗，不会受这里哀伤气氛的影响。他那副神气仿佛表示：伊凡·伊里奇的丧事绝没有理由破坏他们的例会，也就是说不能妨碍他们今天晚上就拆开一副新牌，在仆人点亮的四支新蜡烛照耀下打牌。总之，这次丧事不能影响他们今晚快乐的聚会。他就把这个想法低声告诉从旁边走过的彼得·伊凡内奇，并建议今晚到费多尔·瓦西里耶维奇家打牌。不过，彼得·伊凡内奇今天显然没有打牌的运气。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜同几位太太从内室出来了。她身材矮胖，尽管千方百计要自己消瘦，可是肩膀以下的部分却一个劲儿向横里发展。她穿一身黑衣，头上包一块花边头巾，眉毛像站在棺材旁那个女人一样弯得出奇。她把她们送到灵堂门口，说：“马上要做丧事礼拜了，你们请进。”

施瓦尔茨微微点头站住，显得犹豫不决，是不是接受这个邀请。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜认出彼得·伊凡内奇，叹了一口气，走到他跟前，握住他的手说：“我知道您是伊凡·伊里奇的知心朋友……”她说到这里对他瞧瞧，等待他听了这话后做出相应的反应。彼得·伊凡内奇知道，既然刚才应该画十字，那么这会儿就得握手，叹气，说一句：“真是想不到！”他就这样做了。做了以后，他发觉达到了预期的效果：他感动了，她也感动了。

“现在那边还没有开始，您来一下，我有话要跟您说，”孀妇说，“您扶着我。”

彼得·伊凡内奇伸出手臂挽住她，他们向内室走去。经过施瓦尔茨身边时，施瓦尔茨失望地向彼得·伊凡内奇使了个眼色。“唉，牌打不成了！要是我们另外找到搭档，您可别怪我们。要是您能脱身，五人一起玩也行。”他那淘气的目光仿佛在这么说。

彼得·伊凡内奇更深沉更悲伤地叹了口气，普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜便感激地捏了捏他的手臂。他们走进灯光暗淡、挂着玫瑰红花布窗帘的客厅，在桌旁坐下来：她坐在沙发上，彼得·伊凡内奇坐在弹簧损坏、凳面凹陷的矮沙发凳上。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜想叫他换一把椅子坐，可是觉得此刻说这些话不得体，就作罢了。彼得·伊凡内奇坐到沙发凳上时，想起伊凡·伊里奇当年装饰这客厅时曾同他商量，最后决定用这种带绿叶的玫瑰红花布做窗帘和沙发套。客厅里摆满家具杂物，孀妇走过时，她那件黑斗篷的黑花边在雕花桌上挂住了。彼得·伊凡内奇欠起身，想帮她解开斗篷，沙发凳一摆脱负担，里面的弹簧立刻蹦起来，往他身上弹。孀妇自己解开斗篷，彼得·伊凡内奇又坐下来，把跳动的弹簧重新压下去。但孀妇没有把斗篷完全解开，彼得·伊凡内奇又欠起身，弹簧又往上蹦，还噔地响了一声。等这一切都过去了，她拿出一块洁净的麻纱手绢，哭起来。斗篷钩住和沙发凳的弹簧蹦跳这些插曲使彼得·伊凡内奇冷静下来，他皱紧眉头坐着。这当儿，伊凡·伊里奇的男仆索科洛夫走进来，把这种尴尬局面打破了。他报告普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜，她指定的那块坟地要价两百卢布。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜止住哭，可怜巴巴地瞟了一眼彼得·伊凡内奇，用法语说她的日子很难过。彼得·伊凡内奇默默地做了个手势，表示他深信她说的是实话。

“您请抽烟。”她用宽宏大量而又极其悲痛的语气说，然后同索科洛夫谈坟地的价钱。彼得·伊凡内奇一面吸烟，一面听她怎样详细询问坟地的价格，最后决定买哪一块。谈完坟地，她又吩咐索科洛夫去请唱诗班。索科洛夫走了。

“什么事都是我自己料理。”她对彼得·伊凡内奇说，把桌上的照相簿挪到一边。接着发现烟灰快掉到桌上，连忙把烟灰碟推到彼得·伊凡内奇面前，嘴里说：“要是说我悲伤得不能做事，那未免有点做作。相反，现在只有为他的后事多操点心，我才感到安慰……至少可以排遣点悲伤。”她掏出手绢，又要哭，但突然勉强忍住，打起精神，镇静地说：“我有点事要跟您谈谈。”

彼得·伊凡内奇点点头，不让他身下蠢蠢欲动的沙发弹簧再蹦起来。

“最后几天他真是难受。”

“非常难受吗？”彼得·伊凡内奇问。

“唉，太可怕了！他不停地叫嚷，不是一连几分钟，而是一连几个钟头。三天三夜嚷个不停。实在叫人受不了。我真不懂我这是怎么熬过来的。隔着三道门都听得见他的叫声。唉，我这是怎么熬过来的哟！”

“当时他神志清醒吗？”彼得·伊凡内奇问。

“清醒，”她喃喃地说，“直到最后一分钟都清醒。他在临终前一刻钟跟我们告了别，还叫我们把伏洛嘉带开。”

彼得·伊凡内奇想到，他那么熟识的这个人，原先是个快乐的孩子，小学生，后来成了他的同事，最后竟受到这样的折磨。尽管他觉得自己和这个女人都有点做作，但想到这一点，心里却十分恐惧。他又看见那个前额和那个压住嘴唇的鼻子，不禁感到不寒而栗。

“三天三夜极度的痛苦，然后死去。这种情况也可能随时落到我的头上。”他想，刹那间感到毛骨悚然。但是，他自己也不知怎的，一种常有的想法很快就使他镇静下来：“这种事只有伊凡·伊里奇会碰上，我可绝不会碰上。这种事不应该也不可能落到我的头上。”他想到这些，心情忧郁，但施瓦尔茨分明向他做过暗示，他不该有这种心情。彼得·伊凡内奇思考了一下，镇静下来，详细询问伊凡·伊里奇临终前的情况，仿佛这种事故只会发生在伊凡·伊里奇身上，可绝不会发生在他身上。

在谈了一通伊凡·伊里奇肉体上所受非人痛苦的情况以后（这种痛苦，彼得·伊凡内奇是从普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜神经所受的影响上领会的），孀妇显然认为该转到正题上了。

“唉，彼得·伊凡内奇，真是难受，真是太难受了，太难受了。”她又哭起来。

彼得·伊凡内奇叹着气，等她擦去鼻涕眼泪，才说：“真是想不到……”

接着她又说起来，说到了显然是她找他来的主要问题。她问他，丈夫去世后要怎样向政府申请抚恤金。她装作向彼得·伊凡内奇请教，怎样领取赡养费，不过他看得出，因丈夫去世她可以向政府弄到多少钱，这事她已经了解得清清楚楚，比他知道得还清楚。她不过是想知道，可不可以通过什么办法弄到更多的钱。彼得·伊凡内奇竭力思索，想到几种办法，但最后只是出于礼节骂了一通政府的吝啬，说不可能弄到更多的钱了。于是她叹了一口气，显然是要摆脱这位来客。他理会了，就摁灭香烟，站起身，同孀妇握了握手，走到前厅。

餐厅里摆着伊凡·伊里奇十分得意地从旧货店买来的大钟。彼得·伊凡内奇在那里遇见神父和几个来参加丧事礼拜的客人，还看见一位熟识的美丽小姐，就是伊凡·伊里奇的女儿。她穿一身黑衣，腰身本来很苗条，如今似乎变得更苗条了。她的神态忧郁、冷淡，甚至还有点愤慨。她向彼得·伊凡内奇鞠躬，但那副神气显出仿佛他有什么过错似的。女儿后面站着一个同样面带愠色的青年。彼得·伊凡内奇认识他是法院侦讯官，家里很有几个钱，而且听说是她的未婚夫。彼得·伊凡内奇沮丧地向他们点点头，正要往死人房间走去，这时楼梯下出现了逝者在中学念书的儿子。这孩子活脱就是年轻时的伊凡·伊里奇。彼得·伊凡内奇记得伊凡·伊里奇在法学院念书时就是这个模样。这孩子眼睛里含着泪水，神态也像那些十三四岁的愣小子。他一看见彼得·伊凡内奇，就忧郁而害臊地皱起眉头。彼得·伊凡内奇向他点点头，走进灵堂。丧事礼拜开始了：又是蜡烛，又是呻吟，又是神香，又是眼泪，又是啜泣。彼得·伊凡内奇皱紧眉头站着，眼睛瞅着自己的双脚。他一眼也不看死人，直到礼拜结束他的心情都没有受悲伤气氛的影响，并且第一个走出灵堂。前厅里一个人也没有。充任餐厅侍仆的庄稼汉盖拉西姆从灵堂奔出来，用他那双强壮的手臂努力地在一排外套中间翻寻着，终于把彼得·伊凡内奇的外套找出来，递给他。

“嗯，盖拉西姆老弟，你说呢？”彼得·伊凡内奇想说句话应酬一下，“可怜不可怜哪？”

“这是上帝的意思！我们都要到那里去的。”盖拉西姆露出一排洁白整齐的庄稼汉的牙齿，说完就像在紧张地干活那样猛地推开门，大声呼喊马车夫，把彼得·伊凡内奇送上车，又奔回台阶上，仿佛在考虑还有些什么事要做。

在闻过神香、尸体和石碳酸的臭味以后，彼得·伊凡内奇特别爽快地吸了一大口新鲜空气。

“上哪儿，老爷？”马车夫问。

“不晚。还可以到费多尔·瓦西里耶维奇家去一下。”

彼得·伊凡内奇就去了。果然，他到的时候，第一局牌刚结束，因此他就顺当地成了第五名赌客。

二

伊凡·伊里奇的身世极其普通、极其简单而又极其可怕。

他是个法官，去世时才四十五岁。他父亲是彼得堡一名官员，曾在好几个政府机关任职，虽不能胜任某些要职，但凭着他的资格和身份，从没被逐出官场，因此总能弄到一些有名无实的官职和六千到一万卢布的有名有实的年俸，并一直享受到晚年。

伊里亚·叶斐莫维奇·高洛文就是这样一个多余机关里的多余的三等文官。

他有三个儿子。伊凡·伊里奇排行第二。老大像他父亲一样官运亨通，不过在另一个机关，也快到领干薪的年龄。老三没有出息。他在几个地方都败坏了名声，眼下在铁路上供职。父亲也好，两位哥哥也好，特别是两位嫂子，不仅不愿同他见面，而且非万不得已从不会想到有他这样一个兄弟。姐姐嫁给了格列夫男爵，他同他岳父一样是彼得堡的官员。伊凡·伊里奇是家里所谓的佼佼者[1]。他不像老大那样冷淡古板，也不像老三那样放荡不羁。他介于他们之间：聪明，活泼，乐观，文雅。他跟弟弟一起在法学院念过书。老三没有毕业，念到五年级就被学校开除了；伊凡·伊里奇则毕了业，而且成绩优良。他在法学院里就显示了后来终生具备的特点：能干，乐观，厚道，随和，但又能严格履行自认为应尽的责任，而他心目中的责任就是达官贵人所公认的职责。他从小不会巴结拍马，成年后还是不善于阿谀奉承，但从青年时代起就像飞蛾扑火那样追随上层人士，模仿他们的一举一动，接受他们的人生观，并同他们交朋友。童年时代和少年时代的热情在他身上消失得干干净净。他开始迷恋声色，追逐功名，最后发展到了自由放纵的地步。不过，他的本性还能使他保持一定分寸，不至于过分逾越常规。

在法学院里，他认为自己的有些行为很卑劣，因此很嫌恶自己。但后来看到地位比他高的人都在那样干，而且并不认为卑劣，他也就不以为意，不再把它们放在心上，即使想到也无动于衷。伊凡·伊里奇在法学院毕业，获得十等文官官衔，从父亲手里领到治装费，在著名的沙尔玛裁缝铺里定制了服装，表坠上挂一块刻着“高瞻远瞩”[2]的纪念章，向导师和任校董的亲王辞了行，跟同学们在唐农大饭店欢宴话别，带着从最高级商店买来的时式手提箱、衬衣、西服、剃刀、梳妆用品和旅行毛毯，走马上任，当了省长特派员。这个官职是他父亲替他谋得的。伊凡·伊里奇到了外省，很快就像在法学院那样过得称心如意。他奉公守法，兢兢业业，生活得欢快而又不失体统。他有时奉命到各县视察，待人接物稳重得体，对上待下恰如其分，不贪赃枉法，而且总能圆满完成上司交下的差事，主要是处理好分裂派教徒事件。他虽然年轻放荡，但处理公务却异常审慎，甚至可以说是铁面无私；在社交场中，他活泼风趣而又和蔼有礼，正像他的上司和上司太太——他是他们家的常客——称赞他的那样，是个好小子[3]。他同省里一位死缠住他这个风流法学家的太太有暧昧关系；还同一个女裁缝私通；有时同巡察的副官们狂饮欢宴，饭后还去花街柳巷寻欢作乐。他奉承上级长官，甚至长官夫人，手法高明，无懈可击，从未引起非议，人家至多说一句法国谚语：年轻时放荡在所难免。这一切他都干得体体面面，嘴里说的又是法国话，主要则是因为他跻身在最上层，Thnbsp；容易博得达官显贵的青睐。伊凡·伊里奇就这样干了五年。接着他的工作调动了，因为成立了新的司法机关，需要新的官员。

于是伊凡·伊里奇就调任了这样的新职。

伊凡·伊里奇被推荐任法院侦讯官的职务，他接受了，虽然这位置在另一个省里，因此他得放弃原有的各种关系，另起炉灶，重新结交朋友。朋友们给伊凡·伊里奇饯行，同他一起拍照，还赠给他一个银烟盒留念。那之后，他便走马上任去了。

伊凡·伊里奇当法院侦讯官同样循规蹈矩[4]，公私分明，并且像做特派员一样受到普遍尊敬。对伊凡·伊里奇来说，侦讯官的工作比原来的工作有趣得多，迷人得多。以前让他感到扬扬得意的是，身穿精工缝制的文官制服，昂首阔步地经过战战兢兢等待接见的来访者和对他羡慕不已的官员们面前，一直走进长官办公室，并且跟长官一起喝茶吸烟；但那时直接听命于他的人，只有县警察局的局长和分裂派教徒，而且还是要在他奉命出差的时候。他对待他们总是客客气气，使他们感到，他尽管操着生杀大权，却平易近人，毫无架子。那个时候，这样直接听命于他的人不多。如今伊凡·伊里奇当上法院侦讯官，他懂得就连达官贵人的命运也都操在他手里，他只要在公文上批几句，随便哪个要人都会成为被告或证人来到他面前，并且得站着回答他的问题，如果他不请他坐下的话。伊凡·伊里奇从不滥用权力，相反总是不露锋芒，而这种权力的意识和适当用权的技术，就成了他担任新职后最感兴趣的事。从事这项新职，也就是说审查工作，伊凡·伊里奇很快就掌握了一种本领，能排除一切与本案无关的情节，使各种错综复杂的案情在公文上表现得简单明了，不带丝毫个人意见，完全符合公文要求。这是一项新的工作，而伊凡·伊里奇则属于第一批执行1864年新法典的人。

自从在新地方就任法院侦讯官以来，伊凡·伊里奇结交了一批新朋友，建立了一些新关系，获得了新的社会地位，并多少采取了新作风。他在省里同政府保持一定距离，却周旋于司法界头面人物和豪门巨富之间，对当局稍表不满，发表温和的自由主义言论和开明观点。此外，伊凡·伊里奇就任新职后仍旧讲究服饰，注意仪表，只是不再刮去下巴颏上的胡子而任其自然生长。

伊凡·伊里奇在新地方过得很愉快。他跟一批反对省长的人关系很好；薪俸比以前优厚；他逢场作戏，打打纸牌，以增添乐趣。他头脑聪敏，很会打牌，因此常常赢钱。

伊凡·伊里奇在新地方任职两年后遇见了后来成为他妻子的普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜·米海尔。她是伊凡·伊里奇出入的圈子里最迷人最伶俐最出色的姑娘。伊凡·伊里奇在办公之余，找点消遣，其中就包括同普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜戏谑调情。

伊凡·伊里奇任特派员时常常跳舞，但当上侦讯官后就难得跳了。如今他跳舞只是为了要显示，尽管他身为侦讯官和五等文官，跳舞水平可绝不比别人差。有时晚会将近结束，他就请普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜一起跳舞，主要借这种机会去征服普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜的心。她爱上了他。伊凡·伊里奇并没有明确想到要结婚，但既然人家姑娘爱上了他，他就问自己：“是啊，那么何不就结婚呢？”

普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜出身望族，长得不错，而且小有家产。伊凡·伊里奇可以指望找到一个更出色的配偶，但这个配偶也不错。

伊凡·伊里奇自己有薪俸收入，他希望她也有同样多的进款。她出身名门，又生得温柔美丽，很有教养。说伊凡·伊里奇同她结婚，是因为爱上这位小姐，并且发觉她的人生观同他一致，那不符合事实。说他结婚，是因为在他的圈子里大家都赞成这门婚事，那同样不符合事实。伊凡·伊里奇结婚是出于双重考虑：娶这样一位妻子是幸福的，而达官贵人们又都赞成这门亲事。

伊凡·伊里奇就这样结了婚。

在准备结婚和婚后初期，夫妻恩爱，妻子尚未怀孕，再加上崭新的家具，崭新的餐具，崭新的衣服，日子过得很美满。伊凡·伊里奇认为他原来的生活轻松愉快而又高尚体面，并且受到上流社会的赞许，如今结婚不仅不会损害这种生活，而且使它更加美满。但在妻子怀孕几个月后，出现了一种痛苦难堪而有失体统的新局面，那是他万万没有料到的，而且怎么也无法摆脱。

伊凡·伊里奇认为妻子完全是出于任性[5]，破坏了快乐体面的生活，莫名其妙地动辄猜疑，要求他更加体贴她。不论什么事她都横加挑剔，动不动就对他大吵大闹。

起初伊凡·伊里奇想继续用快乐体面的人生态度来排除烦恼。他不管妻子的情绪，照旧高高兴兴地过日子：请朋友到家里来打牌，自己上俱乐部或者到朋友家串门子。可是有一次妻子气势汹汹地对他破口大骂。这以后只要他稍不顺她的意，她就把他臭骂一顿，显然非把他制服不可，也就是说要他安守在家里，并且像她一样唉声叹气，无病呻吟，这使伊凡·伊里奇感到心惊胆战。他懂得了，夫妇生活，至少是他同妻子的生活，并不能始终维持快乐和体面，相反，这样的气氛常常会被损害，因此必须设法防范。伊凡·伊里奇借口公务繁忙，来对付普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜。他发现这种办法很有效，因此常用它来保卫自己的独立天地。

孩子出生后，喂养很费事，常常发生这样那样的麻烦，不是婴儿害病就是做母亲的害病，有时是真病，有时是假病。不管怎样，伊凡·伊里奇都得照顾，尽管他对这些事一窍不通。伊凡·伊里奇保卫自己独立天地、不受家庭干扰的欲望越来越强烈。

妻子的脾气越来越暴躁，要求越来越苛刻，伊凡·伊里奇也越来越把生活的重心转移到公务上。他更加喜爱官职，醉心功名。

不久，在结婚一年后，伊凡·伊里奇懂得了，夫妇生活虽然也有一些好处，但却是一件很复杂很痛苦的事。而要尽到自己的责任，过一种受社会赞许的体面生活，必须像做官一样建立适当的关系。

伊凡·伊里奇就给自己建立了这样的夫妇关系。他对家庭生活的要求，只是能吃到家常便饭，生活上有照料和过床笫生活，而这些都是她能向他提供的。他主要的要求是维持社会所公认的体面的夫妇关系。此外，他就自寻欢乐，获得了欢乐也就心满意足。要是家里遇到不愉快，他就立刻逃到公务活动的独立天地里去，并在那里自得其乐。

伊凡·伊里奇当侦讯官，声誉显赫，三年后就升任副检察官。新的官职、重要的地位、控诉和拘捕任何人的权力、当众的演说、辉煌的功绩——这一切使伊凡·伊里奇更加官迷心窍。

孩子一个个生下来。妻子变得越来越乖戾，越来越易怒，但伊凡·伊里奇确立的家庭关系几乎不受妻子脾气的影响。

伊凡·伊里奇在这个城市里任职七年，接着被调到另一个省里当检察官。他们搬了家，手头的钱不多，妻子又不喜欢新地方。薪俸尽管比原来多，但生活成本也高了，再说又死了两个孩子，因此伊凡·伊里奇就感到家庭生活比以前更乏味了。

普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜搬到新地方后，不论遇到什么麻烦，总要责怪丈夫。夫妇间不论谈什么事，尤其是谈教育孩子的问题，总会联想到以前的不和，引起新的争吵。夫妇俩如今难得有恩爱的时刻，即使有，也是很短暂的。他们在爱情的小岛上临时停泊一下，不久又会掉进互相敌视的汪洋大海，彼此冷若冰霜。要是伊凡·伊里奇认为家庭生活不该如此，他准会对这种冷漠感到伤心，不过他不仅认为这样的局面是正常的，而且正是他所企求的。他的目标就是要尽量摆脱家庭生活的烦恼，而表面上又要装得若无其事，保持体面。为了达到这一目的，他尽量少同家人待在一起，如果不得已必须这样做，也总是竭力找有旁人在场的机会。不过，伊凡·伊里奇这样过日子，主要靠的是他有公务。他把全部生活乐趣都集中在官场的天地里。而这种乐趣支配了他的整个身心。意识到自己的权力，对任何人都操有生杀大权，每次走进法庭和遇到下属时那种威风凛凛的气派（即使只是表面的），在上司与下属之间周旋的本领，尤其是自觉高明的办事能力——这一切都使他扬扬得意，再加上跟同事们谈天、宴会和打牌，他的生活就显得很充实。总之，伊凡·伊里奇的生活过得合乎他的愿望：快乐而体面。

就这样他又过了七年。大女儿已经十六岁，另外又死了一个孩子，只剩下一个男孩在中学念书。这个孩子是引起夫妇争吵的一大因素。伊凡·伊里奇要送他读法学院，而普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜却偏把他送进普通中学。女儿在家里学习，成绩良好；儿子学得也不错。

三

伊凡·伊里奇婚后就这样过了十七年的光阴。现在他已是一个老检察官了。他推辞了几次工作上的调动，一心想找个更称心的职司，不料出了一件不愉快的事，把他生活的安宁给破坏了。伊凡·伊里奇想谋取大学城首席法官的位置，但被戈佩捷足先得。伊凡·伊里奇十分生气，提出责问，同戈佩吵嘴，又冒犯顶头上司；他从此受冷遇，下一次任命也没有他的份儿。

这是1880年，也是伊凡·伊里奇一生中最倒霉的年头。他一方面入不敷出，另一方面又被人家遗忘。他觉得人家待他极不公平，人家却认为对他已仁至义尽。就连父亲都认为无须再帮助他了。他觉得大家都把他抛弃了，并认为他有三千五百卢布年俸已很不错，甚至可说是十分幸福了。人家待他这么不公平，妻子经常责骂他，家里入不敷出，开始负债。这种情况当然谈不上正常，而且只有他一个人知道。

今年夏天，伊凡·伊里奇为了节省开支，同妻子一起到内弟乡下度假。

在乡下不做事，伊凡·伊里奇第一次不仅感到无聊，而且十分愁闷。他认定无法这样过活，必须断然采取措施。

伊凡·伊里奇不能入睡，在露台上踱了个通宵，决定上彼得堡奔走一番，争取调到其他部门工作，以惩罚他们，惩罚那些不会赏识他才能的人。

第二天早晨，他不顾妻子和内弟的劝阻，乘车上彼得堡。

他唯一的目的就是弄到一个年俸五千卢布的位置。他不再计较是哪个机关，是哪个派别和哪种工作。他只要一个位置，年俸五千卢布的位置，不论政府机关、银行、铁路、玛丽皇后御用机关，甚至海关都行，但一定要有五千卢布收入，一定要离开那个不会赏识他才能的机关。

伊凡·伊里奇此行取得了意外收获。在库尔斯克火车站，头等车厢里上来一个熟人，名叫伊林。伊林告诉他库尔斯克省刚接到电报，部里最近人事上有重大变动，彼得·伊凡内奇的位置将由伊凡·谢苗内奇接任。

这次调动，除了对国家有一定影响外，对伊凡·伊里奇具有特殊意义，因为起用了新人彼得·彼得罗维奇和他的朋友扎哈尔·伊凡内奇。这对他伊凡·伊里奇极其有利，因为扎哈尔·伊凡内奇是伊凡·伊里奇的同学，又是他的好朋友。

在莫斯科，这个消息得到了证实。伊凡·伊里奇来到彼得堡，找到了扎哈尔·伊凡内奇，后者答应给他在原来的司法部里谋一个好差事。

一个星期后，他给妻子发了一封电报。

“扎哈尔接替米勒，我申请后即可提升。”

伊凡·伊里奇通过这次人事调动在他的旧部里获得意外任命：比同事高两级，年俸五千，再加调差费三千五百。伊凡·伊里奇消除了对原来对头和整个机关的怨气，感到十分得意。

伊凡·伊里奇回到乡下，兴高采烈。他好久没有这样快活了。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜也很高兴，夫妇俩和好了。伊凡·伊里奇讲到他在彼得堡怎样受祝贺，原来的对头怎样厚着脸皮巴结他，怎样羡慕他的地位，特别讲到他在彼得堡怎样受人尊敬。

普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜听着他讲，装出相信的样子，也不打岔，心里却盘算着怎样到新地方去重新安排生活。伊凡·伊里奇高兴地看到，她的想法同他的想法不谋而合，他们一度坎坷的生活重又变得快乐而体面了。

伊凡·伊里奇只回家几天。九月十日他就得走马上任。此外，他还得在新地方安顿下来，把家具什物从省里运去，再要添置和定做许多新东西。总之，要根据他同普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜几乎一致的想法把新居布置好。

现在，一切都进行得称心如意，他同妻子又意气相投。他们俩一起生活的时间很少像现在这样投契，除了婚后头几年，还不曾有过。伊凡·伊里奇本想举家搬走，可他的嫂子和姐夫对伊凡·伊里奇一家忽然十分亲热，弄得伊凡·伊里奇只好独自先走。伊凡·伊里奇走了，事业上一帆风顺，同妻子言归于好，这两件事互为因果，使他心情愉快。他找到一座精美的住宅，恰合夫妇俩的心意，高大宽敞的老式客厅、豪华舒适的书房、妻子的房间、女儿的房间、儿子的书房，一切像是为他们特意设计的。伊凡·伊里奇亲自布置房间，选择墙纸，添置家具——从旧货店买来的，式样特别古雅，定制了沙发套和窗帘。房子布置得越来越漂亮，符合他的理想。他布置到一半，发觉比他希望的更美。他相信，等全部完工，将更加富丽堂皇，而绝不会流于庸俗。临睡前，他想象他的前厅将是什么样子。他瞧着没有布置好的客厅，仿佛看到壁炉、屏风、古董架、散放着的小椅子、墙上的挂盘和铜器都已安放得井井有条。他想到妻子和女儿在这方面跟他有同样的爱好，看到这种排场，准会大吃一惊，不禁暗暗高兴。她们一定想不到会有这样的气派。他特别得意的是买到一些价廉物美的古董，使整座房子显得格外豪华。他在信里故意把情况说得差一些，这样她们一看到就会更加惊讶。他热衷于装饰新居，就连对心爱的公务都不那么感兴趣了。有时法院开庭，他也心不在焉：他在考虑究竟用什么样的窗帘顶檐，直的还是拱的。他对这事兴致勃勃，亲自动手安放家具，重新挂上窗帘。有一次他爬到梯子上，指点愚笨的沙发裁缝怎样挂窗帘，一不留神失足掉下来，但他是个强壮而灵活的汉子，立刻站住了，只是腰部撞在窗框上。伤处痛了一阵，不久就好了。这一时期，伊凡·伊里奇觉得自己特别快乐和健康。他写信说：“我感到自己仿佛年轻了十五岁。”他原想到九月底把房子布置好，结果拖到十月半。不过，房子布置得十分雅致——不仅他自己这么认为，凡是看到的人都这么说。

其实，房子里的摆设无非是那种不太富裕却一味模仿富裕人家的小康之家的气派，千篇一律地尽是花缎、红木家具、盆花、地毯、古铜器、发亮铜器等等。一定阶级的人总是拿这些东西来表示他们一定的身份。伊凡·伊里奇家里的摆设同人家没有什么两样，因此引不起人家的注意，但他却扬扬自得，以为与众不同。他到车站去接家眷，把他们带到装修一新的寓所里，系白领带的男仆打开摆满鲜花的前厅，他们走进客厅、书房，高兴得欢呼起来。他领他们到各处观看，得意扬扬地听着他们的称赞，容光焕发，感到十分幸福。当天晚上喝茶的时候，普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜随便问到他是怎么摔跤的，他就笑着做给他们看，他怎样从梯子上掉下来，把沙发裁缝吓坏了。

“幸亏我练过体操。要是换了别人，准会摔坏的，可我只在这儿撞了一下，摸摸有点疼，但已经好多了，只是有点青肿。”

就这样他们在新居开始生活，并且也像一般人移居到新地方那样，觉得还少一个房间，收入虽然增加，但还嫌钱少——少这么五百卢布。不过总的来说，他们感到称心如意了。最初他们过得特别愉快，房子还没有完全布置好，需要再买些什么，定制些什么，有些东西需要搬动，有些东西需要调整。尽管夫妇之间有时意见分歧，但两人对新的生活都很满意，而且有许多事要做，因此没有发生大的争吵。等一切都安排完毕，他们开始感到有点空虚，但当时还需要结交一批新朋友，培养新习惯，因此生活还是很充实。

伊凡·伊里奇上午在法院办公，下午回家吃饭，起初那段时光情绪很好，虽然为房子的事有时也有点烦恼（例如，他发现桌布或沙发罩子上有污点，窗帘系带断了，就会发脾气，因为看到他煞费苦心置办的东西被损坏，心里难过）。不过，伊凡·伊里奇的生活还是过得合乎他的理想：轻松、愉快而体面。他每天早晨九时起床，喝咖啡，看报，然后穿上制服去法院。那儿已为他准备好“轭”，让他一到就套到身上：接见来访者，处理与诉讼有关的问题，主持诉讼案件，出席公开庭和预备庭。他必须排除各种外来干预，免得妨碍诉讼程序，同时严禁徇私枉法，严格依法办事。要是有人想探听什么事，而这事不属伊凡·伊里奇主管，他就不能同这人发生任何关系，但要是这人有正式公文，上面写明事由，那么伊凡·伊里奇就会根据法律许可的范围尽力去办，并且办得不违反人情，也就是说面子上过得去。但只要公事一结束，其他关系也就结束了。分清法律和人情这种本领伊凡·伊里奇已达到登峰造极的地步，而且凭着天赋的才能和长期的经验，他有时还会故意把法律和人情混淆起来。他之所以敢于这样做，那是因为他自信总有能力划清两者的界限，如果需要的话。伊凡·伊里奇办这种事不仅轻松、愉快和体面，简直可以说是得心应手。在休庭时，他吸烟、喝茶，随便谈谈政治、社会新闻和纸牌，而谈得最多的还是官场中的任命。然后，他好像第一小提琴手，出色地演奏完毕，疲劳地乘车回家。回到家里，发现母女俩出去了，有时在接待客人，儿子上学了，有时在跟补课教师复习功课。一切都井井有条。饭后要是没有客人来，伊凡·伊里奇就看些当时流行的书籍。晚上，他坐下来处理公事：批阅文件，查看法典，核对证词。他干这些，既不感到无聊，也不觉得有趣。要是有机会打牌，那么处理公事就感到无聊；要是没有机会打牌，那么处理公事总比独自闲坐或者跟妻子面面相对要好得多。伊凡·伊里奇喜欢举行便宴，邀请有权有势的先生夫人参加。这种消遣跟其他同样身份的人没有差别，犹如他的客厅跟人家的客厅没有差别一样。

他们家里还举行过一次舞会。舞会办得很好，伊凡·伊里奇心情愉快，可惜最后为蛋糕糖果的事同妻子大闹了一场。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜有她的打算，但伊凡·伊里奇坚持要到最高级的糖果铺去买糕点，结果买了许多蛋糕。争吵就是由于蛋糕太多吃不完，而糖果铺的账却高达四十五卢布引起的。争吵很激烈，闹得很不愉快。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜骂他：“傻瓜，低能。”伊凡·伊里奇气得双手抱住脑袋，恨恨地说出离婚之类的话来。不过，晚会本身还是很快活的，前来参加的都是社会名流。伊凡·伊里奇同特鲁峰诺娃公爵夫人跳舞。特鲁峰诺娃公爵夫人的姐姐就是著名的“消灭苦难会”的创办人。身居要职的乐趣在于自尊心的满足，社会活动的乐趣在于虚荣心的满足，但伊凡·伊里奇的真正乐趣却在于打牌。他认为，不管生活上遇到什么烦恼，那像蜡烛一样驱除黑暗的最大乐趣，就是同几个规规矩矩的好搭档坐下来一起打牌，而且一定要四人一起（五人一起打就很难有结果，虽然得装出很感兴趣的样子），认认真真地打（要是顺手的话），然后吃点夜宵，喝一大杯葡萄酒。打过牌以后睡觉，尤其是稍微赢一点钱（赢得太多也不好），伊凡·伊里奇觉得特别愉快。

他们就这样过着日子。他们家的来客都是达官贵人，有的地位显赫，有的年少英俊。

夫妻和女儿待人的态度完全一致。凡是满脸堆笑、投奔到他们那间墙上装饰着日本盘子的客厅来的潦倒亲友，他们都加以排斥。不久，这些寒酸的亲友便不再上门，高洛文家的来客就限于达官贵人。年轻人纷纷追求丽莎，其中包括彼特利歇夫。那是德米特里·伊凡内奇·彼特利歇夫的儿子，又是他财产的唯一继承人，现任法院侦讯官。他也在热烈地追求丽莎，弄得伊凡·伊里奇已在跟普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜商量：要不要让他们一起坐三驾马车，或者举办一次堂会看看表演。他们就这样过着日子，一切都称心如意，没有任何变化。

四

家里人个个身体健康。只有伊凡·伊里奇有时说，他嘴里有一种怪味，左腹有点不舒服，但不能说有病。

这种不舒服的感觉逐渐增长，虽还没有转变为疼痛，但他经常感到腰部发胀，情绪恶劣。他的心情越来越坏，影响了全家快乐而体面的生活。夫妇吵嘴的事越来越多，轻松愉快的气氛消失了，体面也很难维持。争吵更加频繁，夫妇之间相安无事的日子少得就像汪洋大海里的小岛。

如今普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜说丈夫脾气难弄，那倒不是没有理由的。她说话喜欢夸张，往往夸张地说，他的脾气一直很坏，要不是她心地善良，这二十年可真没法忍受。的确，现在的争吵总是由伊凡·伊里奇引起的。他吃饭总要发脾气，往往从吃汤开始。他一会儿发现碗碟有裂痕，一会儿批评饭菜烧得不好吃，一会儿责备儿子吃饭把臂肘搁在桌上，一会儿批评女儿的发式不正派。而罪魁祸首总是普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜起初向他回敬，也对他说了一些难听的话，但有两三次他一开始吃饭就勃然大怒。她明白了，这是一种由进食而引起的病态，就克制自己，不再还嘴，只是催他快吃。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜认为自己的忍让是一种值得称道的美德。她认定丈夫脾气极坏，给她的生活带来不幸。她开始可怜自己。她越是可怜自己，就越是憎恨丈夫。她巴不得他早点死，但又觉得不能这样想，因为他一死就没有薪俸了。而这一点却使她更加恨他。她认为自己不幸极了，因为就连他的死都不能拯救她。她变得很容易发脾气，但又强忍着，而她这样勉强忍住脾气，却使他的脾气变得更坏。

有一次夫妻争吵，伊凡·伊里奇特别不讲理。事后他解释说，他确实脾气暴躁，但这是由于病的缘故。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜就对他说，既然有病，就得治疗，要他去请教一位名医。

他乘车去了。一切都不出他所料，一切都照章办理。又是等待，又是医生装出一副煞有介事的样子——这种样子他是很熟悉的，就跟他自己在法庭上一样，——又是叩诊，又是听诊，又是各种不问也知道的多余问题，又是那种威风凛凛的神气，仿佛在说：“你一旦落到我手里，就得听我摆布。我知道该怎么办，对付每个病人都是这样的。”一切都同法庭上一样。医生对待他的神气，就如他在法庭上对待被告那样。

医生说，如此这般的症状表明您有如此这般的病，但要是化验不能证明如此这般的病，那就得假定您有如此这般的病。要是假定有如此这般的病，那么……对伊凡·伊里奇来说，只有一个问题是重要的：他的病有没有危险？但医生对这个不合时宜的问题置之不理。从医生的观点来说，这问题没有意思，不值得讨论；存在的问题只是估计一下可能性：是游走肾，还是慢性盲肠炎。这里不存在伊凡·伊里奇的生死问题，只存在游走肾和盲肠炎之间的争执。在伊凡·伊里奇看来，医生已明确认定是盲肠炎，但又保留说，等小便化验后可以得到新的资料，到那时再做进一步诊断。这一切，就跟伊凡·伊里奇上千次振振有词地对被告宣布罪状一模一样。医生也是那么得意扬扬，甚至从眼镜上方瞧了一眼“被告”，振振有词地做了结论。从医生的结论中伊凡·伊里奇断定，情况严重，对医生或其他人都无所谓，可是对他却非同小可。这结论对伊凡·伊里奇是个沉重的打击，使他十分怜悯自己，同时十分憎恨那遇到如此严重问题却无动于衷的医生。

不过他什么也没有说，就站起来，把钱往桌上一放，叹了一口气。“也许我们病人常向您提些不该问的问题，”他说，“一般说来，这病是不是有危险？”

医生用一只眼睛从眼镜上方狠狠地瞪了他一下，仿佛在说：被告，你说话要是越出规定的范围，我将不得不命令把你带出法庭。

“我已把该说的话都对您说了，”医生说，“别的，等化验结果出来了再说。”医生结束道。

伊凡·伊里奇慢吞吞地走出诊所，垂头丧气地坐上雪橇回家。一路上他反复分析医生的话，竭力把难懂的医学用语翻译成普通的话，想从中找出问题的答案：“我的病严重？十分严重？或者还不要紧？”他觉得医生所有的话，都表示病情严重。伊凡·伊里奇觉得街上的一切都是阴郁的：马车夫是阴郁的，房子是阴郁的，路上行人是阴郁的，小铺子是阴郁的。他身上的疼痛一秒钟也没有停止，听了医生模棱两可的话后就觉得越发厉害。伊凡·伊里奇如今更加心情沉重地忍受着身上的疼痛。

他回到家里，给妻子讲了看病的经过。妻子听着。他讲到一半，女儿戴着帽子进来，准备同母亲一起出去。女儿勉强坐下来听他讲这无聊的事，但她听得不耐烦了，母亲也没有听完他的话。

“哦，我很高兴，”妻子说，“今后你一定要准时吃药。把药方给我，我叫盖拉西姆到药房去抓药。”说完她就去换衣服。

妻子在屋子里时，他不敢大声喘气，等她走了，他才深深地叹了一口气。

“好吧，”伊凡·伊里奇说，“也许真的还不要紧……”

他听医生的话，服药，养病。验过小便后，医生又改了药方。不过，小便化验结果和临床症状之间有矛盾。不知怎的，医生说的与实际情况不符。也许是医生疏忽了，也许是撒谎，也许有什么事瞒着他。

不过伊凡·伊里奇还是照医生的话养病，最初心里感到安慰。

伊凡·伊里奇看过病后，努力执行医生的指示，讲卫生，服药，注意疼痛和大小便。现在他最关心的是疾病和健康。人家一谈到病人、死亡、复原，特别是谈到跟他相似的病，他表面上装作镇定，其实全神贯注地听着，有时提些问题，把听到的情况同自己的病做着比较。

疼痛没有减轻，但伊凡·伊里奇强迫自己认为好一点了。没有事惹他生气，他还能欺骗自己。要是同妻子发生争吵，公务上不顺利，打牌输钱，他立刻感到病情严重。以前遇到挫折他总是希望时来运转，打牌顺手，获得大满贯，因此还能忍受。可是现在每次遇到挫折，他都会悲观绝望，丧失信心。他对自己说：“唉，我刚刚有点好转，药物刚刚见效，就遇到这倒霉的事……”于是他恨那种倒霉事，恨给他带来不幸并要置他于死命的人。他明白这种愤怒在危害他的生命，但他无法自制。照理他应该明白，他这样怨天尤人只会使病情加重，因此遇到不愉快的事，不应该放在心上，可是他的行为正好相反。他说，他需要安宁，并且特别警惕破坏安宁的事。只要他的安宁稍稍遇到破坏，他就大发雷霆。他读医书，向医生请教，结果有害无益。情况是逐渐恶化的，因此拿今天同昨天比较，差别似乎并不大，他还能聊以自慰，但同医生一商量，就觉得病情在不断恶化，而且发展得很快。尽管如此，他还是经常请教医生。

这个月里他又找了一位名医。这位名医的话，简直同原来那位一模一样，但问题的提法不同。请教这位名医，只增加伊凡·伊里奇的疑虑和恐惧。另外有位医生，是他朋友的朋友，也很出名。这位医生对他的病做了完全不同的诊断。尽管保证他能康复，但提出的问题和假设却使伊凡·伊里奇更加疑虑。一个提倡顺势疗法的医生又做了另一种诊断，给了不同的药，伊凡·伊里奇偷偷地服了一个礼拜。可是，一个礼拜后并没有见效，伊凡·伊里奇对原来的疗法丧失了信心，对这种新疗法也丧失了信心，于是越发沮丧了。有一次，一位熟识的太太给他介绍圣像疗法。伊凡·伊里奇勉强听着，并相信她的话。但这事使他不寒而栗。“难道我真的那样神经衰弱吗？”他自言自语。“废话！真是荒唐，这样神经过敏要不得，应该选定一个医生，听他的话好好疗养。就这么办，这下子主意定了。我不再胡思乱想，我要严格遵照这种疗法，坚持到夏天。到那时会见效的。别再犹豫不决了！”这话说说容易，实行起来可难了。腰痛在折磨他，越来越厉害，一刻也不停。他觉得嘴里的味道越来越难受，还有一股恶臭从嘴里出来，胃口越来越差，体力越来越弱。他不能欺骗自己：他身上出现了一种空前严重的情况。这一点只有他自己明白，周围的人谁也不知道，或者不想知道。他们总以为天下太平，一切如旧。这一点使伊凡·伊里奇觉得格外难受。家里人，尤其是妻子和女儿，热衷于社交活动。他看到，她们什么也不明白，还埋怨他情绪不好，难以伺候，仿佛还是他不对似的。他看出，尽管她们嘴里没说，他已成了她们的累赘，妻子对他的病已有定见，不管他说什么或做什么，她的态度都不会变。

“不瞒您说，”她对熟人说，“伊凡·伊里奇也像一切老实人那样，不能认真遵照医生的话养病。今天他听医生的话服药，吃东西；明天我一疏忽，他就忘记吃药，还吃鳇鱼（那是医生禁止的），而且坐下来打牌，一打就打到深夜一点钟。”

“哼，几时有过这种事？”伊凡·伊里奇恼怒地说，“总共在彼得·伊凡内奇家打过一次。”

“昨天不是跟谢贝克一起打过吗？”

“反正我痛得睡不着……”

“不管怎么说，你这样就永远好不了，还要折磨我们。”

普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜向人家也向伊凡·伊里奇本人说，他生病主要是他自己不好，给她这个做妻子的带来痛苦。伊凡·伊里奇觉得她有这样的看法是很自然的，但心里总感到难受。

在法院里，伊凡·伊里奇发现或者心里感到人家对他抱着奇怪的态度：一会儿，人家把他看作一个不久将把位置空出来的人；一会儿，朋友们不怀恶意地嘲笑他神经过敏，因为他自认为有一种神秘可怕的东西，在不断吮吸他的精神，硬把他往那儿拉。朋友们觉得这事挺好玩，就拿来取笑他。尤其是施瓦尔茨说话诙谐生动而又装得彬彬有礼，使伊凡·伊里奇想起十年前他自己的模样，因而格外生气。

来了几个朋友，坐下来打牌。他拿出一副新牌，洗了洗，发了牌。他把红方块跟红方块叠在一起，总共七张。他的搭档说：没有王牌，给了他两张红方块。还指望什么呢？快乐，兴奋，得了大满贯。伊凡·伊里奇突然又感到那种抽痛，嘴里又有那股味道。他在这种情况下还能为赢得大满贯而高兴，未免太荒唐了。

他瞧着他的搭档米哈伊尔·米哈伊洛维奇，看他怎样用厚实的手掌拍着桌子，客客气气地不去抓一墩牌，却把它推给伊凡·伊里奇，使他一举手就能享受赢牌的乐趣。“他是不是以为我身子虚得手都伸不出去了？”伊凡·伊里奇想，忘记了王牌，却用更大的王牌去压搭档的牌，结果少了三墩牌，失去了大满贯。最可怕的是他看见米哈伊尔·米哈伊洛维奇脸色十分痛苦，却表现得若无其事。他怎么能若无其事，这一点想想也可怕。

大家看出他很痛苦，对他说：“要是您累了，我们就不打了。您休息一会儿吧。”休息？不，他一点也不累，可以把一圈牌打完。大家闷闷不乐，谁也不开口。伊凡·伊里奇觉得是他害得大家这样闷闷不乐，但又无法改变这种气氛。客人们吃过晚饭，各自走散了。伊凡·伊里奇独自留在家里，意识到他的生命遭到了毒害，还毒害了别人的生命，这种毒不仅没有减轻，而且越来越深地渗透到他的全身。

他常常带着这样的思想，再加上肉体上的疼痛和恐惧躺到床上，疼得大半夜不能合眼。可是天一亮又得起来，穿好衣服，乘车上法院，说话，批公文，要是不上班待在家里，那么一天二十四小时，每个小时都得活受罪。而且，在这样的生死边缘上，他只能独自默默地忍受，没有一个人了解他，也没有一个人可怜他。

五

就这样过了两个月光景。新年前夕，他的内弟来到他们城里，住在他们家。那天，伊凡·伊里奇上法院尚未回家。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜上街买东西去了。伊凡·伊里奇回到家里，走进书房，看见内弟体格强壮，脸色红润，正在打开手提箱。他听见伊凡·伊里奇的脚步声，抬起头，默默地对他瞧了一会儿。他的眼神向伊凡·伊里奇说明了问题。内弟张大嘴，正要喔唷一声叫出来，但立刻忍住了。这个动作证实了一切。

“怎么，我的样子变了吗？”

“是的……有点变。”

接着，不管伊凡·伊里奇怎样想使内弟再谈谈他的模样，内弟却绝口不提。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜一回来，内弟就到她屋里去了。伊凡·伊里奇锁上房门，去照镜子，先照正面，再照侧面。他拿起同妻子合拍的照片，拿它同镜子里的自己做着比较。变化很大。然后他把双臂露到肘部，打量了一番，才放下袖子，在软榻上坐下来，脸色变得漆黑。

“别这样，别这样。”他对自己说，霍地站起来，走到写字台边，打开卷宗，他开始批阅公文，可是脑子里什么也进不去。他打开门，走到前厅，客厅的门关着。他踮着脚走到门边，侧着耳朵听。

“不，你说得过分了。”普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜说。

“怎么过分？你没发觉，他已经像个死人了。你看看他的眼睛，没有一点光。他这是怎么搞的？”

“谁也不知道。尼古拉耶夫（一位医生）说如此这般，可我不知道。列谢季茨基（名医）说的正好相反……”

伊凡·伊里奇回到自己屋里，躺下来想：“肾，游走肾。”他回忆起医生们对他说过的话，肾脏怎样离开原位而游走。他竭力在想象中捕捉这个肾脏，不让它游走，把它固定下来。这事看上去轻而易举。“不，我还是去找找彼得·伊凡内奇（那个有医生朋友的朋友）。”他打了铃，吩咐套车，准备出去。

“你上哪儿去，约翰？”妻子露出异常忧愁和矫揉造作的贤惠神情问。

这种矫揉造作的贤惠使他生气。他阴沉着脸对她瞅了一眼。

“我去找彼得·伊凡内奇。”

他去找这个有医生朋友的朋友。然后跟他一起到医生家去。他遇见医生，跟他谈了好半天。

医生根据解剖学和生理学对他的病做了分析，他全听懂了。

盲肠里有点毛病，有点小毛病。全会好的。只要加强一个器官的功能，减少另一个器官的活动，多吸收一点，就会好的。吃饭时，他晚到了一点。吃过饭，他兴致勃勃地谈了一通，但好一阵不能定下心来做事。最后他回到书房，立刻动手工作。他批阅公文，处理公事，但心里念念不忘有一件要事被耽误了。等公事完毕，他才记起那件事就是盲肠的毛病。但他故作镇定，走到客厅喝茶。那里有几个客人，正在说话，弹琴，唱歌。他得意的未来女婿——法院侦讯官也在座。据普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜说，伊凡·伊里奇那天晚上过得比谁都快活，其实他一分钟也没有忘记盲肠的毛病被耽误了。十一点钟他向大家告辞，回自己屋里去。自从生病以来，他就独自睡在书房里。他走进屋里，脱去衣服，拿起一本左拉的小说，但没有看，却想着心事。他想象盲肠被治愈了。通过吸收，排泄，功能恢复正常。“对了，就是那么一回事，”他自言自语，“只要补养补养身体就好了。”他想到了药，支起身来，服了药，又仰天躺下，仔细体味药物怎样在治病，怎样在制止疼痛。“只要按时服药，避免不良影响就行；我现在已觉得好一点了，好多了。”他按按腰部，按上去不疼了。“是的，不疼了，真的好多了。”他灭了蜡烛，侧身躺下……盲肠在逐渐恢复，逐渐吸收。突然他又感觉到那种熟悉的隐痛，痛得一刻不停，而且很厉害。嘴里又是那种恶臭。他顿时心头发凉，头脑发晕。“天哪！天哪！”他喃喃地说。“又来了，又来了，再也好不了啦！”突然他觉得完全不是那么一回事。“哼，盲肠！肾脏！”他自言自语，“问题根本不在盲肠，不在肾脏，而在生和……死。是啊，有过生命，可现在它在溜走，在走，而我又留不住它。是啊！何必欺骗自己呢？除了我自己，不是人人都很清楚我快死了吗？问题只在于还有几个礼拜、几天，还是现在就死。原来有过光明，现在却变成一片黑暗。我此刻在这个世界，但不久就要离开！到哪儿去？”他觉得浑身发凉，呼吸停止，只听见心脏在扑扑跳动。

“等我没有了，那还有什么呢？什么也没有了。等我没有了，我将在哪儿？难道真的要死了吗？不，我不愿死。”他霍地跳起来，想点燃蜡烛，用颤动的双手摸索着。蜡烛和烛台被碰翻，落到地上。他又仰天倒在枕头上。“何必呢？反正都一样。”他在黑暗中瞪着一双眼睛，自言自语。“死。是的，死。他们谁也不知道，谁也不想知道，谁也不可怜我。他们玩得可快乐了（他听见远处传来喧闹和伴奏声）。他们若无其事，可他们有朝一日也要死的。都是傻瓜！我先死，他们后死，他们也免不了一死。可他们还乐呢。畜生！”他愤怒得喘不过气来。他痛苦得受不了。难道谁都得受这样的罪吗！他坐起来。

“总有什么地方不对头，我得定下心，从头至尾好好想一想。”他开始思索。“对了，病是这样开始的。先是腰部撞了一下，但过了一两天我还是好好的。稍微有点疼，后来疼得厉害了，后来请医生，后来泄气了，发愁了，后来又请医生，但越来越接近深渊。体力越来越差，越来越接近……越来越接近……我的身子虚透了，我的眼睛没有光。我要死了，可我还以为是盲肠有病。我想治好盲肠，其实是死神临头了。难道真的要死吗？”他又感到魂飞魄散，呼吸急促。他侧身摸索火柴，用臂肘撑住床几。臂肘撑得发痛，他恼火了，撑得更加使劲，结果把床几推倒了。他绝望得喘不过气来，又仰天倒下，恨不得立刻死去。

这当儿，客人们纷纷走散。普拉斯柯菲·费多罗夫娜送他们走。她听见什么东西倒下，走进来。

“你怎么了？”

“没什么，不留神把它撞倒了。”

她走出去，拿着一支蜡烛进来。他躺着，喘息得又重又急，好像刚跑完了几里路，眼睛停滞地瞧着她。

“你怎么了，约翰？”

“没……什么。撞……倒了。”他回答，心里却想，“有什么可说的。她不会明白的。”

她确实不明白。她扶起床几，给他点上蜡烛，又匆匆走掉了：她还得送客。

等她回来，他仍旧仰天躺着，眼睛瞪着天花板。

“你怎么了，更加不舒服吗？”

“是的。”

她摇摇头，坐下来。

“我说，约翰，我们把列谢季茨基请到家里来好吗？”

这就是说，不惜金钱，请那位名医来出诊。他冷笑了一声说：“不用了。”她坐了一会儿，走到他旁边，吻了吻他的前额。

她吻他的时候，他从心底里憎恨她，好容易才忍住不把她推开。

“再见。上帝保佑你好好睡一觉。”

“嗯。”

六

伊凡·伊里奇看到自己快要死了，经常处于绝望中。

他心里明白，他快要死了，但他对这个念头很不习惯，他实在不理解，怎么也不能理解。

他在基捷韦帖尔的逻辑学里读到这样一种三段论法：盖尤斯是人，凡人都要死，因此盖尤斯也要死。他始终认为这个例子只适用于盖尤斯，绝对不适用于他。盖尤斯是人，是个普通人，这个道理完全正确；但他不是盖尤斯，不是个普通人，他永远是个与众不同的特殊人物。他原来是小伊凡，有妈妈，有爸爸，有两个兄弟——米嘉和伏洛嘉，有许多玩具，有马车夫，有保姆，后来又有了妹妹卡嘉，还有儿童时代、少年时代和青年时代的喜怒哀乐。难道盖尤斯也闻到过他小伊凡所喜爱的那种花皮球的气味吗？难道盖尤斯也那么吻过妈妈的手，听到过妈妈绸衣褶裥的声吗？难道盖尤斯也曾在法学院里因点心不好吃而闹过事吗？难道盖尤斯也那么谈过恋爱吗？难道盖尤斯能像他那样主持审讯吗？

盖尤斯的确是要死的，要他死是正常的，但我是小伊凡，是伊凡·伊里奇，我有我的思想感情，跟他截然不同。我不该死，要不真是太可怕了。

这就是他的心情。

“我要是像盖尤斯那样也要死，那我一定会知道，一定会听到内心的声音，可是我心里没有这样的声音。我和我的朋友们都明白，我跟盖尤斯完全不同。可是如今呢！”他自言自语，“这是不可能的，不可能发生的，可是偏偏发生了。这是怎么搞的？这事该怎么理解？”

他无法理解，就竭力驱除这个想法，把这个想法看成是虚假、错误和病态的，并且用正确健康的想法来挤掉它。但这不只是思想，而是现实，它出现了，摆在他面前。

他故意想想别的事来排挤这个想法，希望从中找到精神上的支持。他试图用原来的一套思路来对抗死的念头。但奇怪得很，以前用这种办法可以抵挡和驱除死的念头，如今却不行。近来，伊凡·伊里奇常常想恢复原来的思绪，以驱除死的念头。有时他对自己说：“我还是去办公吧，我一向靠工作过活。”他摆脱心头的种种疑虑，到法院去。他跟同事们谈话，在法庭上坐下来，照例漫不经心地扫一眼人群，两条干瘦的胳膊搁在麻栎椅扶手上，照例侧身凑近旁边的法官，挪过卷宗，同他耳语几句，然后猛地抬起眼睛，挺直身子，说几句老套，宣布开庭。但审讯到一半，腰部不顾正在开庭，突然又抽痛起来。伊凡·伊里奇定下神，竭力不去想它，可是没有用。它又来了，站在他面前，打量着他。他吓得呆若木鸡，眼睛里的光也熄灭了。他又自言自语：“难道只有它是真的吗？”同事和下属惊奇而痛心地看到，像他这样一位精明能干的法官竟然说话颠三倒四，在审讯中出差错。他竭力振作精神，定下心来，勉强坚持到庭审结束，闷闷不乐地回家去。他明白，法院开庭也不再能回避他想回避的事，他在审讯时也不能摆脱它。最最糟糕的是，它吸引他，并非要他有什么行动，而只是要他瞧着它，面对面地瞧着它，什么事也不做，难堪地忍受着折磨。

为了摆脱这种痛苦，伊凡·伊里奇寻找另一种屏风来自卫，但另一种屏风也只能暂时保护他，不久又破裂了，或者变得透明了，仿佛它能穿透一切，什么东西也挡不住它。

有一次他走进精心布置的客厅——他摔跤的地方，他嘲弄地想，正是为了布置它而献出了生命，因为他知道他的病是由跌伤引起的——他发现油漆一新的桌上有被什么东西划过的痕迹。他研究原因，发现那是被照相簿上弯卷的青铜饰边划破的。他拿起他深情地贴上照片的照相簿，对女儿和她那些朋友的粗野很恼火——有的地方撕破了，有的照片被颠倒了。他把照片仔细整理好，把照相簿饰边扳平。

然后他想重新布置，把照相簿改放到盆花旁的角落里。他吩咐仆人请女儿或者妻子来帮忙，可是她们不同意他的想法，反对搬动。他同她们争吵、生气。但这样倒好，因为他可以不再想到它，不再看见它。

不过，当他亲自动手挪动东西的时候，妻子对他说：“啊，让仆人搬吧，你又要糟蹋自己了。”这当儿，它突然又从屏风后面出现，他又看见了它。它的影子一闪，他还希望它能再消失，可是他又注意到自己的腰。腰还是在抽痛。他再也无法把它忘记，它明明在盆花后面瞧着他。“这是干什么呀？”

“真的，我为了这窗帘就像冲锋陷阵一样送了命。难道真是这样吗？多么可怕而又多么愚蠢哪！这不可能！不可能！但这是事实。”

他回到书房里躺下，又同它单独相处。他同它又面面相对，但对它束手无策。他只能瞧着它，浑身发抖。

七

伊凡·伊里奇生病的第三个月的情况怎样，很难说，因为病情是逐步发展的，不易察觉。但妻子也好，女儿也好，儿子也好，用人也好，朋友也好，医生也好，主要是他自己，都知道，大家唯一关心的事是，他的位置是不是快空出来，活着的人能不能解除由于他存在而招惹的麻烦，他自己是不是快摆脱痛苦。

他的睡眠越来越少；医生给他服鸦片，注射吗啡，但都不能减轻他的痛苦。他在昏昏沉沉中所感到的麻木，起初使他稍微好过些，但不久又感到同样痛苦，甚至比清醒时更不好受。

家里人遵照医生的指示给他做了特殊的饭菜，但他觉得这种饭菜越来越没有滋味，越来越倒胃口。

他大便这件事也被做了特殊的安排。每次大便他都觉得很痛苦，因为不清洁，不体面，有臭味，还得麻烦别人帮忙。

不过，在这件不愉快的事上，伊凡·伊里奇倒也得到一种安慰。每次大便总是由男仆盖拉西姆伺候。

盖拉西姆是个年轻的庄稼汉，衣着整洁，容光焕发，因为长期吃城里伙食长得格外强壮。他性格开朗，总是乐呵呵的。这个整洁的小伙子身穿俄罗斯民族服，做着这种不体面的事，总使伊凡·伊里奇感到困窘。

有一次，他从便盆上起来，无力拉上裤子，就倒在沙发上。他看见自己皮包骨头的大腿，不禁心惊胆战。

盖拉西姆脚蹬散发着柏油味的大皮靴，身上系着干净的麻布围裙，穿着干净的印花布衬衫，卷起袖子，露出年轻强壮的胳膊，带着清新的冬天空气走进来。他目光避开伊凡·伊里奇，竭力抑制着从焕发的容光中表现出来的生的欢乐，免得病人见了不高兴，走到便盆旁。

“盖拉西姆。”伊凡·伊里奇有气无力地叫道。

盖拉西姆打了个哆嗦，显然害怕自己什么地方做得不对，慌忙把他那张刚开始长胡子的纯朴善良而又青春洋溢的脸转过来对着病人。

“老爷，您有什么吩咐？”

“我想，你做这事一定很不好受。你要原谅我，我是没有办法。”

“哦，老爷，好说。”盖拉西姆闪亮着眼睛，露出一排洁白健康的牙齿。“那算得了什么？您有病嘛，老爷。”

他用他那双强壮的手熟练地做着做惯的事，轻悄地走了出去。过了五分钟，又那么轻悄地走回来。

伊凡·伊里奇一直那么坐在沙发上。

“盖拉西姆，”当盖拉西姆把洗干净的便盆放回原处时，伊凡·伊里奇说，“请你帮帮我，你过来。”盖拉西姆走过去。“你搀我一把。我自己爬不起来，德米特里被我派出去了。”

盖拉西姆走过去。他用他那双强壮的手，也像走路一样轻松、利索而温柔地把主人抱起来，一只手扶住他，另一只手给他拉上裤子，想让他坐下。但伊凡·伊里奇要求把他扶到长沙发上。盖拉西姆一点也不费劲，稳稳当当地把他抱到长沙发上坐下。

“谢谢。你真行，干得真轻巧。”

盖拉西姆又微微一笑，想走。可是伊凡·伊里奇同他一起觉得很愉快，不肯放他走。

“还有，请你把那把椅子给我推过来。不，是那一把，让我搁腿。腿搁得高，好过些。”

盖拉西姆端过椅子，轻轻地把它放在长沙发前，然后抬起伊凡·伊里奇的双腿放在上面。当盖拉西姆把他的腿高高抬起时，他觉得舒服些。

“腿抬得高，我觉得舒服些，”伊凡·伊里奇说，“你把这个枕头给我垫在下面。”

盖拉西姆照他的吩咐做了。他又把他的腿抬起来放好。盖拉西姆抬起他的双腿，他觉得确实好过些。双腿一放下，他又觉得不舒服。

“盖拉西姆，”伊凡·伊里奇对他说，“你现在有事吗？”

“没有，老爷。”盖拉西姆说，他已学会像城里仆人那样同老爷说话。

“你还有什么活要干？”

“我还有什么活要干？什么都干好了，只要再劈点木柴留着明天用。”

“那你把我的腿这么高高抬着，行吗？”

“有什么不行的？行！”盖拉西姆把主人的腿抬起来，伊凡·伊里奇觉得这样一点也不疼了。

“那么劈柴怎么办？”

“不用老爷您操心。这我来得及的。”

伊凡·伊里奇叫盖拉西姆坐下抬着他的腿，并同他谈话。真奇怪，盖拉西姆抬着他的腿，他觉得好过多了。

从此以后伊凡·伊里奇就常常把盖拉西姆唤来，要他用肩膀扛着他的腿，并喜欢同他谈天。盖拉西姆做这事轻松愉快，态度诚恳，使伊凡·伊里奇很感动。别人身上的健康、力量和生气往往使伊凡·伊里奇感到屈辱；只有盖拉西姆的力量和生气不仅没有使他觉得伤心，反而使他感到安慰。

伊凡·伊里奇觉得最痛苦的事就是听谎言，听大家出于某种原因都相信的那个谎言，他只是病了，并不会死，只要安心治疗，一定会好的。可是他知道，不论采取什么办法，他都不会好了，痛苦只会越来越厉害，直到死去。这个谎言折磨着他。他感到痛苦的是，大家都知道，他自己也知道他的病很严重，但大家都讳言真相而撒谎，还要迫使他自己一起撒谎。谎言，在他临死前夕散布的谎言，把他不久于人世这样严肃可怕的大事，缩小到访问、挂窗帘和晚餐吃鳇鱼等小事，这使他感到极其痛苦。说也奇怪，好多次当他们就他的情况编造谎言时，他差一点大声叫出来：“别再撒谎了，我快要死了。这事你们知道，我也知道，所以大家别再撒谎了。”但他从来没有勇气这样做。他看到，他不久于人世这样严肃可怕的事，被周围的人看成只是一件不愉快或者不体面的事（就像一个人走进会客室从身上散发出臭气一样），还要勉强维持他一辈子苦苦撑住的“体面”。他看到，谁也不可怜他，谁也不想了解他的真实情况。只有盖拉西姆一人了解他，并且可怜他。因此只有同盖拉西姆在一起他才觉得好过些。盖拉西姆有时通宵扛着他的腿，不去睡觉，还说：“您可不用操心，老爷，我回头会睡个够的。”这时他感到安慰。或者当盖拉西姆脱口而出亲热地说：“要是您没病就好了，我这样伺候伺候您算得了什么？”他也感到安慰。只有盖拉西姆一人不撒谎，显然也只有他一人明白真实情况，并且认为无须隐讳，但他怜悯日益消瘦的老爷。有一次伊凡·伊里奇打发他走，他直截了当地说：“我们大家都要死的。我为什么不能伺候您呢？”他说这话的意思就是，现在他不辞辛劳，因为伺候的是个垂死的人，希望将来有朝一日轮到他的时候也有人伺候他。

除了这个谎言，或者正是由于这个谎言，伊凡·伊里奇觉得特别痛苦的是，没有一个人像他所希望的那样可怜他。伊凡·伊里奇长时期受尽折磨，有时特别希望——尽管他不好意思承认——有人像疼爱有病的孩子那样疼爱他。他真希望有人疼他，吻他，对着他哭，就像人家疼爱孩子那样。他知道，他是个显赫的大官，已经胡子花白，因此这是不可能的，但他还是抱着这样的希望。他同盖拉西姆的关系近似这种关系，因此跟盖拉西姆在一起，他感到安慰。伊凡·伊里奇想哭，要人家疼他，对着他哭，不料这时他的法院同事谢贝克走来了，伊凡·伊里奇不仅没有哭，没有表示亲热，反而板起脸，现出严肃和沉思的神气，习惯成自然地说了他对复审的意见，并且坚持自己的看法。他周围的这种谎言和他自己所做的谎言，比什么都厉害地毒害了他生命的最后日子。

八

有一天早晨，伊凡·伊里奇知道这是早晨，因为每天早晨都是盖拉西姆从书房里出去，男仆彼得进来吹灭蜡烛，拉开一扇窗帘，悄悄地收拾房间。早晨也好，晚上也好，礼拜五也好，礼拜天也好，反正都一样，反正没有区别：永远是一刻不停的令人难堪的疼痛；他意识到生命正在无可奈何地消逝，但还没有完全消逝；那愈益逼近的可怕而又可恨的死，只有它才是真实的，其他一切都是谎言。在这种情况下，几天、几个礼拜和几小时有什么区别？

“老爷，您要不要用茶？”

“他还是老一套，知道老爷太太每天早晨都要喝茶。”他想，接着回答说，“不用了。”

“您要不要坐到沙发上去？”

“他得把屋子收拾干净，可我在这里碍事。我太邋遢，太不整齐了，”他想了想回答说，“不，不用管我。”

男仆继续收拾屋子。伊凡·伊里奇伸出一只手。彼得殷勤地走过去。

“老爷，您要什么？”

“我的表。”

彼得拿起手边的表，递给他。

“八点半了。她们还没有起来吗？”

“还没有，老爷。瓦西里·伊凡内奇（这是儿子）上学去了，普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜关照过，要是您问起，就去叫醒她。要去叫她吗？”

“不，不用了。”他回答，接着想，“要不要喝点茶呢？”于是就对彼得说：“对了，你拿点茶来吧。”

彼得走到门口。伊凡·伊里奇独自留着觉得害怕。“怎么把他留住呢？有了，吃药。”他想了想，说：“彼得，给我拿药来。”接着又想：“是啊，说不定吃药还有用呢。”他拿起匙子，把药吃下去。“不，没有用。一切都是胡闹，都是欺骗，”他一尝到那种熟悉的甜腻腻的怪味，就想，“不，我再也不能相信了。可是那个疼，那个疼，要是能停止一会儿就好了。”他呻吟起来。彼得向他回过头来。“不，你去吧，拿茶来。”

彼得走了，剩下伊凡·伊里奇一个人。他又呻吟起来。他疼得很厉害，可呻吟主要不是由于疼痛，而是由于悲伤。“老是那个样子，老是那样的白天和黑夜。但愿快一点。什么快一点？死，黑暗。不，不！好死不如赖活！”

彼得托着茶盘进来，伊凡·伊里奇茫然看了他好一阵，认不出他是谁，不知道他是来干什么的。他这种目光弄得彼得很狼狈。彼得现出尴尬的神色，伊凡·伊里奇才醒悟过来。

“噢，茶……”他说，“好的，放着。你帮我洗洗脸，拿一件干净衬衫来。”

伊凡·伊里奇开始梳洗。他断断续续地洗手，洗脸，刷牙，梳头，然后照照镜子。他感到害怕，特别是看到他的头发怎样贴着苍白的前额。

彼得给他换衬衫。他知道他要是看到自己的身体，一定会更加吃惊，因此不往身上看。梳洗完毕了，他穿上晨衣，身上盖了一条方格毛毯，坐到扶手椅上喝茶。有那么一会儿他觉得神清气爽，但一喝茶，立刻又感到那种味道、那种疼痛。他勉强喝完茶，伸直腿躺下来。他躺下，让彼得走。

还是那个样子。一会儿出现了一线希望，一会儿又掉进绝望的海洋。老是疼，老是疼，老是悲怆凄凉，一切都是老样子。独个儿待着格外悲伤，想叫个人来，但他知道同人家待在一起更难受。“最好再来点儿吗啡，把什么都忘记。我要请求医生，叫他想点别的办法。这样可真受不了，真受不了！”

一小时、两小时就这样过去了。忽然前厅里响起了铃声。会不会是医生？果然是医生。他走进来，精神饱满，容光焕发，喜气洋洋。那副神气仿佛表示：你们何必这样大惊小怪，我这就来给你们解决问题。医生知道，这样的表情是不得体的，但他已经习惯了，改不掉，好像一个人一早穿上大礼服，就这样穿着一家家去拜客，没有办法改变了。

医生生气勃勃而又使人宽慰地搓搓手。

“啊，真冷，可把我冻坏了。让我暖和暖和身子。”他说这话时的神气仿佛表示，只要稍微等一下，等他身子一暖和，就什么问题都解决了。

“嗯，怎么样？”

伊凡·伊里奇觉得，医生想说：“情况怎么样？”但他觉得不该那么问，就说：“晚上睡得怎么样？”

伊凡·伊里奇望着医生的那副神气表示：“您老是撒谎，怎么不害臊？”但医生不理会他的表情。

伊凡·伊里奇就说：“还是那么糟。疼痛没有消除，也没有减轻。您能不能想点办法……”

“啊，你们病人总是这样。嗯，这会儿我可暖和了，就连普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜那么仔细，也不会对我的体温有意见了。嗯，您好。”医生说着握了握病人的手。

接着医生收起戏谑的口吻，现出严肃的神色给病人看病：把脉，量体温，叩诊，听诊。

伊凡·伊里奇清清楚楚地知道，这一切都毫无意思，全是骗人的，但医生跪在他面前，身子凑近他，用一只耳朵忽上忽下地细听，脸上显出极其认真的神气，像体操运动员一般做着各种姿势。伊凡·伊里奇面对这种场面，屈服了，就像他在法庭上听辩护律师发言一样，尽管他明明知道他们都在撒谎以及为什么撒谎。

医生跪在沙发上，还在他身上敲着。这当儿门口传来普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜绸衣裳的窸窣声，还听见她在责备彼得没有及时向她报告医生的来到。

她走进来，吻吻大夫，立刻振振有词地说，她早就起来了，只是不知道医生来了才没有及时出来迎接。

伊凡·伊里奇对她望望，打量着她的全身，对她那白净浮肿的双手和脖子、光泽的头发和充满活力的明亮眼睛感到嫌恶。他从心底里憎恨她。她的亲吻更激起他对她的难以克制的憎恨。

她对待他和他的病还是老样子。正像医生对病人的态度都已定型不变那样，她对丈夫的态度也已定型不变：她总是亲昵地责备他没有照规定服药休息，总是怪他自己不好。

“嗳，他这人就是不听话！不肯按时吃药。尤其是他睡的姿势不对，两腿搁得太高，这样睡对他不好。”

她告诉医生他怎样叫盖拉西姆扛着腿睡。

医生鄙夷不屑而又和蔼可亲地微微一笑，仿佛说：“有什么办法呢？病人总会做出这样的蠢事来，但情有可原。”

检查完毕，医生看了看表。这时普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜向伊凡·伊里奇宣布，不管他是不是愿意，她今天就去请那位名医来，让他同米哈伊尔·达尼洛维奇（平时看病的医生）会诊一下，商量商量。

“请你不要反对。我是为我自己才这样做的。”她嘲讽地说，让他感到这一切都是为她而做的，因此他不该拒绝。他不作声，皱起眉头。他觉得周围是一片谎言，很难判断是非曲直。

她为他做的一切都是为了她自己。她对他说这样做是为了她自己，那倒是真的，不过她的行为叫人很难相信，因此必须从反面来理解。

十一点半，那位名医果然来了。又是听诊，又是当着他的面一本正经地交谈，而到了隔壁房间又是谈肾脏，谈盲肠，又是一本正经地问答，又是避开他现在面临的生死问题，大谈什么肾脏和盲肠有毛病，米哈伊尔·达尼洛维奇和名医又都主张对肾脏和盲肠进行治疗。

名医临别时神态十分严肃，但并没有绝望。伊凡·伊里奇眼睛里露出恐惧和希望的光芒仰望着名医，怯生生地问他，是不是还能恢复健康。名医回答说，不能保证，但可能性还是有的。伊凡·伊里奇用满怀希望的目光送别医生，他的样子显得那么可怜，以至普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜走出书房付给医生出诊费时都忍不住哭了。

被医生鼓舞起来的希望并没有持续多久。还是那个房间，还是那些图画，还是那些窗帘，还是那种墙纸，还是那些药瓶，还是他那个疼痛的身子。伊凡·伊里奇呻吟起来，给自己注射了吗啡，便迷迷糊糊睡着了。

他醒来时，天色开始发黑。仆人给他送来晚餐，他勉强吃了一点肉汤。于是一切如旧，黑夜又来临了。

饭后七点钟，普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜走进他的房间。她穿着晚礼服，丰满的胸部被衣服绷得隆起，脸上有扑过粉的痕迹。早晨她就提起，今晚她们要去看戏。萨拉·贝娜到这个城里做访问演出，她们订了一个包厢。那也是他的主意。这会儿，他把这事忘记了，她那副打扮使他生气。不过，当他记起是他要她们订包厢去看戏的，认为孩子们看这戏可以获得美的享受，他就把自己的愤怒掩饰起来。

普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜进来的时候得意扬扬，但仿佛又有点负疚。她坐下来，问他身体怎么样，不过他看出，她只是为了应酬几句才问的，并非真的想了解什么，而且知道也问不出什么来。接着她就讲她要讲的话：她本来说什么也不愿去，可是包厢已经订了，爱伦和女儿，还有彼特利歇夫（法院侦讯官，未来的女婿）都要去，总不能让他们自己去，她其实是宁可待在家里陪他的。现在她只希望她不在家时，他能照医生的嘱咐休息。

“对了，费多尔·彼得罗维奇（未来的女婿）想进来看看你，行吗？还有丽莎。”

“让他们来好了。”

女儿走进来。她打扮得漂漂亮亮，露出部分年轻的身体。对比之下，他觉得更加难受。她却公然显示她健美的身体。显然她正在谈恋爱，对妨碍她幸福的疾病、痛苦和死亡感到嫌恶。

费多尔·彼得罗维奇也进来了。他身穿燕尾服，头发烫出波纹，雪白的硬领夹着青筋毕露的细长脖子，胸前露出一大块白硬衬，瘦长的黑裤紧裹着两条强壮的大腿，手上套着雪白的手套，拿着大礼帽。

一个中学生在他后面悄悄走进来。这个可怜的孩子穿一身崭新的学生装，戴着手套，眼圈发黑——伊凡·伊里奇知道为什么会这样。

他总是很怜悯儿子。儿子那种满怀同情的怯生生目光使他心惊胆战。伊凡·伊里奇觉得除了盖拉西姆以外，只有儿子一人了解他、同情他。

大家都坐下来，又问了一下病情。接下来是一片沉默。丽莎问母亲要望远镜。母女俩争吵起来，不知是谁拿了，放在什么地方。这事弄得大家都很不高兴。

费多尔·彼得罗维奇问伊凡·伊里奇有没有看过萨拉·贝娜。伊凡·伊里奇起初没听懂他问什么，后来才说：

“没有，您看过吗？”

“看过了，她演过《阿德里安娜·莱科芙露尔》。”

普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜说，她演那种角色特别好。女儿不同意她的看法。大家谈到她的演技又典雅又真挚——那题目已谈过不知多少次了。

谈话中间，费多尔·彼得罗维奇对伊凡·伊里奇瞧了一眼，不作声了。其他人跟着瞧了一眼，也不作声了。伊凡·伊里奇睁大眼睛向前望望，显然对他们很生气。这种尴尬的局面必须改变，可是怎么也无法改变。必须设法打破这种沉默，谁也不敢这样做，大家都害怕，唯恐这种礼貌周到的虚伪做法一旦被揭穿，真相就会大白。丽莎第一个鼓起勇气，打破了沉默。她想掩饰大家心里都有的感觉，却脱口而出：

“嗯，要是去的话，那么是时候了。”她瞧了瞧父亲送给她的表，说。接着对未婚夫会意地微微一笑，衣服窸窣响着站起来。

大家都站起来，告辞走了。

等他们一走，伊凡·伊里奇觉得好过些，因为虚伪的局面结束了，随着他们一起消失了，但疼痛如旧。依旧是那种疼痛，依旧是那种恐惧，一点也没有缓和，而是每况愈下。

时间还是一分钟又一分钟、一小时又一小时地过去，一切如旧，没完没了，而无法避免的结局却越来越使人不寒而栗。

“好了，你去叫盖拉西姆来。”他对向他提出了问题的彼得给出了这样的回答。

九

妻子深夜才回家。她踮着脚悄悄进来，但他还是听见她的脚步声。他睁开眼睛，连忙又闭上。她想打发盖拉西姆走开，自己陪他坐一会儿。他却睁开眼睛，说：

“不，你去吧。”

“你很难受吗？”

“老样子。”

“服点鸦片吧。”

他同意了，服了点鸦片。她走了。

直到凌晨三时，他一直处在痛苦的迷糊状态中。他仿佛觉得人家硬把他这个病痛的身子往一个又窄又黑又深的口袋里塞，一个劲地往下塞，却怎么也塞不到袋底。这件可怕的事把他折磨得好苦。他又害怕，又想往下沉，不断挣扎，越挣扎越往下沉。他突然跌了下去，随即惊醒过来。依旧是那个盖拉西姆坐在床脚，平静而耐心地打着瞌睡。他却躺在那里，把那双穿着袜子的瘦腿搁在盖拉西姆肩上；依旧是那支有罩的蜡烛，依旧是那种一刻不停的疼痛。

“你去吧，盖拉西姆。”他喃喃地说。

“不要紧，老爷，我坐坐。”

“不，你去吧。”

他放下腿，侧过身子来睡。他开始可怜自己。他等盖拉西姆走到隔壁屋里，再也忍不住，就像孩子般痛哭起来。他哭自己的无依无靠，哭自己的孤独寂寞，哭人们的残酷，哭上帝的残酷和冷漠。

“你为什么要这样做？为什么把我带到这儿来？为什么？为什么这么狠心地折磨我？……”

他知道不会有谁回答，但又因得不到也不可能得到回答而痛哭。疼痛又发作了，但他一动不动，也不呼号。他自言自语：“痛吧，再痛吧！可是为了什么呀？我对你做了什么啦？这是为了什么呀？”后来他安静了，不仅停止哭泣，而且屏住呼吸，提起精神来。他仿佛不是在倾听说话声，而是在倾听灵魂的呼声，倾听自己思潮的翻腾。

“你要什么呀？”这是他听出来的第一句明确的话。“你要什么呀？你要什么呀？”他一再问自己，“要什么？”——“摆脱痛苦，活下去。”他自己回答。

他又全神贯注地倾听，连疼痛都忘记了。

“活下去，怎么活？”心灵里有个声音问他。

“是的，活下去，像我以前那样活得舒畅而快乐。”

“像你以前那样，活得舒畅而快乐吗？”心灵里的声音问。于是他开始回忆自己一生中美好的日子。奇怪的是，所有那些美好的日子现在看来一点也不美好，只有童年的回忆是例外。童年时代确实有过欢乐的日子，要是时光能倒转，那是值得重温的。但享受过当年欢乐的人已经不存在了，存在的似乎只有对别人的回忆。

自从伊凡·伊里奇变成现在这个样子以来，过去的欢乐都在他眼里消失了，或者说，变得不足道了，变得令人讨厌了。

离童年越远，离现在越近，那些欢乐就越显得不足道、越可疑。这是从法学院开始的。在那里还有点真正美好的事：还有欢乐，还有友谊，还有希望。但读到高年级，美好的时光就越来越少。后来开始在官府供职，又出现了美好的时光：那是对一个女人的倾慕。后来生活又浑浑噩噩，美好的时光更少了，越来越少，越来越少。

结婚……是那么意外，那么叫人失望。妻子嘴里的臭味，放纵情欲，装腔作势！死气沉沉地办公，不择手段地捞钱，就这样过了一年，两年，十年，二十年——始终是那么一套。而且越是往后，就越是死气沉沉。我在走下坡路，却还以为在上山。就是这么一回事。大家都说我官运亨通，步步高升，其实生命在我脚下溜掉……如今瞧吧，末日到了！

这究竟是怎么一回事？为什么会这样？生活不该那么无聊，那么讨厌。不该！即使生活确是那么讨厌，那么无聊，那又为什么要死，而且死得那么痛苦？总有点不对头。

“是不是我的生活有些什么地方不对头？”他忽然想到。“但我不论做什么都是循规蹈矩的，怎么会不对头？”他自言自语，顿时找到了唯一的答案：生死之谜是无法解答的。

如今你到底要什么呢？要活命？怎么活？像法庭上听到民事执行吏高呼“开庭了！”时那样活。“开庭了，开庭了！”他一再对自己说。“喏，现在要开庭了！可我又没有罪！”他恨恨地叫道。“为了什么呀？”他停止哭泣，转过脸来对着墙壁，一直思考着那个问题：为什么要忍受这样的恐怖？为什么？

然而，不管他怎样苦苦思索，都找不到答案。他头脑里又出现了那个常常出现的想法：这一切都是由于他生活过得不对头。他重新回顾自己规规矩矩的一生，立刻又把这个古怪的想法驱除掉。

十

又过了两个礼拜。伊凡·伊里奇躺在沙发上已经起不来了。他不愿躺在床上，就躺在长沙发上。他几乎一直面对墙壁躺着，孤独地忍受着那难以摆脱的痛苦，孤独地思索着那难以解答的问题：“这是怎么一回事？难道真的要死吗？”心里有个声音回答说：“是的，是要死的。”——“为什么要受这样的罪？”那声音回答说：“不为什么，就是这样。”除此以外就什么也没有了。

自从伊凡·伊里奇开始生病，自从他第一次看医生以来，他的心情就分裂成两种对立的状态，两种状态交替出现着：一会儿是绝望地等待着神秘而恐怖的死亡，一会儿是充满希望和紧张地观察自己身上的器官。一会儿眼前出现了功能暂时停止的肾脏或者盲肠，一会儿又出现了无可避免的神秘而恐怖的死亡。

这两种心情从一开始生病就交替出现；但随着病情的发展，他就觉得肾脏的功能越来越可疑，越来越虚幻，而日益逼近的死亡却越来越现实。

他只要想想三个月前的身体，再看看现在的情况，看看他怎样一步步不停地走着下坡路，任何侥幸的心情就自然而然土崩瓦解了。

近来，他面向沙发背躺着，感到异常孤寂，那是一种身处在闹市和许多亲友中间却没有人理睬他而感到的孤寂，即使跑遍天涯海角都找不到的孤寂。身处在这种可怕的孤寂中，他只能靠回忆往事度日。一幕幕往事像图画般浮现在他眼前。他总是从近期的事开始，一直回忆到遥远的过去，回忆到童年时代，然后停留在那些往事上。譬如他从今天给他端来的李子酱，就会想到童年吃过的干瘪法国李子，觉得别有风味，吃到果核，满口生津。同时他又会想到当年的种种情景：保姆、兄弟、玩具。“那些事别去想了……太痛苦了。”伊凡·伊里奇对自己说，思想又回到现实上来。他瞧着羊皮沙发上的皱纹和沙发背上的纽扣。“山羊皮很贵，又不牢；有一次就为这事争吵过。还记得当年我们撕坏父亲的皮包，因此受罚，但那是另一种山羊皮，是另一次争吵……妈妈还送包子来给我们吃。”他的思想又停留在童年时代，他又感到很难过。他竭力驱散这种回忆，想些别的事。

在对一系列往事的回忆中，他又想到了那件事：他怎样生病和病情怎样恶化。他想到年纪越小，越是充满生气。生命里善的因素越多，生命力也就越充沛。两者互为因果。“病痛越来越厉害，整个生命也就越来越糟，”他想，“生命开始还有一点光明，后来却越来越暗淡，消逝得越来越快，离死越来越近。”他忽然想到，一块石子落下总是不断增加速度，生命也是这样，带着不断增加的痛苦，越来越快地掉落下去，掉进痛苦的深渊。“我在飞逝……”他浑身打了个哆嗦，试图抗拒，但知道这是无法抗拒的。他的眼睛虽已疲劳，却依旧瞪着前面，瞪着沙发背。他等待着，等待着那可怕的坠落、震动和灭亡。“无法抗拒。”他自言自语，“真想知道，为什么会这样？可是无法知道。要是说我生活得不对头，那还有理由解释，可是不能这么说。”他对自己说，想到自己一辈子奉公守法，过着正派而体面的生活。“不能这么说，”他露出冷笑，仿佛人家会看到他这个样子，并且会因此受骗似的，“可是找不到解释！折磨，死亡……为了什么呀？”

十一

这样过了两个礼拜。在这期间发生了伊凡·伊里奇夫妇所希望的那件事：彼特里歇夫正式来求婚。这事发生在一天晚上。第二天，普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜走进丈夫房间，考虑着怎样向他宣布彼特里歇夫求婚的事，但就在那天夜里，伊凡·伊里奇的病情又有新的发展。普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜发现他又躺在长沙发上，但姿势跟以前不同。他仰天躺着，呻吟着，眼睛呆滞地瞪着前方。

她谈起吃药的事。他把目光转到她身上。她没有把话说完，因为她发现他的目光里充满对她的愤恨。

“看在基督的分儿上，让我安安静静地死吧！”他说。

她正想出去，但这当儿女儿进来向他请安。他也像对妻子那样对女儿望望，而对女儿问候病情的话只冷冷地说，他不久就会让她们解脱的。母女俩默不作声，坐了一会儿走了。

“我们究竟有什么过错呀？”丽莎对母亲说，“仿佛都是我们弄得他这样似的！我可怜爸爸，可他为什么要折磨我们？”

医生按时来给他看病。伊凡·伊里奇对他的问题只回答“是”或者“不是”，并愤怒地盯住医生，最后说：

“您明明知道毫无办法，那就让我去吧！”

“我们可以减轻您的痛苦。”医生说。

“这点您也办不到，让我去吧！”

医生走到客厅，告诉普拉斯柯菲雅·费多罗夫娜情况很严重，只有一样东西可以减轻他的痛苦，就是鸦片。

医生说，他肉体上的痛苦很厉害，这是事实，但精神上的痛苦比肉体上的痛苦更厉害，而这也是让他最难受的事。

他精神上的痛苦就是，那天夜里他瞧着盖拉西姆睡眼惺忪、颧骨突出的善良的脸，忽然想：我这辈子说不定真的过得不对头。

他忽然想，以前说他这辈子生活过得不对头，他是绝对不同意的，但现在看来可能是真的。他忽然想，以前他有过轻微的冲动，反对豪门权贵肯定的好事，这种冲动虽然很快就被他自己克制住，但说不定倒是正确的，而其他一切可能都不对头。他的职务，他所安排的生活，他的家庭，他所献身的公益事业和本职工作，这一切可能都不对头。他试图为这一切辩护，但忽然发现一切都有问题，没有什么可辩护的。

“既然如此，那么现在在我将离开世界的时候，发觉我把天赋予我的一切都糟蹋了，但又无法挽救，那可怎么办？”他自言自语。他仰天躺着，重新回顾自己的一生。早晨他看到仆人，后来看到妻子，后来看到女儿，后来看到医生，他们的一举一动、一言一语，都证实他夜间所发现的可怕真理。他从他们身上看到了自己，看到了他赖以生活的一切，并且明白这一切都不对头，这一切都是掩盖着生死问题的可怕的大骗局。这种思想增加了他肉体上的痛苦，比以前增加了十倍。他不断呻吟，辗转反侧，扯着身上的衣服。他觉得衣服束缚他，使他喘不过气来。他为此憎恨它们。

医生给了他大剂量鸦片，他昏睡过去，但到吃晚饭时又开始折腾。他把所有的人都赶走，不断地翻来覆去。

妻子走过来对他说：“约翰，心肝，你就为了我（为了我？）这么办吧。这没有什么害处，常常还有点用。真的，这没什么。健康的人也常常……”

他睁大眼睛，问：“什么事？进圣餐吗？干什么呀？不用了！不过……”

她哭了。

“好吗，我的亲人？我去叫我们的神父来，他这人挺好。”

“好，太好了。”他说。

神父来了，听了他的忏悔，他觉得好过些，疑虑似乎减少些，痛苦也减轻了，刹那间心里看到了希望。他又想到了盲肠，觉得还可以治愈。他含着眼泪进了圣餐。

他进了圣餐，又被放到床上，刹那间觉得好过些，并且又出现了生的希望。他想到他们曾建议他动手术。“活下去，我要活下去！”他自言自语。妻子走来祝贺；她敷衍了几句，又问：“你是不是感到好些？”他眼睛不看她，嘴里说：“是。”她的服装，她的体态，她的神情，她的腔调，全都向他说明一个意思：“不对头。你过去和现在赖以生活的一切都是谎言，都是对你掩盖生死大事的骗局。”他一想到这点，心头就冒起一阵愤恨，随着愤恨又感觉到肉体上的痛苦，同时意识到不可避免的临近的死亡。接着又增加了一种新的感觉：拧痛、刺痛和窒息。

当他说“是”的时候，他的脸色是可怕的。他说了一声“是”，眼睛直盯住她的脸，接着使出全身的力气迅速地把脸转过去，伏在床上嚷道：“都给我走，都给我走，让我一个人待着！”

十二

自从那时起，他连续三天一刻不停地惨叫，叫得那么可怕，就是隔着两道门听了也觉得毛骨悚然。当他回答妻子的时候，他明白他完了，无法挽救了，末日到了，生命的末日到了，可是生死之谜始终没有解决，永远是个谜。

“哎哟！哎哟！哎哟！”他用不同的音调惨叫着。他开始嚷道：“我不要！”接下去又是哎哟哎哟地惨叫。

整整三天，他一刻不停地在那个黑口袋里拼命挣扎，而一个肉眼看不见的力量却无可抗拒地把他往口袋里塞。他好像一个死刑犯，落到刽子手手里，知道没有生路了。他每分钟都感觉到，不管他怎样挣扎，他是越来越接近那恐怖的末日了。他觉得他的痛苦在于他正被人塞到那个黑窟窿里去，而更痛苦的是他不能爽爽快快落进去。他之所以不能爽爽快快落进去，是因为他认为他的生命是有价值的。这种对自己生命的肯定，阻碍了他，不让他走，使他特别痛苦。

突然，他的胸部和腰部受到猛烈的打击，呼吸更加困难，他掉到窟窿里。在窟窿底里有一道亮光。他觉得自己仿佛身处在火车车厢里，你以为火车在前进，其实却在后退。这时他突然辨出了方向。“是的，一切都不对头，”他自言自语，“但没有关系，可以纠正的。可怎样才算‘对头’呢？”他问自己，接着突然沉默了。

第三天傍晚，他临终前两小时，念中学的儿子悄悄地进来，走到父亲床跟前。垂死的人一直在惨叫，挥动双臂。他的一只手落在儿子头上。儿子捉住他的手，把它贴在嘴唇上，哭了起来。

就在这时候，伊凡·伊里奇掉了下去，看见了光。他领悟到他的生活过得不对头，但还可以纠正。他问自己：怎样才“对头”，接着一动不动地留神听着。他感到有人在吻他的手。他睁开眼睛，对儿子瞧了一眼。他可怜起儿子来。妻子走到他跟前。他对她瞧了一眼。她张开嘴，鼻子上和面颊上挂着眼泪，露出绝望的神情瞧着他。他为她难过。“是的，我把他们害苦了，”他想，“他们真可怜，但等我一死，他们就会好过些。”他想把这话说出来，可是没有力气说。“不过，何必说呢，应该行动。”他想。他对着妻子用目光示意说：“带他走……可怜……你也……”他还想说“原谅我”，但却说了“原来我”。他已经没有力气纠正，只摆了摆手，知道谁需要听懂自然会懂的。

他恍然大悟，原来折磨他的东西消失了，从四面八方消失了，从一切方面消失了。他可怜他们，应该使他们不再受罪。应该使他们，也使自己摆脱种种痛苦。“多么简单，多么快乐。”他想。“疼痛呢？”他问自己，“它哪儿去了？嗳，疼痛，你在哪儿啊？”

他留神倾听。“噢，它在这里。好吧，疼就疼吧。”

“那么死呢？它在哪里？”

他寻找着往常折磨他的死的恐惧，可是没有找到。它在哪里？是什么样的死啊？他一点也不觉得恐惧，因为根本没有死。

没有死，只有光。

“原来如此！”他突然说出声来。“多么快乐呀！”

对于他，这一切都只是一刹那的事。

这一刹那的含义没有再变。但旁人看到，临死前他又折腾了两小时。他的胸膛里咯咯发响，皮包骨头的身体不断抽搐。接着咯咯声越来越少，喘息也越来越微弱。

“过去了！”有人在他旁边说。

他听见这话，心里重复了一遍。“死过去了，”他对自己说，“再也不会有死了。”

他吸了一口气，吸到一半停住，两腿一伸就死了。

[1]原文为法语。（说明：书中脚注均为编者注。）

[2]原文为法语。

[3]原文为法语。

[4]原文为法语。

[5]原文为法语。

三死

一

秋天，两辆马车在大道上疾驰。前面的轿车上坐着两个女人。一个是贵夫人，身体消瘦，脸色苍白。另一个是使女，脸色红润，体态丰满。使女干枯的短发老从褪色的帽子里掉下来，她只好用戴破手套的冻红的手不时把头发塞进去。她那高高的胸脯裹着粗披巾，散发出健康的气息。她那双乌溜溜的眼睛时而望望窗外掠过的田野，时而怯生生地瞧瞧太太，时而不安地打量马车的角落。她的鼻子前面晃动着太太那顶挂在网架上的帽子，她的膝盖上躺着一条小狗，她的腿因地上放着一堆匣子而高高地翘着，在车座弹簧的抖动声和车窗玻璃的叮叮声中，可以隐隐听见她的鞋底碰到匣子的声音。

贵夫人双手叠放在膝盖上，闭着眼睛，稍稍皱起眉头，从胸膛里咳嗽着，身子靠在背后的靠垫上微微摇晃。她头上戴着一顶白色睡帽，娇嫩白净的脖子上系着一条浅蓝色头巾。睡帽底下露出笔直的头皮，把她那搽过油的平整的淡褐色头发分开，苍白的头皮显得没有生气，像死人的皮肤一样。她的脸清秀美丽，但皮肤松弛枯黄，两颊和颧骨泛出红潮。她的嘴唇干燥，不断翕动；稀疏的睫毛没有卷起；凹陷的胸脯使她的旅行呢外套现出一条条直褶。她双目紧闭，脸上现出疲倦、烦躁和常有的痛苦神色。

听差双肘支着软椅，在驭座上打瞌睡。驿车夫神气活现地吆喝着，赶着四匹热汗淋漓的高头大马，偶尔回头望望后面篷车上吆喝着的另一名马车夫。宽阔的平行车辙在泥泞的石灰路上均匀而迅速地向前伸展。天空阴沉寒冷，黑雾不断降落到田野和大路上。马车里很闷，散发出花露水和尘土的气味。病人把头往后一靠，慢慢睁开眼睛，她那双眼睛又大又亮，黑得很美。

当使女外套的下摆稍稍触到太太的腿时，她就用消瘦的纤手神经质地把它推开，并且说：“又来了！”她的嘴痛苦地瘪了一下。玛特廖莎双手提起外套，用强壮的腿支起身子，坐得远一点。她那娇嫩的脸上泛起鲜艳的红晕。病人那双美丽的乌黑眼睛紧紧盯着使女的一举一动。太太两手按住座位，也想支起身子坐得高些，但她力不从心。她的嘴瘪了一下，整个脸由于无可奈何的自嘲而变得难看。“你哪怕帮我一把也好啊！唉！不必了！我自己也能，只是对不起，别把你这些麻袋之类的东西都放在我背后！别这么弄，别碰我！”太太闭上眼睛，接着又迅速地抬起眼皮，瞧了使女一眼。玛特廖莎望着她，咬着红红的下唇。病人从胸膛里吐出深沉的叹息，但叹息到一半又变成了咳嗽。她转过脸去，皱起眉头，双手按住胸口。咳嗽完了，她又闭上眼睛，仍旧一动不动地坐着。轿车和篷车驶进了村庄。玛特廖莎从披巾下伸出一只胖鼓鼓的手，画了个十字。

“什么事？”太太问。

“到站了，太太。”

“我问你为什么画十字？”

“有座教堂，太太。”

病人转身对着窗外，睁大眼睛望着马车经过的那座乡村教堂，动手慢慢地画十字。

轿车和篷车同时在驿站前停下。病人的丈夫和医生下车来到轿车跟前。

“您觉得怎么样？”医生把着她的脉问。

“哦，怎么样，亲爱的，不太累吧？”丈夫用法语问，“你不想下车吗？”

玛特廖莎抱起包裹缩在角落里，免得妨碍他们谈话。“没什么，还是那样，”病人回答，“我不下车。”

丈夫站了一会儿，走进驿站。

玛特廖莎霍地跳下马车，踮着脚跑过泥泞地，也走进驿站大门。

“就算我身体不好，也不能成为您不吃早饭的理由。”

病人含笑对站在车窗旁的医生说。

“他们谁也不来管我。”医生刚轻手轻脚地离开她，跑上驿站台阶，她就这样自言自语，“他们身体好，什么都不在乎。哦！天哪！”

“怎么样，爱德华·伊凡诺维奇？”丈夫遇到医生，快乐地笑着搓搓手说，“我吩咐他们把食盒拿进来，您觉得怎么样？”

“行。”医生回答。

“那么，她怎么样？”丈夫压低声音，扬起眉毛，叹了口气说。

“我说过，她不仅到不了意大利，能到莫斯科就算不错了。特别是碰到这种天气。”

“那怎么办呢？哦，天哪！天哪！”丈夫用手掩住眼睛说。“拿到这儿来！”他对端食盒进来的仆人说。

“本来就该待在家里。”医生耸耸肩膀回答。

“您说，我有什么办法呢？”丈夫反问道，“不瞒您说，我曾想尽办法留住她，我提到费用，提到不得不撇在家里的孩子，提到我的工作，可她什么都不听。她定了在国外生活的计划，仿佛她是个健康人。但如果把她的病情如实告诉她，那就等于要她的命。”

“其实她已经没命了，华西里·德米特里奇，这一点您心里要有数。人没有肺不能活，而肺又不能重新生出来。这确实很让人伤心，难受，但是有什么办法呢？你我所能做到的，只是让她死得尽可能平静些。现在得请神父了。”

“哦，天哪！您要明白我的处境，要问问她有什么遗愿。听天由命吧，我可不能对她说这事。您知道，她这人多么善良……”

“不论怎么说，您还得劝她等路冻硬了再走，”医生意味深长地摇摇头说，“要不路上会出事……”

“阿克秀莎，喂，阿克秀莎！”驿站长的女儿从头上套上一件短袄，在泥泞的后门台阶上跺着脚，尖声喊道，“我们去瞧瞧希尔金家的太太，据说她得了肺病，要到外国去，我还从没见过害痨病的人是什么样子。”

阿克秀莎从门里跳出来，两人手拉着手跑到大门外。她们放慢脚步走过马车，向开着的车窗张望了一下。病人向她们转过头来，发现她们好奇的神色，就皱起眉头转过脸去。

“我的妈呀！”驿站长的女儿连忙转过头来说，“她原来是个多么漂亮的美人，可现在变成什么样了？简直可怕。阿克秀莎，你看见了吗？看见了吗？”

“是啊，真瘦呀！”阿克秀莎附和说，“我们假装到井边去，再去看看。瞧，她转过头去，可我还是看见了。真可怜，玛莎。”

“路上真泥泞啊！”玛莎回答。接着两人都跑回大门里去。

“我的样子一定很可怕，”病人想，“但愿快一点到国外，快一点到国外，到了那边很快就会康复了。”

“你觉得怎么样，我亲爱的？”丈夫走到马车跟前，嘴里还嚼着东西说道。

“问来问去就是这句话，”病人想，“自己还在吃东西！”

“没什么。”她透过牙缝说。

“要知道，亲爱的，我担心这种天气赶路对你更不好。爱德华大夫也这么说。我们还不如回去吧？”

她气呼呼地不吭声。

“天气说不定会好起来，到那时路也就好走了，你的身体也会好些，那时我们再一起去。”

“对不起。要是我早先不听你的话，我现在已到了柏林，身体也完全康复了。”

“有什么办法呢，我的天使，你知道那是办不到的。可现在，你要是肯再等一个月，你的身体就会大大康复，我也可以把事情办完，我们还可以把孩子带去……”

“孩子们身体健康，可是我有病。”

“不过你要明白，亲爱的，在这样的天气里，万一你的病在路上加重……不然至少还在家里。”

“家里，家里怎么样？……叫我死在家里吗？”病人暴躁地说。但死这个字显然使她害怕，她恳求而又询问似的对丈夫瞧瞧。丈夫垂下眼睛没作声。病人的嘴突然像孩子似的瘪了一下，接着眼泪夺眶而出。丈夫用手帕捂住脸，默默地从马车旁走开去。

“不，我要去。”病人抬起眼睛望着天空，抱着双臂，嘴里断断续续地低声说着话。“天哪！这是为什么呀？”她说。泪水流得更多了。她热烈地祈祷了很久，但胸口还是感到疼痛，喘不过气来；天空、田野和道路还是那么阴沉灰暗，秋天的黑雾还是那样不密不稀地落在泥泞的道路上、屋顶上、马车上和车夫们的皮袄上。车夫们热烈而快乐地交谈着，给车轮抹油，套车。

二

轿车套好了，但车夫还在磨蹭。他走进车夫休息的小屋。小屋里又热又闷又暗，充满人气和烤面包、白菜、羊皮袄的气味。正房里有几个车夫，厨娘在炉灶旁忙碌着，炕上躺着一个穿羊皮袄的病人。

“费多尔叔叔！费多尔叔叔！”一个身穿羊皮袄、腰里插着鞭子的年轻车夫走进屋来招呼病人。

“懒鬼，你找费多尔干什么！”一个车夫答应说，“瞧，人家在马车里等你哪。”

“我想问他借双靴子，我这双破了。”小伙子把头发往后一甩，又把手套塞在腰里，回答。“他睡着了？喂，费多尔叔叔！”他走到炕边，又喊道。

“什么事？”一个微弱的声音答应道，接着一张红褐色的瘦脸从炕上探下来。接着，一只毛茸茸的苍白瘦弱的大手拉上一件粗呢大衣，盖住穿着肮脏衬衫的瘦肩膀。“给我点水喝，老弟，你有什么事？”

小伙子递给他一勺水。

“是这么回事，费多尔，”他迟疑不决地说，“你现在大概用不着新靴子了，给我吧，你大概不会到处跑了。”

病人把疲软无力的头俯在光滑的勺子上，稀疏的下垂胡子浸在浑浊的水里，他吃力而贪婪地喝着水。他那蓬乱的胡子很脏，凹陷无神的眼睛勉强抬起来望着小伙子的脸。喝完水，他想举起手来擦擦湿嘴唇，可是没有力气，只能在大衣袖子上蹭一蹭。他没吭声，困难地用鼻子呼吸着，勉强打起精神直盯着小伙子的脸。

“也许你已经答应别人了，”小伙子说，“那就算了。主要是外面地上泥泞，我得出去干活，因此我就想：把费多尔那双靴子借来吧，他大概用不着了。也许你自己要用，那就直说吧……”

病人胸口有什么东西涌上来，咕噜咕噜直响。他佝偻着身子，拼命咳嗽起来。

“他要靴子做什么？”厨娘突然怒气冲冲地嚷起来，嚷得整个屋子都能听见，“他有一个多月没下炕了。嘿，听见他那个咳嗽呀，我连心口都疼了。他要靴子做什么？总不会让他穿着新靴子入土吧。上帝恕我直说，他早该上路了。瞧他那个咳嗽。得把他搬到别的屋子或者什么地方去！听说城里有这种医院，要不他占着整个角落，怎么行。弄得你没有一点儿空地方，还讲究什么干净。”

“喂，谢廖加！快上车，老爷们等着哪！”驿站长向屋里喊道。

谢廖加没等到回答想走，但病人一面咳嗽，一面用目光表示他有话要说。

“谢廖加，你把靴子拿去吧。”他忍住咳嗽，歇了一会儿，“但你听我说，我死后你得给我买块墓碑。”他哑着嗓子加了一句。

“谢谢叔叔，那我拿去了，墓碑我会给你买的。”

“喂，伙计们，听见了没有？”病人还有话要说，但他又佝偻着身子喘不过气来。

“好，听见了，”一个车夫说，“去吧，谢廖加，上车吧，要不站长又要跑来了。你知道，希尔金家的太太正病着呢。”

谢廖加连忙脱下他那双大得出奇的破靴子，把它扔到长凳底下。费多尔叔叔那双新靴子正好合脚，谢廖加端详着那双靴子，向马车走去。

“瞧，多漂亮的靴子！我来给你上点油。”当谢廖加爬上驭座、拿起缰绳时，一个手拿刷子的车夫说，“白白送给你了？”

“你眼红是不是？”谢廖加回答，拉拉粗呢大衣的下摆把腿盖好。“走吧！我的宝贝！”他挥挥鞭子向马吆喝道。于是载着乘客、各种箱子的轿车和篷车就在泥泞的大路上飞驰，渐渐隐没在灰蒙蒙的秋雾里。

生病的车夫留在闷热小屋的炕上，他咳不出痰，好不容易翻了个身，才安静下来。

小屋里，到傍晚一直有人进进出出，来这里吃饭，但谁也不理会病人。晚上，厨娘爬到炕上，伸手从他的腿边拿走羊皮袄。

“你别生我的气，娜斯塔西雅，”病人说，“我很快就会把这地方给你腾出来的。”

“好，好，那有什么，没关系，”娜斯塔西雅含糊地说，“叔叔，你哪儿疼呀？你说吧。”

“五脏六腑都难受。天知道是怎么回事。”

“咳嗽的时候嗓子大概疼吧？”

“哪儿都疼。我快死了，就是那么回事。喔唷，喔唷，喔唷！”病人呻吟道。

“你把腿盖盖好，就这样。”娜斯塔西雅说，顺手替他拉好粗呢大衣，从炕上爬下来。

夜里，小屋里灯光暗淡。娜斯塔西雅和十来个车夫睡在地板上和长凳上，大声打着呼噜。只有病人一人在炕上翻来覆去，微弱地呻吟着，咳嗽着。到早上，他一点声音也没有了。

“昨天晚上我做了一个怪梦，”第二天，厨娘在晨光熹微中伸着懒腰说，“我梦见费多尔叔叔从炕上爬下来，出去劈柴。他说：‘娜斯塔西雅，我来帮你忙。’我就对他说：‘你怎么能劈柴呢？’他却抓起斧头就劈，劈得很有劲，只见木屑飞溅开来。我说：‘你不是有病吗？’他说：‘不，我好了。’他说着抡起斧头猛劈，可把我吓了一跳。我大叫一声就醒了。莫非他死了？喂，费多尔叔叔！叔叔！”

费多尔没有回答。

“可不是，他也许是死了？让我去瞧瞧。”一个刚醒来的车夫说。

一条长满黄褐色茸毛的手臂从炕上垂下来，又白又凉。

“他大概死了，得去告诉驿站长。”车夫说。

费多尔没有亲人，他是个外乡人。第二天，他被埋在小树林后面的新墓地里。娜斯塔西雅一连好几天逢人就说她的梦，并且说是她第一个发现费多尔死了。

三

春天来了。在城里潮湿的街上，湍急的流水潺潺地流过上冻的畜粪；熙来攘往的人群穿着鲜艳的衣衫，热闹地交谈着。在围着篱笆的花园里，树木已经发芽，树枝飒飒地在微风中摇摆。到处都有清澈的水流动着，滴下来……麻雀叽叽喳喳地欢叫，鼓动小翅膀飞来飞去。在向阳的一边，篱笆上、房屋上、树木上，一切都在晃动，一切都闪闪发亮。空中、地上和人们心里都洋溢着青春的欢乐。

大街上一座大公馆门前刚铺上干草；那位急于出国的垂死的女病人就在这个公馆里。

在一间关着的房门口站着病人的丈夫和一个上了年纪的女人。一位神父坐在沙发上，垂下眼睛，手里拿着一包用长巾包着的东西。一位老太太——病人的母亲——躺在屋角那张高背安乐椅里，伤心地哭着。一个使女拿着一块干净手帕伺候老太太；另一个使女用什么东西揉着老太太的太阳穴，并且吹着她睡帽底下的白发。

“嗯，基督保佑您，我亲爱的。”病人丈夫对站在门口上了年纪的女人说，“她那么信任您。您又那么会同她说话，去吧，您去好好劝劝她。”

他刚要给她开门，但表姐拦住他，几次拿手帕按在自己眼睛上，猛地摇摇头。

“好了，这下子我不像哭过了。”她说，接着自己打开门走进去。

丈夫心里十分焦急，似乎完全手足无措。他向老太太走去，但没走几步又转过身，穿过房间，走到神父跟前。神父对他瞧瞧，扬起眉毛，叹了一口气。他那浓密的花白大胡子也扬起来，接着又垂下。

“天哪！天哪！”丈夫说。

“有什么办法？”神父叹息着说，眉毛和胡子又向上扬起，然后又垂下来。

“她妈妈也在这儿！”丈夫几乎绝望地说，“她可受不了这样的打击。要知道她是多么爱她呀，我没见过谁像她这样爱女儿……神父，您最好想法子安慰安慰她，劝她离开这儿。”

神父站起来，走到老太太跟前。

“是的，做母亲的心是谁也无法估量的，”他说，“不过上帝是仁慈的。”

老太太的整个脸突然抽搐起来，她神经质地打着嗝。

“上帝是仁慈的，”等她稍微平静下来，神父继续说，“我可以告诉您，在我的教区里有一个病人，比玛丽雅·德米特里耶夫娜的病重得多，但有个普通市民用草药很快就把他治好了。而且那个市民现在就在莫斯科。我对华西里·德米特里奇说过，不妨请他来试试。至少对病人是个安慰。上帝是万能的。”

“不，她已经没救了，”老太太说，“上帝不召我去，却要把她带走。”接着，她更厉害地打着神经质的嗝，一会儿就昏过去了。

病人的丈夫双手捂住脸，从屋子里跑出来。

他在走廊里首先遇见他那个六岁的男孩，男孩正一个劲儿地追着妹妹。

“请问，要不要把孩子们带到妈妈那儿去？”保姆问。

“不，她不愿看见他们，这会使她伤心的。”

男孩站了一会儿，凝神瞧瞧父亲的脸，突然撒腿向前跑去，嘴里快乐地嚷嚷着。“爸爸，她好像一匹黑马！”男孩指指妹妹叫道。

这时候在另一个房间里，表姐坐在病人旁边，巧妙地和她谈着话，使她对死有个思想准备。医生在另一扇窗前调药水。

病人穿着宽大的白色睡袍坐在床上，四周围着枕头，默默地望着表姐。

“唉，表姐，”病人突然打断她的话说，“你不用来给我做思想准备。不要把我当孩子。我是个基督徒。我什么都知道。我知道我活不长了。我也知道我的丈夫要是早点听我的话，现在我已经到了意大利，说不定——简直可以肯定——身体已经好了。大家都这么对他说。可是有什么办法呢，看来这是上帝的意思。我们大家都有许多罪孽，这一点我知道，但我相信上帝是仁慈的，人人都会得到宽恕，人人准会得到宽恕。我竭力了解自己。我知道我也有许多罪孽，表姐。因此我受了那么多苦。我一直在努力忍受痛苦……”

“那么，我去叫神父来好吗，表妹？你领了圣餐，一定会好过些。”表姐说。

病人点点头表示同意。

“上帝啊！饶恕我这个罪人吧。”她喃喃地说。

表姐走出去，对神父使了个眼色。

“她是个天使！”她含泪对病人丈夫说。

丈夫哭了，神父走进门去，老太太还是不省人事，第一间屋里鸦雀无声。五分钟后，神父从屋里出来，取下长巾，理理头发。

“感谢上帝，她现在比较安静了，”他说，“她想看看你们。”表姐和丈夫走了进去。病人正望着圣像低声哭泣。

“恭喜你，我亲爱的。”丈夫说。

“谢谢！我现在觉得好多了，我感到说不出的快乐，”病人说，薄薄的嘴唇上露出一丝微笑，“上帝真是仁慈！他是仁慈和万能的，是不是？”她又双眼饱含泪水，目光虔诚地望着圣像。

然后她仿佛突然想起什么事，示意丈夫到她跟前去。“我求你的事，你总是不肯做。”她用微弱的声音不满地说。

丈夫伸长脖子，恭顺地听着。“什么事，我亲爱的？”

“我跟你说过多少次，这些医生什么也不懂，倒是有些郎中能治病……神父说……有一个市民……去把他找来。”

“把谁找来呀，我亲爱的？”

“天哪！你什么也不愿懂！……”病人皱起眉头，闭上眼睛。

医生走到她跟前，拿起她的手。她的脉搏显然越来越弱。他对丈夫使了个眼色。病人发现这眼色，害怕地环顾了一下。表姐转过脸去，哭起来。

“不要哭，不要折磨自己，也不要折磨我，”病人说，“这样你会使我失去最后的安宁。”

“你是个天使！”表姐吻着她的手说。

“不，吻这儿，只有对死人才吻手。天哪！天哪！”

当天晚上，病人已成了一具尸体，尸体入殓后，灵柩停在公馆大厅里。大厅门户紧闭，里面坐着一名诵经士，用鼻音有节奏地念着大卫的诗篇。明亮的烛光从高高的银烛台上投射到死者苍白的额上，投射到那双僵硬的白蜡似的手上，投射到膝盖和脚趾处可怕地凸出的衾衣的挺直皱褶上。诵经士并不懂得所念的诗句，只是有节奏地念着；在肃静的屋子里，诗句古怪地交替响起和静止。从遥远的房间里时而传来孩子们的说话声和脚步声。

“你掩面，他们便惊惶，”诗篇说，“你收回他们的气，他们就死亡，归于尘土。你发出你的灵，他们便受造，你使地面更换为新。愿耶和华的荣耀存到永远。”

死者的脸严峻、平静而庄严。她那冰凉的洁白前额、她那紧闭的嘴都一动不动。她看上去全神贯注。但现在她是否理解这些庄严的诗句呢？

四

一个月后，贵夫人的墓上盖起了一座石头小教堂。车夫的坟上却还没有石碑，坟上长出嫩绿的青草，成为这里埋葬着一个人的仅有标志。

“谢廖加，你真造孽，不给费多尔买块石碑，”驿站的厨娘有一次说，“你说过，冬天买，冬天买，可是到现在还不守信用。你这是当着我的面说的。他来找过你一次了，你再不买，他还会来，会把你掐死的。”

“什么，难道我说话不算数吗？”谢廖加回答，“石碑我会买的，我答应过，我会买的，我会花一个半卢布去买。我没有忘记，但得去把它运回来。哪天进城，我一定去买。”

“你哪怕先去竖个十字架也好，”一个年老的车夫插嘴说，“要不太不像话。靴子倒穿在脚上了。”

“叫我到哪儿去弄十字架呀？总不能用木柴削一个吧？”

“你这算什么话？木柴是削不出来的，你带把斧头一早到小树林去，在那儿做一个不就得了吗？砍一棵白蜡树什么的，不就可以做个十字架吗？要不你还得请护林员喝酒。为这么一根废料请他喝酒可划不来。瞧，前天我弄断一根撬棒，我就去砍了一根新的，挺结实，谁也没说过一句话。”

第二天清早，天色刚亮，谢廖加就拿着斧头到小树林里去。

大地万物盖着一层灰白的寒露，没有照到阳光的露水一滴一滴地滴下来。东方破晓，微弱的曙光映在薄云片片的苍穹上。地上的小草，枝头的树叶，都纹丝不动。只有树丛中鸟雀的扑翼声和地上沙沙的响声偶尔打破树林的寂静。在树林边缘，突然响起一阵与大自然格格不入的响声，然后又沉寂了。接着响声又起，并且在一棵一动不动的树干周围有节奏地重复着。一棵树的树梢异乎寻常地颤动起来，苍翠欲滴的叶子飒飒发响，一只红胸鸲栖在树枝上，叽叽地叫着鼓动翅膀，摇摇尾巴，落到另一棵树上。

斧头低低地发出越来越重浊的响声，湿润的白木片飞落到露珠滚滚的草地上，在砍击声中传出一声轻微的折裂声。整棵树颤动了一下，向一边倾斜，又迅速地挺直，根部恐惧地摇摆着。一瞬间又万籁俱寂，接着那棵树向一边倾斜的树干上又发出折裂声，于是枯枝折断，树枝下垂，一棵树树梢朝下轰隆一声倒在潮湿的地上。斧头声和脚步声都静止了。那只红胸鸲叫了一声，拍拍翅膀往高处飞去。被它的翅膀触动的树枝摇晃了一会儿，又像其他树枝一样一动不动了。树林披着纹丝不动的枝叶，在开阔的新的空地上更加快乐地展示出它们的美丽。

最初的几道阳光穿过透明的云片在空中闪了一下，然后照遍大地和天空。朝雾在谷地里像波浪似的翻腾，草木上露珠滚滚，闪闪发亮，透明的云片在蓝幽幽的空中迅速地飞散开来。鸟儿在树丛中扑腾，兴高采烈地啁啾；苍翠欲滴的叶子在树梢上快乐而宁静地飒飒作响，而那些活着的树木的枝叶也在倒下的死树上面庄严地微微晃动。

The Death of Ivan Ilyich

1

In the large law court building, during an adjournment of the Melvinsky trial, the members of the Bench and the public prosecutor had come together in the office of Ivan Yegorovich Shebek, and the conversation touched on the celebrated Krasovsky case. Fyodor Vasilyevich argued vehemently that it was beyond their jurisdiction, Ivan Yegorovich had his own view and was sticking to it, while Pyotr Ivanovich, who had kept out of the discus-sion at the outset and was still not contributing, was perusing a copy of the Gazette which had just been delivered.

‘Gentlemen!’ he said. ‘Ivan Ilyich is dead.’

‘Is he really?’

‘Here you are. Read it yourself,’ he said to Fyodor Vasilyevich, handing him the paper, fresh off the press and still smelling.

There was an announcement within a black border：‘It is with profound sorrow that Praskovya Fyodorovna Golovina informs family and friends that her beloved husband, Ivan Ilyich Golovin, Member of the Court of Justice, passed away on the 4th of February this year, 1882. The funeral will take place on Friday at 1 p. m.’

Ivan Ilyich had been a colleague of the gentlemen assembled there, and they had all liked him. He had been ill for several weeks, and the word was that his ill-ness was incurable. His post had been kept open for him, but there was an understanding that in the event of his death Alexeyev would step into his place, and Alexeyev’s place would be taken by either Vinnikov or Shtabel. So, the first thought that occurred to each of the assembled gentlemen on hearing the news of his death was how this death might affect his own pros-pects, and those of their acquaintances, for transfer or promotion.

‘I’m sure to get Shtabel’s job now, or Vinnikov’s,’ thought Fyodor Vasilyevich. ‘They promised me ages ago, and a promotion like that would give me another eight hundred roubles a year, plus expenses.’

‘I must apply to have my brother-in-law transferred from Kaluga,’ thought Pyotr Ivanovich.‘My wife will be delighted. She won’t be able to tell me I never do any-thing for her people.’

‘I had a feeling he wasn’t going to get better,’ said Pyotr Ivanovich.‘It’s sad.’

‘What was actually wrong with him?’

‘The doctors couldn’t decide. Well, they could, but they all decided differently. The last time I saw him I thought he was going to come through it.’

‘And I haven’t been to see him since Christmas. I kept meaning to go.’

‘Was he all right financially?’

‘His wife had a bit of money, I think. Nothing very much.’

‘Well, we’ll have to go and see her. They live an awfully long way away.’

‘For you they do. Where you live, everywhere’s a long way away.’

‘Look at that. He can’t forgive me for living across the river,’ said Pyotr Ivanovich, smiling at Shebek. The con-versation turned to the long distances between the different parts of the city, and then they walked back into session.

Apart from the speculations aroused in each of them by this death, concerning the transfers and possible changes that this death might bring about, the very fact of the death of someone close to them aroused in all who heard about it, as always, a feeling of delight that he had died and they hadn’t.

‘There you have it. He’s dead, and I’m not’was what everyone thought or felt. But his closest acquaintances, Ivan Ilyich’s so-called friends, couldn’t help thinking that they would now have to fulfil some tedious social obligations such as attending the funeral and calling on the widow to express their condolences.

Closest of all were Fyodor Vasilyevich and Pyotr Ivanovich.

Pyotr Ivanovich was an old friend from law school, and he felt indebted to Ivan Ilyich.

Over dinner he told his wife about the death of Ivan Ilyich and the mooted possibility of her brother being transferred to their district, and then, dispensing with his usual nap, he put on a dress-coat and set off for Ivan Ilyich’s house.

At the entrance stood a carriage and two cabs. Down-stairs in the entrance hall, next to the coat stand, a coffin lid with silk brocade, tassels and gold braid that had been powdered and polished stood propped against a wall. Two ladies in black were taking off their fur cloaks. He knew one of them, Ivan Ilyich’s sister, but not the other. His colleague Schwartz was at the top of the stairs about to come down, but when he saw Pyotr Ivanovich he stopped and gave him a wink that seemed to say, ‘Ivan Ilyich has messed things up - not what you or I would have done.’

Schwartz’s face, with its English sidewhiskers and his lean figure in formal dress, exuded, as always, an air of elegant solemnity and, although the solemnity belied his playful personality, it was particularly poignant here, or so it seemed to Pyotr Ivanovich.

Pyotr Ivanovich allowed the ladies to pass on ahead, and slowly followed them upstairs. Instead of coming down, Schwartz stood waiting at the top. Pyotr Ivanovich knew why; he clearly wanted to arrange a game of whist somewhere that evening. The ladies proceeded upstairs to see the widow, but Schwartz pursed his lips tightly with all seriousness, though his eyes had a mischievous look as he twitched his eyebrows, directing Pyotr Ivanovich off to the right and into the room where the dead man lay.

Pyotr Ivanovich entered the room, and hesitated, as people always do on these occasions, not knowing pre-cisely what to do. The only thing he was certain of was that in this situation you couldn’t go wrong if you made the sign of the cross. Whether or not you should bow at the same time he wasn’t sure, so he went for a comprom-ise, crossing himself as he walked in and giving a bit of a bow as he did so. At the same time, as far as hand and head movements permitted, he glanced round the room. Two young persons, nephews apparently, one of them a schoolboy, were crossing themselves as they left the room. A little old woman was standing there motionless. And a lady with curiously arched eyebrows was whisper-ing to her. A church reader in a frock-coat - a hearty character of considerable spirit - was reading something out in a loud voice and a tone that brooked no contra-diction. Gerasim, the peasant who waited at table, darted ahead of Pyotr Ivanovich, sprinkling something on the floor. Seeing this, Pyotr Ivanovich instantly recognized a slight smell of decaying flesh. When he had visited Ivan Ilyich for the last time he had seen this peasant in Ivan Ilyich’s room, acting as a sick nurse, and Ivan Ilyich had had a special fondness for him.

Pyotr Ivanovich kept on crossing himself, and aimed a slight bow midway between the reader, the coffin and the icons on the corner table. Then, when the business of crossing himself seemed to be going on too long, he paused and took a close look at the dead man.

The dead man lay as all dead men lie, unusually heavy with his dead weight, with rigid limbs sinking into the soft lining of the coffin and his head bowed for eternity on the pillow, and he displayed what dead people always display, a waxen yellow forehead （with bald patches over his hollow temples） and a protruding nose that seemed to be pressing down hard on his upper lip. He had changed a good deal; he was even thinner than he had been when Pyotr Ivanovich had last seen him, but, as with all dead bodies, his face had acquired greater beauty, or, more to the point, greater significance, than it had had in life. Its expression seemed to say that what needed to be done had been done, and done properly. More than that, the expression contained a reproach, or at least a reminder, to the living. The reminder seemed out of place to Pyotr Ivanovich, or at least he felt it didn’t apply to him personally. But an unpleasant feeling came over him, and he crossed himself again, hurriedly - too hurriedly, he thought, the haste was almost indecent - before turn-ing and heading for the door.

Schwartz was waiting for him in the next room with his feet planted wide apart and both hands fiddling with the top hat held behind his back. One glance at his mischievous, immaculately elegant figure and Pyotr Ivanovich felt restored. He could see that Schwartz was above all this, and would be impervious to anything that might have been depressing. His very appearance spoke volumes：in no way would the occasion of Ivan Ilyich’s funeral serve as a reason for cancelling their usual ses-sion; in other words, nothing would prevent them from breaking open a new pack and riffling through the cards that evening while a servant set up four new candles. There was, in fact, no reason to think that this occasion should stop them having a good time that very evening. He said so in a low voice to Pyotr Ivanovich as he walked past, proposing that they meet for a game at Fyodor Vasilyevich’s.

But Pyotr Ivanovich was clearly not destined to play whist that evening. Praskovya Fyodorovna, a short, plump woman whose body expanded from the shoulders down despite her best efforts to the contrary, done out in black, with a lace shawl over her head and the same curiously arched eyebrows as the lady facing the coffin, emerged from her chambers with some other ladies, showed them to the door of the dead man’s room, and said, ‘The service is about to begin. Do go in.’

Schwartz made an indeterminate bow, and stood there without accepting or rejecting this invitation. Praskovya, recognizing Pyotr Ivanovich, gave a sigh, went straight up to him, took him by the hand, and said, ‘I know you were a good friend to Ivan Ilyich...’ And she looked at him, anticipating a suitable response. Pyotr Ivanovich knew that just as he had had to cross himself in there, out here it was necessary to squeeze her hand and say with a sigh, ‘Believe me...’ And that’s what he did. Having done it, he felt that the desired effect had been achieved - he had been touched, and she had been touched.

‘Let’s go in before they get started. I must have a word with you,’ said the widow.‘Give me your arm.’

Pyotr Ivanovich offered an arm and they made their way into the inner rooms, walking past Schwartz, who gave Pyotr Ivanovich a gloomy wink. ‘No whist for you, then. You won’t mind if we find another partner. We might make up a fivesome when you can get free,’ said his mischievous glance.

Pyotr Ivanovich sighed even more deeply and plain-tively, and Praskovya showed her gratitude by squeezing his hand. Proceeding into her drawing-room, which was done out in pink cretonne and lit by one dismal lamp, they sat down near to a table, she on a sofa, he on a low pouffe with broken springs that wobbled unevenly as he sat on it. Praskovya had wanted to warn him off into another chair, but a warning like that did not seem appro-priate in the circumstances, so she thought better of it. As he sat down on his pouffe, Pyotr Ivanovich remem-bered the time when Ivan Ilyich had been decorating this room and had asked his advice about this pink cretonne with the green leaves. On her way past the table to sit down on the sofa - the room was crammed with furniture and knick-knacks - Praskovya snagged the black lace of her black shawl on the carved edge of the table. Pyotr Ivanovich rose slightly to disentangle it, thus releasing the pouffe, which quivered and pushed up at him. The widow began disentangling the lace herself, so Pyotr Ivanovich sat down again, crushing the rebellious pouffe back into submission. But the widow had not finished disentangling herself, so Pyotr Ivanovich rose again, and so did the pouffe, rebellious and even creaking. When this was all over, she took out a clean cambric handker-chief and burst into tears. But Pyotr Ivanovich had cooled somewhat after the episode with the lace and the battle with the pouffe, and he sat there with a scowl on his face. The embarrassment was broken when Sokolov, Ivan Ilyich’s footman, came in to report that the plot which Praskovya had chosen in the cemetery was going to cost two hundred roubles. She had stopped weeping, and she looked at Pyotr Ivanovich with a victimized air as she told him in French how hard things were for her. Pyotr Ivanovich made a silent gesture to acknowledge his absolute conviction that it could not be otherwise.

‘Do smoke if you would like to,’ she said in a tone of voice that was magnanimous yet flat with defeat, and she went on to discuss the cost of the plot with Sokolov. As he lit his cigarette, Pyotr Ivanovich heard that she had made detailed enquiries about the cost of various plots of land before settling on the one she wanted. That was not all：once the plot had been ordered, she went on to make arrangements for the choir. Then Sokolov left.

‘I’m doing everything myself,’ she told Pyotr Ivanovich, pushing aside some albums on the table. Noticing that the table was under threat from the cigarette, she swiftly moved an ashtray across and spoke again. ‘I think it would be hypocritical to claim that I cannot manage practicalities because of my grief. On the contrary, if anything can... I won’t say console me, but... take my mind off things, it’s seeing to what has to be done about him.’ She took out her handkerchief again as if on the verge of tears, but suddenly she seemed to get a grip on her feelings, snapped out of it and spoke calmly. ‘But there is one thing I would like to discuss with you.’

Pyotr Ivanovich bowed his head. The springs shifted under him, but he did not let them have their way.

‘He suffered terribly those last few days.’

‘Did he really?’ asked Pyotr Ivanovich.

‘Oh yes, terribly. The last few minutes, no, hours really, he never stopped screaming. He screamed for three solid days without stopping for breath. It was unbearable. I don’t know how I got through it. You could hear him three rooms away. Oh, I’ve been through it all right!’

‘And was he conscious?’ asked Pyotr Ivanovich.

‘Yes,’ she whispered. ‘To the very end. He said goodbye a quarter of an hour before he died, and he was still ask-ing us to take Volodya away.’

For all the disagreeable awareness of hypocrisy, his own and hers, the thought of the suffering endured by a man he had known so well, first as a happy young lad, then as a schoolboy, then as an adult colleague, left Pyotr Ivanovich with a feeling of horror. Once again he could see that forehead, the nose pressing down on the upper lip, and he felt a pang of fear for himself.

‘Three days and three nights of horrible suffering, and then death. Just think, it could happen to me any time, now,’ he thought, and he felt that momentary pang of fear. But immediately he was saved, without knowing how, by the old familiar idea that this had happened to Ivan Ilyich, not him, and it could not and would not happen to him, and that kind of thinking would put him in a gloomy mood, for which there was no need, as Schwartz’s face had clearly demonstrated. Pursuing this line of thought, Pyotr Ivanovich calmed down and began to show a close interest in the details of Ivan Ilyich’s death, as if death was a chance experience that may have applied to Ivan Ilyich but certainly didn’t apply to him.

After giving a detailed account of the truly horrendous physical agony that Ivan Ilyich had endured （details that Pyotr Ivanovich learned only in terms of the distressing effect they had had on Praskovya）, the widow clearly saw that it was now necessary to get down to business.

‘Oh, Pyotr Ivanovich, it’s dreadful, absolutely dread-ful.’She burst into tears again.

Pyotr Ivanovich gave a sigh, and waited for her to blow her nose. When she had blown her nose, he said, ‘Believe me...’ Then she spoke out again, and told him what must have been the main reason for consulting him：it was all a matter of using the death of her husband to get some money from the Treasury. She made it seem as if she was asking Pyotr Ivanovich’s advice about getting a pension, but he could see that here she knew more than he did, she knew the finest details of this subject down to the last penny that could be screwed out of the Treas-ury in terms of death benefits. What she wanted to know was whether there might be some way of screwing a bit more out of them. Pyotr Ivanovich tried to think of some way of doing this but, having given it some thought and doing the decent thing by cursing the government for being so stingy, he said he thought there was no more to be had. Upon which she gave a sigh, and made no bones about getting rid of her visitor. He got the message, stubbed his cigarette out, stood up, shook hands, and went out into the hall.

In the dining-room with the clock that Ivan Ilyich had prided himself on having acquired in an antique shop, Pyotr Ivanovich came across a priest and a number of people that he knew, here for the funeral, and he saw a pretty young lady whom he also knew, Ivan Ilyich’s daughter. She was all in black. Her tiny waist looked tinier than ever. She looked gloomy, assertive, almost truculent. She bowed to Pyotr Ivanovich in a way that suggested he was to blame for something. Behind the daughter stood a wealthy young man, also known to Pyotr Ivanovich, who looked no less offended - he was an examining magistrate, her fiancé by all accounts. Pyotr Ivanovich gave a gloomy bow in their direction and was about to walk through into the dead man’s room when Ivan Ilyich’s schoolboy son, the image of his father, appeared from behind the stairwell. This was the little Ivan Ilyich that Pyotr Ivanovich remembered from law school. His tear-filled eyes were those of a twelve-or thirteen-year-old boy who has lost his innocence. Seeing Pyotr Ivanovich, he looked embarrassed and scowled morosely. Pyotr Ivanovich gave him a nod and walked into the dead man’s room. The funeral service was soon under way - candles, moaning, incense, tears, sobbing. Pyotr Ivanovich stood there with a frown on his face, staring at the legs of those in front of him. Not once did he look at the dead man or succumb to any feelings of weakness; he was one of the first to leave. There was no one in the hall. Gerasim, the servant of peasant stock, darted out of the dead man’s room, and sorted through all the fur coats with his big strong hands before finding Pyotr Ivanovich’s coat and handing it over.

‘Gerasim. How are you feeling, my boy?’ said Pyotr Ivanovich, who had to say something. ‘A bit sad?’

‘’Tis God’s will, sir.’Twill come to us all,’ said Ger-asim, displaying an even white row of peasant’s teeth, and then, with the air of a man with a lot of work to do, he wrenched the door open, called the driver up and sprang back to the porch steps, wondering what else needed to be done.

Pyotr Ivanovich found it particularly pleasant to inhale the fresh air after the incense, the corpse and carbolic.

‘Where to, sir?’ asked the coachman.

‘It’s still quite early. I think I’ll drop in on Fyodor Vasilyevich.’

And that’s where he went. And there they were, sure enough, finishing the first rubber. He was just in time to make up a fifth.

2

The past history of Ivan Ilyich’s life had been straight-forward, ordinary and dreadful in the extreme.

Ivan Ilyich had died at forty-five, a member of the Court of Justice. He was the son of an official who had worked his way through various ministries and depart-ments in Petersburg, carving out the kind of career which brings people to a position from which, despite their obvious incapacity for doing anything remotely useful, they cannot be sacked because of their status and long years of service, so they end up being given wholly false and fictitious jobs to do for which they receive salaries that are anything but fictitious, anything from six to ten thousand a year, and this enables them to live on to a ripe old age.

Such a man was Ilya Yefimovich Golovin, Privy Coun-cillor, superfluous member of various superfluous institutions.

He had three sons. Ivan Ilyich was the second son. The eldest had carved out the same career as his father but in a different ministry, and was now near to achieving the kind of seniority that confers sinecure status. The third son was a failure. He had gone through a series of jobs, ruining his prospects in all of them, and he now worked for the railways. His father, his brothers and espe-cially their wives not only hated meeting him but forgot his existence unless compelled to do otherwise. Their sister had married Baron Greff, a Petersburg official cut from the same cloth as his father-in-law. Ivan Ilyich was what they called le phénix de la famille. He was neither as cold and starchy as the elder brother nor as profligate as the younger. He was halfway between - an intelligent, lively, personable and decent man. He had attended law school along with his younger brother. The younger brother didn’t finish the course; he was expelled in the fifth grade, whereas Ivan Ilyich passed with honours. As a student he was already the kind of person he remained for the rest of his life, a capable man, cheerful and kind, sociable and convinced of the need to follow the path of duty - duty being anything so designated by higher authority. Boy and man he had avoided toadyism, but from his earliest years he was like a moth to the flame in being drawn towards people in authority, he assumed their mannerisms along with their philosophy of life, and he was on good terms with them. All the distractions of childhood and youth had passed him by leaving scarcely a trace; he had succumbed to both sensuality and vanity, and then in the top classes to liberal thinking, but always within limits unerringly set by his own instinctive feelings.

In his student days he had done things that at first he thought of as utterly revolting, things that made him feel disgusted with himself even as he was doing them, but in later life, noticing that the same things were being done by people of high standing without a qualm, although he couldn’t quite bring himself to think they were good, he did manage to dismiss them, and he felt no pangs of remorse when he recalled them.

When he graduated from law school, qualifying for the tenth grade of the civil service, and received enough money from his father to buy his basic necessities, Ivan Ilyich ordered a new set of clothes from Scharmer’s, hung a medallion on his watch chain inscribed with the words Respice finem, said goodbye to the prince and principal, dined at Donon’s with his friends, and set off for one of the provinces with his fashionable luggage, linen, clothes, shaving tackle, toiletries and travelling rug, all ordered and purchased from the very best shops, to take up a position arranged for him by his father as special assist-ant to the governor.

In the provinces it did not take Ivan Ilyich long to arrange a lifestyle that was as easy and agreeable as the one he had enjoyed at law school. He did his work, pursued his career and at the same time discreetly enjoyed himself. He went off now and then on official visits to country districts, cutting a dignified figure with superiors and inferiors alike, and he prided himself on carrying out his duties, especially in matters concerning religious dissidents, with scrupulous fairness and incorruptibility.

In his official duties, despite his youth and an attitude of some frivolity, he was exceedingly conservative, bureaucratic and even forbidding, but on the social side he was often amusing and witty, and always pleasantly polite - what the governor and the governor’s wife called a bon enfant, and with them he was like one of the family.

In the provinces he had an affair with a lady only too keen to liaise with a smart young lawyer. There was also a milliner, and there were drinking sessions with visiting aides-de-camp, as well as after-dinner excursions to a certain street on the outskirts. There was a need to work on the governor and even the governor’s wife in order to win them over. But all of this bore the stamp of high respectability to such an extent that no one could have called it by a bad name; all of it was catered for by what the French describe as ‘youth having its fling’. All of it was conducted with clean hands, in clean linen, in French phrases, and - what mattered most - at the highest level of society, which meant with approval from those in authority.

Ivan Ilyich spent five years in this kind of service, but the time came for a career change. New legal institutions were opening up; new men were needed.

Ivan Ilyich became one of the new men.

Ivan Ilyich was offered the post of examining magis-trate, and he took it, even though it meant moving to a new province, dropping all his old contacts and establish-ing new ones. Ivan Ilyich was given a send-off by his friends, who presented him with a silver cigarette case; they had a group photograph taken, and off he went to his new job.

As an examining magistrate Ivan Ilyich was just as comme il faut and respectable, just as capable of separ-ating official duty from private life and earning respect as he had been when working as a special assistant to the governor. The new work itself struck Ivan Ilyich as far more interesting and rewarding than his earlier job. Before, he had quite liked strutting about in his Scharmer uniform, sauntering past anxious petitioners and envious officials and walking straight into the governor’s office, where he would sit down for a cup of tea and a smoke. But not many people had been under his authority - only the rural police chiefs and the religious dissidents that he came across on his assignments - and he loved to treat these dependent people with a courteous, almost com-radely spirit, he loved to let them feel that although he had the power to crush them he was being straight with them, treating them like friends. There had not been many of them then, but now that Ivan Ilyich was an examining magistrate he felt that everyone without exception was in his power, even the most important and self-satisfied of people; at a stroke from his pen on headed notepaper any important or self-satisfied person could be brought before him as a defendant or witness to answer questions and be kept on his feet if Ivan Ilyich chose not to let him sit down. Far from abusing this power, he did his best to play it down, but his conscious-ness of that power and the very chance to play it down were what gave his new job its interest and appeal. In the work itself, the process of investigation, Ivan Ilyich soon mastered the technique of distancing himself from all irrelevancies and reducing the most complicated cases to a version that could be set down on paper in objective outline, excluding any personal opinion on his part, while observing all the necessary formalities, which was what mattered most. This was the new way of working, and he was one of the first men to implement the reformed Legal Code of 1864.

Ivan Ilyich’s transfer to a new town and the post of examining magistrate meant meeting new people and making new contacts; he also struck a new attitude, and slightly changed his tone. The new attitude involved dis-tancing himself somewhat from the provincial authorities while cultivating the best circles among the judiciary and the wealthy gentry of the town, and the new tone entailed mild dissatisfaction with the government, a degree of liberalism and a civilized man’s sense of public duty. At the same time, without compromising the fastidiousness of his dress sense, in his new situation he left his chin unshaven, allowing his beard to grow as and where it wanted.

In his new town, too, Ivan Ilyich set himself up very nicely. The section of society opposed to the governor was friendly and agreeable, his pay had gone up, and one thing that made his life particularly pleasurable was the playing of whist, which he now took to with the enjoy-ment of a skilled card-player, astute, quick-thinking and almost invariably a winner.

After two years working in the new town Ivan Ilyich met his future wife. Praskovya Fyodorovna Mikhel was the most attractive, intelligent and colourful young lady in the social circle frequented by Ivan Ilyich. To the list of other distractions and relaxations from his work as an examining magistrate Ivan Ilyich added a mild flirtation with Praskovya.

When he had been an assistant on special commissions Ivan Ilyich had been quite a dancer, but now he was an examining magistrate he took to the floor much less fre-quently. When he danced it was only as if to say, ‘Look, I may be part of the reformed system, and I’ve got as far as Grade 5, but if you want to see me on the floor I can show you that even in dancing I can be the best.’ So, just occasionally, he would take to the floor with Praskovya at the end of an evening, and it was actually while dan-cing like this that he won her heart. She fell in love with him. Ivan Ilyich had no clear and definite plans for mar-riage, but once the girl fell in love with him he began to wonder. ‘When all’s said and done, why shouldn’t I get married?’ he asked himself.

This young woman, Praskovya Fyodorovna, belonged to a good family, and she was quite attractive. She also came with a little money. Ivan Ilyich might have held out for a more brilliant partner, but she was herself a decent catch. Ivan was earning good money, and he could count on something similar from her. It would be a good match - she was a nice girl, quite pretty and a thoroughly decent young woman. To claim that Ivan Ilyich got mar-ried because he was in love with his bride, and saw in her someone who shared his outlook on life, would have been no more justifiable than to say that he married because the match met with the approval of the society that he moved in. Ivan Ilyich married for both reasons. He was pleasing himself by acquiring such a wife, but at the same time he was appealing to his superiors and their sense of propriety.

So, Ivan Ilyich got married.

The process of getting married, and the early days of married life, with conjugal caresses, new furniture, new crockery, new linen, everything up to his wife’s preg-nancy, went very smoothly, to the extent that Ivan Ilyich was beginning to think that marriage would not disrupt his easy, agreeable and enjoyable lifestyle, which was decency itself, approved of by society and something that Ivan Ilyich considered to be part of life itself - and it might even improve it. But it was at this stage, during the first months of his wife’s pregnancy, that something happened, something new, unexpected, unpleasant, dif-ficult and disgusting, something that could not have been anticipated and could not in any way be got rid of.

For no reason that Ivan Ilyich could fathom, other than what he called gaîté de coeur, his wife did begin to disrupt the pleasant and decent run of his life. She became jeal-ous of him for no apparent cause, demanded his closest attention, laid into him and started arguments that were unpleasantly vulgar.

At first Ivan Ilyich hoped to escape the unpleasantness of his new situation by relapsing into the same carefree but respectable way of life that had stood him in good stead before - he tried to ignore his wife’s moodiness and carry on in the easy, agreeable way that he had formerly enjoyed, inviting friends round for a game of cards and trying to get out and drive round to the club or visit people close to him. But there came a time when his wife started shouting at him so furiously, using such foul lan-guage, determined to keep on yelling at him when he failed to do what she wanted, obviously with every inten-tion of keeping it up until he came to heel, stayed in and went through the same anguish that she felt, that Ivan Ilyich was horrified. He realized that married life - at least with his wife - didn’t always mean enjoyment and decency, but, on the contrary, it often disrupted them, and it was therefore necessary to guard against such dis-ruptions. And Ivan Ilyich began to seek ways of doing this. His work was the one thing that impressed Pras-kovya, and it was through work and the commitments associated with it that he took on his wife and asserted his own independence.

When the baby was born, with the various difficulties with feeding, the real and imaginary illnesses of mother and child, which demanded his sympathetic involvement even though he understood nothing about them, the need for Ivan Ilyich to safeguard his independence became even more urgent.

As his wife grew more and more irritable and demand-ing, Ivan Ilyich gradually shifted his life’s centre of gravity on to his work. He loved his work more and more, and became more ambitious than he had been.

It didn’t take him long - no more than a year after his wedding - to realize that although married life did pro-vide some conveniences, it was actually rather a complex and difficult business, and the path of duty, which meant leading a decent life approved of by society, called for a clearly defined attitude, as at work.

And Ivan Ilyich managed to establish such an attitude towards his married life. He required of it whatever domestic conveniences it could provide in terms of meals on the table, a good household and a bed and, most important, the outward show of respectability that soci-ety required. Beyond this, he required some enjoyment and pleasure, and if he found this he was very thankful, but if he was met with rejection and crabbiness he imme-diately took himself off into his own separate, carefully guarded world, the world of work which gave him pleasure.

Ivan Ilyich was considered a good colleague, and within three years he was promoted to assistant chief prosecutor. His new responsibilities, the importance that they entailed, the opportunity of bringing people before the court and sending them to prison, the publicity given to his speeches, and the success enjoyed by Ivan Ilyich in these matters - all of this made his work seem even more enjoyable.

Other children were born. His wife was becoming more and more bad-tempered and crabby, but the new attitude established by Ivan Ilyich towards his home life made him all but impervious to her crabbiness.

After serving for seven years in the same town Ivan Ilyich was transferred to another province, as public pros-ecutor. They moved, they were short of money, and his wife didn’t like the town they had moved to. His salary had gone up, but so had their living expenses. On top of that, two of their children died, and family life became even more unpleasant for Ivan Ilyich.

Praskovya blamed her husband for all the setbacks they were suffering in their new place of residence. Most of the topics of conversation between husband and wife, especially about bringing up the children, led to ques-tions that reminded them of past arguments, and new arguments were liable to flare up at any moment. They were left with a few short periods of amorousness that came over them as husband and wife, but these did not last long. These were nothing more than little islands where they could anchor for a while, only to plunge back into a sea of hidden hostility as they grew further and further apart. This growing apart might have upset Ivan Ilyich if he had thought there was anything wrong with it, but now not only did he consider this state of affairs to be quite normal, he saw it as the whole point of his role in the family. His role was to distance himself increasingly from all the unpleasantness and give it an air of harmless respectability; this he achieved by spend-ing less and less time with the family, and when he was forced to be with them he sought to safeguard his own position by ensuring the presence of others. But the main thing was that Ivan Ilyich did have his work. It was in the world of his work that the whole interest of his life came into focus. And this interest absorbed him totally. The knowledge of the power that he wielded, the possi-bility of ruining anyone that he fancied ruining, the gravitas（even if it was all outward show）which could be sensed as he walked into court or dealt with his subordin-ates, the success that he was enjoying with his superiors and subordinates alike, and, above all, his masterly hand-ling of the cases - all of this gave him pleasure, and, along with chit-chat with colleagues, dinners and whist, filled his life to the full. And so, life in general proceeded for Ivan Ilyich just as he thought it should proceed - pleasantly and respectably.

He lived like this for about seven years. Their daughter, the eldest child, was now sixteen, another child had died and their one remaining son was the subject of strong disagreement. Ivan Ilyich wanted to send him to law school, but Praskovya had defied him by putting him down for the high school. The daughter was being edu-cated at home, and was developing nicely; the boy too was doing quite well at his studies.

3

This was the course that Ivan Ilyich’s life had taken dur-ing the seventeen years that followed his wedding. He was now a senior public prosecutor who had turned down several transfers in the hope of securing an even more desirable position, but then suddenly an unpleasant cir-cumstance arose which looked like completely disrupting the peaceful progress of his life. Ivan Ilyich was expect-ing an appointment as presiding judge in a university town, but Hoppe pipped him at the post and got the job. Ivan Ilyich was livid, and he made some insinuations, taking issue with Hoppe himself and his immediate super-iors. He was met with a chill rebuff, and was overlooked again when the next appointment came up.

This was in 1880.That year was the hardest he ever lived through. It was a year in which it transpired, for one thing, that they couldn’t make ends meet financially, and, for another, that he was a forgotten man and, whereas he saw himself as the victim of an outrageously cruel injustice, everyone else thought it was just the way things went. Even his father saw it as no duty of his to help out. He felt deserted by everyone; they all thought that his situation, with a salary of three thousand five hundred roubles, was perfectly normal, even fortunate. He was the only person who knew that, with all the injust-ices that had been visited upon him, with nothing but nagging from his wife, and the debts that were now mounting up because he was living beyond his means - he was the only one who knew that his position was anything but normal.

That summer, in order to cut costs, he took leave of absence and went with his wife for a country holiday at her brother’s place. In the country, with no work to occupy him, Ivan Ilyich had his first experience of not just boredom but unbearable anguish. He decided he couldn’t go on like this - definite steps must be taken.

During a sleepless night, the whole of which he spent pacing the terrace, he decided he would go to Petersburg and make representations; he would get his own back on those men who had underestimated him, by changing ministries. Next morning he defied all the remonstra-tions from his wife and brother-in-law, and left for Petersburg.

He went with one aim in mind：to get himself a position that would bring in five thousand a year. By now he had no allegiance to any particular ministry, faction or func-tion. All he needed was a job, a job that would bring in five thousand a year, in administration, in one of the banks, with the railways, in one of the charitable institu-tions set up by the Dowager Empress Maria, even in the customs service; all that mattered was five thousand a year and an immediate transfer from the ministry where he was so undervalued.

And his trip was crowned with unexpected, un-believable success. At Kursk, an acquaintance of his, F. S.Ilyin, got into his first-class carriage, sat down and told him that the governor of the province had just received a telegram informing him of a reshuffle in the ministry - Pyotr Ivanovich was being replaced by Ivan Semyonovich.

The proposed reshuffle, whatever its impact on Russia at large, meant something special to Ivan Ilyich：the emergence of Pyotr Petrovich, and also apparently his friend, Zakhar Ivanovich, was very good news for him. Zakhar Ivanovich was a colleague and friend.

The new development had been confirmed in Moscow; now, arriving in Petersburg, Ivan Ilyich looked up Zakhar, who promised him a definite position in his for-mer department, the Ministry of Justice.

Within a week he was able to send the following tele-gram to his wife：Zakhar replaces Miller. Appointment mine with first report.

Because of this change of staff Ivan Ilyich had sud-denly achieved a position in his former ministry which put him two grades higher than his colleagues, with five thousand a year plus three thousand five hundred roubles removal expenses. All the acrimony that he had felt towards his enemies and the ministry in general was for-gotten, and Ivan Ilyich was a happy man.

He returned to the country feeling in high spirits, more contented than he had been for a long time. Praskovya’s spirits had also picked up, and a truce was declared between the two of them. Ivan Ilyich described how hon-oured he had been in Petersburg, how his former enemies had been put to shame and were now licking his boots, how people envied him his new position, and, most of all, how popular he had been in Petersburg.

Praskovya listened to all of this, pretending to believe it and not querying anything, but her real interest was only in sketching out the new way of life that they would lead in the city to which they were moving. And Ivan Ilyich was delighted to see that her plans were his plans, they were together as one, and that his life, having hit a bad patch, was now getting back to its old way, its true path of happy enjoyment and respectability.

Ivan Ilyich had not come back for long. He had to take up his duties on the 10th of September, and before that he had to settle into new surroundings, have all his things brought in from the provinces, buy in and order up many more items - in other words he had set up home just as he had worked things out in his own mind, which was almost exactly as Praskovya had worked things out in her own heart.

And now that everything had been set up so success-fully, and he and his wife were agreed in their aims, having lived together so little of late, they came together more closely than at any time since they were first mar-ried. Ivan Ilyich had intended to move his family in straightaway, but at the insistence of his sister-in-law and brother-in-law, who were suddenly all over Ivan Ilyich and his family, it was arranged for him to go on alone.

Ivan Ilyich set out on his journey. The happy feelings brought on by his success and a rapprochement with his wife, each intensifying the other, never left him. He found a delightful place, a dream apartment for him and his wife. The spacious, high-ceilinged reception rooms with their old-fashioned décor, the gracefully appointed and comfortable study, the rooms for his wife and daughter, the classroom for his son - all of it seemed to have been designed with them in mind. Ivan Ilyich took it upon himself to organize the fittings and furnishings; he chose the wallpaper, purchased furniture, predominantly of the old-fashioned style which he considered to be comme il faut, the upholstery... and the whole thing grew and grew, approaching the ideal that he had set himself. Even halfway through the refurbishment, the whole thing exceeded his expectations. He could see how elegant it would all be, quite comme il faut and devoid of vulgarity, when it was completed. As he went to sleep he would imagine what the large reception room was going to look like. When he glanced into the half-finished drawing-room he could envisage the fireplace, the screen, the whatnot and the little chairs dotted about the room, the plates and dishes on the walls and the bronze pieces, everything in its proper place. He enjoyed the thought of surprising Pasha and Lizanka, who were not without taste them-selves. This was beyond their expectations. He had been particularly successful in tracking down antiques and buying them at bargain prices; they now gave the whole place an air of distinction. He deliberately understated everything in his letters home so that they would be sur-prised. He was so taken up with all of this that the work he loved so dearly interested him less than he had thought it would. In court he found his mind wandering; he would be miles away, wondering whether to have plain or moulded cornices with his curtains. He became so involved that he often did the work himself, rearrang-ing the furniture and rehanging the curtains. On one occasion, climbing a stepladder to show a dull-witted upholsterer how to hang the draperies, he slipped and fell, though he was strong and agile enough to hold on, and all he did was bump his side on a window-frame knob. The bruised place hurt for a while but it soon passed off. And all this time Ivan Ilyich felt particularly well and in the best of spirits.‘I seem to have shed fifteen years,’ he wrote home. He had hoped to get it all finished by the end of September, but things dragged on until mid-October. Still, it was magnificent, and he wasn’t the only one to say so - everybody did.

But these were essentially the accoutrements that appeal to all people who are not actually rich but who want to look rich, though all they manage to do is look like each other：damasks, ebony, plants, rugs and bronzes, anything dark and gleaming - everything that all people of a certain class affect so as to be like all other people of a certain class. And his arrangements looked so much like everyone else’s that they were unremarkable, though he saw them as something truly distinctive. When he met his family at the railway station, brought them home and ushered them into his well-lit furnished apartment and a footman wearing a white tie opened the door into the entrance hall decorated with flowers, and then they went into the drawing-room and the study, ooh-ing and ah-ing with delight, he was a very happy man, showing them around everywhere, revelling in their praise and beaming with delight. That evening, as they took tea, when Pras-kovya asked him casually about his fall he gave a laugh and demonstrated how he had gone flying and given the upholsterer a scare.

‘It’s a good job I’m athletic. Any other man would have killed himself, but all I did was bruise myself a bit here. It hurts when you touch it, but it’s getting better. It is only a bruise.’

And so they began life in their new abode, where, as always happens with people who have recently settled in, they found themselves just one room short, and their new income wouldn’t quite run to it, though it was only a matter of five hundred roubles or so. Still, they were very nicely off, especially during the early days when not everything was finished and work was still to be done - things had to be bought, ordered, rearranged, adjusted. There were one or two disagreements between husband and wife, but both of them were so satisfied and so busy that everything resolved itself without serious arguments. When there was nothing more to be finished off they developed a feeling of dullness and a sense of something missing, but by this time they had got to know new people and formed new habits. Their lives had filled out.

Ivan Ilyich would return for lunch after a morning in court and in those early days he tended to be in a good mood; any slight distress that he suffered came from the apartment itself. （The slightest stain on a tablecloth or upholstery, or a loose cord on the draperies annoyed him; he had put so much effort into the furnishings that the slightest disturbance upset him.） But, all things consid-ered, Ivan Ilyich’s life went along, as he saw it, just as life ought to go - easily, pleasantly, decently. He rose at nine, drank some coffee, read the newspaper, then put on his uniform and went to court. There, the collar that he worked in had been worn into shape and he soon found that it fitted him well - the petitioners, the en-quiries received, the office, the public sessions and the administrative meetings. In all of this the trick was to eliminate the element of crude everyday life that always disrupts the smooth flow of official business; no relation-ships should be entered into beyond the official ones, the reason behind any relationship had to be strictly official and the relationship itself had to be strictly official. Say, for example, a person arrives wanting to know some-thing. This is not the responsibility of Ivan Ilyich; he can have no relationship with such a person. But if this per-son were to approach him in his capacity as a member of the judiciary and in a relationship that can be set down on letterhead paper, within the terms of that relationship Ivan Ilyich will do anything he can, and do it decisively, while maintaining a semblance of friendly human relations - nothing more than common courtesy. At the point where an official relationship breaks off, everything else breaks off, too. The skill of compartmentalizing the official side of things and keeping that apart from his own real life was one that Ivan Ilyich possessed in the highest degree; long practice and natural talent had en-abled him to refine it to such a degree that now he could act like a virtuoso performer, occasionally allowing him-self to mix human and official relationships by way of a joke. He allowed himself this liberty because he felt strong enough whenever necessary to reinstate the dis-tinction between the official and the human by discarding the latter. This was more than just an easy, pleasant and decent thing for Ivan Ilyich to do - he was acting like a virtuoso performer. During his breaks he would have a smoke, drink tea and chat, exchange a word or two about politics, current affairs and cards, and a whole lot more about who was in and who was out. And he would go home tired, but feeling like a virtuoso performer, a first violin in the orchestra, who has given of his best. At home his daughter and his wife would either have been out visiting or would have entertained someone at home, while his son, back from school, would have had a session with his private tutors and gone on to cram whatever it is they teach in schools. Everything was fine. After din-ner, if there were no guests, Ivan Ilyich sometimes read a book that people were talking about, and later in the evening he sat down to do some work, reading through papers, studying the law, comparing depositions and sorting them by statute. This neither bored nor amused him. He found it boring when he might have been play-ing whist, but if whist was off it was better than just sitting there on his own or with his wife. What gave Ivan Ilyich real pleasure, though, was having little dinner par-ties to which he would invite ladies and gentlemen of good social standing and passing the time with them precisely as such people invariably do pass the time, in the way that his drawing-room was exactly like all the others.

One day they held an evening party with dancing. Ivan Ilyich enjoyed it and everything went swimmingly, except for a big row between him and his wife over the cakes and sweets. Praskovya had had her own ideas, but Ivan Ilyich had insisted on bringing in an expensive caterer who had provided too many cakes; the leftovers had caused the row when the caterer’s bill came to forty-five roubles. The row was a big one, very nasty, and it ended with Praskovya calling him a stupid fool while he clutched his head and muttered something about divorce. But he still enjoyed the party. The best people were there and Ivan Ilyich danced with Princess Tru-fonova, whose sister had famously founded the charity known as ‘Take Away My Sorrow’.Pleasure derived from work was self-indulgence, pleasure derived from social-izing tickled his vanity, but real pleasure came to Ivan Ilyich only from playing cards. He was prepared to admit that, at the end of the day, with any amount of unpleas-antness behind him, the one pleasure that outshone all others like a beacon was to sit down and play whist with quiet-mannered partners, good players, always in a four-some （sitting out was such a bore when there were five, and you had to pretend not to mind）, and playing ser-iously and playing well （when you got a decent hand） before going on to supper with a glass of wine. And after a game of cards, especially if he had won a small amount（big winnings were not nice）, Ivan Ilyich would go to bed in the very best of spirits.

This was how they lived. They moved in the best of circles, receiving people of quality, and the younger set.

In their attitude towards the circle of their acquaint-ances husband, wife and daughter were of one mind. Without collusion, each of them in the same way shrugged off and discarded all the shabby friends and relatives who flocked around fawning on them in the drawing-room with the Japanese plates on the walls. It wasn’t long before the shabby friends stopped flocking around and left the Golovin family to the best people in society and no one else. Young men were attracted to their little Liza and one examining magistrate by the name of Petrish-chev, the son of Dmitriy Ivanovich Petrishchev and his sole heir, became so attentive towards her that Ivan Ilyich mentioned this once or twice to Praskovya and wondered whether they ought perhaps to take them out for a ride in a troika or set up some private theatricals. This was how they lived. This was how things went, nothing changed, and everything was fine.

4

They were all in good health. The fact that Ivan Ilyich sometimes complained of a strange taste in his mouth and a funny feeling in his left side didn’t count as ill health. But as it happened this funny feeling began to get worse and turned into, if not pain exactly, a constant dragging sensation in his side, which put him in a bad mood. And this bad mood, which got worse and worse, began to spoil the pleasant, easy-going and respectable way of life that the Golovins had just set up for them-selves. There were more and more quarrels between husband and wife, the pleasant, easy-going way of life lapsed, and they were hard put to keep up an appear-ance of decency. Once again scenes became more and more frequent. They were left once again with nothing more than those little islands, all too few of them, on which husband and wife could come together without an explosion.

And now Praskovya began to say, not without justifi-cation, that her husband was a hard man. With her usual capacity for exaggeration she claimed that he had always been horrible like that and only her good nature had enabled her to put up with it for twenty years. It was true that all the arguments now began on his side. His jibes always started just as they sat down to dinner, often over the soup. There was always something - if it wasn’t chipped crockery or something wrong with the food, he would go on about his son putting his elbow on the table or his daughter’s hair. And it was always Praskovya’s fault. To begin with, Praskovya would take issue with him and say something nasty, but on a couple of occa-sions he flew into such a rage at the beginning of dinner that she realized this was a pathological condition brought on by consuming food, so she bit it all back, stopped objecting and got on with her dinner as fast as she could. Praskovya took great pride in biting things back. Convinced that her husband was a horrible man who had made her life a misery, she was now sorry for herself. And the sorrier she became, the more she hated her husband. She began to wish he was dead, and then not to, because without him there would be no income. All of which made her even more exasperated with him. She felt thoroughly miserable at the thought that not even his death could rescue her. She was exasperated, though she hid it, but her hidden exasperation served only to strengthen his exasperation.

After one scene during which Ivan Ilyich had been particularly unfair and after which, by way of explan-ation, he had admitted being exasperating but claimed he was ill, she told him that if he was ill he needed treat-ment and insisted that he must go and see a famous doctor.

He did. The whole thing turned out just as he had expected, and as it always does. He was made to wait, the doctor was full of his own importance - an attitude he was familiar with because it was one that he himself assumed in court - then came all the tapping and listen-ing, the questions with predetermined and obviously superfluous answers, the knowing look that seemed to say, ‘Just place yourself in our hands and we’ll sort it out, we know what we’re doing, there’s no doubt about it, we can sort things out the same way as we would for anyone you care to name.’It was just like being in court. The way he looked at the accused in court was exactly the way he was being looked at now by the famous doctor.

The doctor was holding forth. Such-and-such demon-strates that in your insides there is such-and-such, but if this is not confirmed by our tests on this-and-that then you will need to go on to such-and-such. And if you go on to such-and-such, then... and so on. As far as Ivan Ilyich was concerned there was only one question that mattered：is this condition life-threatening or not? But the doctor treated this question as irrelevant, and ignored it. From the doctor’s point of view it was a pointless ques-tion not worthy of discussion; the only thing was a balancing of probabilities - floating kidney, chronic col-itis, problem with the blind gut. The question of Ivan Ilyich living or dying didn’t arise; there was just this conflict between the floating kidney and the blind gut. And before his very eyes the doctor resolved the conflict at a brilliant stroke in favour of the floating kidney, with the sole proviso that new evidence might emerge from the urine test, and if that happened the case would have to be reviewed. All of it from start to finish was precisely what Ivan Ilyich himself had done to the accused a thou-sand times and with no less brilliance. Brilliant indeed was the doctor’s summing-up of the situation as he looked in triumph bordering on delight over his glasses at his own prisoner in the dock. From the summary Ivan Ilyich drew only one conclusion：he was in a bad way and the doctor didn’t care, nobody cared probably, but he was in a bad way. And this conclusion left Ivan Ilyich with a sickly feeling, filling him with self-pity and great animos-ity towards the doctor who showed so much indifference to such an important question.

But he said nothing about it. He got up, laid his money on the table and said, with a sigh, ‘I’m sure that when we’re ill we ask a lot of pointless questions. But, er, is it life-threatening or not...?’

The doctor glared at him through one eye over his glasses as if to say, ‘Prisoner in the dock, if you will not confine yourself to answering the questions put to you I shall have to arrange for you to be removed from the courtroom.’

‘I have already told you what I consider necessary and appropriate. Anything further will be determined by the tests.’The doctor bowed.

Ivan Ilyich walked out slowly, climbed gloomily into his sledge and drove home. All the way back he kept going over in his mind everything the doctor had said, trying to translate his confusingly complex technicalities into everyday speech and find in them an answer to one question：am I in a bad way, a really bad way, or is it nothing to worry about just now? And it seemed to him that the message from all that the doctor had said was yes, you’re in a very bad way. Ivan Ilyich thought the streets looked dismal. The drivers looked dismal, the houses looked dismal, and so did the pedestrians and the shops. And in the light of the doctor’s confusing pro-nouncements the pain, that dull, nagging pain that never went away, was taking on a new and more serious signifi-cance. It was with a new feeling of dejection that Ivan Ilyich focused on it.

He reached home and started to tell his wife. His wife listened closely, but halfway through his account their daughter came in wearing a little hat - she and her mother were on their way out. She made an effort to sit down and listen to his boring story, but she couldn’t contain herself for long and her mother gave up listening.

‘Well, I’m very pleased,’ said his wife.‘And now, you listen to me. Make sure you take your medicine properly. Give me the prescription and I’ll send Gerasim to the chemist’s.’ And she went off to get dressed.

He had hardly paused for breath while she was in the room, and when she went out he gave a deep sigh.

‘Oh well,’ he said. ‘Maybe that’s right. Nothing to worry about just now...’

He started taking his medicine and following the doc-tor’s instructions, though these were changed once the urine test results were in. But at this point it turned out that there was some confusion over the test itself and what was supposed to follow it. Without getting at the doctor, it was becoming clear that what was going on was not what the doctor had said. He must have overlooked something, or he had been telling lies, or he was hiding something.

Nevertheless, Ivan Ilyich started to follow his instruc-tions, and from the process of doing so he derived some comfort for a while. Since his visit to the doctor Ivan Ilyich had made it his main preoccupation to follow all instructions to the letter in matters of hygiene, the taking of medicine, focusing on his pain and monitoring all his bodily functions. His main interests were in human sick-ness and human health. When he overheard anyone talking about people who had fallen ill, died or recover-ed, especially if the illness sounded like his own, he tried to hide his agitation but he listened closely, asked lots of questions and applied what he heard to his own illness.

The pain was not getting any less, but Ivan Ilyich made every effort to make himself believe he was feeling better. And he was able to delude himself as long as nothing upset him. But the moment he fell out with his wife, or something went wrong at work or he got a bad hand at whist, he felt the full force of his illness. Before this he had been able to withstand setbacks like these, expecting to put things right before long, to win through, succeed again, come out with a grand slam. But now the slightest setback cut the ground from under him and left him in despair. He would say to himself, ‘Look at that. I was just starting to get better and the medicine was just beginning to work, and now this damn thing comes up, this rotten luck...’ And he raged against his misfortune or against those people who were causing his problems and killing him off; he sensed that it was his own rage that was killing him and he couldn’t control it. It ought to have been obvious to him that raging against his situ-ation and the people around him was only feeding his illness and, because of that, he ought to ignore any unpleasant developments, but he thought the exact opposite：he told himself he needed peace of mind so he had to get on to anything that disrupted his peace of mind, and the slightest disruption left him exasperated. His situation was made worse by the fact that he had taken to reading medical books and consulting doctors. The decline was so gradual that he was able to delude himself by comparing one day with another and seeing little difference. But the moment he consulted a doctor he thought he was going downhill, and fast. Yet, despite this, he kept on consulting the doctors.

That month he went to see another celebrity. This celeb-rity told him more or less the same as the first one, but put things differently. And the consultation with this celebrity served only to reinforce Ivan Ilyich’s doubts and fears. A friend of a friend - a very good doctor - diagnosed something entirely different and, even though he swore he would get better, his questions and assump-tions confused Ivan Ilyich even more and deepened his suspicions. A homeopath produced yet another diagnosis and gave him some medicine, which Ivan Ilyich took for a week or so without telling anyone. But by the end of the week, feeling no better and losing faith in every treat-ment that had been prescribed so far including that one, he felt more despondent than ever. One day a lady of his acquaintance talked to him about the curative powers of icons. Ivan Ilyich caught himself listening closely to what she was saying, and beginning to accept it as fact. This scared him.‘Am I really going weak in the head?’he wondered.‘Nonsense. It’s all rubbish! I’m not falling for stupid ideas like that. I’d rather pick one doctor and stick to what he says. That’s what I’m going to do. That’s it. I’m going to stop thinking about it, and follow the treat-ment to the letter until the summer. Then we’ll see. No more shilly-shallying.’This was easy to say but impossible to do. The pain in his side went on wearing him down and seemed to be getting worse, nagging incessantly, while the taste in his mouth got more and more peculiar and he began to think that his breath smelt awful, and his appetite and strength fell away. The time for fooling himself was over：something new and dreadful was going on inside Ivan Ilyich, something significant, more sig-nificant than anything in his whole life. And he was the only one who knew it; the people around him didn’t know, or didn’t want to know - they thought that every-thing in the world was going on as before. This was what tormented Ivan Ilyich more than anything. He could see that his family - especially his wife and daughter, whose visiting season was in full swing - had no inkling; it annoyed them that he was not much fun and asked so much of them - as if he was to blame. Despite their best efforts to hide it, he could see that he was in their way. His wife had developed an attitude to his illness and she was sticking to it whatever he might say or do. Her atti-tude went like this：‘You know what it’s like,’ she would say to her friends.‘Ivan Ilyich can’t be like other people. He won’t stick to his treatment. One moment he takes his drops and eats what he’s supposed to, and goes to bed when he should; the next day, if I’m not watching him, he doesn’t take his medicine, he eats sturgeon - which he’s not allowed - and he stays up playing whist until one in the morning.’

‘Oh, come on,’ says Ivan Ilyich.‘I did that once, with Pyotr Ivanovich.’

‘What about yesterday, with Shebek?’

‘It made no difference. I couldn’t sleep with all that pain...’

‘Well, it doesn’t matter why. Only you’ll never get bet-ter like that, and it’s getting us down.’

Praskovya’s attitude towards Ivan Ilyich’s illness, of which she made no secret to other people or to him, was that it was all his fault; he was making his wife’s life a misery yet again. Ivan Ilyich felt she was doing this unconsciously, but that didn’t make things any easier for him.

In court Ivan Ilyich noticed, or thought he noticed, the same strange attitude towards him. There were times when he thought people were watching him closely like a man who was about to give up his job; at other times his associates would make friendly little jokes about the way he worried over his health, as if this ghastly, fearful, unheard-of thing that had got going inside him and was now incessantly gnawing at him and inexorably taking him away was a good subject and a laughing matter. The one who infuriated him most was Schwartz, with his playfulness, joie de vivre and all-round respectability which recalled the Ivan Ilyich of ten years before.

His friends have come round for a game of cards. They take their places and deal, softening the new cards. He sorts his diamonds - seven of them. His partner bids no trumps and supports him with two diamonds. Couldn’t be better. This should be a wonderful, joyous moment - a grand slam is on. But suddenly he feels that gnawing pain, that taste in his mouth, and he is struck by the bar-barity of rejoicing in a grand slam.

He glances across at his partner, Mikhail Mikhay-lovich, who is tapping the table with an eager hand, politely and graciously holding back from grabbing the tricks and pushing them towards Ivan Ilyich so that he can enjoy the pleasure of raking them in without having to make any effort or reaching very far.‘Does he think I’m too weak to reach out?’ thinks Ivan Ilyich, forgetting what are trumps and overtrumping his partner with his own, which leaves them three tricks short of a grand slam. And worst of all, he can see how upset Mikhail Mikhaylovich is, and he doesn’t care. And it is awful to think why he doesn’t care.

They can all see that he is distraught, and they say to him, ‘We can stop if you’re feeling tired. Why don’t you have a rest?’ Rest? No, he’s not tired. They finish the rub-ber. They are all gloomy and silent. Ivan Ilyich senses that he has caused the gloom, and he cannot dispel it. They have supper and go home, and Ivan Ilyich is left there alone with the knowledge that his life has been poisoned and is poisoning other people’s lives, and the poison is not wearing off, it is working its way deeper and deeper into his very being.

And he has to take this knowledge to bed with him, along with the physical pain and the terror, often to spend a near-sleepless night because of the pain. And next morning he has to get up again, put on his clothes, go to court, talk, write or, if he doesn’t go out, stay in with every one of those twenty-four hours that make up a day and a night, each one of them an agony. And he has to live like this on the edge of destruction, alone, with nobody at all to understand and pity him.

5

One month passed like this, then another. His brother-in-law came to their town to stay with them for the New Year celebrations. Ivan Ilyich was in court when he arrived. Praskovya was out shopping. On his return Ivan Ilyich walked into his study and found his brother-in-law already there, a strong, fit young man, busy unpacking his own suitcase. He looked up when he heard Ivan Ilyich approaching and stared at him in silence for a moment. That stare told Ivan Ilyich every-thing. His brother-in-law opened his mouth to exclaim, but managed to restrain himself. That movement con-firmed everything.

‘I’ve changed, haven’t I?’

‘Well ... you have rather.’

And after this, however hard Ivan Ilyich tried to raise the subject of his appearance, his brother-in-law wouldn’t say a word. Praskovya arrived home and her brother went to see her. Ivan Ilyich locked the door and went to have a good look at himself in the mirror, full face, then in profile. He picked up a photograph of himself with his wife and compared his likeness with what he now saw in the mirror. The difference was enormous. Then he pulled his sleeves up, looked at his arms, pulled his sleeves back down and sat down on an ottoman, looking blacker than night.

‘No, no. I mustn’t,’ he told himself. He jumped up and went to his desk, where he opened a file and began to read, but he couldn’t go on. He opened the door and went out into the hallway. The door into the drawing-room was shut. He tiptoed over to it and started to listen.

‘No, you’re exaggerating,’ Praskovya was saying.

‘What do you mean, exaggerating? You can’t see it. He’s a dead man. Look at his eyes - there’s no light in them. What is it he’s got exactly?’

‘Nobody knows. Nikolayev [yet another doctor] said something, but I don’t know what it was. Leshchetitsky [the celebrity] said the exact opposite...’

Ivan Ilyich walked away back into his room, lay down and started to think things over. ‘Kidney, a floating kid-ney...’ He could remember everything the doctors had told him about it becoming detached and starting to wander. With an effort of his imagination he tried to catch the kidney, stop it moving and fix it strongly. It seemed to take so little effort.‘No, I’m going back to Pyotr Ivanovich [the friend who was the doctor’s friend].’ He rang the bell, ordered the carriage and prepared to go out.

‘Jean, where are you going?’ asked his wife, looking very gloomy but uncharacteristically kind.

The uncharacteristic kindness infuriated him. He gave her a dark look.‘I’ve got to go and see Pyotr Ivanovich.’

He went to see the friend with the friend who was the doctor, and on with him to the doctor himself, who was in. They had a long talk.

Going through the details of anatomy and physiology in terms of what the doctor considered to be happening in his insides made everything quite clear to him.

There was a little bit of something, a tiny little thing, in his blind gut. It could all be put right. By raising the energy level in one organ and lowering the activity of another, absorption could be achieved and everything would be all right. He was a little late for dinner. He talked cheerfully after dinner, but for some time he couldn’t bring himself to go to his room and work. Even-tually he did go off to his study and he got straight down to it. He worked at the files for a while, but he couldn’t shrug off the awareness that he had some important unfinished personal business that would have to be attended to in the end. When he had finished the files he remembered that this personal business meant thinking about his gut. But instead of giving in to this he went to take tea in the drawing-room. They had guests - there was conversation, piano-playing and singing - and among them was the examining magistrate who was such a good match for his daughter. As Praskovya remarked, he enjoyed the evening more than usual, but never for a minute did he forget that he had some important unfin-ished thinking to do, about his gut. At eleven o’clock he said goodnight and went to his room. He had been sleep-ing alone since his illness began, in a tiny little room next to his study. He went in, undressed and took up a Zola novel, but instead of reading it he lapsed into thought. And in his imagination the longed-for healing of his blind gut took place; absorption was followed by evacuation and its proper function was restored.‘Yes, that’s how it goes,’ he said to himself.‘All you have to do is give nature a helping hand.’He remembered his medicine, eased himself up and took it, then lay on his back focusing on the good that the medicine was doing and the way it was getting rid of the pain.‘Keep taking it regularly and avoid anything harmful. I feel a bit better already, a lot better.’He felt his side - no pain to the touch.‘No, there’s no feeling there. It really is getting a lot better.’He put out the candle and lay on his side...

Absorption; the blind gut was curing itself. Then sud-denly he could feel the same old dull gnawing pain, quiet, serious, unrelenting. The same nasty taste in his mouth. His heart sank and his head swam. ‘O God! O God!’ he muttered. ‘It’s here again, and it’s not going away.’And suddenly he saw things from a completely different angle. ‘The blind gut! The kidney!’ he said to himself. ‘It’s got nothing to do with the blind gut or the kidney. It’s a matter of living or... dying. Yes, I have been alive, and now my life is steadily going away and I can’t stop it. No. There’s no point in fooling myself. Can’t they all see - everybody but me - that I’m dying? It’s only a matter of weeks, or days - maybe any minute now. There has been daylight; now there is darkness. I have been here; now I’m going there. Where?’ A cold shiver ran over him; he stopped breathing. He could hear nothing but the beat-ing of his heart.

‘When I’m dead, what happens then? Nothing happens. So where shall I be when I’m no longer here? Is this really death? No, I won’t have it!’ He jumped up, tried to light the candle, fumbling with trembling hands, dropped the candle and the stick on the floor and flopped back down on to his pillow.‘Why bother? It doesn’t make any differ-ence,’ he said to himself, staring into the darkness with his eyes wide open.‘Death. Yes, it’s death. And not one of them knows, or wants to know. They have no pity for me. Too busy playing.’ （Through the door he could hear the distant sounds of a singing voice and the accompaniment.） ‘They don’t care, but they’re going to die, too. Fools! Me first, then them, but they’ve got it coming to them. And they’re enjoying themselves! Animals!’He was choking with spite. And he felt a wave of agonizing, unbearable misery. It surely wasn’t possible that everybody everywhere should be condemned to this awful horror. He sat up.

‘Something’s not right. I’ve got to calm down and think it through from the beginning.’And he began to think. ‘Yes, the beginning of the illness. I banged my side, but I felt just the same that day and the next. A bit of dis-comfort, then a bit more, then doctors, depression, worry, more doctors, and all the time I was getting nearer and nearer to the edge. Less and less strength. Nearer and nearer. And I’ve been wasting away. No light in my eyes. Death is here, and I’ve been worrying about my gut. Worrying about getting my gut better, and this is death. Is it really death?’

Horror swept over him again, he gasped for breath, bent over and groped for the matches, leaning with one elbow on the bedside table. It was in his way, hurting him; he lost his temper with it, pressing down on it even harder in exasperation, and knocked it over. Breathless and in despair, he flopped down on to his back, expecting to die at any moment.

By this time the guests were leaving. Praskovya was seeing them out. She heard something fall, and came in.

‘What’s the matter?’

‘Nothing. I just dropped something.’

She went out and came back with a candle. He lay there, puffing and panting heavily like a man who has just run a mile. His eyes settled on her.

‘What’s the matter, Jean?’

‘No-thing. I... dropped it.’（‘No use talking to her. She won’t understand,’ he thought.）

And she didn’t. She picked up the candle and lit it for him, then she hurried out of the room to say goodnight to another guest.

When she came back he was still lying there on his back, staring upwards.

‘What’s wrong? Are you feeling worse?’

‘Yes.’

She shook her head and sat down.

‘Listen, Jean. I think perhaps we ought to ask Lesh-chetitsky to visit you at home.’

This meant asking the celebrated doctor to come to them, whatever the expense. He gave her a vitriolic smile and said no. She sat there for a while, then came over and kissed him on the forehead.

He hated her with every fibre of his being while she was kissing him, and it took all his strength not to push her away.

‘Goodnight. God willing, you’ll soon go to sleep.’

‘Yes.’

6

Ivan Ilyich could see that he was dying, and he was in constant despair.

In the depths of his soul Ivan Ilyich knew he was dying but, not only could he not get used to the idea, he didn’t understand it, couldn’t understand it at all.

All his life the syllogism he had learned from Kiese-wetter’s logic - Julius Caesar is a man, men are mortal, therefore Caesar is mortal - had always seemed to him to be true only when it applied to Caesar, certainly not to him. There was Caesar the man, and man in gen-eral, and it was fair enough for them, but he wasn’t Caesar the man and he wasn’t man in general, he had always been a special being, totally different from all others, he had been Vanya with his mama and his papa, with Vitya and Volodya, with his toys, and the carriage-driver, then little Katya, with all the delights, sorrows and rapture of child-hood, boyhood and youth. Did Caesar have anything to do with the smell of that little striped leather ball that Vanya had loved so much? Was it Caesar who had kissed his mother’s hand like that, and was it for Caesar that the silken folds of his mother’s dress had rustled the way they did? Was he the one who had rebelled at law school over the provision of snacks? Had Caesar been in love like him? Could Caesar chair a session like him?

Yes, Caesar is mortal and it’s all right for him to die, but not me, Vanya, Ivan Ilyich, with all my feelings and thoughts - it’s different for me. It can’t be me having to die. That would be too horrible.

These were the feelings that came to him.

‘If I had to be like Caesar and die, I would have been aware of it, an inner voice would have told me, but there hasn’t been anything like that on the inside. I’ve always thought - and all my friends have, too - that we’re not the same as Caesar. And now look what’s happened!’ he said to himself. ‘It can’t be. It can’t be, but it is. How can it be? What’s it all about?’

He couldn’t understand, and he tried to banish the idea - it was false, wrong and morbid - and replace it with proper, healthy thinking. But the same thought - it wasn’t just a thought but something that seemed like reality - kept coming back and facing him.

And in order to dispel these thoughts he started calling up different thoughts one after another, hoping to get support from them. He tried to get back to his earlier ways of thinking which had once protected him from thinking about death. But, strange to say, everything that once had protected him by hiding and eliminating any awareness of death was unable to perform that function now. In these latter days Ivan Ilyich spent most of his time trying to get back to the earlier ways of feeling that had protected him from death. He would say to himself, ‘I must get down to some work. When all’s said and done it’s what I’ve been living for.’ And he would go off to court banishing all his doubts, get into conversation with his colleagues and casually take his seat as he had done so many times before, contemplating the crowd before him with a pensive air and resting his wasted hands on the oaken arms of his chair, leaning over in his usual way to exchange whispered words with a colleague while toy-ing with a file before raising his eyes suddenly and sitting up straight in order to go through the familiar words and begin the proceedings. But then suddenly there it was, the pain in his side, irrespective of where they had got to in the proceedings, and it was beginning to gnaw at him. Ivan Ilyich focused on it, drove the thought of it away, but it continued to make itself felt. It kept coming back, facing him and looking at him, while he sat there rigid, the fire went out of his eyes and he began to wonder whether It was the only truth. And his colleagues and subordinates looked on in distress, amazed that he, a man of such brilliant and subtle judgement, was getting confused and making mistakes. He would pull himself together, try to bring himself round and somehow bring the session to a conclusion, only to return home sadly aware that his judicial work could no longer hide him, as it once had done, from what he wanted to conceal, that he could not use his judicial work to rid himself ofIt. And the worst thing was that It was distracting him not in order to make him do something but only to get him to look It straight in the eye, just look at It and do noth-ing but suffer beyond words.

And in order to escape from this situation Ivan Ilyich sought other forms of consolation, other ways of screening it off; other screens appeared and for a while they seemed to be the saving of him, but immediately they were not so much destroyed as shone right through; it was as ifItcould penetrate anything, no defence being any good.

Sometimes in these latter days he would go into the drawing-room that he had furnished - the very room where he had had his fall, the room which （it was bitterly amusing to reflect） he had given his life to furnish, because he knew his illness had started with that bruise - he would go in and notice a scratch on a lacquered table top left behind by something sharp. Looking for the cause he would find it in the decorative bronzework on an album with one edge bent up. He would pick up the album, an expensive one which he had compiled with loving care, annoyed at the carelessness shown by his daughter and her friends - it was torn in places and some of the photographs were upside down. He would go to a lot of trouble sorting it out and bending the bronzework back into place.

Then it would occur to him to move this entire établissement of albums over into a corner near the flowers. He would call the footman. Either his wife or his daugh-ter would come to help. They wouldn’t agree, they would take issue with him, he would argue and lose his temper - but none of this mattered because he had stopped rememberingIt.Itwas nowhere to be seen.

But once, when he was moving something himself, his wife said, ‘Let the servants do that. You’ll hurt yourself again,’ and suddenly It flashed through the screen - he saw It. It flashed at him and, even as he longed for It to disappear, he couldn’t help focusing on his side - still there, the same ache that would not be ignored, andIt was staring straight at him from behind the flowers. What was it all about?

‘And that’s the truth of it - I’ve lost my life here on this curtain, my battleground. Have I really? How horrible and how stupid! It can’t be! It can’t be, but it is.’

He would go into his study, lie down and find himself alone again with It. Face to face with It. Nothing to be done about It. Only stare at It and go cold.

7

How it came about in the third month of Ivan Ilyich’s illness no one could have said, because it came on imper-ceptibly, by stages, but it happened that all of them - his wife, and daughter, and son, and the servants, and their friends, and the doctors, and most importantly he himself - everybody knew that the only interesting thing about him now was whether it would take him a long time to give up his place, finally release the living from the oppression caused by his presence, and himself be released from his suffering.

He slept less and less. He was given opium and injected with morphine, but this brought no relief. To begin with, the dull feeling of anguish which he experienced in his semi-conscious state gave him a sense of relief simply by being something new, but then it became just as agoniz-ing as the raw pain, perhaps more so.

They gave him special food cooked from recipes pro-vided by the doctors, but the food became more and more tasteless, more and more repulsive.

For the call of nature he also had special arrangements, and each time it was agonizing. The agony came from the dirtiness, the unseemliness, the smell and also the knowledge that someone else had to be involved in it.

But this most unpleasant business brought one con-solation to Ivan Ilyich. The person who came to take things away was Gerasim, the peasant servant who waited on them at table.

Gerasim was a clean, fresh peasant lad, always bright and cheerful, who had fattened up on city food. To begin with, Ivan Ilyich was embarrassed to watch him, always so neatly dressed in his Russian costume, performing such a distasteful service.

One day as he got up from the chamber pot not strong enough to pull up his own trousers he collapsed into a soft armchair and looked down in horror at his bared puny thighs with their starkly protruding muscles.

Who should come in but Gerasim, wearing his thick boots and exuding both their nice tarry smell and that of the fresh winter air, Gerasim with his light but firm tread, sporting a clean hessian apron and a clean cotton shirt, with his sleeves rolled up his bare strong young arms, and without a glance at Ivan Ilyich - to spare the sick man’s feelings he was clearly suppressing the joyful vitality that shone from his face - he walked over to the pot.

‘Gerasim,’ said Ivan Ilyich feebly.

Gerasim started, clearly worried that he might have done something wrong, and in one swift movement he presented to the sick man his fresh, kind, open young face which was showing the first traces of a beard.

‘Yes, sir?’

‘This is not very nice for you, is it? You’ll have to for-give me. I can’t help it.’

‘Please don’t worry, sir.’ And Gerasim’s eyes flashed as he bared his young white teeth. ‘It’s no trouble. You’re a sick man.’

And with his quick strong hands he did his usual thing and walked out with a light step. And five minutes later with the same light step he came back in.

Ivan Ilyich was still sitting there in his armchair.

‘Gerasim，’he said, when the lad had replaced the clean, freshly washed chamber pot, ‘would you mind helping me? Over here.’ Gerasim came across. ‘Lift me up, please. I can’t manage it on my own, and I’ve sent Dmitriy away.’

Gerasim came over. In one movement that was as easy as his way of walking, he put his strong arms gently round Ivan Ilyich, lifted him up and held him with one hand, pulled up his trousers with the other, and tried to settle him down. But Ivan Ilyich asked to be taken across to the sofa. effortlesly and apparently without tightening his grip, Gerasim took him, almost carried him, to the sofa and settled him down there.

‘Thank you. You do everything so... nicely. So well.’

Gerasim gave another smile and made as if to leave the room. But Ivan Ilyich felt so comfortable with him that he didn’t feel like letting him go.

‘That’s better... Would you mind moving that chair over here? No, that one. Under my legs. It feels easier when my legs are up high.’

Gerasim brought the chair over, set it squarely on the floor without banging it down, and lifted Ivan Ilyich’s legs up on to it. Ivan Ilyich felt an easing of the pain as Gerasim raised his legs.

‘I feel better when my legs are up,’ said Ivan Ilyich. ‘Would you put that cushion under me?’

Gerasim did so. He raised his legs again and put the cushion under them. Again Ivan Ilyich felt better when Gerasim was holding his legs. When he lowered them he felt worse.

‘Gerasim,’ he asked, ‘are you busy just now?’

‘Not in the slightest, sir,’ said Gerasim, who had learned from the townspeople how to speak to the masters.

‘What do you have on at the moment?’

‘What do I have on? I’ve done everything there is to do - except chop the firewood for tomorrow.’

‘Well, I’d like you to hold my legs up. Would you mind?’

‘Of course not. I don’t mind.’Gerasim held his legs up, and Ivan Ilyich could have sworn that in this position he couldn’t feel any pain.

‘But what about the firewood?’

‘Don’t you worry about that, sir. We’ll manage.’

Ivan Ilyich told Gerasim to sit down and hold his legs up. He struck up a conversation and, strangely enough, he seemed to feel better with Gerasim holding his legs.

After that Ivan Ilyich would send for Gerasim now and then and have his legs held up on his shoulders. He liked it when they talked to each other. Gerasim did all of this easily, willingly and with a kindliness that Ivan Ilyich found moving. Health, strength and vitality in all other people were offensive to Ivan Ilyich; only Gerasim’s strength and vitality gave him comfort rather than dis-tressed him.

Ivan Ilyich’s worst torment was the lying - the lie, which was somehow maintained by them all, that he wasn’t dying, he was only ill, and all he had to do was keep calm and follow doctor’s orders and then something good would emerge. Whereas he knew that, whatever was done to him, nothing would emerge but more and more agony, suffering and death. And this lie was torture for him - he was tortured by their unwillingness to acknowledge what they all knew and he knew; they wanted to lie to him about his terrible situation, and they wanted him - they were compelling him - to be a party to this lie. All this lying to him, lie upon lie, on the eve of his death, lying that was inexorably reducing the sol-emn act of his death to the same level as their social calls, their draperies, the sturgeon for dinner... it was all a terrible torment for Ivan Ilyich. And strangely enough, on many occasions when they were acting out this farce in front of him, he was within a hair’s breadth of scream-ing at them, ‘Stop all this lying! You know and I know that I’m dying, so the least you can do is stop lying to me.’But he never quite had the nerve to do it. He could see that the awful, terrible act of his dying had been reduced by those around him to the level of an unpleas-ant incident, something rather indecent （as if they were dealing with someone who had come into the drawing-room and let off a bad smell）, and this was done by exploiting the very sense of‘decency’that he had been observing all his life. He could see that no one had any pity for him because no one had the slightest desire to understand his situation. Gerasim was the only one who did understand his situation, and he was sorry for him. This was why Ivan Ilyich felt comfortable only with Ger-asim. It was a comfort to him when Gerasim, sometimes for nights on end, held his legs up and refused to go to bed, saying, ‘Please don’t worry about it, Ivan Ilyich. I’ll catch up on my sleep.’ Or else he would suddenly address him in familiar language and add, ‘It’d be different if you weren’t ill, but with things the way they are why shouldn’t I help you out?’Gerasim was the only one who didn’t lie to him; everything showed that he was the only one who understood what was going on and saw no need to hide it. He just felt sorry for his weak and emaciated master. Once, when Ivan Ilyich was dismissing him, he put it quite bluntly：‘We’ve all got to die one day. Why shouldn’t I give you a hand?’This was to say there was a good reason for not making a fuss about helping out：he was doing it for a dying man and he hoped that when his time came someone would help him out in the same way.

Apart from all this lying, or perhaps because of it, the most tormenting thing of all for Ivan Ilyich was the fact that no one showed him any pity in the way that he wanted them to. There were some moments, after long periods of suffering, when what Ivan Ilyich wanted more than anything else - however embarrassed he would have been to admit it - what he wanted was for someone to take pity on him as if he were a sick child. He wanted to be kissed and cuddled and have a few tears shed over him in the way that children are cuddled and comforted. He knew he was a big man and something of a greybeard, which made this impossible, but nevertheless that is what he wanted. And his relationship with Gerasim offered something close to this, which was why the relationship with Gerasim gave him comfort.

Here is Ivan Ilyich wanting to weep, wanting to be cuddled and have tears shed over him, when in comes his colleague Shebek and, instead of weeping and getting some tenderness, Ivan Ilyich puts on a solemn and serious face, looks thoughtful and from sheer habit not only com-ments on the significance of a decision handed down by the Court of Cassation, but goes on to defend it strongly.

It was this living a lie, all around him and within him, that did most to poison the last days in the life of Ivan Ilyich.

8

It was morning. It was morning only because Gerasim had gone and Pyotr the servant was there, putting out the candles, opening one curtain and quietly tidying up. Morning or evening, Friday or Sunday - it didn’t matter, it was all the same - grinding, agonizing pain, never for a moment relenting; an awareness of life hopelessly slip-ping away but not yet gone; the same terrible, relentless approach of hateful death, the only reality; and still all that lying. With all of this, what did the days, weeks and hours matter?

‘Can I get you some tea, sir?’

‘He likes good order. The masters must have their tea in the morning,’ he thought, but all he said was, ‘No.’

‘Would you care to move over to the sofa, sir?’

‘He wants to tidy the room, and I’m in the way. I am dirt and disorder,’ he thought, but all he said was, ‘No. Leave me alone.’

The servant went about his work again. Ivan Ilyich stretched out one hand. Pyotr came over ready to help.

‘What can I do for you, sir?’

‘My watch.’

Pyotr took the watch, which was lying nearby, and handed it over.

‘Half-past eight. Are they still in bed?’

‘No, sir, they’re not. Master Vasily [his son] has gone to school and madam asked me to wake her if you wanted her. Shall I do that?’

‘No. Don’t brother.’Ivan Ilyich wondered whether to try some tea. Yes. ‘Bring me some tea.’

Pyotr moved towards the door. Ivan Ilyich felt terrified at the thought of being left alone. How could he stop him leaving? Oh yes, medicine. ‘Pyotr, would you give me my medicine?’Well, why not? The medicine might help. He took a spoonful and swallowed it. No, it wouldn’t help. It was all rubbish. Just pretending. He felt sure of this as the old familiar taste returned, sickly and beyond hope. No, his faith was gone. And the pain, the pain, why couldn’t it ease up just for a minute? He gave a groan. Pyotr came back in.

‘No, carry on. Get me some tea.’

Pyotr left the room. Ivan Ilyich groaned, not really from the pain, however terrible that was, but from anguish. It was the same thing all the time, day and night, with no end to it. Make it soon. Make what soon? Death, darkness. No, no. Anything was better than death!

When Pyotr came back in with the tea tray Ivan Ilyich looked at him distractedly for some time, unable to work out who he was or what he was doing there. Pyotr was embarrassed by the long look. The embarrassment brought Ivan Ilyich to his senses.

‘Yes,’ he said. ‘Tea... Good. Leave it there. But I’d like you to help me get washed and put a clean shirt on.’

And Ivan Ilyich began to wash himself. With pauses for rest he washed his hands and face, cleaned his teeth, combed his hair and then took a look in the mirror. He was horrified. The most horrible thing was the limp way his hair stuck to his pallid forehead.

As he had his shirt changed he knew it would be more horrible still to glance down at his body, so he looked away. At last it was done. He put on his dressing-gown, wrapped a rug around himself and sat down in the arm-chair with his tea. For one moment he felt refreshed, but at the first drink of tea there it was again, the same taste, the same pain. He forced the tea down, then lay back and stretched out his legs. He lay down and told Pyotr he could go.

The same thing again. One glittering drop of hope fol-lowed by a raging sea of despair, and nothing but pain, more pain, more anguish, always the same thing. It was depressing to be left alone, and he felt like calling somebody in, but he knew in advance that to have other people there would be even worse. Oh, for another dose of morphine - he might lose himself in that. He must tell that doctor to think of something else. ‘I can’t go on like this. I can’t.’

An hour goes by like this, then another. The bell rings in the hall - could it be the doctor? Yes, it is the doctor, fresh and cheerful, fleshy and hearty, with a look on his face that seems to say, ‘Well now, you seem to have had a bit of a fright, but we’ll soon sort you out.’ The doctor knows that this look is out of place here, but he has assumed it once and for all and he can’t get rid of it any more than a man who has gone out visiting can get rid of the frock-coat he put on that morning.

The doctor rubs his hands cheerfully, reassuringly.

‘Chilly out there. Thick frost. Give me a minute to get warmed up.’His manner of speaking implies that he won’t take long, he just needs to warm up and once he is warmed up he’ll put everything right.

‘Right then. How are you feeling?’

Ivan Ilyich senses that the doctor feels like saying, ‘How’s tricks?’but even he can see that this won’t do, so he says, ‘What sort of night did you have?’

Ivan Ilyich fixes the doctor with a look that seems to ask whether anything would ever make him feel too ashamed to go on lying. The doctor does not wish to understand.

So Ivan Ilyich says, ‘No change. Terrible. The pain won’t go. It’s there all the time. There must be something you can do!’

‘Yes, it’s normal for patients like you to say that sort of thing. Right then. I think I’m warm enough now. Your good lady is a stickler for these things, but even she wouldn’t say I was too cold. So. Good morning to you...’ And the doctor shakes him by the hand.

And now, dropping all the banter, the doctor adopts a serious attitude and begins to examine the patient - pulse, temperature, tapping and listening.

Ivan Ilyich knows full well - it is beyond doubt - that this is all nonsense, an empty sham, but when the doctor goes down on his knees, reaches across him, applies his ear higher up and lower down, and then with the gravest look on his face performs a selection of gymnastic contor-tions, Ivan Ilyich accedes to this just as he once acceded to speeches from lawyers even when he was well aware that they were lying, and why they were lying.

The doctor is still kneeling on the sofa, busily tapping away, when from the doorway comes the rustling of a silk dress and Praskovya can be heard reproaching Pyotr for not letting her know the doctor has arrived.

She comes in, kisses her husband and immediately begins to make it clear that she has been up for some time and only a little misunderstanding has prevented her from being there when the doctor arrived.

Ivan Ilyich looks at her searchingly, resenting every-thing about her, the whiteness, fullness and cleanliness of her arms and neck, the sheen of her hair and the light in her eyes that are so full of life. He loathes her with every fibre of his being. Physical contact with her is agony for him because it brings on a surge of loathing.

Her attitude towards him and his illness is still the same. Just as the doctor has worked out an attitude towards his patients which he cannot now get rid of, she has worked out a particular attitude towards him - he is failing to do something he ought to do, and it’s his fault, and she lovingly reproaches him for it - and she has not been able to rid herself of this attitude towards him.

‘He just won’t do as he’s told! He forgets to take his medicine. And the worst thing is he will lie there in a position that must be bad for him - with his legs up.’

She described how he got Gerasim to hold his legs up for him.

The doctor gave a sweetly condescending smile. ‘Can’t be helped,’ he seemed to be saying. ‘These sick people do sometimes have silly ideas. We can’t blame them.’

When the examination was over the doctor consulted his watch and then Praskovya informed Ivan Ilyich that, like it or not, she had invited a celebrated specialist to visit them that day and, along with Mikhail Danilovich （the name of the regular doctor）, he would conduct an examination and consultation.

‘Now please don’t argue with me. I’m doing this for myself,’ she said sarcastically, implying that she was doing it all for him and this alone deprived him of any right to refuse. He scowled and said nothing. He felt that the lies that enveloped him were now so messy that he could hardly make sense of anything.

Everything she did for him she was doing for herself, and she told him she was doing for herself what she was actually doing for herself, but she made it sound so implausible that he was forced to assume the opposite.

Sure enough, at half-past eleven, the celebrated spe-cialist arrived. More soundings and grave consultations both in his presence and in the next room concerning the kidney and the blind gut, with questions and answers expressed with such an air of gravity that, instead of the real life-and-death question which was the only one star-ing him in the face, up came the question of his kidney and blind gut, which were not doing quite what they should and which would shortly be set upon by Mikhail Danilovich and made to work properly.

The celebrated specialist took his leave looking serious but not hopeless. And in answer to the question put to him diffidently by Ivan Ilyich, whose eyes were glistening with fear and hope, as to whether there was any possi-bility of recovery, he replied that nothing could be guaranteed but there was a possibility. The look of hope on Ivan Ilyich’s face as he watched the doctor leave was so pathetic that when she saw it Praskovya actually burst into tears as she walked out of the study to give the cele-brated specialist his fee.

The lifting of his spirits induced by the doctor’s words of encouragement was short-lived. It was still the same room, the same pictures, curtains, wallpaper, medicine bottles, and the same body, his body, still suffering, racked with pain. And Ivan Ilyich began to moan, so they gave him an injection and he lapsed into unconsciousness.

When he came to, it was getting dark. They brought him his dinner. He forced down a little thin soup, then it was the same again, with another night coming on.

When dinner was over, at seven o’clock, Praskovya came in dressed for going out, with her ample breasts well supported and traces of powder on her face. That morning she had reminded him that they were going to the theatre. Sarah Bernhardt was in town, and they had a box which they had taken at his insistence. By now he had forgotten this, and he was offended to see her dressed up. But he hid his feelings when he remembered having insisted that they reserve the box and go, this being an aesthetic expe-rience of educational value for the children.

As she came in Praskovya had looked pleased with herself, if rather guilty. She sat down on the edge of a chair and asked how he was feeling, though he could see that she was asking for the sake of asking rather than to find out, since she knew there was nothing to find out, and then she launched into what she felt she had to say, that nothing would have induced her to go out tonight, but the box had been reserved, Hélène and her daughter were going and so was Petrishchev （their daugh-ter’s fiancé, the examining magistrate）, and they couldn’t be allowed to go alone. But for that, she would have preferred to stay in with him. And he must be sure to follow the doctor’s orders while she was out.

‘Oh yes, and Fyodor[the fiancé]would like to come in. Do you mind? And Liza.’

‘Let them come in.’

In came his daughter, dressed up to the nines, an exposed young body - while his body was causing him so much suffering. And she was flaunting it. Healthy and strong, obviously in love, she had no time for the illness, suffering and death that were marring her happiness.

In came Fyodor Petrovich, also in evening dress and sporting an à la Capoul hairstyle. The veins stood out on his long neck which was squeezed into its tight collar over a vast expanse of white shirtfront, and his narrow black trousers were tightly stretched over his strong thighs. One of his hands wore a close-fitting white glove and he carried an opera hat.

Creeping in unobtrusively behind him came the school-boy, wearing a new uniform and gloves, poor chap, with terrible dark blue rings under his eyes, the meaning of which was not lost on Ivan Ilyich.

He had always felt sorry for his son. And his fright-ened, compassionate look was dreadful to behold. Apart from Gerasim, Ivan Ilyich thought, Vasya was the only one who understood and felt sorry for him.

They all sat down and asked how he was feeling. Then for a while no one spoke. Liza asked her mother whether she had the opera glasses. Mother and daughter had a little argument about who had put them where. It ended nastily.

Fyodor asked Ivan Ilyich whether he had ever seen Sarah Bernhardt. At first Ivan Ilyich didn’t quite catch what the question was, but then he said, ‘No. Have you?’

‘Yes. In Adrienne Lecouvreur.’

Praskovya mentioned something she had been particu-larly good in. Her daughter demurred. They were off into a conversation about her charm and naturalism as an actress, the same old conversation that everybody else has.

In the midst of it Fyodor looked across at Ivan Ilyich and suddenly broke off. The others looked, and they stopped, too. Ivan Ilyich was staring straight ahead, his eyes glittering, and he was obviously furious with them. Things had to be put right, but there was absolutely no way of putting things right. Somehow the silence had to be broken. No one made a move, and everyone was becoming terrified that the living lie demanded by pro-priety would somehow be shattered and seen by everyone for what it was. It was Liza who made the first move. She broke the silence. She wanted to cover up what everyone was feeling, but by speaking out she revealed it.

‘Oh well, if we’re going it’s time we got started,’ she said, glancing at her watch, a present from her father, and she smiled almost imperceptibly at her young man to convey something known only to the two of them as she got up, rustling her skirts.

They all got up, took their leave and drove off.

When they had gone Ivan Ilyich seemed to feel easier; the lie had gone, gone away with them - but the pain was still there. That same pain, that same feeling of dread made sure that nothing was harder, nothing easier. Every-thing was worse.

Once again the minutes passed one after another, then the hours one after another; it was always the same, end-lessly, and the inevitable end itself was all the more horrible.

‘Yes, send Gerasim in,’ he said in reply to a question from Pyotr.

9

It was late at night when his wife returned. She tiptoed into the room, but he heard her; he opened his eyes and rapidly closed them again. She wanted to dismiss Ger-asim and sit with him herself. He opened his eyes and said, ‘No. You go.’

‘Are you in a lot of pain?’

‘It doesn’t matter.’

‘Take some opium.’

He consented, and drank some. She went away.

Until about three in the morning he was in a state of excruciating pain and delirium. He dreamt that somehow he was being forced, along with his pain, into the depths of a narrow black sack, being forced further and further in and not quite getting there. It was a harrowing, agon-izing process. And he was scared, he wanted to get through and out, he was struggling, trying to help. Then suddenly he lost his hold and fell, and woke up. Gerasim was still there, sitting at the foot of the bed, dozing quietly, patiently. And he himself was lying there with his withered stockinged legs raised up on Gerasim’s shoulders. The same candle was there, with its shade, and the same unremitting pain.

‘Go away, Gerasim,’ he whispered.

‘I don’t mind, sir. I’ll just sit here for a bit longer.’

‘No, you go away.’

He lowered his legs, turned sideways on to one arm and felt sorry for himself. He waited only for Gerasim to go out into the next room, and then he could restrain himself no longer：he burst into tears like a child. He was weeping because of his own helpless state, and his loneli-ness, and other people’s cruelty, and God’s cruelty, and God’s non-existence.

‘Why hastThou done all of this? Why hastThou brought me to this point? Why oh why dostThou torture me like this?...’

He was not expecting any answers; he was weeping because there were not and could not be any answers. The pain struck him again, but he didn’t move and didn’t call out. He said to himself, ‘Here it comes again. Hit me then! But what’s it for? What have I done toThee? What is it for?’

Then he fell silent, and not only stopped crying, he stopped breathing. Suddenly he was all ears; he seemed to be listening not to a voice speaking in words but to the voice of his soul, the thoughts welling up in his mind.

‘What do you want?’ was the first expressible concept that came to him. ‘What do you want? What do you want?’ he repeated to himself. ‘What is it?’

‘No more pain. Staying alive,’ came the answer.

And once again his concentration became so intense that not even the pain could distract him.

‘Staying alive? How?’ asked the voice of his soul.

‘Oh, life like it used to be. Happy and good.’

‘Life like it used to be? Happy and good?’ came the voice.

And in his imagination he started to run through the best times of his happy life. But what was strange was that all the best times of his happy life no longer seemed anything like what they had been before. Nothing did - except the first recollections of his childhood. There, in his childhood, there was something truly happy that he could have lived with if it returned. But the person living out that happiness no longer existed; it was like remem-bering someone quite different.

At the point where he, today’s Ivan Ilyich, began to emerge, all the pleasures that had seemed so real melted away now before his eyes and turned into something trivial and often disgusting.

And the further he was from childhood, the nearer he got to the present day, the more trivial and dubious his pleasures appeared. It started with law school. That had retained a little something that was still really good：there was fun, there was friendship, there was hope. But in the last years the good times had become more exceptional. Then, at the beginning of his service with the governor, some good times came again：memories of making love to a woman. Then it became all confused, and the good times were not so many. After that there were fewer still; the further he went the fewer there were.

Marriage... an accident and such a disappointment, and his wife’s bad breath, and all that sensuality and hypocrisy! And the deadliness of his working life, and those money worries, going on for a year, two years, ten, twenty - always the same old story. And the longer it went on the deadlier it became.

‘It’s as if I had been going downhill when I thought I was going uphill. That’s how it was. In society’s opinion I was heading uphill, but in equal measure life was slipping away from me... And now it’s all over. Nothing left but to die!

‘So what’s it all about? What’s it for? It’s not possible. It’s not possible that life could have been as senseless and sickening as this. And if it has really been as sickening and senseless as this, why do I have to die, and die in agony? There’s something wrong. Maybe I didn’t live as I should have done?’came the sudden thought.‘But how can that be when I did everything properly?’he won-dered, instantly dismissing as a total impossibility the one and only solution to the mystery of life and death.

‘So, what do you want now? To live? Live how? To live as you do in court when the usher yells out, “The Court is in session!”’ ‘Court in session, sessions in court.’ he repeated to himself.‘Here comes judgement! But I’m not guilty,’ he cried out angrily.‘What is this for?’

And he stopped crying, turned to face the wall and let his mind dwell on one single question：‘Why all this hor-ror? What’s the reason for it?’

But, for all his dwelling on it, he could find no answer. And whenever the thought occurred to him - which it often did - that all this was happening to him because he had been living the wrong kind of life, he would instantly remember how proper his life had been and dismiss such a bizarre notion.

10

Another two weeks went by. Ivan Ilyich no longer rose from his sofa. He didn’t care to lie in bed, so he lay on the sofa. And lying there, almost invariably facing the wall, he endured all the inexplicable agony in solitude, and in solitude he brooded on the same inexplicable question：‘What is this? Can it really be death?’ And an inner voice would reply, ‘Yes, that’s what it is.’ ‘What is this torture for?’And the voice would reply, ‘It’s just there. It’s not for anything.’ Above and beyond this there was nothing.

From the very onset of his illness, since the first time he had driven round to see the doctor, his life had divided itself into two opposite and alternating moods：either despair and the anticipation of a horribly incomprehen-sible death, or hope accompanied by an obsessive fascination for the workings of his body. He had eyes for only two things：either a kidney or blind gut that had temporarily stopped doing what it should do, or a hor-ribly incomprehensible death, which there was no way to avoid.

These two moods alternated in him from the very out-set of his illness, but the further the illness progressed the more dubious and preposterous his notions of a kid-ney became, and the more realistic was his awareness of impending death.

All he had to do was remember what he had been like three months before and what he was now, remember how steadily he had gone downhill, and any possibility of hope was shattered.

In his last days of solitude, when he found himself lying there facing the back of the sofa, solitude in the midst of a populous city and his own friends and family - a soli-tude more complete than anything anywhere, at the bottom of the sea or in the bowels of the earth - in these last days of terrible solitude Ivan Ilyich lived only by recreating the past. Images of his past life came back to him one after another. This process always began with the most recent ones and proceeded back to the most remote, to childhood, and there it lingered. If Ivan Ilyich remembered the stewed prunes he had been offered for dinner that day he would remember the raw and wrinkly French prunes of his childhood, their special taste and how his mouth watered when he got down to the stone, and along with the memory of that taste would come a whole series of further memories of that time：his nurse, his brother, his toys. ‘No, don’t, not that. It’s too painful,’ Ivan Ilyich would say to himself, transporting himself back to the present：there it was - a button of the back of the sofa, creases in the morocco.‘Morocco is expen-sive, and it doesn’t wear well. It started an argument. But that was different morocco and a different argument - when we tore father’s briefcase and got punished, and mother brought us some tarts.’ Once again his thoughts were settling on his childhood, and again they were too painful for Ivan Ilyich, so he tried to drive them away and think of something else.

And once again, along with this train of recollections, another train of recollections troubled his spirit - the way in which his illness had grown and got worse. Here, too, the further back he went the more life there was. More goodness in life, more of life itself. The two things were merging. ‘It’s like the pain getting worse and worse - all of my life has been getting worse and worse,’ he thought. There was one point of light back there at the beginning of life, but after that everything had been getting blacker and blacker.‘In inverse proportion to the square of the distance from death,’ he thought. And this image of a stone accelerating as it flies down imprinted itself on his soul. Life, a series of increasing sufferings, flies ever faster towards its end, the most terrible suffer-ing.‘I’m flying somewhere...’ He would shiver and shudder, trying to resist, but he knew by now that resist-ance was impossible, and he would turn his eyes to the back of the sofa, eyes that were weary of looking, but couldn’t stop looking, at what lay ahead. And he was waiting, waiting for that terrible fall, shock and annihila-tion.‘Resistance is impossible,’ he would say to himself.‘But if only I could see what it’s all about! No, that’s impossible, too. There would be an explanation if I could say I’ve been wrong in the way I’ve lived my life. But you couldn’t say that. It’s not possible,’ he would tell himself, recalling how fastidious he had been about the propriety and respectability of his life.‘You can’t say that. It’s not possible,’ he would tell himself, twisting his lips into a smile as if someone might see it and be taken in by it.‘There is no explanation. Agony and death... What for?’

11

Two weeks went by like this. During those two weeks an event took place that Ivan Ilyich and his wife had been hoping for：Petrishchev made a formal proposal. It hap-pened one evening. The next morning Praskovya came in to see her husband, wondering how best to break the news of Fyodor’s proposal, but during that night Ivan Ilyich’s condition had taken another turn for the worse. Praskovya found him on the same sofa, but in a different position. He was lying flat on his back, moaning and staring ahead with a fixed look.

She started talking about his medicine. He transferred his gaze to her. She didn’t finish what she had started to say; there was so much enmity in that gaze, and it was levelled straight at her.

‘For Christ’s sake, let me die in peace!’ he said.

She made as if to leave the room, but at that moment in walked their daughter, who came over to say good morning. He gave her the same look he had directed at his wife, and in response to her enquiries about his health he said drily that soon he would no longer be a burden to them. Both of them sat on for a while, saying nothing, and then they left.

‘What have we done wrong?’ Liza asked her mother. ‘Anyone would think it was our fault. I’m sorry for Papa, but why do we have to suffer?’

The doctor arrived at his usual time. Ivan Ilyich responded to him with a yes and no, fixing him with a malevolent look, and finally he said, ‘Look, you know you can’t help me. Just leave me alone.’

‘We can ease the pain,’ said the doctor.

‘You can’t. Leave me alone.’

The doctor went out into the drawing-room and told Praskovya that things were very bad. Only one thing could help - opium. That might ease the pain, which must be dreadful.

The doctor said that the physical pain must be dread-ful, which was true. But more dreadful than the physical pain was the suffering in spirit, his greatest agony.

His spiritual suffering took the form of a thought that had suddenly struck him that night as he looked at Ger-asim’s sleepy-eyed, good-natured face with its high cheekbones.‘What if I really have been wrong in the way I’ve lived my whole life, my conscious life?’

It occurred to him that what had once seemed a total impossibility - that he had not lived his life as he should have done - might actually be true. It occurred to him that the slight stirrings of doubt he had experienced about what was considered good by those in the high-est positions, slight stirrings that he had immediately repudiated - that these misgivings might have been true and everything else might have been wrong. His career, the ordering of his life, his family, the things that pre-occupied people in society and at work - all of this might have been wrong. He made an attempt at defending these things for himself. And suddenly he sensed the feebleness of what he was defending. There was nothing to defend.

‘But if it’s like that,’ he said to himself, ‘and I am leav-ing this life knowing I have ruined everything I was given, and it can’t be put right, what then?’ He lay on his back and started to go through his whole life again in a different way. Next morning, when he saw his servant, then his wife, then his daughter, then the doctor - their every movement and every word bore out the terrible truth that had been revealed to him during the night. In them he saw himself and all he had lived by, and he could clearly see that it was all wrong; it was all a gross decep-tion obscuring life and death. This knowledge exacerbated his physical suffering, making it ten times worse. He moaned and writhed, and clutched at his clothing, which seemed to be choking and stifling him. And he hated them for it.

After being given a heavy dose of opium he lost con-sciousness, but by dinner time it had all begun again. He sent everyone away and lay there tossing and turning.

His wife came to him and said, ‘Jean, darling, please do this for my sake.’ （For her sake?） ‘It can’t do any harm, and it often helps. Look, it’s nothing much. Even healthy people...’

He opened his eyes wide.

‘What? Take communion? What for? I’m not doing that... Oh, I don’t know...’

She burst into tears.

‘All right, my dear? I’ll send for our priest. He’s such a nice man.’

‘All right. That’s fine,’ he said.

When the priest came and heard his confession, Ivan Ilyich relaxed, feeling some relief from his doubts and therefore from his suffering, and he experienced a moment of hope. His mind turned again to his blind gut and the possibility of a cure for it. When he took com-munion there were tears in his eyes.

When he was laid down after taking communion he felt better for a while; there was hope that he might live on. His thoughts turned to the operation that he had been offered. ‘I want to live. I do want to live,’ he said to himself. His wife came in to greet him after communion. She said the usual things, and then added：‘You really do feel better, don’t you?’

‘Yes,’ he said, looking away.

Her clothes, her figure, the look on her face, the sound of her voice - all said the same thing to him：‘This is wrong. Everything you have lived by, and still do, is a lie, a deception that hides life and death away from you.’ And the moment this thought occurred to him, his hatred welled up, and along with the hatred came physical suf-fering and agony, and along with the agony came awareness of the inevitable destruction that was now so close. There was something different about it：a twisting, shooting pain, and constricted breathing.

The look on his face as he said ‘Yes’ had been dreadful. When he had got the word out, looking straight at her, he wrenched himself over face down remarkably quickly for one so weak, and roared at her：‘Get out! Go away! Leave me alone!’

12

From that moment on the screaming began. It went on unbroken for three days, so terrible that people two rooms away were horrified to hear it. At the moment when he had answered his wife he had realized he was done for, there was no way back, the end was here, the absolute end, and his unresolved doubts would remain as doubts.

‘Oh! Oh! Oh!’ he cried, varying the tone. He began by crying out, ‘Oh no!’ and went on screaming the letter ‘o’. Throughout the three days, during which time had ceased to exist for him, he struggled with the black sack into which he was being crammed by an invisible, unstop-pable force. He resisted like a condemned man resisting his executioner, knowing that he is not going to be spared, and with every minute that passed he sensed that, despite all his fighting and struggling, he was getting nearer and nearer to the thing that terrified him. He sensed that the pain came from being thrust into that black hole and, what was worse, not being able to get through. What was preventing him from getting through was his insistence that his life had been a good one. This vindication of his lifestyle was holding him down, pre-venting him from moving on, and causing him the greatest suffering.

Suddenly he felt a strong jolt in his chest and side, and a further constriction of his breathing. He was into the hole, and there at the end of the hole a kind of light was shining. What was happening to him was like when he had been in a railway carriage and you think you are going forwards but you are really going backwards, and suddenly you know what the right direction is.

‘Yes, it’s all been wrong,’ he told himself, ‘but that doesn’t matter. It’s possible to do the right thing. But what is the right thing?’ he wondered, and suddenly he was calm.

It was nearing the end of the third day, an hour before his death. At that very moment his schoolboy son crept in to see his father and came over to his bed. The dying man was still screaming desperately and waving his arms about. His hand happened to catch the boy’s head. The boy took hold of it, pressed it to his lips and burst into tears.

This was the very moment when Ivan Ilyich had fallen through and seen a light, and it was revealed to him that his life had not been what it should have been, but that it could still be put right. He was wondering what the right thing was, and he had calmed down, listening. Now he could feel someone kissing his hand. He opened his eyes and looked at his son. He felt sorry for him. His wife came over. He looked at her. With her mouth open and the tears not wiped away from her nose and cheek she was looking at him in despair. He felt sorry for her.

‘Yes, I’m hurting them,’ he thought. ‘They feel sorry for me, but they’ll be all right when I’m dead.’He wanted to tell them this, but he wasn’t strong enough to get the words out. ‘Anyway... no good talking. Must do something.’He looked at his wife, motioned to their son and said：‘Take him away... sorry for him... and you...’ He tried to say, ‘Forgive me,’ but it came out as, ‘For goodness...’ Too weak to correct himself, he waved his hand knowing that he who needed to would understand.

And suddenly everything was clear to him：what had been oppressing him and would not go away was now going away, all at once, on two sides, ten sides, all sides. He felt sorry for them, and he must do something to stop hurting them. Set them free, and free himself from all this suffering.‘So nice, and so simple,’ he thought.‘But what about the pain?’he wondered.‘Where’s it gone? Hey, pain, where are you?’

He listened and waited.

‘Oh, here it comes. So what? Bring on the pain.’

‘What about death? Where is it?’

He was looking for his earlier, accustomed fear of death, but he couldn’t find it. Where was death? What death? There was no fear whatsoever, because there was no death.

Instead of death there was light.

‘So that’s it!’ he said suddenly, out loud. ‘Oh, bliss!’

All of this happened to him in a single moment, and the meaning of that moment was not going to change. For those present, his agony went on for another two hours. There was a rattling in his chest. His wasted body shook. Then the rattling and the wheezing dwindled away.

‘He’s gone!’ said someone over him.

He caught these words and repeated them in spirit. ‘Death has gone,’ he told himself.

‘It’s gone.’

He took in some air, stopped halfway through a deep breath, stretched out, and died.

Three Deaths

1

It was autumn. Two carriages were bowling along the highway at a fast trot. In the first carriage there were two women. One was a lady, thin and pale. The other was her maid, with a shiny red face and a stout figure; her short, dry hair kept straggling out from under her faded bon-net, and she pushed it back fitfully with a red hand in a torn glove. Her full bosom, covered by a thick cloth of carpet material, exuded good health, and her black eyes were busy; one moment they were peering through the window at the fields flashing by, then they would glance across diffidently at the mistress, or watch the corners of the carriage with some concern. In front of the maid’s nose dangled her mistress’s bonnet, hanging from the rack, and on her knees lay a puppy. Her feet, raised up on boxes standing on the floor, could just about be heard drumming along with the creaking springs and the rat-tling of the window-panes.

With her hands folded on her lap and her eyes shut the lady rocked feebly against the cushions placed behind her back, frowned slightly and gave a little cough from time to time. She wore a white nightcap on her head, and a light blue scarf was wound round her delicate white neck. A straight parting disappeared under her nightcap, dividing her remarkably sleek, pomaded, light brown hair, and there was something deathly and desiccated in the white skin that formed the parting. The withered, yellowing skin hung loosely over the thin but beautiful contours of her face, with crimson on her prominent cheekbones. Her lips were dry and restless, her thin-ning eyelashes had no curl in them, and a cloth travelling cloak lay in straight folds across her sunken chest. Even though her eyes were shut, the lady’s face gave an impression of weariness, irritation and continual suffering.

A footman, wedged into his seat with his elbows on the sides, was dozing on the box. The coach driver drove his four big, sweating horses, yelling them on and glan-cing back now and then at another driver calling to him from a little open carriage behind them. Broad tyre tracks spread themselves evenly in speeding parallel lines along the limy, muddy road. The sky was grey and cold, and a damp mist was settling on the fields. Inside the carriage it was stuffy, smelling of eau-de-Cologne and dust. The invalid lady put her head back and opened her eyes. Her eyes were splendidly dark, and glittering.

‘Again,’ she said, and her beautiful thin hand nervously pushed away the hem of her maid’s cloak which was brushing lightly against her leg, and her mouth was contorted with pain. Matryosha gathered up her cloak with both hands, half-rose on her strong legs and shifted away. Her fresh face was flushed bright red. The splen-didly dark eyes of the invalid lady followed the maid’s every movement. Her mistress gripped the seat with both hands and also tried to lift herself and sit up higher, but she couldn’t manage it. Her mouth contracted and her whole face twisted itself into an expression of impotent, malevolent irony. ‘A fat lot of help you are! Oh, don’t bother! I can do it myself, and you needn’t shove all your bags behind me. Please don’t! No, don’t touch me. You’ve no idea!’ The lady closed her eyes, then raised her eyelids again sharply and glared at her maid. Matryosha looked back at her, biting her red lower lip. A heavy sigh arose in the invalid’s bosom, but it was a sigh that cut itself short as it turned into a cough. She looked away, scowl-ing, and clutched at her chest with both hands. When the coughing spasm was over she closed her eyes again and sat there without moving. The two carriages, one large and one small, drove into the village. Matryosha reached out from under her cover and made the sign of the cross.

‘What is it?’ asked her mistress.

‘A post station, madam.’

‘Why are you crossing yourself? That’s what I’m ask-ing you.’

‘There’s a church, madam.’

The invalid turned towards the window and began crossing herself slowly, her eyes widening at the sight of the country church that her carriage was driving past.

The two carriages stopped together by the church. From the small one two men emerged：the invalid lady’s husband and a doctor. They walked over to the large carriage.

‘How are you feeling?’ asked the doctor, taking her pulse.

‘How are you, darling? Not too tired?’ asked her hus-band, in French. ‘Would you like to get out?’

Matryosha had scraped up her belongings and was squeezing back into the corner so as not to interfere with their conversation.

‘Not too bad. Just the same,’ the sick woman replied. ‘I’m not getting out.’

The husband stood there for a short while, then went into the station building.

Matryosha skipped down from the carriage and ran tiptoeing in through the gateway.

‘If I feel bad, that’s no reason for you to miss lunch.’The sick lady gave a feeble smile as she spoke to the doc-tor, who was standing by her window.

‘They’re not bothered about me, any of them,’ she added, talking to herself, as soon as the doctor had walked gently away and trotted up the steps into the station house. ‘They’re all right, and that’s all that mat-ters. Oh! My God!’

‘Well then, Edward Ivanovich,’ said the husband, rubbing his hands with a cheerful smile as he welcomed the doctor in.‘I’ve told them to bring the lunch basket in. How does that strike you?’

‘Not a bad idea.’ replied the doctor.

‘How is she doing, then?’ the husband asked with a sigh, lowering his voice and raising his eyebrows.

‘I’ve told you. She won’t make it, not to Italy. She’ll need God’s grace to get to Moscow. Especially in this weather.’

‘What can we do, then? Oh, my God! My God!’ The husband buried his face in one hand. ‘Put it down here,’ he said to the man who was bringing in the lunch basket.

‘She should have stayed put,’ answered the doctor with a shrug.

‘Oh yes, but what could I have done?’ the husband protested. ‘Look, I did all I could to stop her. I told her how about the money involved, leaving the children behind, my work. She just wouldn’t listen. She was plan-ning her life abroad as if she was well again. And telling her about her condition - well, that would have been the same as killing her off.’

‘She’s already been killed off. That’s what you must realize, Vasily Dmitrich. A person cannot live without lungs, and lungs won’t grow back. It’s sad, it’s hard to bear, but what can you do? Only one thing matters for you and me - to give her the most peaceful ending we can. And for that we need a priest.’

‘Oh, my God! You can imagine my situation, having to remind her about her last wishes. Whatever happens, I’m not going to talk to her about that. You know how good she is...’

‘Well, try and persuade her to wait until the roads are frozen over,’ said the doctor, with a meaningful shake of his head. ‘Otherwise something nasty might happen out on the road...’

‘Aksyusha! Hey, Aksyusha!’ yelled the stationmaster’s daughter, throwing a jacket over her head and stamping on the dirty back porch. ‘Let’s go and have a look at that Shirkin lady. She’s supposed to be goin’abroad with that disease in her chest. I ain’t never seen how it is with them consumptives.’

Aksyusha skipped out on to the threshold, and both girls ran out through the gate, linking hands. They slowed down, walked past the carriage and took a look in through the lowered window. The sick lady turned to face them, but when she saw their curiosity she scowled and looked away.

‘Gosh!’ said the stationmaster’s daughter, whirling her head round. ‘She must have been a real beauty - and now look what’s happened to her. It’s horrible. Did you see her, Aksyusha? Did you see her?’

‘Yes, all thin, wasn’t she?’said Aksyusha, eager to back her up. ‘Let’s go and have another look, as if we’re going to the well. She looked away, see, and I never got a good look. It’s such a pity, Masha.’

‘Yes, but look at all this mud!’ said Masha, and they both ran back in through the gate.

‘I must be a terrible sight,’ thought the invalid lady. ‘Must get going, as soon as we can, go abroad. I’ll soon get better there.’

‘Now then, how are you feeling, my dear?’ said her husband, coming over to the carriage and chewing as he came.

‘Always the same question,’ thought the sick woman, ‘but he’s eating.’

‘So-so,’ she managed to get out, through clenched teeth.

‘Do you know what, my dear, I’m afraid you’re going to feel worse out on the road in this weather, and Edward says the same. Don’t you think we should go back home?’

Furious with him, she said nothing.

‘The weather might improve, the road could harden up, and you might feel better. Then we could all travel together.’

‘I’m sorry. If I had stopped listening to you ages ago I’d be in Berlin by now, and I’d be better again.’

‘We can’t help it, my angel. It just wasn’t possible, as you know. And now, if you would just stay on for another month, you’d feel so much better, I could get my business finished and we could bring the children...’

‘The children are well. I’m not.’

‘Darling, you must understand. In this kind of weather, if you take a turn for the worse out on the road... I mean, when you’re at home, at least...’

‘What? What could I do at home? ...Die there?’ The sick woman’s response was venomous. But the word ‘die’ had clearly shaken her; she looked at her husband implor-ingly, her eyes questioning. He looked down, saying nothing. The woman’s mouth crumpled like a child’s, and tears streamed from her eyes. The husband buried his face in a handkerchief, and he walked away from the carriage without a word.

‘No, I’m going on,’ she said, raising her eyes to the heavens and folding her arms. She began to whisper inco-herently. ‘Oh my God, what’s it all for?’ she said, her tears flowing faster than ever. For some time she prayed, fer-vently, but her chest felt so painful and tight, the sky, the fields and the road looked so steeped in their gloomy grey, and the autumn mist never thickened and never thinned as it drizzled down in the same old way on to the muddy road, the roofs, the carriage and the thick coats of the drivers chatting to each other in ringing, cheerful voices while they greased the wheels and got the horses ready for the carriage.

2

The carriage was ready, but the driver was in no hurry. He had disappeared into the drivers’cabin. Inside it was hot and stuffy, dark and oppressive, smelling of people, newly baked bread, cabbage and sheepskins. There were one or two drivers there, a cook was fussing over the stove, and on the stove-top itself a sick man lay stretched out on some sheepskins.

‘Uncle Fedya! Hey, Uncle Fedya!’ said the young driver, still wearing his top-coat and a whip in his belt, as he came in and spoke to the sick man.

‘What’m you doin’hangin’about here askin’after Fedya?’ responded another driver. ‘Look, they’m waitin’for you out in the carriage.’

‘I want to ask him about his boots. Mine are worn out,’ answered the young man, tossing his hair back and straightening the mittens in his belt.‘Maybe he’s asleep. Hey, Uncle Fedya!’ he repeated, walking over to the stove.

‘You what?’ came a feeble voice, and a thin, ruddy face bent down from the stove-top. A broad, skinny, pale and hairy arm jerked a coat up over a bony shoulder in a dirty shirt. ‘Give us something to drink, me lad. What was you saying?’

The lad offered him some water in a dipper.

‘Well, Fedya, it’s...er...like this,’ he said, shifting from one foot to the other. ‘I don’t imagine you needs new boots now. You could let me’ave’em. Seems as if you won’t be doing no walking.’

The sick man brought his weary head down to the shiny dipper, wetting his thin, straggling whiskers in the dark water as he drank feebly but thirstily. His matted beard was dirty, and his sunken clouded eyes didn’t find it easy to look up at the young man’s face. Finishing with the water, he tried to lift one hand to wipe his wet lips, but he couldn’t manage it and he wiped himself on the coat sleeve. Saying nothing, he breathed in heavily through his nose and looked the young man straight in the eye, getting his strength up.

‘Maybe they’re already spoken for,’ said the young man. ‘If they are, it doesn’t matter. The thing is - it’s wet out there, and I’ve got my work to do, and I just thought I’d ask old Fedya about his boots - maybe he don’t need them any more. Perhaps you do need them. Just tell me...’

There was a rumbling and a gurgling in the sick man’s chest. He bent double and started choking on a throaty cough that never really got going.

‘How can he need them?’ the cook snapped unexpect-edly, speaking angrily to the whole cabin. ‘He ain’t been down off that stove for a couple of months. You can hear him. Gives you a pain inside just to listen to him. Can’t be needing no boots, can he? They’re not going to bury him with new boots on. His time’s up, God forgive me, I’m a sinner. You can see he’s cracking up. He ought be taken away into another hut or somewhere else. What I’m saying is, there’s hospitals in town. And what right has he got taking up all that corner? No two ways about it. Some of us don’t have no room at all. And they keeps telling you to keep the place clean.’

‘Hey, Sergey! Get yourself on board. The master and mistress is waiting,’ called the post-controller from outside.

Sergey made as if to go, without waiting for a response, but the sick man’s eyes signalled while he was coughing that he wanted to give him an answer.

‘You can have my boots, Sergey,’ he said, stifling his cough. ‘But listen,’ he added wheezily, ‘you buy me a stone when I’m dead.’

‘Thanks, Uncle. All right, I’ll take them. And I really will get you a stone.’

‘That’s it, then. You heard that, lads.’The sick man was finding it hard to speak, and he bent double again, choking.

‘Sure, we heard,’ said one of the drivers. ‘Get going, Sergey, or the boss’ll be back. That Shirkin lady’s not well, you know.’

Sergey slipped off his worn-out boots - they were too big for him - and chucked them under the bench. Uncle Fyodor’s new boots fitted him nicely, and Sergey looked down at them as he walked out to the carriage.

‘Nice pair of boots! Let me grease them for you,’ said a driver with a handful of axle grease as Sergey got up on his box and gathered the reins. ‘Got’em for nothing?’

‘Not jealous, are you?’Sergey replied, half-rising and tucking the bottom of his coat round his legs.‘Forget it! Come on, me beauties!’ he cried to the horses, cracking the whip, and the two carriages - one large and one small, with their drivers, bags and baggage - disappeared into the grey autumn mist, rocking as they sped away down the wet road.

The sick driver was left behind on his stove in the stuffy hut. Unable to stifle his coughing, he made a big effort, turned on to his other side and lay there still and quiet.

The hut was busy until late in the day with people coming and going and having their supper. Not a sound came from the sick man. As night drew on, the cook climbed up on to the stove and reached across his legs to get at her long coat.

‘Don’t moan at me, Nastasya,’ said the sick man. ‘I’ll soon make room for you in this corner.’

‘All right. All right. Don’t go on about it.’Taint noth-ing,’ muttered Nastasya. ‘Where’s it hurt, Uncle? You can tell me.’

‘It’s me insides. All gone wrong. God knows what.’

‘Throat giving you trouble, with all that coughing?’

‘It all hurts. Time for me to die - and that’s it. Oh, oh, oh...’ moaned the sick man.

‘Cover your feet up.’ Ere, like this,’ said Natasha, clam-bering down and pulling his coat over him as she did so.

A night light burned feebly in the hut. Nastasya and a dozen drivers were asleep on the floor or on benches, snoring loudly. Only the sick man could be heard wheez-ing and coughing as he tossed and turned on the stove. When morning came he was completely quiet.

‘I’ve had a fantastic dream,’ said the cook, stretching herself in the half-light of a new morning. ‘Uncle Fyodor got down from the stove and went out to chop some wood. “Come on, Nastasya.” he says. “Let me give you some help.” And I says to him, “How can you go out chopping wood?” but off he goes with the axe, chopping away like mad and the chips flying everywhere. “What’s all this?” I says. “I thought you was ill.” He says, “No, I’m all right now”, and he swings that axe round - scared me stiff, he did. I shouted out and woke up. He’s not dead, is he? Uncle Fyodor. Hey, Uncle!’

Fyodor didn’t answer.

‘I wonder if he has died. Ought to go and have a look,’ said one of the drivers, who had just woken up.

The scrawny arm dangling down from the stove, covered in reddish hair, was cold and pale.

‘Go and tell the boss it looks like he’s dead,’ said the driver.

Fyodor didn’t have any relatives - he came from miles away. They buried him the next day in the new cemetery beyond the wood, and for several days Nastasya went around telling everybody about her dream and how she had been the first to find out Uncle Fyodor was dead.

3

It was now spring. Gurgling rivulets of water ran down the wet city streets, scurrying between frozen chunks of manure; people bustled about in a bright display of col-our and sound given off by their clothing and their chatter. In little fenced-off gardens the buds had begun to swell on the trees, and you could just catch the murmur of branches rocking in the breeze. Limpid droplets dripped and trickled everywhere... Sparrows squawked and twittered amidst a fluttering of tiny wings. On the sunny side, on fences, houses and trees, everything shim-mered and shone. Joy and youth shone in the sky, and on earth and in the heart of man.

One of the main streets, outside a large house belong-ing to a member of the gentry, had been strewn with fresh straw; inside, the lady who had been rushing to travel abroad lay dying.

The sick lady’s husband and an elderly woman stood by the closed doors of her room. On the sofa sat a priest with downcast eyes, holding on to something wrapped in his stole. In one corner an old woman reclined in a high-backed armchair - the sick lady’s mother - weeping bitter tears. At her side, holding a clean handkerchief, stood a maid waiting to be called; another maid was using some sort of cloth to massage the old woman’s temples while she blew upon her grey head under her cap.

‘Christ be with you, my dear,’ said the husband of an elderly lady standing with him by the door.‘She has so much faith in you, and you know exactly how to talk to her. Try and persuade her, as nicely as you can. Go in and see her.’

He was about to open the door for her, but she, a cousin of the invalid, stopped him, pressed a handkerchief to her eyes several times, and shook her head.

‘Now I don’t look as if I’ve been crying,’ she said, open-ing the door herself and walking through.

The husband was in a state of extreme agitation; he looked distraught. He set off towards the old woman, but within a few strides he turned away and headed for the priest. The priest looked at him, raised his eyebrows to Heaven and sighed. His thick beard, shot through with grey, also raised and lowered itself.

‘My God, my God!’ said the husband.

‘What can we do?’ said the priest with another sigh, and once again his eyebrows and his short beard were raised and lowered.

‘And her mother’s here!’ said the husband, on the verge of despair. ‘That will finish her off. So much love, so much love for her, and she... oh, I don’t know. Maybe you could comfort her, Father, and get her to go away.’

The priest got up and went to the old lady.

‘Quite so,’ he said. ‘No one can appreciate a mother’s heart. But God is merciful.’

The old lady’s face suddenly started to twitch all over, and she was retching with hysteria.

‘God is merciful,’ continued the priest once she was a little calmer. ‘I can tell you this. In my parish there was a man who was ill - much worse than Marya Dmitrievna - and - do you know what? - he was cured in no time by a tradesman with some herbs. And you’ll find that trades-man alive in Moscow today. I was just saying to Vasily Dmitrievich that we might give him a try. At least it would bring some comfort to the poor woman. For God, all things are possible.’

‘No, she’s not going to live,’ put in the old woman. ‘It should be me, but God’s taking her.’ And her hysterical retching came on so strongly that she fell into a faint.

The invalid’s husband buried his face in his hands and rushed out of the room.

Out in the passage the first person he ran into was a six-year-old boy chasing a younger girl as fast as his legs would carry him.

‘What would you like me to do? Should I take the children in to see their mother?’ asked the nanny.

‘No, she doesn’t want to see them. It will upset her.’

The boy stopped for a moment, looked his father straight in the face, lashed out with his foot and ran off again yelling with delight.

‘She’s being a black horse, Daddy!’ cried the little boy, pointing to his sister.

Meanwhile, in the next room the invalid’s cousin was sitting at her side, conducting a forced conversation in which she was trying to prepare her for death. The doctor stood by another window, stirring his drink.

The sick woman was sitting up in bed, clad in a white dressing-gown and beset with pillows on every side, watching her cousin in silence.

‘Oh, my dear friend,’ she said, suddenly interrupting, ‘don’t prepare me. Don’t treat me like a child. I’m a Chris-tian. I know it all. I know I haven’t got long to live, and I know that if only my husband had listened to me I’d have been in Italy by now, and I might have been better - I probably would have been. Everybody told him. But there’s nothing we can do. It seems to have been God’s will. We all bear many sins, I know that, but I trust in God’s mercy that all will be forgiven. It must surely be that all will be forgiven. I am trying to come to terms with myself. I too have borne many sins, my dear. But think how much I have suffered. I’ve tried to bear my sufferings with patience...’

‘So, should I tell the priest to come in? You’ll feel better when you’ve taken communion,’ said her cousin.

The invalid inclined her head in agreement.

‘God forgive me, sinner that I am,’ she whispered.

Her cousin went out and winked at the holy father.

‘She’s an angel!’ she said to the husband with tears in her eyes.

The husband burst into tears, the priest walked in through the door, the old woman was still lost to the world, and in the room itself all was completely quiet. Five minutes later the priest emerged from the room, took off his stole and ran a hand through his hair.

‘Thank God she’s calmer now,’ he said. ‘She wants to see you.’

The cousin and the husband went in. The invalid was weeping softly, looking at an icon.

‘Well done, my darling,’ said her husband.

‘Thank you! I feel so well now. I feel a kind of sweetness,’ said the invalid, a gentle smile playing on her thin lips. ‘God is so merciful! Isn’t that right? So merciful, and omnipotent.’ And she looked at the icon again, her eyes brimming with tears and eager with supplication.

Then suddenly she seemed to remember something. She beckoned her husband closer. ‘You never want to do what I ask,’ she said in a feeble and petulant voice.

Her husband craned his neck, listening submissively. ‘What’s that, darling?’

‘How many times have I told you the doctors are ignor ant? There are folk healers, and they can cure people... The priest was telling me just now... about a tradesman... Send for him.’

‘Who?’

‘Oh God! You’re determined not to understand!...’The invalid scowled and closed her eyes.

The doctor came over and took her hand. Her pulse was getting noticeably weaker and weaker. He winked at the husband. The invalid noticed the gesture and looked round in alarm.

‘Don’t cry, and torment yourself or me,’ said the patient. ‘You’re taking away my last consolation.’

‘You’re an angel!’ said her cousin, kissing her hand.

‘No. Kiss me here. Only dead people get kissed on the hand. Oh God! Oh God!’

By that evening the patient had become a body, and the body lay in its coffin in the biggest room in the large house. A deacon sat alone in that great room with the doors wide open, intoning the Psalms in a nasal voice. A bright waxy light fell from the tall silver candlesticks on to the pallid face of the dead lady, the heavy waxen hands and the frozen folds of her pall, which stuck up horribly at her knees and toes. The deacon droned on, with no understanding of his words - words which rang out and died away horribly. Now and then the sounds of chil-dren’s voices and their rumpus floated in from a distant room.

‘Thou hidestThy face, they are troubled,’ ran the psal-ter. ‘Thou takest away their breath, they die and return to their dust. Thou sendest forthThy spirit, they are cre-ated, andThou renewest the face of the earth. The glory of the Lord shall endure for ever.’

The face of the dead lady was stern, tranquil and majes-tic. Neither on her clear cold brow nor on her tightly closed lips was there any movement. She was all ears. But was she even now understanding those solemn words?

4

A month later a stone chapel had been erected above the dead lady’s grave. Above the driver’s grave the stone had yet to appear; nothing more than bright green grass came up from the mound that served as the only indication of the past existence of a man.

‘It’ll be a sin on your conscience,’ said the cook one day at the post station, ‘if you don’t buy a stone for Fyo-dor. You kept on saying, “It’s winter. It’s winter,” but now it’s different - why don’t you keep your promise? You know I witnessed it. He’s been back once to ask why you haven’t bought it. Next time he’ll throttle you.’

‘What are you on about? Have I gone back on my word?’ Sergey answered. ‘I’m going to buy him a stone, like I said, and I will. I’ll shell out one and a half roubles. I haven’t forgotten, but it’s got to be fetched. When I’m in town I’ll go and buy it.’

‘At least you ought to stick a cross up, that’s what I says,’ put in an old driver. ‘’Tis just plain wrong if you don’t. You’m wearing his boots.’

‘Where am I going to get a cross from? I can’t chop one out of a log.’

‘Can’t chop one out of a log - what are you talking about? Take your axe, get yourself out in the forest first thing, and you can cut one there. Go on, cut a little ash tree down... and there’s your cross. Either that or buy the forester a few drinks. Doesn’t mean you’ve got to treat him for any old bit of rubbish. Couple of days ago when I broke me splinter bar I cut meself a smashing new one, and nobody said nothing about it.’

Early next morning at the crack of dawn Sergey took his axe and went into the woods.

Everything was covered with a cold blanket of dew that was still settling, untouched by the sun. The east was getting imperceptibly brighter, reflecting its feeble light on the vault of heaven that was still thinly veiled with clouds. Not a blade of grass below, not a leaf on the top-most branches stirred. Only now and then the disturbing sounds of wings flapping in the brushwood or a rustling on the ground intruded on the silence of the forest. Then suddenly a strange noise, alien to the world of nature, rang out and died away on the edge of the forest. But the noise came again and repeated itself rhythmically at the bottom of the trunk of one of the motionless trees. One of the treetops gave an unusual shudder, its sappy leaves whispering, and a little robin who had been sitting on one of its branches gave a chirrup and flitted about a couple of times before cocking its tail and transferring to another tree.

Down below, the ring of the axe sounded more and more muffled, sappy white splinters flew down on to the dewy grass, and through the chopping came a slight creaking sound. The tree shook throughout its whole body, lurched over and quickly straightened up, wob-bling with alarm upon its roots. Everything was quiet for a moment, but then the tree lurched again, another creak came from its trunk, and with its branches snapping and its boughs dangling it crashed down crown first on to the damp ground. The sounds of chopping and the foot-steps stopped. The robin gave a chirrup and fluttered up higher. Its wings snagged against a twig, which shook for a moment or two before settling its leaves like all the others. The trees revelled in the beauty of their branches all the more joyously in the newly created space.

The first rays of the sun found their way through the thinning clouds, shone out against the sky and ran across the ground and sky together. Mist rolled down the valleys in waves, the dew glittered as it toyed with the greenery, and limpid whitening cloudlets sped across the azure firmament. Birds stirred in the thickets, twittering their happy song for all they were worth. On high, the succu-lent leaves whispered in peace and joy, and the boughs of the living trees slowly stirred themselves, looking down in majesty on the dead tree that lay flat out on the ground.

我们为何为同一件事哭和笑

[理解矛盾情感的复杂性，能够使我们避免片面解读伟人及其悲痛。][1]

我们在史书中读到，安提柯对儿子非常不满，因为他刚才在一场争斗中把他的敌人皮洛士国王杀了，提了头颅来献给他；他看到头颅却号啕大哭起来。还有洛林的勒内公爵打败勃艮第的查理公爵后不久也为他的死亡惋惜，还在他的葬礼上服丧。在奥雷战役中，蒙福尔伯爵战胜查理·德·布卢瓦，赢得了他的布列塔尼公爵封邑，战胜者看到敌人的尸体，深表哀悼。但是读了这些不应该立刻惊叫：

普天之下，人的心灵

都隐藏这些不同的感情，

脸上表现时而喜悦时而阴郁。

——彼特拉克

有人把庞培的首级献给恺撒时，史书记载说他转过头去，仿佛看到了丑恶、惨不忍睹的情景。他们两人长期一起商量国家大计，同舟共济，相互协助，建立联盟，所以不应该认为这个举动完全是装腔作势，像这位说的：

他想这回可以安心当岳丈了。

眼泪是挤出来的，

呻吟发自欢愉的心。

——卢卡努

因为，虽然我们大部分行为实际上只是门面与装饰，有时也可能是真心的：

继承人当面哭，背后笑。

——普布利流斯·西鲁斯

然而在评判这些事时，必须考虑我们的心灵怎样经常受各种情欲的冲击。就像我们的躯体内是各种体液[2]的大汇合，根据我们的性情使其中一种占主导地位；同样，我们的心灵内也有各种不同的活动冲击它，必然也有一个活动统率全局。但是这种优势并不会一直保持下去，我们的心灵变化不定，那些原本较弱的活动也会趁势反扑，收复失地。从这里看出，不但孩子一切都天真地从本性出发，经常为同一件事哭和笑，我们中间也有人虽然很想出外旅行，在跟家人和朋友道别时，却也不能吹嘘，否则会感到勇气受挫；眼泪若没有完全流出来，至少踏上马镫时会黯然神伤。不管好人家的女儿心里燃着怎样的热情，还是要把她们从母亲的脖子上拉下来，送到夫婿家，不管这位好心的同伴怎么说：

维纳斯是不是跟新娘有冤仇，

还是为了哄骗快活的爹娘，

在房前床边流几滴眼泪？

眼泪也可能不是真的！上帝帮帮我吧！

——卡图鲁斯

一个人人皆曰可杀的人死了，还是有人悼念，也是不奇怪的。

当我斥责仆人时，真的是火冒三丈，不是装模作样骂几声；但是怒气发过以后，他若对我有所要求，我还是乐意帮他忙；我立即把这一页翻了过去。当我骂他笨蛋蠢驴，不是要他一辈子背这个名声，也不想收回这句话立即再称他是正人君子。没有一种品质只配我们拥有，而且永远拥有。如果自言自语算不上是疯子行为，没一天我不听到心里在骂自己：“大笨蛋！”这绝不是在说我自己真是这样的人。

如果谁看到我在妻子面前一会儿冷若冰霜，一会儿春风满面，就认为这都是装的，他就是个傻子。尼禄下令淹死自己的母亲，跟她分手时突然动了情，对这次母子诀别感到厌恶与怜悯。

有人说太阳放光不是连续不断的，它是不停地让一束束新光照射着我们，以至我们辨别不出而以为是连续的了：

太阳，不歇的以太之源，火的洪流，

使天空永远白昼如新，

光明接着光明。

——卢克莱修

我们的心灵也是巧思纷呈，细流无声。

阿尔塔巴努斯无意中看到他的侄子泽尔士，问他为什么刚才神色大异。泽尔士正在考虑他的军队无比强大，要通过赫勒斯旁海峡去进攻希腊。起初看到有成千上万人归他指挥，踌躇满志，面露欣喜之情。但是继而就在同时想到那么多的生命至迟在本世纪内就要消失，不由得皱起眉头，伤心得落下了眼泪。

我们曾经坚定不移地报仇雪耻，为胜利而欢天喜地，可是也因而落眼泪。我们不是为了胜利而落泪，事情没有丝毫变化，只是我们不是怀着同一颗心去看待它，看到的就是另一副面目。因为每件事都有不同的侧面、不同的光线。心头想起血缘之亲、昔日的情谊，根据不同情况会激动一时，但是轮廓的闪现那么突然，我们无法把握。

说到速度，什么也比不上

思想的闪动，要来就来，

思想灵活多变，超过任何

置于目光下、落入感觉中的物体。

——卢克莱修

由于这个原因，要用这一系列断断续续的闪念构筑一个物体，必然会出差错。蒂莫利昂经过深思熟虑大义灭亲以后，他哭了，他哭的不是祖国恢复了自由，他哭的不是暴君，他哭的是他的兄弟。当他的一部分职责完成后，另一部分职责又要他履行了。

[1]每篇散文前的附加内容均为英文版译者M. A.斯克里奇（M. A.Screech）单独添加，由谢万容单独翻译。——编者注

[2]古希腊有“体液学说”，认为机体的生命取决于四种体液：血液、黏液、黄胆汁和黑胆汁。每一种液体与一定的“气质”相适应，每个人的气质则取决于他体内占优势的那种液体。例如，在蒙田那个时代，人们认为忧郁症是体液不平衡、黑色胆汁分泌过多所致。——编者注

论良心

[良心最初指纵容默许。良心的概念深深吸引着蒙田，即我们个人的是非观，抑或是我们的负罪感与正义感。宗教战争期间，蒙田目睹了种种残忍行径、诬告栽赃，见惯了对犯人的严刑拷打，由此开始重点反思良心。他发现，非常奇怪的是，“拷问”（刑讯逼供）所依凭的道德准则似乎正是出于人们对良心力量的尊重——一个人内心是负罪还是无辜，都体现在他忍受苦痛的能力是削弱还是增强上。蒙田此篇主要受圣·奥古斯丁和璜·路易斯·斐微斯的启发。关于奥古斯丁的《上帝之城》，斐微斯曾经写下一篇激情洋溢的笔记，谈论要减少人们对酷刑的过度信任。]

内战时期，我的兄弟拉勃鲁斯领主和我有一次在旅途中，遇见一位风度翩翩的贵族，他属于我们的敌对派别，但是我并不知道，因为他掩饰得很巧妙。这类战争中最糟的是局势错综复杂，从外表、语言和穿戴来说，敌人和你无法得以区分，双方接受同样的法律，遵守同样的习俗，呼吸同样的空气，难免混淆不清。我害怕在一个陌生地方遇见我们的军队，不得不说出自己的名字，这时真是生死难卜。我以前遇到过这样的事，在那次不幸的遭遇中，我人马俱损，不但如此，他们还残忍地杀害了一名意大利宫廷侍从贵族，我精心培育过他，一个有着光明前程的年轻的生命就这样消失了。

但是那位贵族非常容易惊慌失措，我看他每次遇见骑马的人过来，穿越效忠于国王的城市，都吓得要死，我终于猜到他的恐惧是由于他的良心而来的。这名青年觉得，人家通过他的面具和大氅上的十字架可以看到他内心的秘密意图。良心的力量竟是那么奇妙！良心使我们背叛，使我们控诉，使我们战斗；在没有外界证人的情况下，良心会追逐我们，反对我们：

用无形的鞭子抽打，充当刽子手。

——朱维纳利斯

这已是妇孺皆知的故事：一个名叫贝苏斯的帕奥尼人，被人指责说他故意打下一个鸟窝，把里面的小鸟统统杀光，他说自己做得有理，因为这些小鸟不停地无端指责他害死了自己的父亲。这桩弑父罪进行得滴水不漏，直到那时也没有人知晓；但是良心提出了申冤，使这个背上沉重赎罪包袱的人无法自制。

柏拉图认为，惩罚紧紧跟在罪恶的后面，赫西俄德纠正了柏拉图的说法，他说惩罚是与罪恶同时开始的。谁在等待惩罚，就在受惩罚；谁该受惩罚，就在等待惩罚。恶意给怀恶意的人带来痛苦：

做坏事的人最受做坏事的苦！

——拉丁谚语

胡蜂刺伤了人，但是自己受害更深，因为它从此失去了自己的刺和力量。

它们把自己的生命留在了伤疤里。

——维吉尔

由于自然界的矛盾对立规律，斑蝥身上分泌一种自身毒液的解毒素。所以，即使人在作恶时感受到乐趣，良心上却会适得其反，产生一种憎恶感，引起许多痛苦和联想，不论睡时醒时都折磨着自己。

这样的罪人不在少数，

在睡梦或谵妄中自怨自艾，

泄露了长期隐藏的罪过。

——卢克莱修

暴君阿波罗多罗斯在梦中见到自己被斯基泰人剥掉了皮，放在一口锅里煮，他的心喃喃地对他说：“你的所有痛苦都是我引起的。”伊壁鸠鲁说：“坏人无处藏身，因为他们躲在哪儿都不安宁，良心会暴露他们。”

没有一名罪人在自我判决中得到赦免，

这才是主要的惩罚。

——朱维纳利斯

良心可使我们恐惧，也可使我们坚定和自信。我敢于说人生道路上经过许多险阻而步伐始终不乱，就是因为我对自己的意图深有了解，自己的计划光明正大。

人的内心充满恐惧还是希望，

全凭良心的判断。

——奥维德

这类例子成千上万，这里只需举出同一个人物的三个例子。

西庇阿有一次在罗马人民面前被指控犯了一桩大罪，他不但不要求宽恕或向法官讨情，还对他们说：“好哇，你们还不是靠了我才有权力审判每个人，如今竟要起我的脑袋来了。”

又有一次，人民法庭对他起诉，他决不声辩，只是侃侃而谈：“来吧，我的公民们，去向神祇拜谢，也是在今天这样的日子，让我战胜了迦太基人。”说罢，他大踏步向神庙走去，只见所有人跟在他后面，其中还有他的起诉人。

又是人民法庭应加图的要求，传讯西庇阿，要他对安蒂奥克省的一切开支做出汇报。西庇阿为此事来到元老院，从袍子下抽出账册，说这本账册把一切收支原原本本记了下来；但是他没有同意把它转交给法院档案室保存，说他不愿意自取其辱，便在元老院当着众人的面亲手把账册撕成碎片。我不相信这个饱经沧桑的灵魂会弄虚作假。李维说他天性慷慨豪爽，一向气度恢宏，他决不会当个罪人，低三下四去声辩自己是无辜的。

苦刑是一项危险的发明，这像是在检验人的耐性而不是检验人的真情。能够忍受苦刑的人会隐瞒真情，不能够忍受苦刑的人也会隐瞒真情。痛苦能够使我供认事实，为什么就不能使我供认非事实呢？另一方面，如果那个受到无理指责的人有耐性忍受这些折磨，罪有应得的人难道就没有耐性忍受这些折磨，去获得美好的生命报偿吗？

我相信这项发明的理论基础是建立在良心力量的想法上。因为对有罪的人，似乎利用苦刑可以使他软弱，说出他的错误；然而无罪的人则会更加坚强，不畏苦刑。说实在的，这个方法充满不确定性和危险。

为了躲过难忍的痛苦，什么话不会说，什么事不会做呢？

痛苦会迫使无辜的人撒谎。

——普布利流斯·西鲁斯

审判者折磨人是为了不让他清白死去，而结果是让那个人受尽折磨后清白死去。成千上万的受刑者脑袋里装满了假忏悔。我想到亚历山大审判菲罗塔斯的情景，以及他受折磨的过程。我尤其要以菲罗塔斯作为例子。

然而有人却说，揭示人类弱点的许多发明中，苦刑还是痛苦最少的一项发明。

依我看来也是最不人道、最无意义的发明！有许多被希腊和罗马称为野蛮的国家，在这方面却不及希腊和罗马野蛮，它们认为折磨和杀害一个人们对其错误还只是心存怀疑的人，是可怕的残酷行为。你不知道实情，他又能怎么样呢？你不想无缘无故地杀他，对他做的事却比杀他还糟糕，你没有不公正吗？事情就是如此：多少次他宁愿无缘无故地死去，也不愿接受审讯，这种审讯往往比死刑还痛苦，这等于在执行死刑以前已把人处决了。

我不知道从哪儿听来这个故事，但是它如实地代表了我们良心的公正。一名村妇在一位军队司令兼大法官面前控诉一名士兵，说他抢去了她仅剩下的喂几个小孩的一点点面糊，这支军队已把四周村庄掠夺一空。然而没有证据。这位将军首先告诫妇女要对自己说的话仔细想一想，若是诬告就要判罪，她坚持不改口，将军下令割开士兵的肚子验证事实真相。妇女说的话是对的。罪证确凿。

命运与理智经常相遇在一条道上

[罗马的审查官对蒙田有关命运（区别于天意）的言论甚是不满——这很奇怪，因为几个世纪以来，变幻莫测的命运以及命运之轮早已是老生常谈。（“命运”一词在蒙田散文中出现多达三百五十次。）]

命运变幻无常，在我们面前展现的面貌也就千变万化。这不也是在明白无误地伸张正义吗？瓦朗蒂努瓦公爵恺撒·波齐亚决心要毒死科尔内托的红衣主教阿德里安，他的父亲亚历山大六世教皇偕同他到梵蒂冈吃晚饭。公爵事先差人送了一瓶毒酒交给司膳总管，嘱他好好看管。教皇在儿子之前到，要求喝酒，司膳总管以为这是瓶好酒，交给他就是给教皇喝的，就倒了一杯敬教皇；公爵本人恰在上点心时赶到，以为他自己的那瓶酒还没开过，也就拿来喝了；这样父亲立即暴死，儿子长期受病痛折磨，命运更加悲惨。

有时候命运好像有意跟我们作对。德斯特雷领主是旺多姆殿下的军旗手，里克领主是阿尔斯霍特公爵的随从副官，虽分属对立的部队，但都在追求封凯泽尔领主的妹妹（在前线相邻的两支部队常有这样的事）。里克领主求婚成功；但是在婚礼那天，不幸的是新郎在上床之前，要去逞能来取悦新娘，离家到了圣奥梅尔附近跟人交了手，却让德斯特雷领主占了上风，把他捉了当俘虏。

离开年轻郎君的怀抱，

让一个冬天，又一个冬天，

在漫漫长夜中烧尽了他们的烈火。

——卡图鲁斯

为了摆足威风，德斯特雷迫使那位夫人亲自来向他求情，把他的俘虏客客气气还给她；人也确实放了，法国贵族从不拒绝夫人的要求。

君士坦丁（一世），海伦娜的儿子，创立了君士坦丁帝国；多少世纪以后，又是一个君士坦丁（十一世），也是海伦娜的儿子，断送了君士坦丁帝国。这不像是巧妙的命运安排吗？

有时候，命运喜欢跟奇迹争高低。我们知道克洛维斯国王围困昂古莱姆时，城墙自个儿坍塌，如有神助。布歇援引某位作者的话，虔诚者罗伯特二世国王在围城时，偷偷离开前线溜回奥尔良庆祝圣埃尼昂节，正当他弥撒做到中途顶礼膜拜时，围城的城墙不攻自破了。这跟我们在米兰战争中发生的事恰恰相反。朗佐统帅在为我们包围阿罗纳城时，命人在一堵大墙下埋炸药。这堵墙突然被炸离地面，又直挺挺落下竖在地基上，被困的人还是安然无恙。

有时候，命运还会治病。费雷斯的亚逊胸口长了个脓疮，医生都已束手无策，他一心要摆脱折磨，即使死了也甘心。在一次战役中他奋不顾身冲进敌阵，被刺穿身子，恰巧伤在病患处，脓疮破裂，这下子治愈了。

命运在艺术技艺方面不是还超过了画家普罗托盖纳斯吗？画家画了一条疲劳的狗，全身什么部位都感到很称心，但就是狗嘴里的口水画得不中意，他对自己的画发起了脾气，拿起一块蘸满各种颜料的海绵朝它扔了过去，要把它都擦掉；命运让那块海绵恰好扔在狗嘴上，在上面留下的正是艺术家想画而画不出的艺术效果。

有时，命运不是在指导我们、改正我们吗？英格兰伊莎贝尔女王率领一支军队去支援儿子反对她的丈夫，要从泽兰回到王国内；她若按原计划抵达港口必然完了，敌人都在那里等着她，但是命运却不顾她的意愿让她在一个安全地点登了陆。那位古人，拿起石头要砸狗，却砸死了自己的老娘，不是很有理由念一念这句诗吗？

命运比我们更有主意。

——米南德

蒂莫利昂在西西里岛阿德拉诺暂住，伊塞特召了两名士兵要杀他。他们决定在他献祭时动手。他们混在人群中，正在相互发信号趁机会下手时，突然来了第三个人，在其中一位头上狠狠砍了一剑，待他死在地上后，自己拔腿就跑。那位同伴以为自己被人识破，脱不了身，奔到祭台，答应把一切都招供出来，要求宽恕。

正当他在交代阴谋过程时，那第三个人被大家当作谋杀犯抓住了，推推搡搡穿过人群到了蒂莫利昂和在场的显贵面前。这时那个人大叫饶命，说他杀死的只是杀他父亲的凶手。他运气来得正好，当场有人证明他的父亲确是在利恩泰奈人的城里被那个他杀死报仇的人杀的。他由于这件巧事得到了一大笔赏金，既报了父亲的仇，又救了西西里父母官的命。这样的命运在讨回公道方面，是任何人精心制定的法律也难以达到的。

最后一个例子。这件事还不能清楚说明命运总是倾向于善良与赤诚之心吗？伊格纳蒂乌斯父子被罗马三世执政放逐，决定做出惊人之举，互相结束对方的生命，不让暴政者得逞施加酷刑。他们手握宝剑朝着对方奔去。命运指挥着他们的剑头，两剑都立即夺去他们的生命，为了表彰这么美好的父子情，还让他们有力气从洞穿的身子里抽出鲜血淋漓的手臂与宝剑，相互紧紧拥抱，再也一动不动。刽子手无法把他们分离，只得一下子割下两人的头颅，让两具尸体始终有尊严地贴在一起，伤口对着伤口深情地吮吸着对方的血与残留的生命。

论对懦夫行为的惩罚

[文艺复兴时期的法律学者，如安德烈·蒂亚居伊想要通过研究人的动机与局限，从而缓和社会的严刑峻法。在这里，蒙田效仿前者，对战争年代的男士们表达了深切担忧。]

曾听到一位亲王、杰出的将领说过，一名士兵不能因丧失勇气而被处死。他在用餐时听到德·韦尔万领主一案，后者因献出布洛涅而被判处死刑。

因软弱造成的错误与因恶意造成的错误，中间有巨大的差别，这样说实在是有道理的。恶意是我们有心鼓动自己违背天性形成的理智规则。至于软弱，不妨也拿天性来自我辩护，说是它造成了我们这样的不完美和缺陷，以至不少人想到，只有违背自己良心做事才可以加以责备。这条规则，使一部分人形成这样的看法，反对对异教徒和无信仰者使用极刑，同样认为律师和法官不必承担无知渎职的责任。

但是，说到懦夫行为，最常见的惩罚是当众羞辱。据说这条规则最早是由法学家夏隆达斯提出的，在他以前，希腊法律以死刑处分临阵脱逃的人。夏隆达斯只是罚那些人穿上妇女服装在广场中央坐三天，指望他们羞愧后恢复勇气，还能入伍打仗。“与其让男人血流在地上，还不如让他血涌到脸上。”（德尔图良）

从前，罗马法律对逃兵也是判死罪。据安米阿努斯·马西利纳斯的叙述，在帕提亚战役中，有十名士兵冲锋时转身往回跑，朱利安皇帝先把他们逐出军队，后来据说依古法处死。然而另一次，有人犯了相似的罪过，他只是处分他们跟囚徒一起待在辎重部队。罗马人对在卡尼战役中逃跑的士兵，还有在同一场战争中随同执政官法尔维乌斯吃败仗的士兵，惩罚再严也不至把他们处死。

然而有一事必须提防，羞辱使他们失去颜面，不但会使他们冷漠无情，还会将他们变为敌人。

在我们祖辈那个时代，弗朗杰领主当过德·夏蒂永元帅的副官，受德·夏巴纳元帅派遣，取代杜·吕德大人当富恩塔拉比亚总督。他把富恩塔拉比亚拱手让与西班牙人，因此被废除贵族称号，他与他的后代都被贬为平民，要缴人头税，不准入伍当兵。这一严厉的判决是在里昂执行的。后来纳索伯爵带军队开进吉兹时，城里的全体贵族都遭到类似的惩罚；后来其他类似的事也复如此处理。

然而，如果无知与懦夫行为过于恶劣或明显，超出了一般的程度，那时就有理由把它看成是确凿的证据，说明当事人的狡猾和恶意，并以此定罪。

论言过其实

[尽管蒙田对语言的运用已炉火纯青，他本人却鄙视文字，崇尚行动或“实事”。早在开始散文创作之前，他就曾在雷蒙德·塞朋德《自然神学》一书译作的开篇献词——“给父亲的一封信”中表达了该观点。对“行动胜于雄辩”的尊重，正是他景仰古代斯巴达王国的原因，同时也是当世所欠缺的品质。]

从前一位修辞学家说，他的职业是把小事物说得大，显得大。这就像鞋匠给一对小脚丫做上一双大鞋子。在斯巴达靠吹牛说谎为职业就会挨鞭子。我相信阿基达默斯国王听到修昔底德的回答不会不表示惊讶。国王问他与伯里克利角斗谁更强，他回答说：“这不好验证，因为我在角斗中把他摔倒在地，他却说服在场观看的人说他没有倒地，于是他赢了。”

有人让女人戴上面纱，涂脂抹粉，这为害不大，因为不能看到她们处在自然状态，不是大不了的损失；而其他人要欺骗的不是我们的眼睛，而是我们的判断，要歪曲和败坏的是事物的本质。像克里特、斯巴达这样的城邦，局势稳定，治理有方，并不重视雄辩家。

阿里斯托给修辞学下了个聪明的定义：说服老百姓的技术。苏格拉底、柏拉图则说是骗人和拍马的艺术。有人从大道理上否定它，却在自己的训诫中到处使用。

伊斯兰教禁止向孩子传授修辞学，因为它无用。

雅典人发现修辞学的使用在都城里有上升趋势，这是很有害的，下令把煽动情绪的主要篇章，连同前言和结论部分一齐删去。

修辞学的发明，是为了操纵和煽动一群乌合之众和暴徒。这个工具专门用于病态政体，就像是药。在那些庸人、无知的人或任何人独占一切的地方，如雅典、罗德岛和罗马，在那些局势纷争不已的地方，演说家才应运而生。的确，在这些政体里，很少有人是不靠口才而平步青云的；庞培、恺撒、克拉苏、卢库卢斯、兰图卢斯，都是慷慨陈词以后得到极大的支持，最后登上权柄的高位，他们依仗口才更甚于军队，这与太平盛世的看法是相悖的。

L.沃卢姆努斯当众演说，支持Q.法比乌斯和P.德基乌斯当选为执政官，他说：“这些人是为战争而生的，建功立业的大人物，打嘴仗也毫不示弱，是真正的执政人才；头脑精明，说话服众和博学多才，可以管理城市，执政主持民事裁判工作。”

当政局一片混乱，内战的风暴搅得人心惶惶时，罗马城内的雄辩家如沐春风，就像一块没有开垦的荒地上野草丛生。这样看来，由单独君主控制的政府不像其他政府那样需要这种东西；因为百姓愚昧轻信，耳边听了甜言蜜语，很容易受到操纵和误导，不会用理智的力量去审察和认识事物的真相；对这种轻信态度，我要说，在君主个人身上是不容易存在的，良好教育与好言规劝也较为容易使他免受这种毒药的危害。在马其顿和波斯就没出过一个有名气的雄辩家。

我刚才跟一位意大利人谈过话，才引起我说了上面一番话。他曾给已故的红衣主教加拉法当过司膳总管，直至主教过世。我请他谈谈他的差使。他神色严肃，把这门讲究口腹之欲的学问，一本正经地说了一通，仿佛在跟我讲神学的大道理。他向我细分不同的胃口：饥饿时的胃口，上了两三道菜后的胃口；什么方法吃了只不过使胃舒服，什么方法引得胃口大开；调料使用方法，一般的，特殊的，针对菜肴的特点和作用；不同季节的沙拉也不同，有需要加热的，也有需要冷食的，如何搭配花色使它们赏心悦目。在这之后，又说到上菜的顺序，其中的微妙大有讲究。

怎样切兔肉，如何斩鸡块，

当然都大有学问。

——朱维纳利斯

言辞里充满崇论闳议，就像在发表治国大略。这使我想起我的朋友：

太咸啦！烧煳啦！淡啦！恰到好处！

下次就照这样做！我教他们，

以我浅薄的学识尽心尽力。

总之，德梅亚，我要他们

拿锅子当镜子，教他们毫不留一手。

——泰伦提乌斯

埃米利乌斯·波勒斯从马其顿回来，宴请希腊人；希腊人对他宴会的组织安排大加赞赏；但是我这里说的不是他们做了什么，而是他们说了什么。

我不知道别人听了是不是与我有同感。当我听到我们的建筑师踌躇满志，大谈壁柱、下楣、挑檐、科林斯和陶立克柱型，还有他们类似的行话，我不由自主地想到阿波里东宫；实际上，我发现那是指我家厨房上那几条质地单薄的横档。

当你听到有人说替代、隐喻、讽喻这类语法词汇，那不是像在指某个罕见冷僻的语言现象吗？其实是涉及你的女仆唠叨的用语。

还有一种与此相近的花招，就是用罗马人的显赫官衔来称呼我们的官吏，然而他们在职务上没有丝毫相似之处，更没有那样的权威与权力。这种做法我相信，总有一天会说明我们这个世纪的荒谬绝伦，把古代荣耀了几个世纪的一两位人物的最光辉称号，不恰当地加到我们中意的人身上。称柏拉图是神，这是举世公认的，谁也不会嫉妒。然而意大利人，他们自诩整体上跟他们那个时代的其他民族相比，更为隽智和明白事理，这话有点道理，但是不久前却把那个尊号安到了阿雷蒂诺头上，这一位除了说话诙谐刻薄，确有高明之处，只是经常牵强附会，莫名其妙。就算他口才高明，我也看不出他有什么才能超越他同一世纪的大多数作家，更不用说跟古人的神号相去甚远了。

“伟大”这个词，我们却动辄加在并不比群众伟大的亲王身上。

探讨哲学就是学习死亡

[蒙田一直以来安于愁思，如今却是轻描淡写。他被死亡的恐惧所困扰，这种恐惧通常源于行将就木时所遭受的折磨——以前人们往往难逃临死的苦痛。对此，蒙田的处理可谓言辞雄辩，却并不客观冷漠，而是努力找寻普通人身上的美好品质。]

西塞罗说，探讨哲学不是别的，只是准备死亡。尤因探讨与静观可以说是让我们的灵魂脱离肉体而独自行动，有点像在学习与模拟死亡；或者也可以说，人类的一切智慧与推理归根结底，就是要我们学习不怕死亡。

说实在的，理智不是在冷嘲热讽，而是把目标定在使我们满足上。理智的工作，总的是要人活得好，要我们如《圣经》所说的“终身喜乐行善”。世上人人都是这种看法，尽管表达形式各有不同，快乐是我们的目标；与此不同的看法一出笼就被排斥，若有人说什么他的目的是让我们受苦受难，那谁会去听呢？

在这方面，哲学宗派之间的分歧只表现在口头上。“别去听那些美妙的妖言。”（塞涅卡）在这么一个神圣的学科中不应该有那么多的顽固与恶言。某人不论扮演什么角色，扮演的总是他自己。他们不论说什么，即使谈到美德，瞄准的最终目标也是感官享乐。他们听到这个词那么反感，而我偏要在他们耳边说个不休。如果这个词意味着最强的欢乐与极度的满足，那时美德的介入才胜过其他东西的介入。这种感官享乐不论如何纵情胡闹，粗野强健，也只是更加享乐而已。我们还不如称为欢乐，更容易接受，更温和自然，而不是曾用的“精力”一词。

另一种感官享乐——若也可用这个好名词的话——较为庸俗，也是应该相提并论的，但并不更占优势。我觉得它不像美德那样不包含放肆与邪念。除了感受更短暂、更流动、毫无新鲜感，它还有熬夜、挨饿、辛苦和血与汗；此外还有各种各样的情感折磨，然后再有这种沉重的满足，这无异于一种受罪了。

我们还大错特错地认为，这些磨难可以成为温情的刺激物与调味品，好像大自然中的万物相生相克；也不要说当我们转向美德时，同样的障碍与困难会压倒它，使它变得严峻、不可接近；而在美德介入的情况下，会使这种神圣完美的欢乐更高尚、更兴奋、更昂扬，要胜过低级的享乐许多。

一个人权衡他的所失与所得，不知道美德的温馨与作用，当然是不配认识这种欢乐的。有人劝导我们说美德的追求艰辛曲折，美德的享受则是愉快的，这岂不是在对我们说它不会令人快乐吗？因为哪个人曾有法子获得过它呢？最成功的人也只是做到向往它，接近它，而没有获得过它。

但是那些人错了，要知道追求我们所认识的任何乐趣，这本身就是乐趣；行动包含的乐趣，存在于我们眼前的美好目标，因为这是与大部分激情共生共灭的。在美德中闪闪发光的愉悦福乐，自有千百条渠道小路，引导你进入第一个入口，直至最后一道墙。那时美德的主要好处是对死亡的蔑视，这样使人的一生过得恬然安逸，让我们专注于愉悦的享受，不如此，其他一切享乐都会黯然无光。

这说明为什么一切规则都集中和会合在这个主题上。虽则那些规则也一致认为要蔑视痛苦、贫困和其他隶属于人生的遭遇，这在关心的程度上不一样，因为有的遭遇不是必然发生的（许多人一生中没有经历过贫困，有的还不曾有过疼痛的病患，如音乐师色诺菲吕斯，他活了一百零六岁，身体一直良好），还可以在万不得已时轻生，把烦恼一了百了。但是死亡本身则是不可避免的。

人人都被推向同一个方向，

我们的命运在缸里转动，

迟早会从里面跃出，

上了船，

带往不归路。

——贺拉斯

因而，要是死亡使我们害怕，这就成了一个说不完的痛苦话题，而又不能使心情纾解一丝一毫。死亡从哪儿都可以向我们袭击；我们就会不停地左右窥视，像进了一座疑阵以防不测：“这就像永世悬在坦塔罗斯头上的岩石。”[3]（西塞罗）我们的法院经常把罪犯送到案发地点处决，一路上押着他们经过漂亮的房子，让他们拣好吃的吃个痛快：

……西西里岛的盛宴

也引不起他的馋涎。

鸟语与琴声

都不能使他入眠。

——贺拉斯

不妨想一想，他们能够高兴起来吗？游街的最终意图昭然若揭，难道不会败坏他们领受这一切恩典的兴致？

他打听道路，他掐算日子，

走了多少还剩下多少，

想到眼前的极刑痛不欲生。

——克洛迪安

我们生涯的终点是死亡，我们必须注视的是这个结局；假若它使我们害怕，怎么可能走前一步而又不发愁呢？凡人的药方是把它置之脑后。只是愚蠢透顶才会这么懵然无知！真是把马笼头套在了驴子尾巴上。

因为他决定了往回走。

——卢克莱修

他经常跌入陷阱也就不足为奇了。这让我们这些人一说到死亡就害怕，大多数人像听到魔鬼的名字一样画十字。由于遗嘱中必然提到这件事，就别指望在医生给他们宣读终审判决以前，他们会动手立遗嘱。在痛苦与惊慌之间，他们会以怎样清晰的判断力，给你凑合出一份遗嘱，只有天知道了。

由于这个词听在他们的耳朵里太刺激，这个声音对他们又像不吉利，罗马人学会了用婉转的说法来减弱或冲淡它的含意。不说：他死了，他停止了生命；只说：他活过了。只要是“活”，即使过去式也感到安慰。我们的“故人某某”就是从他们那里借来的。

说到这里，是不是像俗语说的，时间就是金钱？我生于一五三三年二月的最后一天，是按现行的以正月为一年之始的年历来说的[4]。恰好十五天前刚过了三十九岁，至少还可以活那么久；可是急着去考虑那么远的事不是发疯吗？但怎么说呢，年轻人与老年人同样都会抛下生命。刚刚进来的人照样可以随即离去。再衰老的人，只要还看到玛土撒拉[5]走在前面，都相信自己的身子还可以撑上二十年。

再说，你这个可怜的傻瓜，谁给你规定了寿限啦？你这是根据医生的胡说八道。还不如瞧一瞧事实与经验吧。按照事物的常规，你活到今天已是鸿运高照了。你已超过了常人的寿数。为了证明这一点，算一算你的朋友中间有多少人在你这个年龄以前已经谢世，肯定比达到你的年龄的人要多。再来列一张表，记上一生中名声显赫的人，我敢打赌在三十五岁前死的要比在这以后死的多。把耶稣基督作为人类的楷模，也是十分理智与虔诚的，因为耶稣在三十三岁就结束了人生。亚历山大是最伟大的凡人，也是在这岁数去世的。

死亡又有多少种袭击方式？

时时刻刻需要提防危险，

人是难以预料的。

——贺拉斯

且不说发高烧和胸膜炎病人。谁想到一位布列塔尼公爵会在人群中挤死？我的邻居克莱芒五世教皇进入里昂也是这样。你没看到我们的一位国王在比武游戏中被误伤丧了命吗？他的一位祖先竟会被一头公猪撞死？埃斯库罗斯眼看一幢房子要坍塌，徒然躲到空地上，有一只苍鹰飞过空中，从爪子里丢下一块乌龟壳，把他砸死了。还有人被一颗葡萄核梗死；一位皇帝在梳头时被梳子划破头皮而死；埃米利乌斯·李必达脚绊在门槛上，奥菲迪乌斯进议院时撞上了大门。还有死于女人大腿间的教士科内利乌斯·加吕，罗马巡逻队长蒂日利努斯，曼图亚侯爵吉·德·贡萨格的儿子吕多维可。

更糟糕的例子是柏拉图派哲学家斯珀西普斯和我们的一位教皇。可怜的伯比乌斯法官给诉讼一方八天期限，自己却突然得病，没有活到那个时候。凯乌斯·朱利乌斯是医生，在给病人上眼药膏时，死神来给他闭上了眼睛。我还该说一说我自己的弟弟，圣马丁步兵司令，年二十三岁，早已显出大胆勇敢，打网球时球击中他左耳上方，表面看不出挫伤和破裂，他甚至没有坐下来休息，但是五六小时后，他死于这次球击引起的中风。

这些都是发生在我们眼前的例子，稀松平常，怎么还能够不去想到死亡呢？怎么能够不觉得死神每时每刻在掐我们的脖子呢？

你们或许会对我说，既然不管怎样总是要来的，大家就不用去操这份心了吧？我同意这个看法；若有什么方法可以躲过死亡的袭击，即使是藏在一张牛皮底下，我也不是个会退缩回避的人。因为我只要过得自在就够了；我自己尽量往最好的方面去做，至于荣耀与表率则不在我的考虑之内。

我宁可被人看成傻子与呆子，

只要我的古怪令我痛快，叫我开心，

也不去当个聪明人愤愤不平。

——贺拉斯

以为这样就能做到了，这也是妄想。他们来了，他们去了，他们骑马，他们跳舞，闭口不谈死亡。这一切多么美好。毫不注意，毫不防范，当死亡降临到他们身上，或者他们的妻儿朋友身上时，则悲痛欲绝，呼天抢地，愤怒失望！你们几曾见过如此萎靡、恍惚、混乱！我们必须及早防范。一个头脑明白的人，对待死亡却像动物似的混混沌沌，我认为这是要不得的，也会让我们付出沉重的代价。如果死亡是个可以躲开的敌人，我建议大家不妨拿起胆小鬼的武器。但是既然它是不可避免的，既然退缩求饶和勇敢面对，它都是要把你抓走的：

他对逃跑中的壮汉穷追不舍，

也不放过胆怯的后生

露出的腿弯与背脊。

——贺拉斯

既然没有铁甲保护你：

躲在盔甲下也是枉然，

死神会让他露出后缩的脑袋。

——普罗佩提乌斯

我们必须学习挺身而出，面对它进行斗争。为了打落它的气势，我们必须采取逆常规而行的办法。不要把死亡看成是一件意外事，要看成是一件常事，习惯它，脑子里常常想到它。时时刻刻让它以各种各样的面目出现在我们的想象中。马匹惊跳，瓦片坠落，针轻轻一刺，立即想到：“要是这就是死亡呢？”这时候我们要坚强，要努力。

欢天喜地的时候，总是想到我们的生存状态，不要纵情而忘乎所以，记得多少回乐极会生悲，死亡会骤然而至。埃及人设宴，席间在上好菜时，叫人抬上一具干尸，作为对宴客的警告。

照亮你的每一天都当作最后一天，

赞美它带来的恩惠与意外的时间。

——贺拉斯

死亡在哪里等着我们是很不确定的，那就随时恭候它。事前考虑死亡也是事前考虑自由。谁学习了死亡，谁也就学习了不被奴役。死亡的学问使我们超越任何束缚与强制。一个人明白了失去生命不是坏事，那么生命对他也就不存在坏事了。可怜的马其顿国王当了波勒斯·伊米利厄斯的俘虏，差人求他不要把他带到凯旋仪式上，伊米利厄斯答复说：“让他向自己求情吧。”

其实，在一切事情上，天公若不助一臂之力，手段与心计都很难施展。我本性并不忧郁，但爱好空想。从小对什么事都没像对死亡想得那么多，即使在放荡的岁月也是这样。

年少风流，青春欢悦。

——卡图鲁斯

在女人堆里寻欢作乐时，有人以为我站在一旁醋性大发，或者抱着希望拿不定主意，其实我在想着今已不知是谁的那个人，他就在几天前突然发高烧一命呜呼了；当他离开这样一次盛会时，满脑子是闲情、爱欲和好时光，像我一样，耳边也响着同样的话：

好时光即将消逝，消逝后再不回来。

——卢克莱修

这个想法不会比其他事情更叫我皱眉头。最初想到这类事不可能没有感触。但是日子一久，翻来覆去想多了，无疑也就习以为常了，否则我会终日提心吊胆；因为从来没有人会那么舍弃生命，没有人会那么不计较寿命的长短。直到今天为止，我一直精力充沛，极少生病，健康既没有使我对生命的期望增大，疾病也没有使我对生命的期望减少。我觉得自己每分钟都在逃过一劫。我不停地对自己唱：“另一天会发生的事，今天也会发生。”

说真的，意外与危险并不使我们更靠近死亡。如果我们想到，即使没有这桩好像威胁着我们的最大事件，还有成千上万桩其他事件悬在我们头上，我们就会明白，不论精力充沛还是高烧难退，在海上还是在家里，战场上还是休息中，死亡离我们都一样近。“谁都不比谁更脆弱，也不比谁对明天更有把握。”（塞涅卡）

去世前我有事要做，即使只需一小时就可完成，我也不敢说一定有时间去做完。日前有人翻阅我的记事册，发现一份备忘录，列上我在死前要做的事。我实实在在地对他说，那时我离家才一里地，还精神十足，心情愉快，但还是匆匆把这些事记了下来，因为没把握一定能够回到家。我这个人脑子随时随地在想东西，随即把它们记在心里，时刻做好充分准备；当死亡突然降临，对我也不算是突如其来的新鲜事。

应该随时穿好鞋子，准备上路，尤其要注意和做到的是这事只与自己有关。

短短的一生内何必计划成堆？

——贺拉斯

不算上这件事我们已经够忙碌的了。有一个人抱怨死亡，只是因为死亡使他功亏一篑，没有打完一场漂亮的胜仗；另一个人自思自叹，没把女儿嫁出去或把孩子教育安排好就会撒手人寰；这人舍不得抛下妻子，那人离不开儿子，这都是人生的主要乐趣。

我现在——感谢上帝——处于这样的状态下，可以应召离开，对什么事都毫无牵挂，虽然对人生尚有依恋，失去它会感到哀伤。我正在给自己松绑，已跟大家告别了一半，除了对自己。没有人对离开世界做了那么干脆与充分的准备，那么彻底摆脱一切，如同我正在做的一样。

可怜啊可怜，他们说，只要一个凶日

就会掳走我在世上的全部财富！

——卢克莱修

而建筑师说：

工程未完成，前功尽弃，

墙头砌到一半，摇摇欲坠。

——维吉尔

凡事不必筹备过于长期的规划，至少对于看不到其完成的事也保持热诚。我们生来是为了行动：

当我死时，但愿正在工作。

——奥维德

我愿意大家行动，尽量延长生命的功能，死神来时我若正在园子里种菜，不在乎它，更不在乎园子还没种完。我看见过一个人死去，他到了人生最后关头，不停地埋怨命运割断了他手中的历史之线，他还只写到我们的第十五或第十六位国王。

谁也不能说，对财物的留恋

不会也存在于你的残骸中。

——卢克莱修

应该摆脱这些庸俗有害的心态。正因为如此，坟墓盖在教堂附近，在城市里人来人往最多的地方，据利库尔戈斯说，这是为让男女老少不要看到死人而发毛，不断看见骸骨、坟墓和送灵，提醒着我们什么是人的处境：

古代用杀人给宴会助兴，

让武士相互残杀，

身子跌倒在酒杯上，

鲜血洒满宴席。

——西流斯·伊塔利库斯

埃及人在宴会结束后，给宾客展示一张死神的巨像，举像的人对着他们大叫：“喝吧，玩吧，死后你就是这个样。”因而我也养成了习惯，不但心里老惦念着死，嘴边也念叨着死，干什么都没那么乐意地去打听人的死亡，他们那时说过些什么，脸上表情怎么样，神态如何；读史书时也最注意这方面的章节。

我的书里充斥着这些例子，也可看出我对这些材料情有独钟。如果我编书，就要出一部集子，评论形形色色的死亡。教人如何死亡，也是在教人如何生活。

狄凯阿科斯编了一部题目类似的书，但内容不同，不很实用。

有人跟我说，事实远远超出想象，当人到了那个地步，剑法再高明也有失手时。让他们去说吧，事前考虑必定大有裨益。再说，脸不变色心不动，从容前赴，难道不算本领吗？

况且，大自然会伸出援助之手，给我们勇气。如果是暴卒，我们来不及害怕。若情况相反，我发觉随着病情的进展，也自然而然对生命日益蔑视。我发现身体有病时比身体健康时更易下决心去死。尤其我并不眷恋人生的欢乐，理由是我已开始失去享受的乐趣，对死亡也看得不如以前那么害怕。这使我希望做到离生愈远，离死愈近，也愈容易实行生与死的交替。

我在许多情况下试验过恺撒的说法：事物远看时常比近看显得大。我发觉自己健康时要比生病时更怕死亡。当我高高兴兴时，欢乐与力量使我把生与死的状态看得明显不成比例，成倍夸大烦恼以及它们造成的心理压力，我真的有病缠身时从来不至于如此。

我希望死亡来时我也有这样好的心态。体验变化与衰退很正常：这好比是大自然悄悄让我们在不知不觉中衰败凋零。往日青春年少的活力，在一位老人身上还留下多少？

唉，老人身上还剩下多少生命。

——马克西米努斯

恺撒有一名卫兵，神情憔悴，在街上向他走来，要求他批准自己去寻死。恺撒看他失魂落魄的样子，风趣地回答：“你居然以为自己在活着。”谁要是猝然消失，我相信我们谁都难以忍受。但是我们被它牵着手，从一条感觉不出的斜坡上，慢慢地一步步滑入这种惨境，再与之相适应。所以当青春在我们身上消逝时我们不觉得震动。虽然从本质与实情来说，青春消逝也是一种死亡，要比郁郁而死及寿终正寝更加严酷的死亡。尤其从恶活到不活这个跳跃不是很沉重，还比不得从青春欢乐的人生跌入痛苦艰难的境地。

佝偻的身躯背不起重担，心灵也是如此。必须让心灵开朗飞扬才能顶住这个死敌的压力。因为心灵害怕时就永远不会安宁。一旦心灵安宁了，它就可以自豪地说，焦虑、恐惧甚至微不足道的烦恼不足以干扰它。这差不多超越了我们人类的处境。

坚如磐石的心动摇不了，

无论是暴君威逼的目光，

亚得里亚海上肆虐的风暴，

还是朱庇特的霹雳掌。

——贺拉斯

心灵就成了情欲与贪婪的主宰，匮乏、羞耻、贫困和其他一切厄运的主宰。谁能够主宰谁就应去获得这种心灵优势。这才是至高无上的自由，让我们养成浩气去取笑武力与不公，嘲弄监牢与铁链：

我叫你戴上手铐脚镣，

交给一个恶吏看管——神会来救我的。

——你是说：我会死的，以死来一了百了？

——贺拉斯

在我们的宗教中，人最可靠的基础就是蔑视生命。不光是理智的推理要我们这样去做：有一件东西失去后不可能后悔，我们又为什么害怕失去呢？而且既然我们受到那么多死亡方式的威胁，害怕一切方式还不如忍受一种方式而少受些痛苦吧？既然死亡是不可避免的，什么时候来也就不管它了吧？当苏格拉底听人说：“三十僭主已经判了你死刑。”他回答：“自然法则也会轮到他们的。”

走在摆脱一切苦难的旅程上难过起来，这是何等的愚蠢！

一切事物随我们诞生而诞生，同样，一切事物随我们死亡而死亡。为一百年后我们不会活着的一切哭泣，犹如为一百年前我们不曾活过的一切哭泣，都是一样傻。死亡是另一种生命的开始，正如我们当年哭闹着到来，正如我们艰难地走进这个生命，正如我们进去时换下了以前的面纱。

凡事仅有一次也就无所谓痛苦。有什么理由为瞬息的事去担那么长久的忧？活得短与活得长在死亡面前都一样。对于不复存在的东西，长与短也不存在。亚里士多德说，希帕尼斯河上有些小动物只能活上一天。上午八点钟死的属于青春夭折，下午五点钟死的属于寿终正寝。对这段时间的幸与不幸斤斤计较，我们中间谁见了不会嘲笑？我们最长与最短的生命，若与永恒相比，或者跟山川、星辰、树木甚至某些动物相比，也是同样可笑。

但是大自然逼迫我们走上这条路。它说：你们怎么来到也就怎么走出这个世界。从死到生这条路你们走时不热情也不害怕，从生到死你们也这样去走。你们的死亡是宇宙秩序的一个组成部分，地球生命中的一刹那—

世人之间传递生命，

就像赛跑手交接火炬。

——卢克莱修

事物这样紧密安排，我能为你做出任何改变吗？这是你诞生的条件，死亡也是你的一部分；你这是在躲避自己。你享受的人生对生与对死均是有份的。你诞生的第一天引导你走向死，也同样引导你走向生。

第一时刻提供生命，同时也侵蚀生命。

——塞涅卡

诞生时开始了死亡，根源中包含了终结。

——马尼利乌斯

你生活的一切，是从生命那里窃取的；你活着是对生命的侵害。你一生中不断营造的是死亡。当你在生命中，你也是在死亡中。当你不再活着时，你的死亡也过去了。

因此，你若更喜欢如此，在活过了以后再死吧。可是在生活中你是个垂死的人，垂死的人要比已死的人遭受死亡的冲击更严酷，更强烈，更本质。

你若得到过人生的好处，享尽了欢乐，那就心满意足地走吧。

为何不像酒足饭饱的宾客一样离开人生宴席？

——卢克莱修

你若不曾欢度人生，它对你没有用处，失去它又有什么要紧的呢？你留下又做什么用呢？

必然要失去的时间，一事无成的时间，

又何必苦苦去延长呢？

——卢克莱修

生命本身既不好也不坏：按照你给它什么位子才会有好坏之分。你若生活了一天，也就一切都看见了。一天与天天是相同的。没有其他的光，也没有其他的暗。这个太阳，这个月亮，这些星星，这样的排列，跟你的祖先欣赏到的一样，也将让你的后代同样欣赏。

你的祖先看到的不是别的，

你的后代也不会看到其他。

——马尼利乌斯

再差的话，我的喜剧里每一幕的演员搭配与剧情变化也都在一年内轮转一遍。如果你注意到我的四季更替，这四季包含了尘世的童年、青年、壮年和老年。它完成它的工作，没有其他奥妙，只是周而复始，永无止境。

我们绕着我们永远待着的圈子在转。

——卢克莱修

一年四季环绕着自己的足迹转动。

——维吉尔

我决不会故意给你设计其他的新消遣。

我不能给你有什么创新，

新的游戏同老的游戏一样。

——卢克莱修

你给别人让出位子，犹如别人曾给你让出位子。

平等是公正的主要组成部分。人人逃脱不了的地方你也逃脱不了，这能怨谁吗？不管你活着还是不活，你不能把你死的时间减少一二。这一切都是徒劳的，你在你害怕的这个状态里依然待得这么长，犹如你在吃奶的婴儿时期死去一样—

你就是称心如意活了几世纪，

死亡还是千秋万代存在下去。

——卢克莱修

我将妥善安排你，不让你有任何怨言—

你知道吧，死亡不会让

另一个你活下来，站在

你的尸体前哭泣。

——卢克莱修

也不让你留恋你那么难舍的生命—

无人会想起他一己的生命，

我们也不会悼念自身伤心。

——卢克莱修

死比无还不值得害怕，还有什么比无更少的吗？

在我们看来死亡代表失去，

但已经是无，还能失去什么呢？

——卢克莱修

这跟你在生时与死时都无关。生时，因为你还存在；死时，因为你不再存在。

谁都不会在寿数已尽前去世。你死后留下的时间，正如你生前过去的时间，都不是你的，跟你无关。

从前天长地久的时间，

对我们已了无影踪。

——卢克莱修

你的生命不论在何地结束，总是整个留在了那里。生命的价值不在于岁月长短，而在于如何度过。有的人寿命很长，但内容很少；当你活着的时候要提防这一点。你活得是否有意义，这取决于你的意愿，不是岁数多少。你不停往那儿走的地方，你可曾想过会走不到吗？何况条条道路都是有尽头的。

如果有人相伴可以给你安慰，世界不正是跟你并肩而行吗？

你的生命结束，万物跟随你死亡。

——卢克莱修

不是一切都随着你摇晃而摇晃吗？哪有什么不跟着你一起衰老的呢？成千上万的人、动物、其他生灵都在你死亡的一刻死亡：

白天接着黑夜，黑夜接着白天，

不会听不到

葬礼上的哭丧声

与婴儿的呱呱声响成一片。

——卢克莱修

既然身后无路，倒退又有什么用？你见过不少人很乐意死去，借此结束了莫大的苦难。但是不乐意死去的，你曾经见过吗？有的事你没亲自经历过，也没通过别人体验过，就加以谴责，岂不是太天真了吗？你为什么要抱怨我和命运？我们错待你了吗？是你控制我们，还是我们控制你？你虽说年纪还不大，生命却已经到了尽头。人无论大小都是一个完整的人。人及其生命都不是以尺子来丈量的。萨图恩是掌管时间与生命的神，儿子喀戎听了他介绍不死的条件后，断然拒绝永生。

“你可以想象对于人来说永生永世不死，实在比我给他规定的有限人生更难忍受，更艰苦。如果你不会死，你会不停地咒骂我没给你准备死亡。我有意在死亡中增添了一些悲情，免得你看到死亡来得方便，过于迫切和随便地去拥抱它。为了让你把节制铭记在心，既不逃避生，也不逃避死——这是我对你的要求——我把生与死调节在苦与乐之间。

“你们七贤中的第一人泰勒斯，我教导他说生与死并无区别；因而，有人问他为什么不去死，他非常聪明地回答：‘因为这并无区别。’

“水、土、火以及我们这个球体建筑的其他组件，既构成你的生命，也构成你的死亡。你为什么担心最后一天？它并不比其他的每一天更促成你的死亡。劳累不是最后一步走出来的，只是在最后一步表现出来了。每天都走向死亡，最后一天走到了。”

以上是我们大自然母亲的忠告。我经常思忖怎么会这样，就是战争期间，我们在自己和别人身上见到死亡的面目，不像在家里见到的那么狰狞，无从相比，要不又是一大群医生与哭哭啼啼的人。同样是死，村民与老百姓心里要比其他阶层的人泰然得多。

我相信实际上还是我们围绕死者露出可怕的神情，制造阴沉的气氛，比死亡本身更加吓人。生活完全变了样，老母妻儿号啕大哭，惊慌发呆的亲友前来吊丧，脸色苍白、两眼垂泪的一大群仆人四处张罗，不见日光的一个房间里点着蜡烛，床头围着医生与教士；总之，我们四周惊恐万状。在那时候，我们未死的人也被埋葬在土里了。孩子看到自己的小朋友戴了面具会害怕，我们也是这样。人的面具与事物的面具同样应该摘掉。摘掉以后，我们发现罩在面具之下的这个死亡，跟不久前一名仆人或丫鬟平平静静的死亡并无两样。

铲除了这一切繁文缛节，死亡是幸福的！

[3]据希腊神话，坦塔罗斯把儿子剁成碎块祭神，触怒主神宙斯，将他永世置于随时会砸落的岩石下。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为译者注。）

[4]原先以复活节为一年之始。

[5]《圣经·旧约》中的人物，据说活了九百六十九岁。

How We Weep and Laugh at the Same Thing

[An understanding of the complexity of conflicting emotions helps us to avoid trivial interpretations of great men and their grief.]

When we read in our history books that Antigonus was severely displeased with his son for having brought him the head of his enemy King Pyrrhus who had just been killed fighting against him and that he burst into copious tears when he saw it; and that Duke René of Lorraine also lamented the death of Duke Charles of Burgundy whom he had just defeated, and wore mourning at his funeral; and that at the battle of Auroy which the Count de Mont-fort won against Charles de Blois, his rival for the Duchy of Brittany, the victor showed great grief when he hap-pened upon his enemy’s corpse：we should not at once exclaim，

Et cosi aven che l’animo ciascuna

Sua passion sotto et contrario manto

Ricopre, con la vista hor’chiara hor bruna.

[Thus does the mind cloak every passion with its opposite, our faces showing now joy, now sadness.]

When they presented Caesar with the head of Pompey our histories say that he turned his gaze away as from a spectacle both ugly and displeasing. There had been such a long understanding and fellowship between them in the management of affairs of State, they had shared the same fortunes and rendered each other so many mutual services as allies, that we should not believe that his behaviour was quite false and counterfeit - as this other poet thinks it was：

tutumque putavit

Jam bonus esse socer; lachrimas non sponte cadentes

Effudit, gemitusque expressit pectore lœto.

[And now he thought it was safe to play the good father-in-law; he poured out tears, but not spontaneous ones, and he forced out groans from his happy breast.]

For while it is true that most of our actions are but mask and cosmetic, and that it is sometimes true that

Hœredis fletus sub persona risus est;

[Behind the mask, the tears of an heir are laughter;]

nevertheless we ought to consider when judging such events how our souls are often shaken by conflicting emo-tions. Even as there is said to be a variety of humours assembled in our bodies, the dominant one being that which normally prevails according to our complexion, so too in our souls：although diverse emotions may shake them, there is one which must remain in possession of the field; nevertheless its victory is not so complete but that the weaker ones do not sometimes regain lost ground because of the pliancy and mutability of our soul and make a brief sally in their turn. That is why we can see that not only children, who artlessly follow Nature, often weep and laugh at the same thing, but that not one of us either can boast that, no matter how much he may want to set out on a journey, he still does not feel his heart a-tremble when he says goodbye to family and friends：even if he does not actually burst into tears at least he puts foot to stirrup with a sad and gloomy face. And however noble the passion which enflames the heart of a well-born bride, she still has to have her arms prised from her mother’s neck before being given to her hus-band, no matter what that merry fellow may say：

Est ne novis nuptis odio venus, anne parentum

Frustrantur falsis gaudia lachrimulis,

Ubertim thalami quas intra limina fundunt?

Non, ita me divi, vera gemunt, juverint.

[Is Venus really hated by our brides, or do they mock their parents’joy with those false tears which they pour forth in abundance at their chamber-door? No. So help me, gods, their sobs are false ones.]

And so it is not odd to lament the death of a man whom we would by no means wish to be still alive.

When I rail at my manservant I do so sincerely with all my mind：my curses are real not feigned. But once I cease to fume, if he needs help from me I am glad to help him：I turn over the page. When I call him a dolt or a calf I have no intention of stitching such labels on to him for ever：nor do I believe I am contradicting myself when I later call him an honest fellow. No one characteristic clasps us purely and universally in its embrace. If only talking to oneself did not look mad, no day would go by without my being heard growling to myself, against myself, ‘You silly shit!’ Yet I do not intend that to be a definition of me.

If anyone should think when he sees me sometimes look bleakly at my wife and sometimes lovingly that either emotion is put on, then he is daft. When Nero took leave of his mother whom he was sending to be drowned, he nevertheless felt some emotion at his mother’s departure and felt horror and pity.

The sun, they say, does not shed its light in one con-tinuous flow but ceaselessly darts fresh rays so thickly at us, one after another, that we cannot perceive any gap between them：

Largus enim liquidi fons luminis,œtherius sol

Inrigat assidue cœlum candore recenti,

Suppeditatque novo confestim lumine lumen.

[That generous source of liquid light, the aethereal sun, assiduously floods the heavens with new rays and ceaselessly sheds light upon new light.]

So, too, our soul darts its arrows separately but imperceptibly.

Artabanus happened to take his nephew Xerxes by sur-prise. He teased him about the sudden change which he saw come over his face. But Xerxes was in fact thinking about the huge size of his army as it was crossing the Hellespont for the expedition against Greece; he first felt a quiver of joy at seeing so many thousands of men devoted to his service and showed this by a happy and festive look on his face; then, all of a sudden his thoughts turned to all those lives which would wither in a hundred years at most：he knit his brow and was saddened to tears.

We have pursued revenge for an injury with a resolute will; we have felt a singular joy at our victory... and we weep：yet it is not for that that we weep. Nothing has changed; but our mind contemplates the matter in a dif-ferent light and sees it from another aspect：for everything has many angles and many different sheens. Thoughts of kinship, old acquaintanceships and affections suddenly seize our minds and stir them each according to their worth：but the change is so sudden that it escapes us：

Nil adeo fieri celeri ratione videtur

Quam si mens fieri proponit et inchoat ipsa.

Ocius ergo animus quam res se perciet ulla,

Ante oculos quarum in promptu natura videtur.

[Nothing can be seen to match the rapidity of the thoughts which the mind produces and initiates. The mind is swifter than anything which the nature of our eyes allows them to see.]

That is why we deceive ourselves if we want to make this never-ending succession into one continuous whole. When Timoleon weeps for the murder which, with noble determination, he committed, he does not weep for the liberty he has restored to his country; he does not weep for the Tyrant：he weeps for his brother. He has done one part of his duty：let us allow him to do the other.

On conscience

[Conscience originally meant connivance. Conscience in the sense of our individual consciousness of right and wrong or of our own guilt or rectitude fascinated Montaigne. It became a vital concern of his during the Wars of Religion with their cruel-ties, their false accusations and their use of torture on prisoners. Such moral basis as there was for the ‘question’ （judicial tor-ture） seems, curiously enough, to have been a respect for the power of conscience - of a man’s inner sense of his guilt or innocence which would strengthen or weaken his power to with-stand pain. A major source of Montaigne’s ideas here is St Augustine and a passionate note by Juan Luis Vives in his edition of the City of God designed to undermine confidence in torture.]

During our civil wars I was travelling one day with my brother the Sieur de la Brousse when we met a gentleman of good appearance who was on the other side from us; I did not know anything about that since he feigned otherwise. The worst of these wars is that the cards are so mixed up, with your enemy indistinguishable from you by any clear indication of language or deportment, being brought up under the same laws, manners and climate, that it is not easy to avoid confusion and disorder. That made me fear that I myself would come upon our own troops in a place where I was not known, be obliged to state my name and wait for the worst. That did happen to me on another occasion：for, from just such a mishap, I lost men and horses. Among others, they killed one of my pages, pitifully：an Italian of good family whom I was carefully training; in him was extinguished a young life, beautiful and full of great promise.

But that man of mine was so madly afraid! I noticed that he nearly died every time we met any horsemen or passed through towns loyal to the King; I finally guessed that his alarm arose from his conscience. It seemed to that wretched man that you could read right into the very secret thoughts of his mind through his mask and the crosses on his greatcoat. So wondrous is the power of conscience! It makes us betray, accuse and fight against ourselves. In default of an outside testimony it leads us to witness against ourselves：

Occultum quatiens animo tortore flagellum.

[Lashing us with invisible whips, our soul torments us.]

The following story is on the lips of children：a Paeon-ian called Bessus was rebuked for having deliberately destroyed a nest of swallows, killing them all. He said he was right to do so：those little birds kept falsely accusing him of having murdered his father! Until then this act of parricide had been hidden and unknown; but the aveng-ing Furies of his conscience made him who was to pay the penalty reveal the crime.

Hesiod corrects that saying of Plato’s, that the punish-ment follows hard upon the sin. He says it is born at the same instant, with the sin itself; to expect punishment is to suffer it：to merit it is to expect it. Wickedness forges torments for itself,

Malum consilium consultori pessimum,

[Who counsels evil, suffers evil most,]

just as the wasp harms others when it stings but especially itself, for it loses sting and strength for ever：

Vitasque in vulnere ponunt.

[In that wound they lay down their lives.]

The Spanish blister-fly secretes an antidote to its poi-son, by some mutual antipathy within nature. So too, just when we take pleasure in vice, there is born in our con-science an opposite displeasure, which tortures us, sleeping and waking, with many painful thoughts.

Quippe ubi se multi, per somnia sœpe loquentes,

Aut morbo delirantes, procraxe ferantur,

Et celata diu in medium peccala dedisse.

[Many indeed, often talking in their sleep or delirious in illness, have proclaimed, it is said, and betrayed long-hidden sins.]

Apollodorus dreamed that he saw himself being flayed by the Scythians then boiled in a pot while his heart kept muttering, ‘I am the cause of all these ills.’ No hiding-place awaits the wicked, said Epicurus, for they can never be certain of hiding there while their conscience gives them away.

Prima est hœc ultio, quod se

Judice nemo nocens absolvitur.

[This is the principal vengeance：no guilty man is absolved：he is his own judge.]

Conscience can fill us with fear, but she can also fill us with assurance and confidence. And I can say that I have walked more firmly through some dangers by reflecting on the secret knowledge I had of my own will and the innocence of my designs.

Conscia mens ut cuique sua est, ita concipit intra

Pectora pro facto spemque metumque suo.

[A mind conscious of what we have done conceives within our breast either hope or fear, according to our deeds.]

There are hundreds of examples：it will suffice to cite three of them about the same great man.

When Scipio was arraigned one day before the Roman people on a grave indictment, instead of defending him-self and flattering his judges he said：‘Your wishing to judge, on a capital charge, a man through whom you have authority to judge the Roman world, becomes you well!’

Another time his only reply to the accusations made against him by a Tribune of the People was not to plead his cause but to say：‘Come, fellow citizens! Let us go and give thanks to the gods for the victory they gave me over the Carthaginians on just such a day as this!’ Then as he started to walk towards the temple all the assembled people could be seen following after him - even his prosecutor.

Again when Petilius, under the instigation of Cato, demanded that Scipio account for the monies that had passed through his hands in the province of Antioch, Scipio came to the Senate for this purpose, took his account-book from under his toga and declared that it contained the truth about his receipts and expenditure; but when he was told to produce it as evidence he refused to do so, saying that he had no wish to act so shamefully towards himself; in the presence of the Senate he tore it up with his own hands. I do not believe that a soul with seared scars could have counterfeited such assurance. He had, says Livy, a mind too great by nature, a mind too elevated by Fortune, even to know how to be a crim-inal or to condescend to the baseness of defending his innocence.

Torture is a dangerous innovation; it would appear that it is an assay not of the truth but of a man’s endurance. The man who can endure it hides the truth：so does he who cannot. For why should pain make me confess what is true rather than force me to say what is not true? And on the contrary if a man who has not done what he is accused of is able to support such torment, why should a man who has done it be unable to support it, when so beautiful a reward as life itself is offered him?

I think that this innovation is founded on the import-ance of the power of conscience. It would seem that in the case of the guilty man it would weaken him and assist the torture in making him confess his fault, whereas it strengthens the innocent man against the torture. But to speak the truth, it is a method full of danger and uncer-tainty. What would you not say, what would you not do, to avoid such grievous pain?

Etiam innocentes cogit mentiri dolor.

[Pain compels even the innocent to lie.]

This results in a man whom the judge has put to the tor-ture lest he die innocent being condemned to die both innocent and tortured. Thousands upon thousands have falsely confessed to capital charges. Among them, after considering the details of the trial which Alexander made him face and the way he was tortured, I place Philotas.

All the same it is, so they say, the least bad method that human frailty has been able to discover. Very inhumanely, however, and very ineffectually in my opin-ion. Many peoples less barbarous in this respect than the Greeks and the Romans who call them the Barbarians reckon it horrifying and cruel to torture and smash a man of whose crime you are still in doubt. That ignorant doubt is yours：what has it to do with him? You are the unjust one, are you not? who do worse than kill a man so as not to kill him without due cause! You can prove that by seeing how frequently a man prefers to die for no reason at all rather than to pass through such a questioning which is more painful than the death-penalty itself and which by its harshness often anticipates that penalty by carrying it out.

I do not know where I heard this from, but it exactly represents the conscience of our own Justice：a village woman accused a soldier before his commanding general - a great man for justice - of having wrenched from her little children such sops as she had left to feed them with, the army having laid waste all the surrounding vil-lages. As for proof, there was none. That general first summoned the woman to think carefully what she was saying, especially since she would be guilty of perjury if she were lying; she persisted, so he had the soldier’s belly slit open in order to throw the light of truth on to the fact. The woman was found to be right. An investiga-tory condemnation!

On punishing cowardice

[Renaissance Jurisconsults such as Tiraquellus were concerned to temper the severity of the Law by examining motives and human limitations. Montaigne does so here in a matter of great concern to gentlemen in time of war.]

I once heard a prince, a very great general, maintain that a soldier should not be condemned to death for coward-ice：he was at table, being told about the trial of the Seigneur de Vervins who was sentenced to death for sur-rendering Boulogne.

In truth it is reasonable that we should make a great difference between defects due to our weakness and those due to our wickedness. In the latter we deliberately brace ourselves against reason’s rules, which are imprinted on us by Nature; in the former it seems we can call Nature herself as a defence-witness for having left us so weak and imperfect. That is why a great many people believe that we can only be punished for deeds done against our con-science：on that rule is partly based the opinion of those who condemn the capital punishment of heretics and misbelievers as well as the opinion that a barrister or a judge cannot be arraigned if they fail in their duty merely from ignorance.

Where cowardice is concerned the usual way is, cer-tainly, to punish it by disgrace and ignominy. It is said that this rule was first introduced by Charondas the law-giver, and that before his time the laws of Greece condemned to death those who had fled from battle, whereas he ordered that they be made merely to sit for three days in the market-place dressed as women：he hoped he could still make use of them once he had restored their courage by this disgrace - ‘Suffundere malis hominis sanguinem quam effundere.’ [Make the blood of a bad man blush not gush.]

It seems too that in ancient times the laws of Rome condemned deserters to death：Ammianus Marcellinus tells how the Emperor Julian condemned ten of his sol-diers to be stripped of their rank and then suffer death, ‘following,’ he said, ‘our Ancient laws’.Elsewhere how-ever Julian for a similar fault condemned others to remain among the prisoners under the ensign in charge of the baggage. Even the harsh sentences decreed against those who had fled at Cannae and those who in that same war had followed Gnaeus Fulvius in his defeat did not extend to death.

Yet it is to be feared that disgrace, by making men desperate, may make them not merely estranged but hostile.

When our fathers were young the Seigneur de Franget, formerly a deputy-commander in the Company of My Lord Marshal de Châtillon, was sent by My Lord Marshal de Chabannes to replace the Seigneur Du Lude as Gov-ernor of Fuentarabia; he surrendered it to the Spaniards. He was sentenced to be stripped of his nobility, both he and his descendants being pronounced commoners, liable to taxation and unfit to bear arms. That severe sentence was executed at Lyons. Later all the noblemen who were at Guyse when the Count of Nassau entered it suffered a similar punishment; and subsequently others still.

Anyway, wherever there is a case of ignorance so crass and of cowardice so flagrant as to surpass any norm, that should be an adequate reason for accepting them as proof of wickedness and malice, to be punished as such.

On the vanity of words

[Montaigne, despite his own mastery of language, despised words and admired deeds or‘matter’.He showed this before he embarked on the Essays in the dedicatory letter of his transla-tion of Raymond Sebond’s Natural Theology, addressed to his father. What Montaigne admired in ancient Sparta - and what he found lacking in his own day - was a genuine respect for action over rhetoric.]

In former times there was a rhetorician who said his job was to make trivial things seem big and to be accepted as such. He is a cobbler who can make big shoes fit little feet. In Sparta they would have had him flogged for prac-tising the art of lying and deception. And I am sure that Archidamus their king did not hear without amazement the answer given by Thucydides when he asked him whether he was better at wrestling than Pericles：‘That,’ Thucydides replied, ‘would be hard to prove：for after I have thrown him to the ground in the match he persuades the spectators that he did not have a fall and is declared the winner.’Those who hide women behind a mask of make-up do less harm, since it is not much of a loss not to see them as they are by nature, whereas rhetoricians pride themselves on deceiving not our eyes but our judge-ment, bastardizing and corrupting things in their very essence. Countries such as Crete and Sparta which main-tained themselves in a sound and regulated polity did not rate orators very highly.

Ariston wisely defined rhetoric as the art of persuading the people; Socrates and Plato, as the art of deceiving and flattering; and those who reject this generic descrip-tion show it to be true by what they teach. The Mahometans will not allow their children to be taught it because of its uselessness. And the Athenians, despite the fact that the practice of it was esteemed in their city, realizing how pernicious it was, ordained that the main part of it which is to work on the emotions should be abolished, together with formal introductions and perorations.

It is a means invented for manipulating and stirring up the mob and a community fallen into lawlessness; it is a means which, like medicine, is used only when states are sick; in states such as Athens, Rhodes and Rome where the populace, or the ignorant, or all men, held all power and where everything was in perpetual turmoil, the ora-tors flooded in. And in truth few great men in those countries managed to thrust themselves into positions of trust without the help of eloquent speech：Pompey, Caesar, Crassus, Lucullus, Lentulus and Metellus all made it their mainstay for scrambling up towards that grandiose authority which they finally achieved, helped more by rhetoric than by arms, contrary to what was thought right in better times. For Lucius Volumnius, making a public address in favour of the candidates Quintus Fabius and Publius Decius during the consular elections, declared, ‘These are great men of action, born for war; they have consular minds, uncouth in verbal conflict. Subtle, eloquent, learned minds are good but for Praetors, admin-istering justice in the City.’

Rhetoric flourished in Rome when their affairs were in their worst state and when they were shattered by the storms of civil war, just as a field left untamed bears the most flourishing weeds.

It would seem that polities which rely on a monarch have less use for it than the others：for that animal-stupidity and levity which are found in the masses, making them apt to be manipulated and swayed through the ears by those sweet harmonious sounds without succeeding in weighing the truth of anything by force of reason - such levity, I repeat, is not so readily found in one individual man; and it is easier to protect him by a good education and counsel from being impressed by that poison. No famous orator has ever been seen to come from Macedo-nia or from Persia.

What I have just said was prompted by my having talked with an Italian who served as chief steward to the late Cardinal Caraffa until his death. I got him to tell me about his job. He harangued me on the art of feeding with a professional gravity and demeanour as though he were explaining some important point of Theology. He listed differences of appetite：the appetite you have when you are hungry, the one you have after the second and third courses; what means there are of simply satis-fying it or of sometimes exciting it and stimulating it; how to govern the commonwealth of sauces, first in gen-eral then in particular, listing the qualities of every ingredient and its effects; the different green-stuffs in their season, the ones which must be served hot, the ones which must be served cold as well as the ways of decorating them and embellishing them to make them look even more appetizing. After all that he embarked upon how the service should be ordered, full of fine and weighty considerations：

nec minimo sane discrimine refert

Quo gestu lepores, et quo gallina secetur!

[For it is of no small importance to know how to carve a hare or a chicken!]

And all this was inflated with rich and magnificent words, the very ones we use to discuss the government of an empire. I was reminded of that man in the poem：

Hoc salsum est, hoc adustum est, hoc lautum est parum,

Illud recte; iterum sic memento; sedulo

Moneo quœ possum pro mea sapientia.

Postremo, tanquam in speculum, in patinas, Demea,

Inspicere jubeo, et moneo quid facto usus sit.

[‘This is too salty; this has been burned; this needs to be properly washed; this is excellent - remember that next time.’I advise them carefully as far as my wisdom allows; finally I tell them, Demea, to polish the dishes until they can see their faces in them as in a mirror. I tell them the lot.]

Even the Greeks after all highly praised the order and arrangement which were observed in the banquet which Paulus Aemilius threw for them on his return from Mace-donia; but I am not talking here of deeds but of words.

I cannot tell if others feel as I do, but when I hear our architects inflating their importance with big words such as pilasters, architraves, cornices, Corinthian style or Doric style, I cannot stop my thoughts from suddenly dwelling on the magic palaces of Apollidon：yet their deeds concern the wretched parts of my kitchen-door!

When you hear grammatical terms such as metonymy, metaphor and allegory do they not seem to refer to some rare, exotic tongue? Yet they are categories which apply to the chatter of your chambermaid.

It is a similar act of deception to use for our offices of state the same grandiloquent titles as the Romans did, even though they have no similarity of function and even less authority and power. Similar too - and a practice which will, in my judgement, bear witness one day to the singular ineptitude of our century - is our unworthily employing for anybody we like those glorious cognomens with which Antiquity honoured one or two great men every few hundred years. By universal acclaim Plato bore the name divine, and nobody thought to dispute it with him：now the Italians, who rightly boast of having in general more lively minds and saner discourse than other peoples of their time, have made a gift of it to Aretino, in whom （apart from a style of writing stuffed and sim-mering over with pointed sayings, ingenious it is true but fantastical and far-fetched, and apart from his eloquence - such as it is） I can see nothing beyond the common run of authors of his century, so far is he from even approach-ing that‘divinity’of the Ancients.

And the title Great we now attach to kings who have nothing beyond routine greatness.

To philosophize is to learn how to die

[Montaigne comes to terms with his melancholy, now somewhat played down. He remains preoccupied with that fear of death - fear that is of the often excruciating act of dying - which in older times seems to have been widespread and acute. His treat-ment is rhetorical but not impersonal. Montaigne is on the way to discovering admirable qualities in common men and women.

Cicero says that philosophizing is nothing other than getting ready to die. That is because study and contem-plation draw our souls somewhat outside ourselves, keeping them occupied away from the body, a state which both resembles death and which forms a kind of appren-ticeship for it; or perhaps it is because all the wisdom and argument in the world eventually come down to one con-clusion; which is to teach us not to be afraid of dying.

In truth, either reason is joking or her target must be our happiness; all the labour of reason must be to make us live well, and at our ease, as Holy Scripture says. All the opin-ions in the world reach the same point, that pleasure is our target even though they may get there by different means; otherwise we would throw them out immediately, for who would listen to anyone whose goal was to achieve for us pain and suffering?

In this case the disagreements between the schools of philosophy are a matter of words. ‘Transcurramus solertis-simas nugas.’ [Let us skip quickly through those most frivolous trivialities.] More stubbornness and prickliness are there than is appropriate for so dedicated a vocation, but then, no matter what role a man may assume, he always plays his own part within it.

Even in virtue our ultimate aim - no matter what they say - is pleasure. I enjoy bashing people’s ears with that word which runs so strongly counter to their minds. When pleasure is taken to mean the most profound delight and an exceeding happiness it is a better companion to virtue than anything else; and rightly so. Such pleasure is no less seriously pleasurable for being more lively, taut, robust and virile. We ought to have given virtue the more favour-able, noble and natural name of pleasure not （as we have done） a name derived from vis （vigour）.

There is that lower voluptuous pleasure which can only be said to have a disputed claim to the name not a priv-ileged right to it. I find it less pure of lets and hindrances than virtue. Apart from having a savour which is fleeting, fluid and perishable, it has its vigils, fasts and travails, its blood and its sweat; it also has its own peculiar sufferings, which are sharp in so many different ways and accom-panied by a satiety of such weight that it amounts to repentance.

Since we reckon that obstacles serve as a spur to that pleasure and as seasoning to its sweetness （on the grounds that in Nature contraries are enhanced by their contraries） we are quite wrong to say when we turn to virtue that identical obstacles and difficulties overwhelm her, making her austere and inaccessible, whereas （much more appro-priately than for voluptuous pleasure） they ennoble, sharpen and enhance that holy, perfect pleasure which virtue procures for us. A man is quite unworthy of an acquaintance with virtue who weighs her fruit against the price she exacts; he knows neither her graces nor her ways. Those who proceed to teach us that the questing after virtue is rugged and wearisome whereas it is delight-ful to possess her can only mean that she always lacks delight. （For what human means have ever brought any-one to the joy of possessing her?） Even the most perfect of men have been satisfied with aspiring to her - not possessing her but drawing near to her. The contention is wrong, seeing that in every pleasure known to Man the very pursuit of it is pleasurable：the undertaking savours of the quality of the object it has in view; it effectively constitutes a large proportion of it and is consubstantial with it. There is a happiness and blessedness radiating from virtue; they fill all that appertains to her and every approach to her, from the first way in to the very last barrier.

Now one of virtue’s main gifts is a contempt for death, which is the means of furnishing our life with easy tranquillity, of giving us a pure and friendly taste for it; without it every other pleasure is snuffed out. That is why all rules meet and concur in this one clause. It is true that they all lead us by common accord to despise pain, pov-erty and the other misfortunes to which human lives are subject, but they do not do so with the same care. That is partly because such misfortunes are not inevit-able. （Most of Mankind spend their lives without tasting poverty; some without even experiencing pain or sick-ness, like Xenophilus the musician, who lived in good health to a hundred and six.） It is also because, if the worse comes to worse, we can sheer off the bung of our misfortunes whenever we like：death can end them. But, as for death itself, that is inevitable.

Omnes eodem cogimur, omnium

Versatur urna, serius ocius

Sors exitura et nos in œter-

Num exitium impositura cymbœ.

[All of our lots are shaken about in the Urn, destined sooner or later to be cast forth, placing us in everlasting exile via Charon’s boat.]

And so if death makes us afraid, that is a subject of con-tinual torment which nothing can assuage. There is no place where death cannot find us - even if we constantly twist our heads about in all directions as in a suspect land：‘Quae quasi saxum Tantalo semper impendet.’ [It is like the rock for ever hanging over the head of Tantalus.]Our assizes often send prisoners to be executed at the scene of their crimes. On the way there, take them past fair mansions and ply them with good cheer as much as you like -

...non Siculœ dapes

Dulcem elaborabunt saporem,

Non avium cytharœque cantus

Somnum reducent -

[even Sicilian banquets produce no sweet savours; not even the music of birdsong nor of lyre can bring back sleep] -

do you think they can enjoy it or that having the final purpose of their journey ever before their eyes will not spoil their taste for such entertainment?

Audit iter, numeratque dies, spacioque viarum

Metitur vitam, torquetur peste futura

[He inquires about the way; he counts the days; the length of his life is the length of those roads. He is tortured by future anguish.]

The end of our course is death. It is the objective neces-sarily within our sights. If death frightens us how can we go one step forward without anguish? For ordinary people the remedy is not to think about it; but what brutish insensitivity can produce so gross a blindness? They lead the donkey by the tail：

Qui capite ipse suo instituit vestigia retro.

[They walk forward with their heads turned backwards.]

No wonder that they often get caught in a trap. You can frighten such people simply by mentioning death（most of them cross themselves as when the Devil is named）; and since it is mentioned in wills, never expect them to draw one up before the doctor has pronounced the death-sentence. And then, in the midst of pain and terror, God only knows what shape their good judgement kneads it into!

（That syllable‘death’struck Roman ears too roughly; the very word was thought to bring ill-luck, so they learned to soften and dilute it with periphrases. Instead of saying He is dead they said He has ceased to live or He has lived. They found consolation in living, even in a past tense! Whence our‘late’ （feu） So-and-So：‘he was’So-and-So.）

Perhaps it is a case of, ‘Repayment delayed means money in hand’, as they say; I was born between eleven and noon on the last day of February, one thousand five hundred and thirty-three （as we date things nowadays, beginning the year in January）; it is exactly a fortnight since I became thirty-nine：‘I ought to live at least as long again; meanwhile it would be mad to think of something so far off’. - Yes, but all leave life in the same circum-stances, young and old alike. Everybody goes out as though he had just come in. Moreover, however decrepit a man may be, he thinks he still has another twenty years to go in the body, so long as he has Methuselah ahead of him. Silly fool, you! Where your life is concerned, who has decided the term? You are relying on doctors’tales; look at facts and experience instead. As things usually go, you have been living for some time now by favour extraordinary. You have already exceeded the usual term of life; to prove it, just count how many more of your acquaintances have died younger than you are compared with those who have reached your age. Just make a list of people who have ennobled their lives by fame：I wager that we shall find more who died before thirty-five than after. It is full of reason and piety to take as our example the manhood of Jesus Christ：his life ended at thirty-three. The same term applies to Alexander, the greatest man who was simply man.

Death can surprise us in so many ways：

Quid quisque vitet, nunquam homini satis

Cautum est in horas.

[No man knows what dangers he should avoid from one hour to another.]

Leaving aside fevers and pleurisies, who would ever have thought that a Duke of Brittany was to be crushed to death in a crowd, as one was during the state entry into Lyons of Pope Clement, who came from my part of the world! Have you not seen one of our kings killed at sport? And was not one of his ancestors killed by a bump from a pig? Aeschylus was warned against a falling house; he was always on the alert, but in vain：he was killed by the shell of a tortoise which slipped from the talons of an eagle in flight. Another choked to death on a pip from a grape; an Emperor died from a scratch when combing his hair; Aemilius Lepidus, from knocking his foot on his own doorstep; Aufidius from bumping into a door of his Council chamber. Those who died between a woman’s thighs include Cornelius Gallus, a praetor; Tigillinus, a captain of the Roman Guard; Ludovico, the son of Guy di Gonzaga, the Marquis of Mantua; and - providing even worse examples - Speucippus the Platonic philoso-pher, and one of our Popes.

Then there was that wretched judge Bebius; he was just granting a week’s extra time to a litigant when he died of a seizure：his own time had run out. Caius Julius, a doc-tor, was putting ointment on the eyes of a patient when death closed his. And if I may include a personal example, Captain Saint-Martin, my brother, died at the age of twenty-three while playing tennis; he was felled by a blow from a tennis-ball just above the right ear. There was no sign of bruising or of a wound. He did not even sit down or take a rest; yet five or six hours later he was dead from an apoplexy caused by that blow.

When there pass before our eyes examples such as these, so frequent and so ordinary, how can we ever rid ourselves of thoughts of death or stop imagining that death has us by the scruff of the neck at every moment?

You might say：‘But what does it matter how you do it, so long as you avoid pain?’I agree with that. If there were any way at all of sheltering from Death’s blows - even by crawling under the skin of a calf - I am not the man to recoil from it. It is enough for me to spend my time con-tentedly. I deal myself the best hand I can, and then accept it. It can be as inglorious or as unexemplary as you please：

prœtulerim delirus inersque videri,

Dum mea delectent mala me, vel denique fallant,

Quam sapere et ringi.

[I would rather be delirious or a dullard if my faults pleased me, or at least deceived me, rather than to be wise and snarling.]

But it is madness to think you can succeed that way. They come and they go and they trot and they dance：and never a word about death. All well and good. Yet when death does come - to them, their wives, their children, their friends - catching them unawares and unprepared, then what storms of passion overwhelm them, what cries, what fury, what despair! Have you ever seen anything brought so low, anything so changed, so confused?

We must start providing for it earlier. Even if such brutish indifference could find lodgings in the head of an intelligent man （which seems quite impossible to me） it sells its wares too dearly. If death were an enemy which could be avoided I would counsel borrowing the arms of cowardice. But it cannot be done. Death can catch you just as easily as a coward on the run or as an honourable man：

Nempe et fugacem persequitur virum,

Nec parcit imbellis juventœ

Poplitibus, timidoque tergo;

[It hounds the man who runs away, and it does not spare the legs fearful backs of unwarlike youth;]

no tempered steel can protect your shoulders;

Ille licet ferro cautus se condat œre,

Mors tamen inclusum protrahet inde caput;

[No use a man hiding prudently behind iron or brass：Death will know how to make him stick out his cowering head;]

we must learn to stand firm and to fight it.

To begin depriving death of its greatest advantage over us, let us adopt a way clean contrary to that common one; let us deprive death of its strangeness; let us frequent it, let us get used to it; let us have nothing more often in mind than death. At every instant let us evoke it in our imagination under all its aspects. Whenever a horse stum-bles, a tile falls or a pin pricks however slightly, let us at once chew over this thought：‘Supposing that was death itself?’ With that, let us brace ourselves and make an effort. In the midst of joy and feasting let our refrain be one which recalls our human condition. Let us never be carried away by pleasure so strongly that we fail to recall occasionally how many are the ways in which that joy of ours is subject to death or how many are the fashions in which death threatens to snatch it away. That is what the Egyptians did：in the midst of all their banquets and good cheer they would bring in a mummified corpse to serve as a warning to the guests：

Omnem crede diem tibi diluxisse supremum.

Grata superveniet, quœ non sperabitur hora.

[Believe that each day was the last to shine on you. If it comes, any unexpected hour will be welcome indeed.]

We do not know where death awaits us：so let us wait for it everywhere. To practise death is to practise freedom. A man who has learned how to die has unlearned how to be a slave. Knowing how to die gives us freedom from subjection and constraint. Life has no evil for him who has thoroughly understood that loss of life is not an evil. Paulus Aemilius was sent a messenger by that wretched King of Macedonia who was his prisoner, begging not to be led in his triumphant procession. He replied：‘Let him beg that favour from himself.’

It is true that, in all things, if Nature does not lend a hand art and industry do not progress very far. I myself am not so much melancholic as an idle dreamer：from the outset there was no topic I ever concerned myself with more than with thoughts about death - even in the most licentious period of my life.

Jucundum cum aetas florida ver ageret.

[When my blossoming youth rejoiced in spring.]

Among the games and the courting many thought I was standing apart chewing over some jealousy or the uncer-tainty of my aspirations：meanwhile I was reflecting on someone or other who, on leaving festivities just like these, had been surprised by a burning fever and his end, with his head full of idleness, love and merriment - just like me; and the same could be dogging me now：

Jam fuerit, nec post unquam revocare licebit.

[The present will soon be the past, never to be recalled.]

Thoughts such as these did not furrow my brow any more than others did. At first it does seem impossible not to feel the sting of such ideas, but if you keep handling them and running through them you eventually tame them. No doubt about that. Otherwise I would, for my part, be in continual terror and frenzy：for no man ever had less confidence than I did that he would go on living; and no man ever counted less on his life proving long. Up till now I have enjoyed robust good health almost uninterruptedly：yet that never extends my hopes for life any more than sickness shortens them. Every moment it seems to me that I am running away from myself. And I ceaselessly chant the refrain, ‘Anything you can do another day can be done now.’

In truth risks and dangers do little or nothing to bring us nearer to death. If we think of all the millions of threats which remain hanging over us, apart from the one which happens to appear most menacing just now, we shall real-ize that death is equally near when we are vigorous or feverish, at sea or at home, in battle or in repose. ‘Nemo altero fragilior est：nemo in crastinam sui certior.’ [No man is frailer than another：no man more certain of the morrow.]

If I have only one hour’s work to do before I die, I am never sure I have time enough to finish it. The other day someone was going through my notebooks and found a declaration about something I wanted done after my death. I told him straight that, though I was hale and healthy and but a league away from my house, I had hastened to jot it down because I had not been absolutely certain of getting back home. Being a man who broods over his thoughts and stores them up inside him, I am always just about as ready as I can be：when death does suddenly appear, it will bear no new warning for me. As far as we possibly can we must always have our boots on, ready to go; above all we should take care to have no outstanding business with anyone else.

Quid brevi fortes jaculamur œvo

Multa?

[Why, in so brief a span do we find strength to make so many projects?]

We shall have enough to do then without adding to it.

One man complains less of death itself than of its cut-ting short the course of a fine victory; another, that he has to depart before marrying off his daughter or arrang-ing the education of his children; one laments the company of his wife; another, of his son; as though they were the principal attributes of his being.

I am now ready to leave, thank God, whenever He pleases, regretting nothing except life itself - if its loss should happen to weigh heavy on me. I am untying all the knots. I have already half-said my adieus to everyone but myself. No man has ever prepared to leave the world more simply nor more fully than I have. No one has more completely let go of everything than I try to do.

Miser o miser, aiunt, omnia ademit

Una dies infesta mihi tot prœmia vitœ.

[‘I am wretched, so wretched,’ they say：‘One dreadful day has stripped me of all life’s rewards.’]

And the builder says：

Manent opera interrupta, minaeque

Murorum ingentes.

[My work remains unfinished; huge walls may fall down.]

We ought not to plan anything on so large a scale - at least, not if we are to get all worked up if we cannot see it through to the end.

We are born for action：

Cum moriar, medium solvare inter opus.

[When I die, may I be in the midst of my work.]

I want us to be doing things, prolonging life’s duties as much as we can; I want Death to find me planting my cabbages, neither worrying about it nor the unfinished gardening. I once saw a man die who, right to the last, kept lamenting that destiny had cut the thread of the history he was writing when he had only got up to our fifteenth or sixteenth king!

Illud in his rebus non addunt, nec tibi earum

Jam desiderium rerum super insidet una!

[They never add, that desire for such things does not linger on in your remains!]

We must throw off such humours; they are harmful and vulgar.

Our graveyards have been planted next to churches, says Lycurgus, so that women, children and lesser folk should grow accustomed to seeing a dead man without feeling terror, and so that this continual spectacle of bones, tombs and funerals should remind us of our human condition：

Quin etiam exhilarare viris convivia cœde

Mos olim, et miscere epulis spectacula dira

Certantum ferro, sœpe et super ipsa cadentum

Pocula respersis non parco sanguine mensis;

[It was once the custom, moreover, to enliven feasts with human slaughter and to entertain guests with the cruel sight of gladiators fighting：they often fell among the goblets, flooding the tables with their blood;]

so too, after their festivities the Egyptians used to display before their guests a huge portrait of death, held up by a man crying, ‘Drink and be merry：once dead you will look like this’; similarly, I have adopted the practice of always having death not only in my mind but on my lips. There is nothing I inquire about more readily than how men have died：what did they say? How did they look? What expression did they have? There are no passages in the history books which I note more attentively. That I have a particular liking for such matters is shown by the examples with which I stuff my book. If I were a scribbler I would produce a compendium with commentaries of the various ways men have died. （Anyone who taught men how to die would teach them how to live.） Dicearchus did write a book with some such title, but for another and less useful purpose.

People will tell me that the reality of death so far exceeds the thought that when we actually get there all our fine fencing amounts to nothing. Let them say so：there is no doubt whatsoever that meditating on it before-hand confers great advantages. Anyway, is it nothing to get even that far without faltering or feverish agitation?

But there is more to it than that：Nature herself lends us a hand and gives us courage. If our death is violent and short we have no time to feel afraid：if it be otherwise, I have noticed that as an illness gets more and more hold on me I naturally slip into a kind of contempt for life. I find that a determination to die is harder to digest when I am in good health than when I am feverish, especially since I no longer hold so firmly to the pleasures of life once I begin to lose the use and enjoyment of them, and can look on death with a far less terrified gaze. That leads me to hope that the further I get from good health and the nearer I approach to death the more easily I will come to terms with exchanging one for the other. Just as I have in several other matters assayed the truth of Caesar’s assertion that things often look bigger from afar than close to, I have also found that I was much more ter-rified of illness when I was well than when I felt ill. Being in a happy state, all pleasure and vigour, leads me to get the other state quite out of proportion, so that I men-tally increase all its discomforts by half and imagine them heavier than they prove to be when I have to bear them.

I hope that the same will apply to me when I die. It is normal to experience change and decay：let us note how Nature robs us of our sense of loss and decline. What does an old man still retain of his youthful vigour and of his own past life?

Heu senibus vitae portio quanta manet.

[Alas, what little of life’s portion remains with the aged.]

When a soldier of Caesar’s guard, broken and worn out, came up to him in the street and begged leave to kill himself, Caesar looked at his decrepit bearing and said with a smile：‘So you think you are still alive, then?’

If any of us were to be plunged into old age all of a sudden I do not think that the change would be bearable. But, almost imperceptibly, Nature leads us by the hand down a gentle slope; little by little, step by step, she engulfs us in that pitiful state and breaks us in, so that we feel no jolt when youth dies in us, although in essence and in truth that is a harsher death than the total extinc-tion of a languishing life as old age dies. For it is not so grievous a leap from a wretched existence to non-existence as it is from a sweet existence in full bloom to one full of travail and pain.

When our bodies are bent and stooping low they have less strength for supporting burdens. So too for our souls：we must therefore educate and train them for their encounter with that adversary, death; for the soul can find no rest while she remains afraid of him. But once she does find assurance she can boast that it is impossible for anx-iety, anguish, fear or even the slightest dissatisfaction to dwell within her. And that almost surpasses our human condition.

Non vultus instantis tyranni

Mente quatit solida, neque Auster

Dux inquieti turbidus Adriœ,

Nec fulminantis magna Jovis manus.

[Nothing can shake such firmness：neither the threatening face of a tyrant, nor the South Wind（that tempestuous Master of the Stormy Adriatic）nor even the mighty hand of thundering Jove.]

She has made herself Mistress of her passions and her lusts, Mistress of destitution, shame, poverty and of all other injuries of Fortune. Let any of us who can gain such a superiority do so：for here is that true and sovereign freedom which enables us to cock a snook at force and injustice and to laugh at manacles and prisons：

in manicis, et

Compedibus, sœvo te sub custode tenebo.

Ipse Deus simul atque volam, me solvet：opinor,

Hoc sentit, moriar. Mors ultima linea rerum est.

[‘I will shackle your hands and feet and keep you under a cruel gaoler.’ - ‘God himself will set me free as soon as I ask him to.’（He means, I think, ‘I will die’：for death is the last line of all.）]

Our religion has never had a surer human foundation than contempt for life; rational argument （though not it alone） summons us to such contempt：for why should we fear to lose something which, once lost, cannot be regretted? And since we are threatened by so many kinds of death is it not worse to fear them all than to bear one? Death is inevitable：does it matter when it comes? When Socrates was told that the Thirty Tyrants had condemned him to death, he retorted, ‘And nature, them！’

How absurd to anguish over our passing into freedom from all anguish. Just as our birth was the birth of all things for us, so our death will be the death of them all. That is why it is equally mad to weep because we shall not be alive a hundred years from now and to weep because we were not alive a hundred years ago. Death is the origin of another life. We wept like this and it cost us just as dear when we entered into this life, similarly stripping off our former veil as we did so. Nothing can be grievous which occurs but once; is it reasonable to fear for so long a time something which lasts so short a time? Living a long life or a short life are made all one by death：long and short do not apply to that which is no more. Aristotle says that there are tiny creatures on the river Hypanis whose life lasts one single day：those which die at eight in the morning die in youth; those which die at five in the evening die of senility. Which of us would not laugh if so momentary a span counted as happiness or unhappiness? Yet if we compare our own span against eternity or even against the span of mountains, rivers, stars, trees or, indeed, of some animals, then saying shorter or longer becomes equally ridiculous.

Nature drives us that way, too：‘Leave this world,’ she says, ‘just as you entered it. That same journey from death to life, which you once made without suffering or fear, make it again from life to death. Your death is a part of the order of the universe; it is a part of the life of the world：

inter se mortales mutua vivunt...

Et quasi cursores vitaï lampada tradunt.

[Mortal creatures live lives dependent on each other; like runners in a relay they pass on the torch of life.]

Shall I change, just for you, this beautiful interwoven structure! Death is one of the attributes you were created with; death is a part of you; you are running away from yourself; this being which you enjoy is equally divided between death and life. From the day you were born your path leads to death as well as life：

Prima, quae vitam dedit, hora, carpsit.

[Our first hour gave us life and began to devour it.]

Nascentes morimur, finisque ab origine pendet.

[As we are born we die; the end of our life is attached to its beginning.]

All that you live, you have stolen from life; you live at her expense. Your life’s continual task is to build your death. You are in death while you are in life：when you are no more in life you are after death. Or if you prefer it thus：after life you are dead, but during life you are dying：and death touches the dying more harshly than the dead, in more lively a fashion and more essentially.

‘If you have profited from life, you have had your fill; go away satisfied：

Cur non ut plenus vitae conviva recedis?

[Why not withdraw from life like a guest replete?]

But if you have never learned how to use life, if life is useless to you, what does it matter if you have lost it? What do you still want it for?

Cur amplius addere quœris

Rursum quod pereat male, et ingratum occidat omne?

[Why seek to add more, just to lose it again, wretchedly, without joy?]

Life itself is neither a good nor an evil：life is where good or evil find a place, depending on how you make it for them.

‘If you have lived one day, you have seen everything. One day equals all days. There is no other light, no other night. The Sun, Moon and Stars, disposed just as they are now, were enjoyed by your grandsires and will enter-tain your great-grandchildren：

Non alium videre patres：aliumve nepotes

Aspicient.

[Your fathers saw none other：none other shall your progeny discern.]

And at the worst estimate the division and variety of all the acts of my play are complete in one year. If you have observed the vicissitude of my four seasons you know they embrace the childhood, youth, manhood and old age of the World. Its play is done. It knows no other trick but to start all over again. Always it will be the same.

Versamur ibidem, atque insumus usque;

[We turn in the same circle, for ever;]

Atque in se sua per vestigia volvitur annus.

[And the year rolls on again through its own traces.]

I have not the slightest intention of creating new pastimes for you.

Nam tibi prœterea quod machiner, inveniamque

Quod placeat, nihil est, eadem sunt omnia semper.

[For there is nothing else I can make or discover to please you：all things are the same for ever.]

Make way for others as others did for you. The first part of equity is equality. Who can complain of being included when all are included?

‘It is no good going on living：it will in no wise shorten the time you will stay dead. It is all for nothing：you will be just as long in that state which you fear as though you had died at the breast;

licet, quod vis, vivendo vincere secla,

Mors œterna tamen nihilominus illa manebit.

[Triumph over time and live as long as you please：death eternal will still be waiting for you.]

‘And yet I shall arrange that you have no unhappiness：

In vera nescis nullum fore morte alium te,

Qui possit vivus tibi te lugere peremptum,

Stansque jacentem.

[Do you not know that in real death there will be no second You, living to lament your death and standing by your corpse.]

“You”will not desire the life which now you so much lament.

Nec sibi enim quisquam tum se vitamque requirit...

Nec desiderium nostri nos afficit ullum.

[Then no one worries about his life or his self; ...we feel no yearning for our own being.]

Death is less to be feared than nothing - if there be any-thing less than nothing：

multo mortem minus ad nos esse putandum

Si minus esse potest quam quod nihil esse videmus.

[We should think death to be less - if anything is‘less’than what we can see to be nothing at all.]

‘Death does not concern you, dead or alive; alive, because you are：dead, because you are no more.

‘No one dies before his time; the time you leave behind you is no more yours than the time which passed before you were born; and does not concern you either：

Respice enim quam nil ad nos ante acta vetustas

Temporis œterní fuerit.

[Look back and see that the aeons of eternity before we were born have been nothing to us.]

‘Wherever your life ends, there all of it ends. The usefulness of living lies not in duration but in what you make of it. Some have lived long and lived little. See to it while you are still here. Whether you have lived enough depends not on a count of years but on your will.

‘Do you think you will never arrive whither you are ceaselessly heading? Yet every road has its end. And, if it is a relief to have company, is not the whole world pro-ceeding at the same pace as you are?

Omnia te vita perfuncta sequentur.

[All things will follow you when their life is done.]

Does not everything move with the same motion as you do? Is there anything which is not growing old with you? At this same instant that you die hundreds of men, of beasts and of other creatures are dying too.

Nam nox nulla diem, neque noctem aurora sequuta est,

Qua non audierit mistos vagitibus ægris

Ploratus, mortis comites et funeris atri.

[No night has ever followed day, no dawn has ever followed night, without hearing, interspersed among the wails of infants, the cries of pain attending death and sombre funerals.]

‘Why do you pull back when retreat is impossible? You have seen cases enough where men were lucky to die, avoiding great misfortunes by doing so：but have you ever seen anyone for whom death turned out badly? And it is very simple-minded of you to condemn something which you have never experienced either yourself or through another. Why do you complain of me or of Destiny? Do we do you wrong? Should you govern us or should we govern you? You may not have finished your stint but you have finished your life. A small man is no less whole than a tall one. Neither men nor their lives are measured by the yard. Chiron refused immortality when he was told of its characteristics by his father Saturn, the god of time and of duration.

‘Truly imagine how much less bearable for Man, and how much more painful, would be a life which lasted for ever rather than the life which I have given you. If you did not have death you would curse me, for ever, for depriving you of it.

‘Seeing what advantages death holds I have deliberately mixed a little anguish into it to stop you from embracing it too avidly or too injudiciously. To lodge you in that moderation which I require of you, neither fleeing from life nor yet fleeing from death, I have tempered them both between the bitter and the sweet.

‘I taught Thales, the foremost of your Sages, that living and dying are things indifferent. So, when asked “why he did not go and die then,” he very wisely replied：“Because it is indifferent.”

‘Water, Earth, Air and Fire and the other parts of this my edifice are no more instrumental to your life than to your death. Why are you afraid of your last day? It brings you no closer to your death than any other did. The last step does not make you tired：it shows that you are tired. All days lead to death：the last one gets there.’

Those are the good counsels of Nature, our Mother.

I have often wondered why the face of death, seen in ourselves or in other men, appears incomparably less terrifying to us in war than in our own homes - otherwise armies would consist of doctors and cry-babies - and why, since death is ever the same, there is always more stead-fastness among village-folk and the lower orders than among all the rest. I truly believe that what frightens us more than death itself are those terrifying grimaces and preparations with which we surround it - a brand new way of life：mothers, wives and children weeping; visits from people stunned and beside themselves with grief; the presence of a crowd of servants, pale and tear-stained; a bedchamber without daylight; candles lighted; our bedside besieged by doctors and preachers; in short, all about us is horror and terror. We are under the ground, buried in our graves already! Children are frightened of their very friends when they see them masked. So are we. We must rip the masks off things as well as off people. Once we have done that we shall find underneath only that same death which a valet and a chambermaid got through recently, without being afraid. Blessed the death which leaves no time for preparing such gatherings of mourners.

我喜欢看它折叠里程

❧[5]

我喜欢看它折叠里程

并舔过山谷，

然后停下来在水槽那儿补给；

之后，令人惊愕，绕过

一叠群山，

盛气凌人，窥探

路边的棚屋；

然后修剪一副残骸

好和它的半边毛皮合体，再蜿蜒穿过，[6]

用可怕，呜呜的音节

一路抱怨；

之后追赶自己跑下山

像半尼其[7]一样嘶鸣；

然后，像一颗星星般准时，

停在它自己的马厩门口

温顺而全能——

[5]这首诗是写火车的。19世纪时，人们对火车有许多好奇和想象。诗文中常见，绘画、摄影也一样。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明之外，均为译者注。）

[6]这句是关于火车运动对风景裁剪的形象描述。火车行过，穿过风景，如同撕裂一个完整的身体，同时遮挡了一半风景。“quarry”是被捕获的鹿的一部分骨架，扔给猎狗吃的。“pare”是剥皮修剪。诗中第一节让人联想到猫儿、马儿，而到第二节，对火车代表的工业革命这个庞然大物，心理上感觉可怕，还不明所以，狄金森对感受到的它潜在的全能和毁灭性做了隐喻。这两句的力量，体现了一个诗人捕捉集体心理、预言时代的能力。文德勒谈这首诗，问诗中可能暗示了哪些动物，其实它既暗示某些动物，又暗示了上帝，科技来临相当于上帝重现。狄金森的父亲曾致力于把火车引入艾摩斯特市，火车站后来就设在离狄金森家不远的地方。文德勒说诗中的火车是狄金森自己的戏仿，表面上看知书达礼，温文尔雅，实际上却像那个庞大的机器一般，充满兽性和全能。

[7]半尼其，出自《马可福音》3：17：“还有西庇太的儿子雅各和雅各的兄弟约翰，又给这两个人起名叫半尼其，就是雷子的意思。”

没能把我们全都触摸的米达斯

❧

没能把我们全都触摸的米达斯[9]，

摸过的东西中的一个，

是那倾心相诉的浪子，

乐而无忧的金莺。

这般沉醉，他用

戏谑的占卜[10]否认它；

这般炫目，我们错把他

当成一座降落的藏宝窟[11]。

花言巧语的家伙，骗子，

贪图享欲的人，一个贼，——

偶尔也是一个演说家，

销魂首领；

果园的耶稣，

一边欺骗一边诱走

全部的玫瑰精油

为他的潜逃之需。

金丝雀的光芒，

鸟中的流星，

谣曲和歌手

露天表演般的华丽道别。

我从没想过伊阿宋

是为了寻求什么金羊毛；

可那时我是个乡下人，

想法只为图个安宁。

可要是真有个伊阿宋，

传统容忍我

看苹果树上

他失去的报偿。

[9]米达斯，希腊神话中弗里吉亚国王，“点石成金”的出处来自他的故事。他解救了酒神狄俄尼索斯的老师西勒诺斯，酒神允他实现他的愿望，他希望触手所碰一切成金。愿望实现，最终他的女儿也被他变成了一座金子雕像。他悔恨不已，再求酒神解救。酒神让他去帕克托罗斯河洗澡，洗去了点石成金的魔力。米达斯后舍弃王位，追随酒神。“米达斯的触摸”因此成为一个隐喻。

[10]“占卜”（divine），参见《创世记》44：15：约瑟对他们说：你们做的是什么事呢？你们岂不知像我这样的人必能占卜吗？

[11]“藏宝窟”（mine），一词双关，既是“藏宝库”，也暗指“我的宝贝”“我的珍宝”。

狄金森诗集版本概要

狄金森生前的诗歌作品主要在朋友和家人之间流传。在1850年至1866年间，共有10首诗由她的朋友交给报纸匿名发表。1878年，诗人海伦·亨特·杰克逊（Helen Hunt Jackson）哄诱狄金森在《诗人的面具》（A Masque of Poets）中发表了一些诗歌，这是一本作者完全匿名的诗集。

1886年狄金森去世后，她的妹妹拉维尼亚发现了数百首之前狄金森从未示人的诗歌手稿。狄金森总共留下了大约1800首诗歌。拉维尼亚认为狄金森的诗歌理应得到出版。在她的努力下，梅布尔·卢米斯·托德（Mabel Loomis Todd）和托马斯·温特沃斯·希金森（Thomas Wentworth Higginson）于1890年编辑出版了第一本狄金森诗集《狄金森诗歌》（Poems of Emily Dickinson）。两位编辑对狄金森的诗歌按照当时的诗歌阅读传统和他们自己对诗歌的认识做了大量修改，包括规范标点、增加标题、按照韵律需要修改用词等等。第一版诗集取得了很大成功，一年后，他们又出版了《狄金森诗歌第二卷》（Poems of Emily Dickinson, Second Series）。其后，托德又分别于1894年编辑出版了《狄金森书信集》（Dickinson’s Letters）和1896年的《狄金森诗歌第三卷》（Poems of Emily Dickinson, Third Series）。

狄金森的外甥女玛莎·狄金森·比安奇（Martha Dickinson Bianchi）不赞同托德和希金森对狄金森诗歌的过度编辑，根据她从拉维尼亚和狄金森的嫂嫂苏珊·狄金森（Susan Dickinson）那儿继承的狄金森手稿，先后编辑出版了六卷狄金森诗歌。她采取了与托德截然不同的编辑方式，不改变原诗的韵律，不添加标题。1945年，托德的女儿完成了托德生前未完成的对所保留的全部狄金森手稿的编辑，出版了《旋律霹雳》（Bolts of Melody）。这样，在几个不同的版本中，狄金森的大多数诗歌均得以出版，但是并没有一个完整收录所有诗歌的选集。

1955年托马斯·H.约翰逊（Thomas H. Johnson）的《狄金森诗歌》出版。约翰逊的版本基本完整收录了狄金森的诗歌。他依据狄金森手稿，忠实于狄金森的原文。此外，他对狄金森的诗歌按照年代进行了排列。这是一个划时代的文学事件，对诗歌界和读者重新认识评价狄金森起到了决定性作用。

拉尔夫·W.富兰克林在约翰逊的成就之上，进一步关注手稿和诗人的书写过程。1981年，他出版了带有狄金森手稿复印件的版本《狄金森手稿集》（The Manuscript Books of Emily Dickinson）。之后，1998年他又出版了《狄金森诗歌全集》（The Poems of Emily Dickinson）。2016年克蕾斯坦纳·米勒（Cristanne Miller）编辑出版了一个全新版本《狄金森诗歌：如她所保留》（Emily Dickinson’s Poems：As She Preserved Them），声称最忠实地保留了狄金森诗歌原作的状态。

2016年重印的《企鹅经典：小黑书》系列中的这本狄金森诗选，是1933年马丁·塞克尔（Martin Secker）从玛莎·狄金森·比安奇1924年编选出版的《狄金森诗全集》（The Complete Poems of Emily Dickinson）中摘选的。这个版本目前已经非常少见了。自从1955年约翰逊版本出版以来，通行的英文版本和各种翻译版本都是以约翰逊、富兰克林等人的版本为基础编辑翻译的。这个早期版本的再版，对读者和研究者了解早期狄金森诗歌出版和认知状况非常有益，可以和大家熟悉的通行版本对照阅读。

周琰

2018年7月

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

来呀，我脸面黝黑的孩子们，

排好队形，准备好你们的武器，

手枪带上了吗？锋利的斧子带上了吗？

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

因为我们不能在这里徘徊，

我们必须前进，亲爱的，我们必须一马当先，

我们是年轻力壮的民族，别的民族全依靠我们，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

啊，你们青年，西部的青年，

如此性急、充满活力，充满男儿的骄傲和友情，

我清楚看见了你们，西部的青年，看见你们大步当先，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

年长的民族止步了吗？

他们在大洋彼岸暮气沉沉，不再学习了吗？

我们来扛起这永恒的使命、责任和课业吧，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

我们将过去的一切抛在身后，

一个更新、更强的世界，多种多样的世界，豁然开朗，

我们抓住这鲜活健朗的世界，劳动和行进的世界，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

我们的分遣队源源不断进发，

走下悬崖，穿过关隘，攀上陡峭的山岭，

我们在未知的道路中征服、占据、冒险、勇闯，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

我们砍倒原始的森林，

我们截停江河的流水，我们摇动大地，钻探内里，

我们测量广阔的原野，我们在处女地垦荒，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

我们是科罗拉多的男人，

从巨大的山峰，从庞大的齿形山脉和高原，

从矿井和沟壑，从狩猎的小径上，我们来了，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

从内布拉斯加来，从阿肯色来，

我们是内陆中部的人种，从密苏里来，与大陆血脉相连，

伙伴们扣紧彼此的手，所有的南方人，所有的北方人，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

啊，不可阻挡，不知停歇的民族！

啊，大家都可爱！对大家的柔情令我胸口作痛！

啊，我伤怀而又雀跃，我欣喜若狂地爱着大家，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

举起那伟大的母亲般的女主人，

高高地摇动着娇巧的女主人，比一切灿烂如星的女主人都高，（你们全都低下头吧，）

举起有獠牙并且好战的女主人，严峻、冷漠、武装的女主人，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！[6]

看，我的孩子们，勇敢的孩子们，

看在我们后方的蜂拥人群的分儿上，我们决不能退让或动摇，

以往世代的数以百万的幽灵在我们身后皱眉催促，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

前进又前进，紧簇的队伍，

永远有增补，死者的位置被迅速填充，

穿越战斗，穿越战败，依然前行而永不停止，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

啊，在前进中死去！

我们当中有人委顿而死吗？时候到了吗？

那么我们在行进中死去正当其时，缺口会迅速填补！

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

世界上所有的脉搏，

各就各位地以西部运动的拍子，为我们跳动，

有单独有联合，稳稳地移向前方，全为我们，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

生活中复杂多变的盛会，

所有的形态和展览，所有干活的工人，

所有的水手和陆上的人，所有的主人和奴隶，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

所有不幸的沉默的恋人，

所有在监狱坐牢的人，所有的义人和恶人，

所有欢喜的人，所有哀愁的人，所有活着的人，所有垂死的人，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

我也跟我的灵魂和肉体，

组成好奇的三者，我们在路途上跋涉、游荡，

穿过死荫之地的这些海岸，幽灵们紧紧相随，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

看，那迅疾滚动的星球！

看，它四周的兄弟星球，所有一簇簇的恒星和行星，

所有灿烂的白昼，所有多梦的神秘之夜，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

这一切关乎我们，和我们同在，

它都是为了初始而必要的劳作，后继者尚在胚胎中等待，

我们这今日向前的队伍，我们开辟着行进的道路，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

你们啊，西部的女儿！

你们啊，青春的和年长的女儿！你们啊，母亲们和妻子们！

你们千万不要失散，在我们的队伍里你们团结向前吧，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

潜伏在大草原上的歌手！

（别的大陆上裹着尸衣的诗人呀，你们已完成工作，可以歇息了，）

很快我会听见你们来临的婉转歌喉，很快你们会起来跟我们同行，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

不是为了甜美的娱乐，

不是靠枕和软鞋，不是宁静的日子和学者的生活，

不是安全乏味的财富，寡淡的享受对我们无用，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

贪嘴的宴饮者总是在宴饮？

肥胖的沉睡者总是在睡觉？他们锁门上闩了吗？

我们的餐食粗糙如故，毯子铺地而眠，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

夜幕降临了吗？

近来的路是否太过辛苦？我们是否气馁地停下过，在路途上垂头打盹儿？

但是我让你们在小径上休息短短的一小时，放空身心，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

直到随着号角的吹响，

黎明远远地发出呼唤—听！我听见它嘹亮清楚的呼声，

快呀！赶到军队的前头！—快呀！冲上你们的位置，

开拓者！啊，开拓者！

给你

不管你是谁，我只怕你行走的是梦中的道路，

我只怕这些所谓的现实即将从你的脚下和手中消融。

即便此刻，你的五官、欢乐、言谈、房子、职业、举止、烦恼、蠢事、装束、罪行，也已经散逸离开你，

你真正的灵魂和肉体出现在我面前，

它们摆脱了事务，摆脱了商业、店铺、工作、农场、衣服、房子、购买、出售、进食、饮酒、受苦、死亡。

不管你是谁，现在我把手放在你身上，你来做我的诗，

我以嘴唇俯近你的耳朵低语，

我爱过很多女人和男人，但是都没有我爱你这么深。

噢，过去我拖沓又迟钝，

我许久以前就应该径直向你奔来，

我早就应该仅仅叨念着你，我早就应该仅仅歌唱着你。

我会离开所有人来创作你的赞美诗，

没有人曾经了解你，但是我了解你，

没有人曾经公平地对待你，你也未曾公平地对待自己，

没有人觉得你处处完美，只有我觉得你完美，

没有人不会把你放在次要位置，只有我这个人决不同意把你放在次要位置，

只有我一人看见你内在的潜能，不让任何主人、所有权人、优越者、上帝凌驾于你。

画家们画出人头攒动的群体和一切的中心人物，

从中心人物的头部放射金色的光轮，

但是我画出无数的头部，画笔下却没有一个不带着金色的光轮，

从我的手从每个男人和女人的大脑中它流泻出来，永远灿烂。

啊，关于你，我能唱多少壮阔和荣耀的歌！

你还不知道你是什么，你一生都在自己身上酣睡，

你的眼皮大部分时间就像闭着一般，

你做过的事已经在滑稽模仿中回来，

（你的节俭、知识、祈祷，如果不在滑稽模仿中回来，还能怎样回来？）

滑稽模仿并不是你，

我看见你潜藏在其下和其中，

我在无人追逐你的地方追逐你，

沉默、书桌、轻佻的表情、黑夜、日常习惯，如果这些对别人和你自己构成一重重的掩盖，你对于我却是没有掩盖的，

刮净的脸、游移的眼神、不纯净的肤色，如果这些阻挡着别人却并不阻挡我，

光鲜的衣着、畸形的体态、烂醉、贪婪、早死，我把这些全都抛在一边。

凡是男人或女人具有的天赋，你无一不具备，

凡是男人或女人具有的贤德和美好，也同样存于你身上，

别人身上的任何胆量或毅力，也同样存于你身上，

任何等待着别人享受的快乐，也同样等待着你来享受。

至于我，我什么也不给任何人，除了我谨慎交给你的，

每当我咏唱任何人，乃至上帝的荣耀之歌，那都是我为你唱的荣耀之歌。

不管你是谁！要不顾风险获取你自己的一切！

这些东方和西方的气象跟你相比都平淡无奇，

这些广阔的草原、滔滔不息的江河，你就像它们一样广阔而滔滔不息，

这些天昏地暗、狂风暴雨、雷霆、大自然的运动、分解时显现的挣扎，你是掌控它们的男女主宰，

你就是大权在握的男女主宰，掌控着大自然、狂风暴雨、痛苦、激情、分解。

镣铐从你的脚踝脱落，你找到可靠的独立，

无论老少、无论男女，粗鲁、卑微、被其他人拒绝，你不管什么本性都传播你自己，

穿过出生、生命、死亡、埋葬，通路都齐备，没有一样缺少，

穿过愤怒、丧失、野心、无知、厌倦，你凭着本性举足落步。

法兰西，合众国的第18年[7]

一个伟大的年份和地方。

一声粗嘎不协调的新生的尖叫传出，比什么都更深地触动母亲的心。

我行走在我的东部海岸上，

听见那小嗓子隔着浪涛传来，

看见那神圣的婴儿在她醒来的地方哀哀啼哭，炮声隆隆，咒骂声、嘶喊声、建筑物的倒塌声不绝，

阴沟中流淌的血、一具具尸体、成堆的尸体、被死囚车运走的尸体并不那么令我恶心，

屠杀的碾压并不那么令我绝望—频频齐发的枪弹并不那么令我震惊。

我苍白、沉默、冷峻，我能对那种常年积怨的报复说什么？

我能期求不一样的人性？

我能期求人民有木头和石头的品性？

还是期求正义在命运或时间中得不到伸张？

啊，自由！啊，你是我的伙伴！

这里也有火光，有霰弹和斧子的储存，以备必要的时候拿出来，

这里也压抑已久，却永远不会被摧毁，

这里也终会奋起反抗，杀气腾腾、慷慨激昂，

这里也要求着彻底的清算。

所以我要拿起笔向海的那边遥遥致敬，

我并不否认有血红可怕的降生和洗礼，

但是我记得所听见的小嗓子的啼哭，于是我无比信任地等待，不管要多久，

从今以后我要为一切土地维护那个遗留的事业，心怀悲哀但雄辩有力，

我带着爱意把这些话语送去巴黎，

猜想那里有些歌曲作者将会明白我的含义，

因为我猜想法兰西依然有音乐的潜流，滔滔汩汩，

啊，我已经听见乐器在拨动，响声很快就会淹没一切干扰的杂音，

啊，我觉得东风吹来了一首胜利和自由的进行曲，

它传到这里，使我欣喜得如痴如狂，

我要快快把它变作言辞，说明它的真意，

我还要为你唱一支歌，我的女人[8]。

我和我的全部[9]

我和我的全部，永远在锻炼，

为了抵受冷和热，为了举枪能瞄准，为了航船，为了骑马，为了生育出众的孩子，

为了随时清晰地说话，为了在普通人中间感到亲切，

也为了在大地和海洋情势可怕时站住脚跟。

不为了做一个刺绣工，

（永远会有许多刺绣工，我也欢迎他们，）

却为追求事物的本质，并追求男子和女子的内在。

不为了雕出装饰品，

却为了用潇洒自如的刻刀凿出许多无上神明的头和四肢，为了合众国使他们得以行走和说话。

让我用自己的方式，

让别人去生成律法，我不要理会律法，

让别人去歌颂杰出的人并支持和平，我支持骚动和冲突。

我不歌颂杰出的人，我对公认最高明的人也当面指责。

（你是谁？是什么让你一生偷偷地内疚？

你要回避自己的一生？你要在翻拣和闲话中度过一生？

你是谁，念念叨叨地死记硬背，年份、页数、语言、往事，

至今也意识不到你没法儿恰当地说一个词儿？）

让别人去完成范例吧，我从来不完成范例，

我像大自然一样用无穷的律法来开始篇章，新鲜现代而持久。

我不把什么当作义务给予，

别人作为义务给予的，我作为活生生的冲动给予。

（我要把心的行动作为义务来给予吗？）

让别人去解决问题，我什么都不解决，我唤起无法回答的问题，

我看见并触摸的他们是谁，他们怎么样？

这些像我一样的人怎么样？他们用温柔的直接和迂回的路线吸引我贴近。

我呼吁世界不要轻信我朋友们的讲述，而要像我一样，聆听我的敌人，

我要求你永远拒绝那些要解说我的人，因为我也解说不了自己，

我要求不要因我建立任何理论或学派，

我要求你潇洒地离开，就像我做的那样潇洒地离开。

在我之后，远景！

啊，我看见生命并不短促，而是悠长得难以计量，

从此我在世界上行走，贞洁，自持，清早就起床，稳健地成长，

每小时都是未来几个世纪的精子，还属于更久以后的世纪。

我必须紧紧跟上空气、水、大地的这些不断的教诲，

我感受到我没有时间可以浪费。

流星的一年（1859—1860）[10]

流星的一年！沉思的一年！

我要用回顾的文字系定你的一些事情和征兆，

我要歌唱你的第16届总统任期的竞争，

我要歌唱一位高个子的白发老人，如何在弗吉尼亚登上绞刑架，

（我就在左右，咬紧牙关默默站着，观看，

我站在你身边，老人，当时你平静冷漠，只是年纪和没有愈合的伤口使你颤抖着，登上了绞刑架；）

我要在我丰富的歌曲中歌唱你各州的人口普查报告，那些人口和产品的报表，我要歌唱你的航船和运载的货物，

曼哈顿骄傲的黑船纷纷来了，有的满载移民，有的装着黄金从巴拿马地峡来，

我要歌唱这一切，我要对所有前来的人表示欢迎，

我也要歌唱你，英俊少年！年轻的英格兰王子，我欢迎你！

（你可曾记得你和贵族随从们经过曼哈顿的汹涌人群？

我站在人群中，只对你依依不舍地注目；）

我也不要忘了歌唱那条大船开进我海湾的奇观，

伟大东方号形体匀称而庄重，她以600英尺[11]的身长，开进我的海湾，

她迅速地行驶，被无数的小船包围，小船我也不忘歌唱；

不忘北方出现的不期而至的彗星，闪耀在天宇，

不忘奇异浩大的流星队伍，炫目而清晰，在我们头上笔直飞行，

（一瞬间，只有一瞬间，队伍在我们头上划过一簇簇超凡的光球，

然后离去了，沉没在黑夜中，不见了；）

对这些骤然来去的事情，我歌唱—我借着它们的微光来照亮并拼凑这些颂歌，

你的颂歌呀，啊，善恶杂陈的一年—预感不祥的一年！

彗星和流星的一年，短暂又奇异—看！这儿还有一个也同样短暂又奇异！

既然我匆匆地掠过你，很快要坠落不见，这首歌是什么呢？

我除了是你的一颗流星还是什么？

因为前人

一

因为前人，

因为我的父系母系和以往各时代的积累，

因为那些倘若没有，就不会有今时此地之我的一切，因为埃及、印度、腓尼基、希腊和罗马，

因为凯尔特人、斯堪的纳维亚人、阿尔比人和撒克逊人[12]，

因为古时的海上冒险、法律、手工技艺、战争和旅行，

因为诗人、北欧诗人、萨迦、神话和神谕[13]，

因为奴隶的售卖，因为狂热者，因为吟游诗人、十字军和修道士，

因为我们来到这个新大陆之前的那些旧大陆，

因为那些日益衰落的王国和国王，

因为那些日益衰落的宗教和神父，

因为从我们自己眼前的大海岸回望而去的小海岸，

因为向前奔去终于到达现在的数不清的年头，

你和我已经抵达—阿美利加已经抵达，正在创造今年，

今年！它推动着自己奔向数不清的未来岁月。

二

啊，但是这无关岁月—而是关于我，关于你，

我们触碰所有的法律并估量所有的前人，

我们是北欧诗人、传神谕的人、修道士和骑士，我们容纳了他们还大有余地，

我们站在无始无终的时间之内，我们站在恶与善之内，一切围绕我们转动，黑暗和光明同样多，

太阳和它的星系围绕我们转动，

它的太阳，它太阳的太阳，全都围绕我们转动。

至于我，（矛盾的、狂躁的，身处暴烈的日子中间，）

我有所有人的意念，我是所有人并信仰所有人，

我相信唯物论是真的，唯灵论是真的，什么我都不排斥。

（我忘了什么吗？忘了过去的任何东西吗？

到我这里来，不管是谁，不管是什么，直到我给你承认。）

我尊重亚述[14]、中国、条顿[15]和希伯来人，

我接纳每一个理论、神话、神和半神，

我清楚从前的故事、圣书、族谱都是真的，没有例外，

我坚信过去的每一天都非得那样不可，

决不可能胜过它实际的样子。

而今天则一定是这样，阿美利加一定是这样，

今天和阿美利加决不可能胜过它们实际的样子。

三

以各州的名义，以你和我的名义：过去，

以各州的名义，以你和我的名义：现在的时间。

我知道过去伟大，未来也将会伟大，

我知道两者奇异地接合于现在的时间，

（为了我展现的他，为了平凡的普通人，如果你是普通人，这便是为了你，）

今天我所在之处，你所在之处，就有一切时日、一切民族的中心。

民族和时日对于我们曾经衍生的、将要衍生的一切意义也尽在其间。

百老汇大街的庆祝游行[16]

一

从大洋西边的日本来了

彬彬有礼、脸颊微黑、带两把佩剑的使节，

他们靠坐在敞篷四轮马车上，没有帽子，面无表情，今天驱车穿过曼哈顿。

自由啊[17]！我不知别人是否看见我的所见，

在队伍中跟日本贵族们一起的，还有跑腿的人，

走在后面，流连在前面、周围，或在行列中前进，

但是我要给你唱一首亲身见闻的歌，自由。

当百万双脚的曼哈顿自由自在走下她的人行道，

当声如惊雷的礼炮用我喜爱的豪迈咆哮叫我抖擞，

当浑圆的炮口从我喜爱的浓烈硝烟中吐出它们的敬意，

当火光闪烁的礼炮使我精神大振，云霞在我的城市上空蒙了一层如纱如影的华盖，

当数不清的华丽杆子，码头上的密林，彩色缤纷，

当每一条盛装打扮的船都把她的旗帜升到最高，

当信号旗低垂而沿街的窗户挂下彩带，

当百老汇被行走和驻足的人完全占领，最是密密麻麻，

当房屋的正面万头攒动，当千万双眼睛同时盯住一个方向，

当来自岛国的客人们行进，当游行队伍前移到视线之内，

当传召令发下，当等候数千年的答案有了回应，

我也站起身，回应着，走下人行道，汇入人群，和大家一同注视。

二

神采飞扬的曼哈顿！

阿美利加的同志们！东方，终于到我们这里来了。

到我们，到我的城市中间，

我们高峻的大理石屋顶和美丽的铁构建筑分列两旁，中间的大街走着游行队伍，

今天地球另一端的人来了。

女创世者来了，

语言的巢穴、诗歌的传递者、远古的遗民，

脸色红润，思虑深沉，出神陶醉，激情炽热，

香气蒸腾，衣裳宽大而飘逸，

有黝黑的面容，有专注的灵魂和闪亮的眼睛，

梵天的子民来了。

看呀，我悦耳的歌！游行队伍中的这些那些都向我们闪现，

队伍随着移动而变化，像个神奇的万花筒在我们眼前移动变化。

因为不只有使节或来自岛屿的晒黑的日本人，

轻巧沉默的印度人出现了，甚至亚细亚大陆也出现了，

它的过去，它的死者，

在如夜如晨的朦胧中发生的奇观和无法索解的寓言，

包裹着的奥秘，古老而未知的蜜蜂，

北方，闷热的南方，东方的亚述，希伯来人，最古的古人，

巨大而荒凉的城市，滑行的此刻，所有这些那些都在庆祝的游行中。

地理学，全世界，都在其中，

大洋[18]，成群的岛屿，波利尼西亚，更远的海岸，

今后你要面向的海岸—你呀，自由！你金色的西海岸和它遥遥相对，

那里的国家和它们的居民，千百万人一起奇妙地身临此地，

拥挤的集市，两侧或尽头都神像成行的庙宇，和尚、婆罗门和喇嘛，

官老爷、农民、商人、机械工和渔夫，

歌女和舞女、沉醉迷狂的人、宫禁里的皇帝，

孔夫子自己、大诗人和英雄豪杰、战士、各个种姓，所有人，

聚集成群，从四面八方涌来，从阿尔泰的山岭，

从西藏，从中国的四条蜿蜒长流的大江，

从南方的许多半岛和仿佛大陆般的岛屿，从马来西亚，

这些以及属于它们的一切都向我清楚显现，被我领会，

我也被它们领会，被它们友爱地拥抱，

最后如同在这里一样我歌咏他们所有人，自由！为了他们也为了你。

因为我也扬起了声音加入这游行的行列，

我是歌手，我在盛会之上发出洪大的歌声，

我歌咏我那西海上的世界，

我歌咏远方众多的海岛，密集如满天的星辰，

我歌咏那空前壮阔的新帝国，在灵视之中看见了它，

我歌咏女主人阿美利加，我歌咏一个更高的权威，

我歌咏一千座新兴的城市，将要在那些海岛群中拔地而起，

我的帆船和蒸汽船在群岛中间穿梭，

我的星条旗在风中拍动，

商路打开了，沉睡的几个世纪结束使命，民族再生，再次青春，

人生、事业都恢复了—目标我不知道—但是古老的亚洲一定会更新，

从这一天开始被世界包围。

三

你呀，世界的自由！

你将会千秋万代稳坐当中，

因为今天亚洲的贵族从一边来到你面前，

因为明天英国女王要从另一边派她的长子来见你。

迹象在倒转，地球被合围，

圆环已合拢，旅程已结束，

盒子盖只是微微打开着，香气却从整个盒子里喷涌而出。

年轻的自由！对待那可敬的亚洲、一切的母亲，

你从今以后要始终体贴而热情，因为你就是一切，

向那个越过群岛向你发来消息的远方母亲俯下你骄傲的头吧，

就这一次俯下你骄傲的头吧，年轻的自由。

那些孩子向西漫游了那么久吗？跨过那么宽广的地方吗？

自乐园[19]以来迷茫的世世代代向西闯荡了那么久吗？

多少个世纪为了你、为了某些原因，朝那个方向不断前行而不为人知？

时代都理由充分，它们已大功告成，现在它们也应该被掉转方向，从那边朝你行来，

自由呀，时代现在也应该看在你的分儿上，顺从地向东挺进。

[1]写《普遍性之歌》前，惠特曼经受了一些个人生活的考验，包括中风瘫痪和丧母之痛。此诗重申了他的信仰，也反映出他研读黑格尔哲学受到的影响。（说明：书中脚注除特别标明的之外，均为译者注。）

[2]“真实”者，指世间存在的各种殊相；“理想”者，指普遍性的事物共相。

[3]希腊神话中，英雄忒修斯凭借阿里阿德涅交给他的线团，循着细线前行，走出迷宫。

[4]本书出于声韵与音节字数的考量，统一使用“阿美利加”来翻译America，而不用美利坚或美国。

[5]“整体”的原文ensemble是超验主义的概念，这股思潮认为万物都包含宇宙的缩影。惠特曼受超验主义代表人物爱默生影响很深。

[6]读者若觉得这四行突兀难解，可以查看乔万尼·巴蒂斯塔·提埃坡罗（Giovanni Battista Tiepolo）绘于18世纪的著名穹顶画《行星和大陆的寓言》中的美洲一幅，那里便有一个作为美洲化身的“女主人”。

[7]此诗写于1860年，是美国南北战争（1861—1865）爆发前夕，当时的社会气氛已是山雨欲来（参见《流星的一年》）。惠特曼在诗中想象远在他出生之前的一个年份—法国大革命时期“革命法庭”活动到达高潮的1794年，那年是美利坚合众国成立的第18年。

[8]“我的女人”原文为法语ma femme，也表示“我的妻子”，这里指拟人化的民主理想。

[9]此诗可说是惠特曼创作观的阐述，他将《草叶集》视为以文字表达的全部自己。

[10]此诗写于1865年美国南北战争结束时。诗中回忆的总统竞选是1860年林肯对道格拉斯的宣战，林肯当选总统。被处死的老人是美国起义领袖、废奴主义者约翰·布朗，处决时间在1859年12月。年轻的英格兰王子指维多利亚女王的长子爱德华（后来的英王爱德华七世），1860年10月他18岁，到访纽约，惠特曼的日记中有记载。伟大东方号是著名的英国铁制蒸汽轮船，1860年首次航越大西洋，6月末抵达纽约。“预感不祥的一年”一语指当时战争已如箭在弦上的气氛。

[11]一英尺约为25到34厘米。——编者注

[12]这一行诗里全是古意盎然的名称。阿尔比恩（Albion）是大不列颠岛最古老的名称，阿尔比人（Alb）即阿尔比恩的居民。

[13]北欧诗人原文为skald，在维京人时期，他们是斯堪的纳维亚（北欧）地区传诵英雄传奇的诗人，萨迦（saga）是北欧从前用来流传神话、史诗和英雄故事的文学类型。

[14]亚述：兴起于两河流域的国家。公元前8世纪末，亚述帝国逐步强大，先后征服了小亚细亚东部、埃及等地，亚述人在两河流域频繁活动约两千年，后失去霸主地位，不再有独立的国家。——编者注

[15]条顿：古代日耳曼人的一个分支，公元前4世纪时分布在易北河下游的沿海地带，后来逐步和日耳曼其他民族融合，后世以条顿人泛指日耳曼人及其后裔。——编者注

[16]此诗最初发表于1860年6月27日的《纽约时报》，纪念11天前在纽约市百老汇大街上欢迎访美日本使团的庆祝游行。

[17]原文是Libertad，惠特曼习惯用这个西班牙语单词的大写来表示拟人化的自由。

[18]当指太平洋。

[19]即伊甸园，象征人类最初纯真原始的状态。

海流

出自晃荡不停的摇篮[20]

出自晃荡不停的摇篮，

出自学舌鸟的喉咙、往复如梭的音乐，

出自九月的午夜，

荒芜的沙地和远处的田野上，起了床的孩子独自游荡，光着头，光着脚，

沐浴在一阵阵洒落的光晕下，

俯临着影子们像是活的一样交缠扭摆的神秘游戏，

走出了荆棘和黑莓生长的灌木丛，

记忆中的那只鸟，在我耳边唱过歌，

记忆中悲伤的兄弟，让我听见过一阵阵高低起伏的歌声，

从迟迟升起又胀鼓鼓的仿佛含着泪水的半个黄月亮底下，

从薄雾里最先响起的那些渴望和爱的乐音，

从我心中一千个永不停息的应答，

从自此苏醒的无数词句，

从那个比什么都更强大更悦耳的词语，

从词句如今又开始重返的故地，

就像一群飞鸟，啁啾、腾起、从头顶掠过，

匆匆被送到这里，趁着一切还没有被我忘却，

一个男人，由于这些泪水又成了小男孩，

扑倒在沙地上，面对海浪，

我，痛苦和欢乐的歌手、连接今天和未来的人，

接纳一切暗示来运用它们，但又迅速地跃过它们，为一件往事歌唱。

从前在鲍玛诺克[21]，

当空气中飘着丁香的芬芳，五月的草正在生长，

从亚拉巴马来了两个披着羽毛的客人，

双双落在海岸上的荆棘丛里，

他们的窝，有四只浅绿带褐色斑点的蛋，

每天那雄鸟在附近飞来飞去，

每天那雌鸟蹲在窝里，安安静静，眼睛发亮，

每天，我这好奇的男孩，从不走得太近，从不惊动他们，

小心地窥察着、吸收着、转译着。

闪呀！闪呀！闪呀！

倾注你的温暖，太阳！

我们晒太阳，双双做伴。

双双做伴！

风吹向南，风吹向北，

白天明亮，夜晚黑暗，

家乡，或者远离家乡的河流山脉，

只要我们相守，

就一直唱歌，忘记时光。

突然有一天，

上午雌鸟没有蹲在鸟巢里，

也许被捕杀了，她的伙伴不知道，

下午也没有回来，第二天也没有，

再也没有出现。

从此以后整个夏天在大海的声音中，

在黑夜里满月当空而天气较平静的时分，

在波涛哗哗汹涌的海上，

或者白天在丛丛荆棘之上，

我时常看见那只遗留的雄鸟飞过，

听见那来自亚拉巴马的孤独客声。

吹吧！吹吧！吹吧！

海风狂吹鲍玛诺克的海岸吧；

我等呀等，直到你把我的伙伴吹回来。

是的，当星光闪烁，

他彻夜站在长满青苔的木桩尖上，

几乎就在海浪的拍拍打打中，

孤单的歌手，奇异而催泪。

他呼唤他的伙伴，

他倾吐的心声，人类中只有我懂得。

是的，我懂得我的兄弟，

别人也许不懂，但我一直珍重每一粒乐音。

因为我不止一次懵懵懂懂地溜到海滩，

安静，避开月光，把自己藏在阴影里，

现在还记得那些模糊的形状、回响、种种声音和景象，

浪花破开的白手臂不知疲倦地挥舞着，

我，光脚的孩子，被风吹动着头发，

倾听了很久很久。

倾听来保存、来歌唱，时而转译乐音，

来追随你的歌声，兄弟。

抚慰！抚慰！抚慰！

后浪紧紧地抚慰着前浪，

又被下一个浪紧紧地拥抱、拍打，

但是我所爱的不抚慰我了，不抚慰了。

低垂的月亮，迟迟升起，

它那么迟缓——噢，我想它是重负着爱情，爱情。

啊，大海疯狂地扑向陆地，

怀着爱情，爱情。

啊，黑夜！我看见的莫不是我的爱侣在浪花里翻飞？

我在那白浪里看见的小黑点是什么？

嘹亮！嘹亮！嘹亮！

我嘹亮地呼唤你，我的爱侣！

我抛出我高亢清晰的声音越过波浪，

你一定知道在这里的是谁，是谁，

你一定知道我是谁，爱侣。

低垂的月亮！

你黄褐色脸盘上的暗点是什么？

啊，就是她的形状，我伙伴的形状！

月亮啊别再扣留她，还给我吧。

陆地！陆地！噢，陆地！

不管我转向何方，噢，我想你可以交还我的伙伴，只要你肯，

因为不管我望向何方，我都好像是依稀看见了她。

啊，上升的星星！

也许我渴望的那个也会升上天空，和你们一同升起。

啊，喉咙！啊，颤动的喉咙！

发出更清晰的声音越过空气！

穿透树林、大地，

我渴望的那个一定在某地切盼着听见你。

放声歌唱吧！

寂寞此地，黑夜之歌！

孤单爱恋之歌！死亡之歌！

在那迟缓的、消殒的黄月亮下面歌唱！

啊，在月亮下，在她几乎沉入大海的地方！

啊，不顾一切的绝望之歌。

但是轻些！压低！

轻些！让我只是呢喃吧，

你呀，喧嚣的大海，请你也停一停，

因为我相信我听见了伙伴正在什么地方回应着，

那么微弱，我得安静，安静地听，

但不能彻底安静，那样她可能不会立即来我这儿。

来这儿呀爱侣！

我在这儿！这儿！

我只用这刚能听见的歌声向你宣告我自己，

这轻柔的呼唤是给你的，我的爱，给你的。

不要上当去了别的地方，

那是风的呼啸，不是我的声音，

那是翻飞的、翻飞的浪花，

那些是树叶的影子。

噢，黑暗！噢，徒然！

噢，我多么苦闷多么哀伤。

啊，天空中月亮旁边的褐色光晕，低垂在海上！

啊，海中散乱的倒影！

啊，喉咙！啊，搏动的心！

我彻夜无效地唱着，无效。

啊，过往！啊，快活的日子！啊，欢乐的歌！

在空中，在树林，在田野上，

爱过！爱过！爱过！爱过！爱过！

但是我的伙伴不再，不再跟着我了！

我俩不再双双。

咏叹调沉寂了，

别的一切都还继续，星光闪闪，

风在吹，鸟的乐音在久久地回响，

凶猛的老母亲[22]不断发出她愤怒的呻吟，

在鲍玛诺克岸边沙沙作响的灰色海滩上，

半个黄月亮变大了，耷拉着，下垂着，几乎贴到大海的脸，

男孩心醉神迷，波浪戏弄着他的赤脚，空气撩拨着他的头发，

长久禁闭在心里的爱，现在自由了，现在终于轰然爆发了，

咏叹调的含义，耳朵、灵魂，迅速地将它储存，

奇异的眼泪淌下脸颊，

三者[23]在那里对话，各有各的言说，

低声部是狂野的老母亲在不断地叫着，

阴冷地应和着男孩的灵魂的提问节奏，嘶嘶吐出某个淹没的秘密，

回答那起步的诗人。

不是精灵就是鸟了！（男孩的灵魂说，）

你真是在对你的伙伴唱歌？还是其实是对我？

因为，那时是个孩子，我舌头的用处还在沉睡，现在却听见了你的话语，

现在我一瞬间知道了我为何而生，我觉醒了，

已经有一千名歌手、一千首歌，比你的歌更清晰、更嘹亮，也更哀伤，

一千种婉转的回声被我内心的生命振起，永不消亡。

哦，你这孤独的歌手，只身唱歌，投影出我的未来，

哦，孤独的我在倾听，我将会永远不息让你不被遗忘，

我将永远不会逃避，永远不会有震颤的回声、

有不得满足的爱的呼喊被我听而不闻，

我将永远不再是那一夜之前的平静的孩子，

在那下沉的黄月亮照临的海边，

使者在那里被唤醒，看见了火，甜蜜的内心地狱，未知的渴求，我的天命。

啊，给我线索！（它潜伏在这黑夜的某个地方，）

啊，如果我可以得到那么多，再多给一些！

就一个词吧，（因为我能征服它，）

那个最终的词，超乎一切的词，

不着痕迹，送来了—它是什么？—我在倾听；

你低语着的就是它吗，海浪，一直是它？

从你晶莹的浪沫和潮湿的沙中来的就是它？

大海对此回答，

没有延宕，没有匆忙，

一整夜都在对我低语，在天亮前已十分清楚，

喃喃对我说着那个低沉悦耳的词：死亡，

一再地说死亡，死亡，死亡，死亡，

嘶嘶发出的美妙音调，不像那鸟鸣也不像我这孩子的激动心跳，

却渐渐向我一个人贴近，在我脚边簌簌响动，

从那里平稳地爬上我的耳朵，轻柔地冲洗我的全身，

死亡，死亡，死亡，死亡，死亡。

这我没有忘记，

但对于我那幽暗的精灵和兄弟，

在鲍玛诺克的灰色海滩月光下给我唱的歌，

我将它和一千首应答的歌任意融合，

使我自己觉醒于那个时刻的歌，

海浪传来的那个词是开启它们的钥匙，

那钥匙关乎最甜蜜的歌和一切的歌，

那强大悦耳的词，悄悄爬上我的脚—

（或者像一个老婆婆晃动着摇篮，衣裳发出好闻的气味，在旁边弯腰，）

大海给我的低语。

在海船后面

在海船后面，在呼呼的风后面，

在桅杆和绳索拉紧的灰白船帆后面，

底下，千万个波浪在奔走，高高抬着脖子，

不停地向着大船的航迹流动而去，

海洋的波浪们汩汩冒着水泡，惬意地东张西望，

波浪，起伏的波浪，形状不定，高高低低，你追我赶，

欢笑而轻快，跑着弧线，奔向旋转的急流，

那里是大船的航行和转向把海面破开的地方，

大大小小的波浪便在那汪洋中热切地流动，

在海船过处的航迹中，波浪在阳光下闪耀、游戏，

一支混杂的队伍，带着无数斑斓的泡沫和碎片，

追随着雍容疾驰的船，追随她的航迹。

[20]这是惠特曼自传性的名篇，像歌剧（启迪惠特曼开创其自由体的艺术形式）一般层次繁复，大开大阖。诗中有几个独立又有所交融的声音，分别为成年时的诗人、学舌鸟和童年时的诗人，大海则以暗示向童年时的诗人发出话语。

[21]鲍玛诺克：纽约州长岛的印第安语名称，惠特曼出生在那里，他对这个能唤起他童年回忆的名称情有独钟。

[22]惠特曼常用老母亲来喻指大海。他写诗有时喜欢采用一些法文词，法文中“母亲”（la mère）与“大海”（la mer）同音。

[23]三者指雄鸟、大海和孩子。

[24]原文lines可能暗指诗行，惠特曼有多首涉及漫步的诗，这似乎是他获取灵感的一种方式。

[25]Sea-gluten（海胶）是惠特曼生造的复合词，可能指海中动物的黏稠分泌物或富含蛋白的动物组织。

[26]父亲喻指生养了诗人的鲍玛诺克岛，与大海母亲相对，可能也兼指和诗人关系疏离的生身父亲。

[27]英文tear既表示裂口（名词）、撕裂（动词），也表示眼泪，此诗利用了词义的这个叠合来组织意象。

[28]惠特曼依据法国史学家儒勒·米什莱的一首诗作的英译本而改写成此诗。早在尚未出版《草叶集》的年轻岁月，惠特曼已读过米什莱的著作，颇受其熏陶。

[29]即木星。

[30]即金牛座的昴宿星团。希腊神话中，七姊妹星是肩负天宇的阿特拉斯的七个女儿。

[31]“钥匙”（clef）一词为法文，意思是可以用它解开宇宙的奥秘。

[32]宣叙调又译朗诵调，原指歌剧里介乎歌唱和说话之间的演唱方式，与咏叹调相比，宣叙调着重叙事，旋律简单。

[33]巴尼加特是新泽西州的一个长达30英里的海湾，惠特曼晚年住在新泽西州肯顿，有时会到访此地。原诗为十四行商籁体，每行均以现在分词-ing形式来结尾；不计括号部分的问句，全诗始终没有出现陈述句的谓语动词，从头到尾用状语成分来描述情态，紧张感十足。

[34]Comb可以表示梳子，也可以表示鸡冠或蜂窝状的东西，这里暗喻浪头。

译后记

这本小册子分为两个部分，共十九首诗。惠特曼晚年亲自编订了《草叶集》（1891—1892）最终版，企鹅出版社从中摘选两个相邻而完整的子集《候鸟》《海流》组成了这个微型选本。

《候鸟》探索了不同类型的运动变化，有宇宙从缺陷趋于完美的进程，有美国向西的开拓，有自我身份的追寻，也有历史的波澜、文明的盛衰。这组诗并不包含惠特曼的代表作，但是它视野宏大，富于诗人早期作品的特色，自有动人之处。《海流》则喻示着诗人创作重心的转变：基调从开拓精神、唯物论和个人性走向了内省、唯灵论以及同物无虑的信仰。而自《草叶集》问世以来，恐怕《海流》就比《候鸟》更能抓住读者的心，它语调亲密，多用诗人童年记忆中的大海、沙滩、星月、飞鸟组织意象，探索那“勾连万物”的“茫茫相似”（《独自在黑夜的海滩上》）。诗与诗环环相扣，回味深长，头两首《出自晃荡不停的摇篮》《当我跟生命之海一同退潮》早已成为经典，值得一读再读。

十几年前，由于成长和爱情的经历，我被惠特曼的一些诗深深打动，翻译过诗人最终收录在子集《芦笛》的一组十二首诗以及另一首自传性的名作##There Was a Child Went Forth$$（标题拙译为《有一个孩子脱颖而出》）。《草叶集》在我国已经有多个全译本，选译本更难计数，我本来以为自己不会再动翻译惠特曼的念头了。文学译本有时代性，此番企鹅出版社希望用新文字来呈现这位19世纪大诗人的风貌，我考虑后愿意尝试。翻译它，从准备到译成不过短短几个月，却重新燃烧起我对惠特曼的热情。译稿完成对于我大概不会是结束，而是一个新开始。

无论选择与否，我们都走在前人铺过的路上（见本书《因为前人》一诗）。我事先挑选了两个颇受好评的《草叶集》全译本作参考，工作之中也将它们展卷置于案头。我借鉴了这些译本的样式和语调，有时遇到特别优美灵巧的处理，自问无法更进一步或别开生面的时候，就沿用了前辈的译法。为此，我要郑重向这两位前辈译者——邹仲之先生和已故的赵萝蕤先生致以谢忱和敬意。然而，任何译本都只是一种诠释，原文才是译者的圣经。我对每首诗的主题、词义、句法、韵律都独立推敲，任何细节均不欲盲从前贤，务求从原著中得到肺腑之中的感情共鸣及理性体会才落笔。翻译有时像是跟作者对话，但这次翻译与其说是惠特曼和我的对话，不如说是四方（他、三位译者）隔着时空的交谈，只不过我只记录了自己的心得。当下读来，我满意这份记录，但是选手并不能同时做裁判。本人在原诗理解和风格再现方面跟前辈有何差异，在文字取舍间可能有何得失，我不想自己举例，感兴趣的读者可以自行比较。盼望大家慷慨赐教，推动惠特曼中译的继续进步。

本书的编辑白姗提了许多细致而宝贵的意见，令译稿得有寸进，也要向她道谢。

除了上述两个译本，此书的注释、译后记里对本书两组诗的阐释，还参考了Routledge出版社1998年版《惠特曼百科全书》、Norton出版社的英文《草叶集》，并其他几部英文传记和研究专著。

惠特曼自由奔放的诗篇给人潇洒的印象，却绝非随意散漫的创作：从他36岁时自费出版薄薄一册的《草叶集》首版开始，到72岁临终前发表极厚重的第九版《草叶集》定本，数十年之间，诗人屡次仔细修改自己的每首作品，使技法趋于成熟、内容趋于饱满，有手稿和不同版次为证。如果说诗在翻译中折损属于必然，那么我也努力追随了前人的脚步来减少折损，力求从形式和精神两方面趋近原作。惠特曼擅长以“你”呼唤读者，常令人在当下看见自己，肉体灵魂都感受到他的永在。希望我的工作没有辜负诗人的一片苦心。

郑远涛2018年5月记于美国西海岸

（时为惠特曼出生月、他诞辰的第199周年）

BIRDS OF PASSAGE

Song of the Universal

1

Come said the Muse,

Sing me a song no poet yet has chanted,

Sing me the universal.

In this broad earth of ours,

Amid the measureless grossness and the slag,

Enclosed and safe within its central heart,

Nestles the seed perfection.

By every life a share or more or less,

None born but it is born, conceal’d or unconceal’d the seed is waiting.

2

Lo! keen-eyed towering science,

As from tall peaks the modern overlooking,

Successive absolute fiats issuing.

Yet again, lo! the soul, above all science,

For it has history gather’d like husks around the globe,

For it the entire star-myriads roll through the sky.

In spiral routes by long detours,

（As a much-tacking ship upon the sea,）

For it the partial to the permanent flowing;

For it the real to the ideal tends.

For it the mystic evolution,

Not the right only justified, what we call evil also justified.

Forth from their masks, no matter what,

From the huge festering trunk, from craft and guile and tears,

Health to emerge and joy, joy universal.

Out of the bulk, the morbid and the shallow,

Out of the bad majority, the varied countless frauds of men and states,

Electric, antiseptic yet, cleaving, suffusing all,

Only the good is universal.

3

Over the mountain-growths disease and sorrow,

An uncaught bird is ever hovering, hovering,

High in the purer, happier air.

From imperfection’s murkiest cloud,

Darts always forth one ray of perfect light,

One flash of heaven’s glory.

To fashion’s, custom’s discord,

To the mad Babel-din, the deafening orgies,

Soothing each lull a strain is heard, just heard,

From some far shore the final chorus sounding.

O the blest eyes, the happy hearts,

That see, that know the guiding thread so fine,

Along the mighty labyrinth.

4

And thou America,

For the scheme’s culmination, its thought and its reality,

For these （not for thyself） thou has arrived.

Thou too surroundest all,

Embracing carrying welcoming all, thou too by pathways broad and new,

To the ideal tendest.

The measur’d faiths of other lands, the grandeurs of the past,

Are not for thee, but grandeurs of thine own,

Deific faiths and amplitudes, absorbing, comprehending all,

All eligible to all.

All, all for immortality,

Love like the light silently wrapping all,

Nature’s amelioration blessing all,

The blossoms, fruits of ages, orchards divine and certain,

Forms, objects, growths, humanities, to spirtual images ripening.

Give me O God to sing that thought,

Give me, give him or her I love this quenchless faith,

In Thy ensemble, whatever else withheld withhold not from us,

Belief in plan of Thee enclosed in Time and Space,

Health, peace, salvation universal.

Is it a dream?

Nay but the lack of it the dream,

And failing it life’s lore and wealth a dream,

And all the world a dream.

To You

Whoever you are, I fear you are walking the walks of dreams,

I fear these supposed realities are to melt from under your feet and hands,

Even now your features, joys, speech, house, trade, manners, troubles, follies, costume, crimes, dissipateaway from you,

Your true soul and body appear before me,

They stand forth out of affairs, out of commerce, shops, work, farms, clothes, the house, buying, selling, eating, drinking, suffering, dying.

Whoever you are, now I place my hand upon you, that you be my poem,

I whisper with my lips close to your ear,

I have loved many women and men, but I love none better than you.

O I have been dilatory and dumb,

I should have made my way straight to you long ago,

I should have blabb’d nothing but you, I should have chanted nothing but you.

I will leave all and come and make the hymns of you,

None has understood you, but I understand you,

None has done justice to you, you have not done justice to yourself,

None but has found you imperfect, I only find no imperfection in you,

None but would subordinate you, I only am he who will never consent to subordinate you,

I only am he who places over you no master, owner, better, God, beyond what waits intrinsically in yourself.

Painters have painted their swarming groups and the centre-figure of all,

From the head of the centre-figure spreading a nimbus of gold-color’d light,

But I paint myriads of heads, but paint no head without its nimbus of gold-color’d light,

From my hand from the brain of every man and woman it streams, effulgently flowing forever.

O I could sing such grandeurs and glories about you!

You have not known what you are, you have slumber’d upon yourself all your life,

Your eyelids have been the same as closed most of the time,

What you have done returns already in mockeries,

（Your thrift, knowledge, prayers, if they do not return in mockeries, what is their return?）

The mockeries are not you,

Underneath them and within them I see you lurk,

I pursue you where none else has pursued you,

Silence, the desk, the flippant expression, the night, the accustom’d routine, if these conceal you from others or from yourself, they do not conceal you from me,

The shaved face, the unsteady eye, the impure complexion, if these balk others they do not balk me,

The pert apparel, the deform’d attitude, drunkenness, greed, premature death, all these I part aside.

There is no endowment in man or woman that is not tallied in you,

There is no virtue, no beauty in man or woman, but as good is in you,

No pluck, no endurance in others, but as good is in you,

No pleasure waiting for others, but an equal pleasure waits for you.

As for me, I give nothing to any one except I give the like carefully to you,

I sing the songs of the glory of none, not God, sooner than I sing the songs of the glory of you.

Whoever you are! claim your own at any hazard!

These shows of the East and West are tame compared to you,

These immense meadows, these interminable rivers, you are immense and interminable as they,

These furies, elements, storms, motions of Nature, throes of apparent dissolution, you are he or she who is master or mistress over them,

Master or mistress in your own right over Nature, elements, pain, passion, dissolution.

The hopples fall from your ankles, you find an unfailing sufficiency,

Old or young, male or female, rude, low, rejected by the rest, whatever you are promulges itself,

Through birth, life, death, burial, the means are provided, nothing is scanted,

Through angers, losses, ambition, ignorance, ennui, what you are picks its way.

France, the 18th Year of These States

A great year and place.

A harsh discordant natal scream out-sounding, to touch the mother’s heart closer than any yet.

I walk’d the shores of my Eastern sea,

Heard over the waves the little voice,

Saw the divine infant where she woke mournfully wailing, amid the roar of cannon, curses, shouts, crash of falling buildings,

Was not so sick from the blood in the gutters running, nor from the single corpses, nor those in heaps, nor those borne away in the tumbrils,

Was not so desperate at the battues of death-was not so shock’d at the repeated fusillades of the guns.

Pale, silent, stern, what could I say to that long-accrued retribution?

Could I wish humanity different?

Could I wish the people made of wood and stone?

Or that there be no justice in destiny or time?

O Liberty! O mate for me!

Here too the blaze, the grape-shot and the axe, in reserve, to fetch them out in case of need,

Here too, though long represt, can never be destroy’d,

Here too could rise at last murdering and ecstatic,

Here too demanding full arrears of vengeance.

Hence I sign this salute over the sea,

And I do not deny that terrible red birth and baptism,

But remember the little voice that I heard wailing, and wait with perfect trust, no matter how long,

And from to-day sad and cogent I maintain the bequeath’d cause, as for all lands,

And I send these words to Paris with my love,

And I guess some chansonniers there will understand them,

For I guess there is latent music yet in France, floods of it,

O I hear already the bustle of instruments, they will soon be drowning all that would interrupt them,

O I think the east wind brings a triumphal and free march,

It reaches hither, it swells me to joyful madness,

I will run transpose it in words, to justify it,

I will yet sing a song for you ma femme.

Myself and Mine

Myself and mine gymnastic ever,

To stand the cold or heat, to take good aim with a gun, to sail a boat, to manage horses, to beget superb children,

To speak readily and clearly, to feel at home among common people,

And to hold our own in terrible positions on land and sea.

Not for an embroiderer,

（There will always be plenty of embroiderers, I welcome them also,）

But for the fibre of things and for inherent men and women.

Not to chisel ornaments,

But to chisel with free stroke the heads and limbs of plenteous supreme Gods, that the States may realize them walking and talking.

Let me have my own way,

Let others promulge the laws, I will make no account of the laws,

Let others praise eminent men and hold up peace, I hold up agitation and conflict.

I praise no eminent man, I rebuke to his face the one that was thought most worthy.

（Who are you? and what are you secretly guilty of all your life?

Will you turn aside all your life? will you grub and chatter all your life?

And who are you, blabbing by rote, years, pages, languages, reminiscences,

Unwitting to-day that you do not know how to speak properly a single word?）

Let others finish specimens, I never finish specimens,

I start them by exhaustless laws as Nature does, fresh and modern continually.

I give nothing as duties,

What others give as duties I give as living impulses,

（Shall I give the heart’s action as a duty?）

Let others dispose of questions, I dispose of nothing, I arouse unanswerable questions,

Who are they I see and touch, and what about them?

What about these likes of myself that draw me so close by tender directions and indirections?

I call to the world to distrust the accounts of my friends, but listen to my enemies, as I myself do,

I charge you forever reject those who would expound me, for I cannot expound myself,

I charge that there be no theory or school founded out of me,

I charge you to leave all free, as I have left all free.

After me, vista!

O I see life is not short, but immeasurably long,

I henceforth tread the world chaste, temperate, an early riser, a steady grower,

Every hour the semen of centuries, and still of centuries.

I must follow up these continual lessons of the air, water, earth,

I perceive I have no time to lose.

Year of Meteors（1859-60）

Year of meteors! brooding year!

I would bind in words retrospective some of your deeds and signs,

I would sing your contest for the 19th Presidentiad,

I would sing how an old man, tall, with white hair, mounted the scaffold in Virginia,

（I was at hand, silent I stood with teeth shut close, I watch’d,

I stood very near you old man when cool and indifferent, but trembling with age and your unheal’d wounds you mounted the scaffold；）

I would sing in my copious song your census returns of the States,

The tables of population and products, I would sing of your ships and their cargoes,

The proud black ships of Manhattan arriving, some fill’d with immigrants, some from the isthmus with cargoes of gold,

Songs thereof would I sing, to all that hitherward comes would I welcome give,

And you would I sing, fair stripling! welcome to you from me, young prince of England!

（Remember you surging Manhattan’s crowds as you pass’d with your cortege of nobles?

There in the crowds stood I, and singled you out with attachment;）

Nor forget I to sing of the wonder, the ship as she swam up my bay,

Well-shaped and stately the Great Eastern swam up my bay, she was 600 feet long,

Her moving swiftly surrounded by myriads of small craft I forget not to sing;

Nor the comet that came unannounced out of the north flaring in heaven,

Nor the strange huge meteor-procession dazzling and clear shooting over our heads,

（A moment, a moment long it sail’d its balls of unearthly light over our heads,

Then departed, dropt in the night, and was gone;）

Of such, and fitful as they, I sing — with gleams from them would I gleam and patch these chants,

Your chants, O year all mottled with evil and good-year of forebodings!

Year of comets and meteors transient and strange-lo! even here one equally transient and strange!

As I flit through you hastily, soon to fall and be gone, what is this chant,

What am I myself but one of your meteors?

With Antecedents

1

With antecedents,

With my fathers and mothers and the accumulations of past ages,

With all which, had it not been, I would not now be here, as I am,

With Egypt, India, Phenicia, Greece and Rome,

With the Kelt, the Scandinavian, the Alb and the Saxon,

With antique maritime ventures, laws, artisanship, wars and journeys,

With the poet, the skald, the saga, the myth, and the oracle,

With the sale of slaves, with enthusiasts, with the troubadour, the crusader, and the monk,

With those old continents whence we have come to this new continent,

With the fading kingdoms and kings over there,

With the fading religions and priests,

With the small shores we look back to from our own large and present shores,

With countless years drawing themselves onward and arrived at these years,

You and me arrived-America arrived and making this year,

This year! sending itself ahead countless years to come.

2

O but it is not the years — it is I, it is You,

We touch all laws and tally all antecedents,

We are the skald, the oracle, the monk and the knight, we easily include them and more,

We stand amid time beginningless and endless, we stand amid evil and good,

All swings around us, there is as much darkness as light,

The very sun swings itself and its system of planets around us,

Its sun, and its again, all swing around us.

As for me, （torn, stormy, amid these vehement days,）

I have the idea of all, and am all and believe in all,

I believe materialism is true and spiritualism is true, I reject no part.

（Have I forgotten any part? any thing in the past?

Come to me whoever and whatever, till I give you recognition.）

I respect Assyria, China, Teutonia, and the Hebrews,

I adopt each theory, myth, god, and demi-god,

I see that the old accounts, bibles, genealogies, are true, without exception,

I assert that all past days were what they must have been,

And that they could no-how have been better than they were,

And that to-day is what it must be, and that America is,

And that to-day and America could no-how be better than they are.

3

In the name of these States and in your and my name, the Past,

And in the name of these States and in your and my name, the Present time.

I know that the past was great and the future will be great,

And I know that both curiously conjoint in the present time,

（For the sake of him I typify, for the common average man’s sake, your sake if you are he,）

And that where I am or you are this present day, there is the centre of all days, all races,

And there is the meaning to us of all that has ever come of races and days, or ever will come.

A Broadway Pageant

1

Over the Western sea hither from Niphon come,

Courteous, the swart-cheek’d two-sworded envoys,

Leaning back in their open barouches, bare-headed, impassive,

Ride to-day through Manhattan.

Libertad! I do not know whether others behold what I behold,

In the procession along with the nobles of Niphon, the errand-bearers,

Bringing up the rear, hovering above, around, or in the ranks marching,

But I will sing you a song of what I behold Libertad.

When million-footed Manhattan unpent descends to her pavements,

When the thunder-cracking guns arouse me with the proud roar I love,

When the round-mouth’d guns out of the smoke and smell I love spit their salutes,

When the fire-flashing guns have fully alerted me, and heaven-clouds canopy my city with a delicate thin haze,

When gorgeous the countless straight stems, the forests at the wharves, thicken with colors,

When every ship richly drest carries her flag at the peak,

When pennants trail and street-festoons hang from the windows,

When Broadway is entirely given up to foot-passengers and foot-standers, when the mass is densest,

When the façades of the houses are alive with people, when eyes gaze riveted tens of thousands at a time,

When the guests from the islands advance, when the pageant moves forward visible,

When the summons is made, when the answer that waited thousands of years answers,

I too arising, answering, descend to the pavements, merge with the crowd, and gaze with them.

2

Superb-faced Manhattan!

Comrade Americanos! to us, then at last the Orient comes.

To us, my city,

Where our tall-topt marble and iron beauties range on opposite sides, to walk in the space between,

To-day our Antipodes comes.

The Originatress comes,

The nest of languages, the bequeather of poems, the race of eld,

Florid with blood, pensive, rapt with musings, hot with passion,

Sultry with perfume, with ample and flowing garments,

With sunburnt visage, with intense soul and glittering eyes,

The race of Brahma comes.

See my cantabile! these and more are flashing to us from the procession,

As it moves changing, a kaleidoscope divine it moves changing before us.

For not the envoys nor the tann’d Japanee from his island only,

Lithe and silent the Hindoo appears, the Asiatic continent itself appears, the past, the dead,

The murky night-morning of wonder and fable inscrutable,

The envelop’d mysteries, the old and unknown hive-bees,

The north, the sweltering south, eastern Assyria, the Hebrews, the ancient of ancients,

Vast desolated cities, the gliding present, all of these and more are in the pageant-procession.

Geography, the world, is in it,

The Great Sea, the brood of islands, Polynesia, the coast beyond,

The coast you henceforth are facing — you Libertad! from your Western golden shores,

The countries there with their populations, the millions en-masse are curiously here,

The swarming market-places, the temples with idols ranged along the sides or at the end, bonze, brahmin, and llama,

Mandarin, farmer, merchant, mechanic, and fisherman,

The singing-girl and the dancing-girl, the ecstatic persons, the secluded emperors,

Confucious himself, the great poets and heroes, the warriors, the castes, all,

Trooping up, crowding from all directions, from the Altay mountains,

From Thibet, from the four winding and far-flowing rivers of China,

From the southern peninsulas and the demi-continental islands, from Malaysia,

These and whatever belongs to them palpable show forth to me, and are seiz’d by me,

And I am seiz’d by them, and friendlily held by them,

Till as here them all I chant, Libertad! for themselves and for you.

For I too raising my voice join the ranks of this pageant,

I am the chanter, I chant aloud over the pageant,

I chant the world on my Western sea,

I chant copious the islands beyond, thick as stars in the sky,

I chant the new empire grander than any before, as in a vision it comes to me,

I chant America the mistress, I chant a greater supremacy,

I chant projected a thousand blooming cities yet in time on those groups of sea-islands,

My sail-ships and steam-ships threading the archipelagoes,

My stars and stripes fluttering in the wind,

Commerce opening, the sleep of ages having done its work, races reborn, refresh’d,

Lives, works resumed — the object I know not — but the old, the Asiatic renew’d as it must be,

Commencing from this day surrounded by the world.

3

And you Libertad of the world!

You shall sit in the middle well-pois’d thousands and thousands of years,

As to-day from one side the nobles of Asia come to you,

As to-morrow from the other side the queen of England sends her eldest son to you.

The sign is reversing, the orb is enclosed,

The ring is circled, the journey is done,

The box-lid is but perceptibly open’d, nevertheless the perfume pours copiously out of the whole box.

Young Libertad! with the venerable Asia, the all-mother,

Be considerate with her now and ever hot Libertad, for you are all,

Bend your proud neck to the long-off mother now sending messages over the archipelagoes to you,

Bend your proud neck low for once, young Libertad.

Were the children straying westward so long? so wide the tramping?

Were the precedent dim ages debouching westward from Paradise so long?

Were the centuries steadily footing it that way, all the while unknown, for you, for reasons?

They are justified, they are accomplish’d, they shall now be turn’d the other way also, to travel toward you thence,

They shall now also march obediently eastward for your sake Libertad.

SEA-DRIFT

Out of the Cradle Endlessly Rocking

Out of the cradle endlessly rocking,

Out of the mocking-bird’s throat, the musical shuttle,

Out of the Ninth-month midnight,

Over the sterile sands and the fields beyond, where the child leaving his bed wander’d alone, bareheaded, barefoot,

Down from the shower’d halo,

Up from the mystic play of shadows twining and twisting as if they were alive,

Out from the patches of briers and blackberries,

From the memories of the bird that chanted to me,

From your memories sad brother, from the fitful risings and fallings I heard,

From under that yellow half-moon late-risen and swollen as if with tears,

From those beginning notes of yearning and love there in the mist,

From the thousand responses of my heart never to cease,

From the myriad thence-arous’d words,

From the word stronger and more delicious than any,

From such as now they start the scene revisiting,

As a flock, twittering, rising, or overhead passing,

Borne hither, ere all eludes me, hurriedly,

A man, yet by these tears a little boy again,

Throwing myself on the sand, confronting the waves,

I, chanter of pains and joys, uniter of here and hereafter,

Taking all hints to use them, but swiftly leaping beyond them,

A reminiscence sing.

Once Paumanok,

When the lilac-scent was in the air and Fifth-month grass was growing,

Up this seashore in some briers,

Two feather’d guests from Alabama, two together,

And their nest, and four light-green eggs spotted with brown,

And every day the he-bird to and fro near at hand,

And every day the she-bird crouch’d on her nest, silent, with bright eyes,

And every day I, a curious boy, never too close, never disturbing them,

Cautiously peering, absorbing, translating.

Shine! shine! shine!

Pour down your warmth, great sun!

While we bask, we two together.

Two together!

Winds blow south, or winds blow north,

Day come white, or night come black,

Home, or rivers and mountains from home,

Singing all time, minding no time,

While we two keep together.

Till of a sudden,

May-be kill’d, unknown to her mate,

One forenoon the she-bird crouch’d not on the nest,

Nor return’d that afternoon, nor the next,

Nor ever appear’d again.

And thenceforward all summer in the sound of the sea,

And at night under the full of the moon in calmer weather,

Over the hoarse surging of the sea,

Or flitting from brier to brier by day,

I saw, I heard at intervals the remaining one, the he-bird,

The solitary guest from Alabama.

Blow! blow! blow!

Blow up sea-winds along Paumanok’s shore;

I wait and I wait till you blow my mate to me.

Yes, when the stars glisten’d,

All night long on the prong of a moss-scallop’d stake,

Down almost amid the slapping waves,

Sat the lone singer wonderful causing tears.

He call’d on his mate,

He pour’d forth the meanings which I of all men know.

Yes my brother I know,

The rest might not, but I have treasur’d every note,

For more than once dimly down to the beach gliding,

Silent, avoiding the moonbeams, blending myself with the shadows,

Recalling now the obscure shapes, the echoes, the sounds and sights after their sorts,

The white arms out in the breakers tirelessly tossing,

I, with bare feet, a child, the wind wafting my hair,

Listen’d long and long.

Listen’d to keep, to sing, now translating the notes,

Following you my brother.

Soothe! soothe! soothe!

Close on its wave soothes the wave behind,

And again another behind embracing and lapping, every one close,

But my love soothes not me, not me.

Low hangs the moon, it rose late,

It is lagging-O I think it is heavy with love, with love.

O madly the sea pushes upon the land,

With love, with love.

O night! do I not see my love fluttering out among the breakers?

What is that little black thing I see there in the white?

Loud! loud! loud!

Loud I call to you, my love!

High and clear I shoot my voice over the waves,

Surely you must know who is here, is here,

You must know who I am, my love.

Low-hanging moon!

What is that dusky spot in your brown yellow?

O it is the shape, the shape of my mate!

O moon do not keep her from me any longer.

Land! land! O land!

Whichever way I turn, O I think you could give me my mate back again if you only would,

For I am almost sure I see her dimly whichever way I look.

O rising stars!

Perhaps the one I want so much will rise, will rise with some of you.

O throat! O trembling throat!

Sound clearer through the atmosphere!

Pierce the woods, the earth,

Somewhere listening to catch you must be the one I want.

Shake out carols!

Solitary here, the night’s carols!

Carols of lonesome love! death’s carols!

Carols under that lagging, yellow, waning moon!

O under that moon where she droops almost down into the sea!

O reckless despairing carols.

But soft! sink low!

Soft! let me just murmur,

And do you wait a moment you husky-nois’d sea,

For somewhere I believe I heard my mate responding to me,

So faint, I must be still, be still to listen,

But not altogether still, for then she might not come immediately to me.

Hither my love!

Here I am! here!

With this just-sustain’d note I announce myself to you,

This gentle call is for you my love, for you.

Do not be decoy’d elsewhere,

That is the whistle of the wind, it is not my voice,

That is the fluttering, the fluttering of the spray,

Those are the shadows of leaves.

O darkness! O in vain!

O I am very sick and sorrowful.

O brown halo in the sky near the moon, drooping upon the sea!

O troubled reflection in the sea!

O throat! O throbbing heart!

And I singing uselessly, uselessly all the night.

O past! O happy life! O songs of joy!

In the air, in the woods, over fields,

Loved! loved! loved! loved! loved!

But my mate no more, no more with me!

We two together no more.

The aria sinking,

All else continuing, the stars shining,

The winds blowing, the notes of the bird continuous echoing,

With angry moans the fierce old mother incessantly moaning,

On the sands of Paumanok’s shore gray and rustling,

The yellow half-moon enlarged, sagging down, drooping, the face of the sea almost touching,

The boy ecstatic, with his bare feet the waves, with his hair the atmosphere dallying,

The love in the heart long pent, now loose, now at last tumultuously bursting,

The aria’s meaning, the ears, the soul, swiftly depositing,

The strange tears down the cheeks coursing,

The colloquy there, the trio, each uttering,

The undertone, the savage old mother incessantly crying,

To the boy’s soul’s questions sullenly timing, some drown’d secret hissing,

To the outsetting bard.

Demon or bird! （said the boy’s soul,）

Is it indeed toward your mate you sing? or is it really to me?

For I, that was a child, my tongue’s use sleeping, now I have heard you,

Now in a moment I know what I am for, I awake,

And already a thousand singers, a thousand songs, clearer, louder and more sorrowful than yours,

A thousand warbling echoes have started to life within me, never to die.

O you singer solitary, singing by yourself, projecting me,

O solitary me listening, never more shall I cease perpetuating you,

Never more shall I escape, never more the reverberations,

Never more the cries of unsatisfied love be absent from me,

Never again leave me to be the peaceful child I was before what there in the night,

By the sea under the yellow and sagging moon,

The messenger there arous’d, the fire, the sweet hell within,

The unknown want, the destiny of me.

O give me the clew! （it lurks in the night here somewhere,）

O if I am to have so much, let me have more!

A word then, （for I will conquer it,）

The word final, superior to all,

Subtle, sent up — what is it? — I listen;

Are you whispering it, and have been all the time, you sea-waves?

Is that it from your liquid rims and wet sands?

Whereto answering, the sea,

Delaying not, hurrying not,

Whisper’d me through the night, and very plainly before daybreak,

Lisp’d to me the low and delicious word death,

And again death, death, death, death,

Hissing melodious, neither like the bird nor like my arous’d child’s heart,

But edging near as privately for me rustling at my feet,

Creeping thence steadily up to my ears and laving me softly all over,

Death, death, death, death, death.

Which I do not forget,

But fuse the song of my dusky demon and brother,

That he sang to me in the moonlight on Paumanok’s gray beach,

With the thousand responsive songs at random,

My own songs awaked from that hour,

And with them the key, the word up from the waves,

The word of the sweetest song and all songs,

That strong and delicious word which, creeping to my feet,

（Or like some old crone rocking the cradle, swathed in sweet garments, bending aside,）

The sea whisper’d me.

第一章　三英里十字标

/

这部传记的主人公，出自世人公认最古老的家族之一。因此，其名号之源起佚失不明，亦不足为奇。数百万年前，现今名为“西班牙”（Spain）的那个国家，在创世的混沌中躁动地翻腾不息。随着岁月流逝，植物出现了；根据自然规律，只要有植物的地方便会有兔子；而有兔子的地方，势必会有狗，这是上天的旨意。此事毋庸置疑，毫无争议。不过，说起为何捉兔子的狗被称作“西班牙猎犬”（Spaniel），疑难也就随之而来。有史学家提出，彼时迦太基人登陆西班牙，一干士兵齐声呼喊：“Span！Span！”因为每簇矮树中、每丛灌木里都有兔子飞蹿而出，陆地上热闹非凡，兔子遍地。而在迦太基语中，“span”即是“兔子”之意。因此，这块陆地便被称为“Hispania”，即“兔之乡”；而那些一看到兔子就撒腿开追的犬类，便被命名为西班牙猎犬，即猎兔犬。

我们中大多数人会满足于这种说法，不再深究。然而在真理的驱策下，有必要补充另一种截然不同的思路。有批学者声称，“Hispania”这个词与迦太基语中的“span”毫无关系，而是由巴斯克[1]语中的“españa”一词衍生而来，意为“边缘”或“边界”。若果真如此，就必须将这幅由兔子、灌木丛、狗与士兵构成的浪漫美好的图景从脑海中抹去，我们只能假定西班牙猎犬之所以得名，是因为西班牙被称为“españa”。第三派考古学者则坚持认为，正如一个男人会称呼自己的情妇“怪物”或“猴子”，西班牙人也会将自己最心爱的狗儿称作“弯弯”或“曲曲”（“españa”一词也包含这些意思）。但因为世人皆知西班牙猎犬的模样恰恰相反，所以这种猜测过于天马行空，不必当真。

略过上述乃至更多无须在此多言的理论，我们来到十世纪中叶的威尔士。那时西班牙猎犬这一品种已经出现，据说是好几个世纪前，由一个姓伊佛（Ebhor）或伊沃尔（Ivor）的西班牙家族引进，到了十世纪中叶俨然已是身价不菲的名犬。豪厄尔·达[2]在其《律法书》中记载道：“国王的西班牙猎犬价值一镑。”倘若我们回想一下一镑钱在公元九四八年能买到多少东西—多少妻妾、奴隶、马匹、公牛、火鸡和鹅—就会知道彼时西班牙猎犬已是价值连城、声名远扬了。它在国王身侧已有一席之地。其血统显赫历时之久，远胜于许多知名君主。当金雀花家族、都铎家族和斯图亚特家族还在别人家的田地里跟在人后扶犁躬耕时，它已安闲自在地身居皇宫了；当霍华德家族、卡文迪什家族和拉塞尔家族[3]尚未从史密斯、琼斯和汤姆金斯[4]们当中脱颖而出时，西班牙猎犬家族早已卓尔不群。时节如流，从西班牙猎犬的主干上又陆续分出一些旁支。随着历史滚滚向前，西班牙猎犬在英国逐渐分化出至少七个不同的著名品种—克伦伯长毛垂耳狗、苏塞克斯猎狗、诺福克梗犬、黑色田野猎犬、可卡犬、爱尔兰水猎犬及英格兰水犬。它们皆源自同一种史前西班牙猎犬，特征却各不相同，因此享有的特权自然也不尽相同。至伊丽莎白女王在位时，菲利普·西德尼爵士[5]在其著作《世外桃源》[6]中称犬类中亦有贵族。“……灵缇、西班牙猎犬和猎犬，”他评述道，“第一类可视为犬中王公贵族，第二类可视为绅士，最后一类则是犬辈中的草莽。”

但倘若我们可以由此假设西班牙猎犬会像人类一样，以灵缇为尊，以猎犬为贱，那我们就不得不承认，犬类的高低贵贱比人类的尊卑来得更合情理—至少，凡是研究过西班牙猎犬俱乐部章程的人都会得出这一结论。在西班牙猎犬高贵庄严的外表上，缺陷与优点都一目了然。例如，浅色眼睛就不受欢迎，卷曲的耳朵就更糟糕了，天生的淡色鼻子或头顶上的冠毛[7]堪称致命缺陷。同样，西班牙猎犬的优点也有明确的界定：头部必须平滑；口鼻须上扬，但幅度不可过于突兀；头盖骨要相对圆润，发育良好，有足够的空间容纳睿智的大脑；眼睛须饱满有神，但不至于向外鼓出；脸部表情应大体上显得聪慧而温和。具备这些特征的西班牙猎犬备受青睐，作育种之用；而那些经年累月顶着冠毛、长着淡色鼻子的西班牙猎犬，则被剥夺了族群的种种特权和奖赏。日后，裁决者便将此奉为铁律，同时赏罚分明，以确保令行禁止。

然而，反观人类社会，我们会发现尊卑贵贱的标准是何等混乱—令人费解！没有哪个机构有权裁定人种孰优孰劣，“纹章院”[8]或许是最接近西班牙猎犬俱乐部的组织了，至少在维护家族的正统性方面还下了些功夫。可当我们质问怎样才算出身高贵⸺眼睛的颜色应该是浅是深，耳朵应该是卷是直，头顶的髻毛是否至关重要，我们的裁决者看的却只是纹章罢了。或许你一枚纹章也没有，那你便是无名之辈。可一旦你能证明自己持有十六枚四等分纹章[9]，并有权佩戴冠状头饰，那么人们就会认为你不仅出身显赫，还是簪缨世族。因此在整个梅费尔[10]，所有的松饼保温盘上都刻有蹲伏的狮子或跃起的美人鱼，无一例外。就连我们的亚麻布商都要在门上镶嵌皇室纹章，仿佛那样就可以证明他们的床单睡着足够安全。声称自己出身高贵的人比比皆是，人人都强调头衔的价值。可当我们追溯像波旁[11]、哈布斯堡[12]还有霍亨索伦[13]那样的皇室，就不难发现，无论他们曾经头戴多少冠冕，身披多少四等分纹章，纹章上面又画着多少蹲伏或后足站立的狮子和豹子，他们如今都遭到罢黜，流亡在外，尊严尽失。见此情形，我们只能摇摇头，承认还是西班牙猎犬俱乐部的裁决者眼光独到。—将注意力从这些大事件上挪开，来看看弗勒希在米特福德（Mitford）家中度过的早期生活，我们就会直接认识到此言非虚。十八世纪尾叶前后，著名的西班牙猎犬中的一支居住在雷丁[14]附近某位米德福德（Midford）或米特福德博士家中。这位绅士遵从纹章院的规定，选用字母“t”拼写自己的姓氏，从而自称是伯特勒姆城堡的米特福德家族在诺森伯兰的旁系后裔。他的妻子娘家姓拉塞尔，是真正的贝德福德公爵家族的后裔，虽说只是远亲。然而，由于米特福德博士的祖先在择偶时十分草率任性，毫无原则，导致他自称的高贵血统无人承认，传宗接代的资格也被剥夺。他的眼睛颜色很浅，耳朵卷曲，头部还有那致命的顶髻。换言之，他是个极其自私自利、鲁莽豪奢、市侩俗气，毫无诚意—嗜赌成性的人。他败光了自己的财产、妻子的财产和女儿的收入。他飞黄腾达时抛妻弃女，体弱多病时又回来压榨她们。但他确有两项优势：一是容貌英俊—他原本貌如太阳神阿波罗，直到因暴饮暴食和酗酒无度而变成了酒神巴克斯；二是他真心实意地爱狗。然而毋庸置疑的是，若是真有相当于西班牙猎犬俱乐部的人类机构，就算把姓氏拼写中的“d”改成“t”，就算自称和伯特勒姆城堡的米特福德家族沾亲带故，他亦不能免遭侮辱蔑视、排挤放逐，或是免于恶名昭著，被视作不该传宗接代的“杂种”。不过他是个人类，所以没有什么能阻止他娶到一位出身世家、血统高贵的名媛，也没有什么可以阻止他活过耄耋之龄，豢养繁衍数代的灵缇和西班牙猎犬，并生养一个女儿。

所有对弗勒希确切出生年份的考据都以失败告终，月份和日子自然更不必提。不过他很可能生于一八四二年初，而—还极有可能是特雷（Tray，公元一八一六年生）的直系后代。可惜，能证明特雷是一条纯正的红色可卡犬的各项特质，只在诗歌这一不可靠的媒介中尚有记载。米特福德博士曾因特雷“在田野上表现优异”，拒绝以二十几尼[15]的价格把他卖掉，我们完全有理由相信弗勒希正是这条“纯种老可卡犬”之子。唉！对于幼年弗勒希的大部分细致描绘，我们也只能仰赖于诗歌了。他的毛色是那种特有的深棕色，在阳光照射下会闪闪发光，变成“通体金黄”。他“淡褐色的温柔眼眸透着惊异”，耳朵犹如“流苏”，“纤细的脚”上“穗毛覆盖”，尾巴粗壮。抛去押韵的需要和诗歌语言的不准确性，以上特征无不符合西班牙猎犬俱乐部的认证标准。我们不能否认，弗勒希的确是一条纯种的红色可卡犬，—具有该犬种所有的完美特征。

出生后的头几个月，他住在雷丁附近一间名为“三英里十字标”的雇工小屋里。米特福德家穷困潦倒—克伦哈波克是仅有的仆人—连椅套也由米特福德小姐亲手缝制，用的是最廉价的布料；家里最重要的家具似乎是一张大桌子，最重要的房间是一间宽敞的温室。弗勒希不可能享受到豪华的待遇，譬如防雨犬舍，散步的水泥道，伴随左右的女仆或男仆，而眼下，这些本应是他这种等级的狗理当享有的。不过他依然茁壮成长—他天性活泼，尽情享受着青春和性别天然赋予他的大多数乐趣及某些特权。米特福德小姐确实常常足不出户。她必须连续数小时为父亲高声朗读，再陪他玩克里比奇牌戏[16]。等他终于呼呼大睡后，她还得在温室的桌前不停地写啊写啊写啊，设法付账和还债。但最终，期待已久的时刻总算到来。她会把纸张推到一旁，扣上帽子，拿起雨伞，带着她的狗儿们去田野散步。西班牙猎犬天生极通人性，而弗勒希，正如他的故事所证明的那样，对人类情绪更是有着超乎寻常的敏锐感知力。看见亲爱的女主人总算能呼吸新鲜空气，任由风吹乱她的银发，为她自然清爽的脸庞增添红润，抚平她宽大眉头上的皱纹，他开心得欢欣雀跃—那种狂野一半是受她的喜悦感染。她大步穿过高高的草丛，他则四处跳跃着，不断拨开绿色的帘幕。清凉的露珠和雨滴在他鼻子周围散成一道道七彩的雾气，地面忽硬忽软、忽热忽冷，硌着、挠着、搔着他脚底柔软的肉垫。林林总总的味道微妙地交织杂糅，刺激着他的鼻孔：泥土浓郁的气息，花朵香甜的味道，树叶和荆棘无可名状的气味，穿过道路时的酸味儿，进入豆田间的呛鼻味儿。猛然，风刮来一股味道，比任何气味都更刺激、更浓烈、更折磨人—那味道扯开他的大脑，激发了千般直觉，释放出万种回忆—那是野兔的味道，是狐狸的味道。他仿佛被湍流裹挟的鱼儿，遽然一闪，越奔越远。他忘记了女主人，忘记了一切人类。他听见黑皮肤的人影高喊着：“Span！Span！”他听见鞭子劈啪抽打的声音。他拼命跑啊冲啊。终于，魔咒的力量消退了，他停下来，满是困惑，难为情地摇着尾巴，慢慢地小跑着穿过田野，回到米特福德小姐身旁。她正站在那里一边高喊：“弗勒希！弗勒希！弗勒希！”一边挥舞着雨伞。但至少有那么一次，天性的召唤变得尤为不可抗拒—狩猎的号角激起他内心深处的本能，唤醒了一种更狂暴、更强烈的情绪。在一声欣喜若狂的野性呼唤中，他跨越了一切记忆，抹去草丛、树木、野兔和狐狸。爱在他眼中点燃了火炬，他听见了维纳斯狩猎的号角！就这样，在远未脱离幼犬期时，弗勒希就当了父亲。

在一八四二年，即使是男子有了这种行为，也必须让作传之人找个借口替他搪塞过去；倘若是女人，则任何借口都不顶用，必须将她的名字可耻地从书中彻底抹去。不过，狗的道德标准，无论更好或更糟，总之必定与我们人类的标准大相径庭。从这点来看，弗勒希的行为，不仅在今日无须遮遮掩掩，即便在当时也不会为世上最纯洁、最坚贞的群体所不容。这句话绝非空口无凭，证据便是，皮由兹博士[17]的长兄迫切地希望买下弗勒希。根据皮由兹博士的性格，我们可以推断其兄长可能的性格，并由此断定，无论幼时何等轻浮，弗勒希身上想必具备某种严谨稳重、前途无量的潜能，预示了其未来的优异性情。不过他可爱的天性还有另一项更加重要的证明，那就是尽管皮由兹先生想买，米特福德小姐却拒绝出售。在赚钱这件事情上她已黔驴技穷，完全不知道下部悲剧该写什么，下部年鉴如何编制，甚至不得不咬咬牙暂时向朋友求助。对她而言，拒绝皮由兹博士兄长的那笔钱定非易事。曾经有人出价二十英镑买弗勒希的父亲，米特福德小姐大可以为弗勒希要价十到十五英镑。这可是个大数目，拿在手上是一笔可观的钱财。有了这十到十五英镑，她可以更换新椅套，重新在温室种满花花草草，为自己添置衣柜和满满一柜子服饰—“整整四年，”她在一八四二年写道，“我都没有买过一顶软帽、一件斗篷、一条长裙，甚至一副手套。”

但卖掉弗勒希绝无可能。他是少数与金钱无关的事物之一。而在这些事物当中，有一类更为珍贵，它们是精神的象征，是无价之宝，是无私友谊最恰当的代表。弗勒希难道不正是这种事物？难道她不该秉着友谊的精神，把他送给一位挚友—如果一个人真能有幸结识这样一位—一位与其说是朋友，更像是女儿的挚友？这位朋友整个夏季都与世隔绝，待在温波尔街某宅邸后侧的卧室里。这位朋友不是别人，正是英国首屈一指的女诗人，才华横溢、命运多舛、受人爱戴的伊丽莎白·巴雷特[18]本人！每当米特福德小姐注视着在阳光下翻滚跳跃的弗勒希，每当她身处巴雷特小姐的伦敦住所，坐在那间笼罩于常春藤阴影下的幽暗卧室里的一张长沙发上，这想法便愈加频繁地从她脑海中闪过。没错，弗勒希配得上巴雷特小姐，巴雷特小姐也配得上弗勒希。这是巨大的牺牲，也是必要的牺牲。因此，大概是在一八四二年初夏的某一天，或许有人看见惹人注目的一人一犬沿温波尔街而行—一位矮小敦实、衣衫褴褛的年长女士，面色红润、满鬓苍白，用狗链牵着一条精力异常充沛、好奇心极重、血统绝对纯正的金色小可卡犬。他们几乎走完了整条街，一直到五十号门前才终于停住。米特福德小姐略带惶恐地按响门铃。

哪怕是今天，依然没有人能不带惶恐地按响温波尔街上那些宅邸的门铃。那是伦敦街道中最庄严肃穆、最没有人情味的一条。的确，当整个世界仿佛即将毁于一旦、文明的基石摇摇欲坠时，你只消去一趟温波尔街，漫步在那条林荫道上，看一眼那些房子，思索它们的整齐划一，去为那些如出一辙的窗帘惊叹，去欣赏那些端正匀称的黄铜门环，观察屠夫解牛、厨工买肉，暗自估算那些住户的收入并推想他们随后也不免顺应上帝的安排，走向人生必然的结局；你只消去温波尔街，深吸一口权贵们呼吸的宁静空气，就能满怀感激地长叹一声：纵使科林斯[19]陷落、墨西拿[20]震毁，多少王权随风而逝，多少古代帝国已化为灰烬，温波尔街却始终岿然不动。从温波尔街转入牛津街，一声祷告便从心头冉冉升起，涌上嘴边：但愿温波尔街的一砖一瓦都不会重砌，每幅窗帘都无须清洗，屠夫终日供应，厨工始终能买到里脊肉、腰腿肉、胸脯肉、羊排及牛肉，但愿这一切永不改变，直到永远。因为只要温波尔街存在一天，文明便可存续。

纵然是现在，温波尔街管家们的举止仍然一板一眼，而在一八四二年的夏天，他们更是小心翼翼。当时穿戴制服的规矩远比现在严苛：擦拭银器时须系戴绿色粗呢围裙，开启大门时须穿条纹马甲及黑色燕尾服，诸如此类的礼节都要严格遵守。因此米特福德小姐和弗勒希很有可能在门口等了至少有三分半钟。不过终于，五十号的大门轰然洞开，米特福德小姐和弗勒希被请入室内。米特福德小姐是这里的常客，尽管早已见惯眼前的巴雷特宅邸，却依旧为之折服。可面对此景，弗勒希感受到的无疑是难以抗拒、无与伦比的震撼。直到这一刻，除了三英里十字标的那间雇工小屋，他从未踏足任何其他住宅。小屋的木板光秃秃的，垫子均已磨损，座椅都很廉价。而这里没有一样东西是光秃秃的，没有一样东西是磨损的，也没有一样东西是廉价的—这弗勒希一眼就能看出来。主人，巴雷特先生，是位富商，家中人丁兴旺，有不少已经成年的儿女，还有与之相称的众多仆役。他的住宅装潢符合十九世纪三十年代晚期的流行风尚，无疑还带着些许东方风韵。正因为对东方着迷，他才在什罗普郡建造了一栋宅邸，为其装点上摩尔式建筑[21]中常见的穹顶与新月标志。温波尔街不会容忍那种奢靡，但我们可以想见，在那些高大幽暗的房间里，必定摆满了铺有软垫的厢式凳子和桃花心木雕刻，桌脚弯曲盘绕，金银丝线细工饰品端放其上；匕首与刀剑挂在深酒红色的墙壁上；壁龛中摆着他从东印度带回来的奇珍异宝，地板上铺着厚实的名贵地毯。

不过，当米特福德小姐跟着男管家，弗勒希跟在米特福德小姐身后小步走着时，鼻中所闻比眼前所见更令他吃惊。从楼梯的通风井飘来阵阵温暖的香气，来自烹制的烤肉、浇在禽肉上的卤汁和文火炖的汤—对鼻孔而言，要是闻惯了克伦哈波克每餐给的少得可怜的炸薯条和肉末土豆散发出的乏善可陈的味道，这些香味几乎和食物本身一样令人沉醉。和食物香气掺杂在一起的，还有很多其他的味道—杉木、檀香木和桃花心木的味道，男人与女人身体的气息，男仆和女仆的气息，外套和长裤的味道，硬布裙和斗篷的味道，织锦窗帘的味道，丝绒窗帘的味道，煤渣和雾的味道，红酒和雪茄的味道。他经过的每一个房间—餐厅、起居室、图书室、卧室—都飘出自己特有的味道，它们交织在一起，混合成屋内的总体气味。要是他先踏出一只脚爪，再迈出另一只，脚掌便会陷入柔软厚重的地毯中，因其充满柔情蜜意的爱抚而难以抬起。最后，他们来到房子尽头一扇关闭的门前，轻叩一下，门就轻轻开了。

巴雷特小姐的卧房想必一片幽暗—一如往常，正像各方记载的那样。绿色锦缎窗帘本就会将光线遮去不少，而到了夏天，窗台花盆中的常春藤、红花菜豆、田旋花和旱金莲还纷纷冒出，让光线更加昏暗。一开始，在这片暗淡的绿色阴翳中，弗勒希只看见五个白色球体在半空中神秘莫测地闪烁，其余便什么都辨认不出了。这次，又是屋内的气味率先震慑住了他。想象一位学者一步步踱下台阶，进入一座陵墓，发现自己身处地下墓穴之中，里面覆满霉菌、泥土黏滑，充斥着腐朽—久远的酸臭味，而他只能借着手中那盏摇晃不停的小灯发出的光芒，模糊地看见几座半毁的大理石半身像在半空中闪闪发光，就这么深一脚浅一脚地来回转变着方向，瞥一眼这里，瞧一眼那里—只有这样一位探险家在古城废墟之下踏入墓穴时的种种心境，方可与弗勒希在温波尔街初次踏入病患卧室，并被古龙水的味道拨乱了每根神经时那种混乱的情感相提并论。

弗勒希非常缓慢而轻悄地用鼻子不断嗅闻，用脚爪不停抓刨，逐渐分辨出几件家具的轮廓。窗旁的庞然大物或许是个衣橱，旁边那个想来必是斗柜。房间中央逐步显形的像是一张镶了边的桌子，接着，扶手椅和书桌模糊而怪异的形状也慢慢显露。但是每样东西都经过乔装打扮。衣橱顶部立着三尊白色半身像；斗柜上高高竖起一个书架，书架又盖着猩红色的美利奴羊毛织物；盥洗台上装了一圈冠状的搁架，搁架上又立着另外两尊半身像。房间内没有一件东西保持原貌，每样东西同时又是另一样东西，就连遮光帘也不是普通薄纱制成的，而采用了精心设计的彩绘织物[1]，上面画着城堡、城门、树林，还有几个正在散步的农人。梳妆镜的反射把所有物体照得更加扭曲，以至于屋内仿佛有十尊诗人的半身像而不是五尊，有四张桌子而不是两张。冷不丁，弗勒希生出一种更可怕的困惑。透过墙上的洞，他猛地瞥见了另一条狗，双目炯炯闪烁，吐着舌头，正盯着自己看！他目瞪口呆地僵在那里，随后满怀敬畏地走向前。

弗勒希就这样一会儿进一会儿退，几乎没听到低声细语、喋喋不休的说话声，只当是远方的风呼呼地拂过树梢。他谨小慎微、如履薄冰地继续勘查，就如探险家在森林中前进时，将步伐轻抬轻放，不确定阴影处是否藏着一头狮子，或某段树根是不是条眼镜蛇。然而最后，他意识到有几个庞然大物在自己头顶上喧哗，由于先前那一小时已经被弄得神经衰弱，他颤抖着躲到一扇屏风后。说话声停止了。一扇门关上了。一时间，他愣住了，既困惑又紧张。随后，记忆仿若张牙舞爪的老虎朝他扑将过来。他觉得自己孤立寡与—被遗弃了。他冲到门边，门是关着的。他抓挠着，倾听着。他听见正在下楼的脚步声。他听得出，那是女主人熟悉的脚步。脚步声戛然而止。—慢—声音再度响起，继续下楼而去。米特福德小姐正缓慢地拖着沉重的步伐，不情不愿地走下楼。她离开了，他听见她的脚步声渐行渐远，他被恐慌攫住了。随着米特福德小姐一步一步走下台阶，一扇又一扇门在他面前关上，随之一起远去的还有自由、田野、野兔、草地，以及他热爱、尊敬的女主人—那为他洗澡，打他，即便自己食不果腹却仍与他分享盘中食物的可亲可爱的老妇人—同样关闭的还有他所知晓的一切快乐、爱与人类的善意！不好！前门也砰的一声合上了！他孤零零的。她把他抛弃了。

接着，绝望与痛苦之浪将他淹没，不可挽回、冷酷无情的命运将他击倒，他仰首长啸。一个声音唤道：“弗勒希。”他没有听见。那声音又唤了一遍：“弗勒希。”他大吃一惊。他原以为自己遗世独立。他转过身。难道房间里还有什么活物跟他在一起？沙发上有东西吗？无论那是什么，他只奢望这东西能去把门打开，这样他还有可能冲出去追上米特福德小姐，然后发现一切不过是一场捉迷藏的游戏，就像他们从前在家里的温室玩的一样—弗勒希箭步奔向沙发。

“噢，弗勒希！”巴雷特小姐喊道。生平第一次，她面对面看到他的脸；生平第一次，弗勒希看到了那位躺在沙发上的女士。

他们俩都惊诧万分。浓密的鬈发从巴雷特小姐的脸颊两侧垂荡下来，明亮的大眼睛熠熠生辉，一张大嘴带着笑意。弗勒希的两片大耳朵从脸颊两边垂下来，眼睛同样又大又亮，嘴也很宽。他们长得有些相像。他们互相注视时，心里都觉察到：这是我！—随即又想到：可我们又是多么不同！她有一张体弱多病、苍白憔悴的脸，一直以来与空气、光线和自由隔绝。他则有着动物幼崽红润温热的脸，健康—充满活力。各不相同，却又像是从一个模子里铸出来似的，他俩能否彼此唤醒对方身上蛰伏的个性，使对方更加完整呢？原来她本可以是—这样；而他—噢，不！他俩之间隔着一道世间最不可逾越的物种鸿沟。她会说话，他却不能。她是个女人，他却是条狗。就这样，他们凝望着对方，如此惺惺相惜，却又如此迥然相异。然后，弗勒希纵身一跃，跳上沙发，趴到此后将永远属于他的地盘—巴雷特小姐脚边的毯子上。

[1]巴斯克（Basque），欧洲比利牛斯山西部地区的古老居民，绝大多数居住在西班牙北部，是欧洲民族风俗、传统服饰保存最为完好的一个民族。（说明：书中脚注均为译者注。）

[2]豪厄尔·达（Howel Dda，约880-950），公元10世纪时的威尔士国王，曾被尊称为“所有威尔士人的国王”。

[3]霍华德、卡文迪什和拉塞尔皆为英国知名的贵族姓氏。

[4]史密斯、琼斯和汤姆金斯是英国最为常见的平民姓氏。

[5]菲利普·西德尼爵士（Sir Philip Sidney，1554-1586），伊丽莎白一世时期的廷臣、政治家、诗人和学者，被认为是当时的模范绅士。

[6]此书的全名为《彭布罗克女伯爵的世外桃源》（The Countesse of Pembroke’s Arcadia），是西德尼所写最长、最有名的散文体田园传奇故事。

[7]犬类头顶的波浪状毛发。

[8]西欧自公元12世纪始普遍使用纹章图案，因为从一开始纹章的使用就与封建等级有关，到中世纪后期，佩戴纹章表示出身高贵。英国纹章院建立于1484年，院长为世袭职位。

[9]将盾四等分以显示继承权的一种方法。一个纹章持有者的婚生子孙及一个纹章女继承人将继承两枚纹章，在父母死亡时，该纹章将在盾上分成四等份。

[10]梅费尔（Mayfair），伦敦市上流住宅区。

[11]波旁（Bourbon），是欧洲历史上一个跨国王朝，曾断断续续地统治过纳瓦拉、法国、西班牙、那不勒斯与西西里、卢森堡等国，以及意大利若干公国。

[12]哈布斯堡（Hapsburg），欧洲历史上最强大、统治领域最广的皇室，曾统治神圣罗马帝国、西班牙王国、奥地利大公国、奥地利帝国、奥匈帝国。

[13]霍亨索伦（Hohenzollern），欧洲的三大王朝之一，为勃兰登堡·普鲁士（1415-1918）及德意志帝国（1871-1918）的主要统治家族。

[14]雷丁（Reading），英格兰南部伯克郡首府。

[15]1663年英国发行的一种金币，等于21先令，1813年停止流通。后仅指等于21先令（即1.05英镑）的币值单位，常用于规定费用、价格等。

[16]克里比奇牌戏，一种双人、三人或四人玩的纸牌戏，用插在有孔的记分板上的小钉记分。

[17]皮由兹（Edward Bouverie Pusey，1800-1882），英国东方语言学家、科学家，英国国教会内牛津运动的领导人之一。

[18]伊丽莎白·巴雷特（Elizabeth Barrett，1806-1861），英国维多利亚时代最受人尊敬的诗人之一。15岁时不幸骑马跌损了脊椎，从此下肢瘫痪达24年。她39岁那年结识了小她6岁的诗人罗伯特·勃朗宁，生命从此揭开了新的篇章。

[19]科林斯（Corinth），古希腊南部海港城市，地处海峡要冲，是当时最强大繁荣的城市之一，后多次被攻陷和洗劫。

[20]墨西拿（Messina），位于意大利西西里岛的东端，为海峡最窄处，乃欧洲大陆进入西西里岛的隘口，多次在地震中倾覆。

[21]指摩尔人结合伊斯兰教与基督教艺术风格创造的一种建筑类型，其特色包含不加装饰的拱顶、简单的马蹄形圆拱，或是拥有繁复装饰的拱形、有亮丽釉彩的青花磁砖，以及阿拉伯文或者几何图形的装饰。

第二章　后面的房间

/

历史学家告诉我们，一八四二年的夏天只是一个平凡的夏天，然而对弗勒希来说，这个夏天是如此不同，他想必一定怀疑过这世界是否依然如故。那是一个在卧室里度过的夏天，是和巴雷特小姐一起度过的夏天，是在文明的心脏伦敦度过的夏天。起初，他除了那间卧室和里面的家具之外，看不到任何其他东西；但仅这些就够他大开眼界了。光是识别、区分并正确称呼他在那儿见到的这些各不相同的物什，就足以令他晕头转向。还没等他习惯那些桌子、半身像和盥洗台—他依然闻不惯古龙水的味道—他们就碰上一个难得的好天气：晴朗无风，暖而不热，干爽无尘，适合一个久卧病榻的人出去透透气。这一天来了，巴雷特小姐可以安心地进行大冒险，和姐妹一起出门购物。

叫好了马车，巴雷特小姐从沙发上起身，蒙上面纱，把自己包裹严实，走下楼梯。弗勒希当然跟着她一起去了。他一跃跳进马车，来到女主人身旁。他蜷缩在她的膝头，整个伦敦最壮观的盛况蓦地呈现在他面前，令他满眼惊奇。他们驶过牛津街。他看见几乎完全用玻璃盖成的房子，看见光彩夺目的饰带在窗前交叉着系在一起，窗沿上堆满了小丘似的粉红、紫色、黄色和玫瑰色的璀璨花朵。马车停了下来。他走进充满神秘感的拱廊商场，笼罩在彩色薄纱织成的云彩和罗网之中。上百万种从中国与阿拉伯远道而来的微弱、易散的芬芳钻入他的感官深处。柜台上长而亮泽的丝绸锦缎轻快地一闪而过，厚重的邦巴辛毛葛[22]缓缓卷动，色泽更为深沉。剪刀咔嚓作响，钱币闪闪发光，纸张折了又折，绳带系了又系。轻轻点头的羽饰，随风飘扬的饰带，仰首抬头的马儿，身披黄色制服的仆役，一晃而过的脸孔，一切都跳跃着，上上下下地舞蹈着。弗勒希沉浸在这包罗万象的感受中，满足地打盹、入眠、做梦，渐渐不省人事，直到被抱出车厢，温波尔街的大门再次在他身后合上。

翌日，见天气依旧宜人，巴雷特小姐勇敢地尝试了一项更为大胆的冒险—坐在巴思椅[23]上，让人推着她去温波尔街散步。弗勒希又一次陪她出门。他头一回听见自己的爪子在伦敦坚硬的人行道铺路石上嗒嗒作响。炎炎夏日里，伦敦街道散发出的所有气味头一回对他的鼻孔展开了猛烈进攻。他闻到排水沟里令人昏厥的臭味、铁栏杆腐蚀后发出的苦味、地下室里腾起的浓烈烟熏味—这些气味比他在雷丁周边的田野中闻到过的任何气味都要复杂、腐败，它们相互抵触、混合杂陈，超越了人类嗅觉可以辨别的范畴。因此尽管巴思椅不停前进，他却停下了脚步，惊愕地识别并细细品味这些气味，直到项圈被猛地一扯，被拽着继续前行。当他跟着巴雷特小姐的巴思椅在温波尔街上散步时，川流不息的人类躯体亦令他头晕目眩。硬衬裙在他头顶飕飕摆动，长裤刷过他的侧身，车轮时而擦着它的鼻尖碾过，驶过的货车携来极具破坏性的狂风，在他耳畔咆哮，掀动他脚掌周围的长毛。于是他惊惶地俯冲。幸运的是，项圈上的铁链拉住了他，巴雷特小姐把他紧紧抱在怀里，否则他说不定就冲出去出事了。

终于，带着每一根怦怦跳动的神经、每一种嗡嗡作响的感官，弗勒希总算来到了摄政公园。当他再次见到似乎阔别了多年的绿草、繁花和树林，昔日田野里狩猎的号角就响彻耳际，他立刻向前冲去，渴望像当年在家乡的田野里那般驰骋。然而，此刻却有某种沉重的力量卡在他颈部，使他向后踉跄跌倒。那儿难道不是树林和草丛吗？他问道。这些难道不是自由的信号吗？每次米特福德小姐出门散步时，他不都是径直向前冲吗？为什么在这里他却成了囚徒呢？他停下了脚步。在这儿，他观察到，团簇的花朵比老家的那些紧密得多，它们一株株整齐而僵硬地排列在窄小的地里，中间隔着一条条坚实的黑色步道。男士们头戴泛着光泽的高筒礼帽，脸色阴沉地在步道上来回走动。见到他们，他颤抖地靠近巴思椅，欣然接受了链条的庇护。于是，在对类似的散步习以为常之前，他脑中已经生成了一个全新的概念。通过拼凑各种现象，他得出一个结论：有花床的地方，就会有沥青步道；有花床和沥青步道的地方，就会有戴泛着光泽的高筒礼帽的男士们；有花床、沥青步道及戴泛着光泽的高筒礼帽的男士们的地方，狗就得用链条牵着。尽管公园大门告示上写的字他一个也不认识，却已无师自通地学会了一课—在摄政公园里，狗都必须用链条牵着。

从一八四二年夏天的种种奇妙体验中获得的核心知识，很快让他又新长了见识：犬类并不平等，而—是互不相同的。以前在三英里十字标，弗勒希不分轩轾地与小酒馆里的狗及乡绅的灵缇厮混，并不知道补锅匠的狗和自己有什么区别。而他孩子的母亲，虽美其名曰西班牙猎犬，也很可能只是条杂种狗，不是耳朵有所偏差，就是尾巴美中不足。然而，弗勒希很快便发现，伦敦的犬类严格地按照等级划分：有的狗拴了链条，有些则整天乱跑；有些坐马车出门透气，用紫色罐子喝水，有些却蓬头垢面、不戴项圈，在排水沟中苟—偷生。由此，弗勒希开始怀疑，或许狗也分三六九等，有些是高等的，另一些是低等的。偶尔，他会捕捉到人们对温波尔街上的狗评头论足的只言片语，由此证实了自己的猜测：“看见那条无赖没，绝对是杂种狗！……哎呀老天爷，这条西班牙猎犬真漂亮，绝对是英国血统最纯正的之一！……可惜啊，他的耳朵要是能再卷一点儿就好了……看他的头顶还有顶髻！”

从男仆们站在邮筒旁或酒馆外交换赛马情报时说出的此类话语，还有他们或赞美或奚落的语调中，弗勒希在夏天结束前就明白了犬类之间也没有什么平等可言：有些狗尊贵，有些狗低贱。那么，他属于哪一类呢？弗勒希一回到家，就迫不及待地对着镜子仔细地审视起自己来。谢天谢地，他天生是条血统尊贵的狗！他的头部顺滑，眼睛凸出却不鼓起，脚周围覆盖着长毛，可以媲美温波尔街上血统最纯正的可卡猎犬。他满意地注意到自己喝水用的是紫色的水罐—那是他这个阶层的特权。他默默地低下脑袋，让链条扣住他的项圈—这是这一阶层必须付出的代价。差不多就在这时，巴雷特小姐注意到他瞪着镜子发愣，却做出了错误的判断。他是个哲学家，她思忖着，他准是在思索表象和现实之间的差别。事实正好相反，他其实是个贵族，正孤芳自赏呢！

可是夏日的好天气稍纵即逝。秋风渐起，巴雷特小姐又在自己的卧房安营扎寨，彻底过起了与世隔绝的生活。弗勒希的生活也同样发生了改变。在户外接受了一番教育之后，他如今又得在室内接受教育，而后者对弗勒希这种脾性的狗而言，无疑是史无前例的酷刑了。他唯有在巴雷特小姐的女仆威尔逊的陪伴下才能出门透气，出门时间往往又极短，马虎了事。其余时间他只能待在沙发上，蜷缩在巴雷特小姐脚边。这完全阻碍了他的本能，与他的天性背道而驰。去年，当伯克郡刮起阵阵秋风时，他还能在野地里奔跑，在收割后留下的麦茬堆间欢快地蹦跳；如今，当常春藤轻轻叩响窗玻璃时，巴雷特小姐就吩咐威尔逊去检查窗户有没有关紧。看到窗台花盆里栽种的红花菜豆和旱金莲的叶子渐渐变黄枯败，她把身上的印度披肩裹得更严实了。当十月的雨猛烈地敲打窗户，威尔逊便燃起壁炉，将煤炭堆得高高的。秋意渐浓，随后入冬，第一场雾染黄了空气。威尔逊和弗勒希甚至没法摸索着走到邮筒或药剂师那儿去。他们折回家后，发现房里一片昏暗，什么都看不清，只有那几尊惨白的半身像在衣橱上反射着黯淡的光。遮光帘上的农人和城堡都消失不见了，窗户玻璃上只能映出一片平淡无奇的黄色。弗勒希觉得自己和巴雷特小姐就像单独住在一个铺满垫褥、燃着炉火的洞穴里。屋外的车马络绎不绝，发出低沉模糊的回响；时不时会有嘶哑的叫声从下方的街道传来，“修旧椅子旧篮子喽”；有时又会传来阵阵管风琴的乐声，声音先是越来越近、越来越响，再一路远去、逐渐消失。但这些声音中没有一种意味着自由、行动或运动。无论是风雨交加的日子，还是富有自然气息的秋日，抑或是寒气逼人的隆冬，如今在弗勒希看来都同样毫无意义，他眼中只剩下温暖和静止，台灯的柔光，以及拉窗帘和拨捣炉火的动作。

一开始，这种感觉令他难以承受。若碰上多风的秋日，想到山鹑零零散散地在麦茬堆里栖息，他就忍不住绕着房间蹦跶。他仿佛在微风中听到了枪声。每当外面传来犬吠，他就会忍不住竖起颈毛，冲到门边。可只要巴雷特小姐唤他回去，并把手放在他的项圈上，他又无法抗拒另一种感觉—它如此急迫、矛盾、令人不悦—他不知道该如何称呼它，也不知道自己为什么会屈服于它。他一动不动地趴在她的脚边，驯服着、控制着、压抑着自己天性当中最强烈的本能—那便是他在卧室学校学到的最重要的一课，其难度之高，许多学者学习希腊语时都不曾如此费劲；在众多战役里，将军们为获胜付出的艰辛还不及它的一半。但彼时，巴雷特小姐就是老师。随着日子一周周过去，弗勒希越发强烈地感受到，他俩之间存在某种紧密的纽带，令人不适却又振奋人心。因此，倘若他的快乐会使她痛苦，那么他的快乐将不再是快乐，而是三倍的痛苦。这不争的事实每天都可以得到验证。有人开了门，吹着口哨唤他过去。他为什么不愿出去呢？他明明渴望新鲜空气和运动，长时间趴在沙发上已使他的四肢痉挛疼痛。他也始终闻不惯古龙水的味道。可是不行—尽管门敞开着，他也不愿从巴雷特小姐身边离开。他踌躇着走向门口，半路又折回沙发旁。“弗勒希，”巴雷特小姐写道，“是我的朋友—我的伙伴—爱我胜过爱屋外的阳光。”她没法出门，被桎梏于沙发上。“笼中鸟也有好故事。”她这样写道，事实也的确如此。而弗勒希呢，他本可以自由地拥抱整个世界，却选择放弃了温波尔街上的各种气味，只为陪伴在她左右。

然而，有时那纽带却几近断裂；他俩之间存在着理解上的鸿沟。有时他们会躺着互相凝视，脸上都写满了困惑。为什么，巴雷特小姐纳闷着，弗勒希会突然颤抖，发出呜咽的声音，猛地惊起并竖着耳朵听着什么。她什么也听不见，什么也看不到，房间里除了他俩别无他人。她完全猜不到原来是她姐妹养的查理王小猎犬福利刚从门外经过，或是某位仆役刚在地下室赏给那只古巴寻血犬卡蒂利内一根羊骨头。可是弗勒希对此一清二楚，他全都听见了，欲望与贪婪交替起伏，令他躁动难安。然而巴雷特小姐即使凭借诗人的卓越想象力，也无法猜透威尔逊那湿漉漉的雨伞对弗勒希而言意味着什么，不知道这会触发他怎样的回忆—他忆起森林和鹦鹉，还有哞哞叫着的野象；她也不可能知道，当凯尼恩先生被拉铃绳绊了个踉跄时，弗勒希听到的是黝黑的人影在山中咒骂，耳边萦绕的是一声声“Span！Span！”，在一阵含糊不清、融于血脉的狂怒中，他咬了这位先生。

同样的，弗勒希也琢磨不透巴雷特小姐的情绪。她竟可以手里拿着一根黑色的棍子，在一张白纸上来回划动，这么一躺就是好几个小时。她的眼睛里会突然盈满泪水，可这是为什么呢？“噢，我亲爱的霍恩先生，”她写道，“随后我的健康状况江河日下……接下来就被迫去托基[24]放逐自己了……那成了我终生的噩梦，它从我的生命中夺走了太多，我在信中无法尽述；请您在任何情况下都不要提起。千万不要提及，亲爱的霍恩先生。”可房间里并没有什么声音或气味能惹哭巴雷特小姐啊。还有一次，巴雷特小姐依然挥舞着那根黑色棍子，却突然爆发出一阵笑声。她刚画好一张“简洁传神的弗勒希画像，滑稽得与我相像”。她在图下写道，可惜他“不完全是我的替身，因为他比我有用得多”。她向弗勒希展示的那团黑色污迹有什么好笑的呢？他什么都闻不到，什么都听不见，屋子里除了他俩，并无他人。事实是他俩无法用言语交流，而这无疑引发了诸多误会。然而，这难道不也构成了他们之间一种特殊的亲密吗？“写作，”一次巴雷特小姐在一上午的艰辛创作后慨叹道，“写作，写作……”或许她确曾怀疑过：文字是否真的可以道尽一切？文字是否真能表达什么？文字难道不会摧毁那些超越文字的象征意义吗？至少有那么一次，巴雷特小姐似乎真这么认为。她当时正躺着，陷入沉思，完全忘了弗勒希的存在，心中的思绪是如此哀伤，以至于泪水滴落枕上。忽然间，有个毛茸茸的脑袋压在了她身上：大而明亮的双眼在她眼前闪烁。她一惊，那是弗勒希吗，还是牧羊的潘神？难道她不再是一个住在温波尔街上的病人，而成了阿卡狄亚[25]某片阴暗幽深树林中的希腊仙子？亲吻她嘴唇的，是那位蓄满虬髯的山神吗？在那一瞬间，她化身为林中仙子，弗勒希则变成了潘。太阳在燃烧，爱迸发出光芒。但假使弗勒希真能开口说话—他难道不是早该对爱尔兰的马铃薯病害发表一番真知灼见吗？

弗勒希的心中也涌起了不同寻常的感受。当他看见巴雷特小姐纤细瘦弱的手优雅地从镶边圆桌上拿起某只银盒或某样珍珠饰物时，感觉自己那毛茸茸的爪子似乎也开始跟着收缩起来，不禁希望这爪子能化为十根修长的手指。当听见她低沉的声音发出不计其数的音节时，他希望有一天自己粗鲁的吼声也能变得像她口中吐出的字词一样，简单短小却蕴含着神秘的意义。当看见那几根手指还能握住一根笔直的棍子，一刻不停地在白纸上来回挥动时，他渴望有朝一日自己也能像她一样，把白纸涂黑。

然而，他真的能像她一样书写吗？—值得高兴的是，这个问题完全是多余的，因为在不争的事实面前，我们必须承认，一八四二至一八四三年间的巴雷特小姐并非什么林中仙子，而是一个卧床不起的病人；弗勒希也绝非什么诗人，只是一条红色的可卡犬；而温波尔街也不是阿卡狄亚，只是温波尔街而已。

就这样，悠长的时光在宅邸后部的那间卧房里悄然而逝，没留下任何踪影，只有上下楼梯的脚步声、从远处传来前门关闭的声响、扫帚轻敲地板的嗒嗒声和邮差的敲门声反映着光阴的流逝。卧房内，煤炭烧得噼啪作响，光影滑过五尊惨白的半身像的眉头，滑过书架以及盖在书架上的红色美利奴羊毛织布。不过有时，上下楼梯的脚步声不是经过门口，而是停在门外。眼见门把手转动，门居然打开了，有人进了房间。多神奇啊，家具竟然改头换面！声音和气味形成的奇妙旋涡立即开始旋转！它们卷过桌脚，又撞上衣橱尖锐的边缘！来人或许是威尔逊，端来一盘食物或一杯药；也有可能是巴雷特小姐的两位姐妹之一—阿拉贝尔或亨丽埃塔；也有可能是巴雷特小姐七位兄弟中的一个—查尔斯、塞缪尔、乔治、亨利、艾尔弗雷德、塞普蒂默斯或奥克塔维厄斯。而—，每周都有那么一两次，弗勒希会预感有什么重要的事情即将发生。床会被仔细地改装成沙发的模样，扶手椅会被拉到床边，巴雷特小姐自己则会得体地披上印度披肩。有人会把盥洗用具全都藏到乔叟和荷马的半身像底下，弗勒希也会由人梳洗一番。大约到了下午两三点，门外会传来特定、清晰却不尽相同的敲门声。巴雷特小姐会突然涨红了脸，微笑着伸出手。接着有人便会走进来—来人或许是亲爱的米特福德小姐，她面色红润、精神抖擞、喋喋不休，怀里还会抱着一把天竺葵。或许是凯尼恩先生，他是一位身形敦实、衣着考究、善良可亲的绅士，总会随身带一本书来。也可能是詹姆森太太，她的相貌特征和凯尼恩先生正好相反—她的“面容极其苍白—有着清澈的浅色眼眸，薄薄的双唇毫无血色……窄窄的鼻子和下巴向外凸出”。每位访客的举止、气味、声调和口音都各具特色：米特福德小姐喜欢喋喋不休地唠叨，态度虽欠稳重，却实实在在；凯尼恩先生彬彬有礼，富有教养，由于缺了两颗门牙而有些口齿不清[2]；詹姆森太太一颗牙都不少，她的动作就和她说话的方式一样干脆利落。

弗勒希蜷缩在巴雷特小姐脚边，任由各种各样的声音在他头上轻轻飘荡，就这样过了一小时又一小时。巴雷特小姐笑着、告诫着、惊叫着、叹息着，随即又笑了。终于，弗勒希如释重负地意识到，他终于得到了片刻的安宁—就连米特福德小姐也有住口的时候。难道已经晚上七点了吗？她从中午起就一直待在这儿了！她得赶快起身去赶火车。凯尼恩先生合上他的书—他一直在大声朗读—背对着炉火站起身来。詹姆森太太以一种迅速而生硬的动作，把每根手指塞进手套，一拉到底。接着，他们或是轻轻拍拍弗勒希，或是扯扯他的耳朵。道别仪式总是冗长得令人难以忍受，但最终，詹姆森太太、凯尼恩先生，甚至连米特福德小姐都站起身来，道别告辞。他们时而会想起什么，又忘记什么，再找到什么，最后走到门边，打开门—谢天谢地—终于走了。

巴雷特小姐脸色苍白，满脸倦容地陷进枕头堆里。弗勒希爬到她身旁，紧贴着她。感谢上帝，他们俩又能独处了。但访客们停留的时间太长了，已经到了晚餐时间。地下室开始升腾起食物的香味。威尔逊端着巴雷特小姐的晚餐盘来到门口，把餐盘放在主人身旁的桌上，掀起盖子。然而经过更衣、谈话等一番折腾，再加上室内的高温以及道别引发的种种骚乱，巴雷特小姐已经累得没有力气进食了。看见盘中为她准备的晚餐，肥羊排、山鹑翅（或是鸡翅），她只能发出一声轻叹。当着威尔逊的面，她会用刀叉胡乱地戳弄几下。可门一旦关上，只剩下他俩，她就立刻做了个手势。她举起叉子，上面叉着一整个鸡翅膀。弗勒希跑向前。巴雷特小姐点点头。弗勒希动作温和、小心翼翼地将鸡翅扯下来，不让一点儿残渣掉到地上，然后整个吞进肚中，不留半点儿痕迹。另有半个沾满浓郁奶油的米布丁也以同样的方式消失得无影无踪。没有什么能比弗勒希的配合更干净利落。他一如既往地趴在巴雷特小姐的脚边，显然睡着了；恢复了精神的巴雷特小姐躺着休息，看上去刚吃完一顿丰盛的晚餐。楼梯上再次传来一阵脚步声，比其他脚步声都要沉重、从容、坚定，在楼梯口戛然而止。庄重的敲门声响起，听起来不像是在请求获准进入，而是在要求里面的人开门。门打开了，一个最阴郁、最威严的年长男士走了进来—正是巴雷特先生本人。他的目光立刻扫过餐盘。食物都吃光了吗？她服从他的命令了吗？是的，盘子空了。巴雷特先生重重地坐进女儿身旁的那把椅子，仿佛在肯定她的顺从。当那幽暗的躯体靠近弗勒希时，阵阵惊惧令他瑟瑟发抖、脊背发凉，就像野蛮人在雷声的怒吼中听见上帝的声音时，立刻颤抖着躲进花丛中。随后威尔逊吹了声口哨，弗勒希满怀愧疚地偷溜了出去，蹑手蹑脚地爬出房间，冲下楼梯，仿佛巴雷特先生能看穿他的心思，而这些心思又十恶不赦。一股令他畏惧的力量潜入了卧房，他无力与之抗衡。有一次他意外闯回房里，只见巴雷特先生双膝跪地，在女儿身边祈祷。

[22]邦巴辛毛葛（bombazine），丝、棉纱和毛等织成的斜纹布，通常染黑用作悼念服装。

[23]巴思椅（bath-chair），一种轮椅，供病人或伤残人士使用，有的带有篷盖或玻璃罩。

[24]托基（Torquay），英国英格兰西南部德文郡的一个海滨城镇，气候温暖。

[25]阿卡狄亚（Arcady），古希腊地名，在今伯罗奔尼撒半岛中部，以其居民过着田园牧歌式淳朴生活著称，引申为“世外桃源”。

第三章　蒙面人

/

在温波尔街宅邸深处的卧房里接受的这种教育，会对一条普通的狗产生深远影响。但弗勒希可不是什么普通的狗。他虽说精力充沛，却也喜欢沉思；他虽属于犬科，却对人类情绪极度敏感。对于这样一条狗，这间卧房内的氛围带来的影响非比寻常。所以，如果说他在变得敏感细腻的同时，弱化了自身一些更为严峻的品质，我们也不能怪罪于他。自然地，整日将希腊辞典枕于头下，他注定会变得不喜欢吠叫和咬人；他逐渐偏爱猫的安静，而不是狗的鲁莽好动。而与这两者相比，他又更偏好人情味儿。巴雷特小姐也竭尽全力来提高并培养他这方面的能力，让他精益求精。有一次，她从窗上取下一架竖琴，放在他身旁，问他是否觉得这架可以制造音乐的竖琴本身具有生命力。弗勒希经过一番凝视和聆听，似乎沉思和迟疑了片刻，最终认定答案为否。接着，她又会领着他一起站在镜子前，问他为什么会吠叫和颤抖。面朝他站着的那只小棕狗，不正是他自己吗？但什么才是“自己”呢？是人们看见的外表吗？还是他内心的本质呢？弗勒希同样琢磨起这个问题，却感到现实世界是如此复杂难懂，只好把身子贴近巴雷特小姐，热烈地亲吻她，内心的感情溢于言表—无论如何，至少这是真实的。

他此前从没思考过这些问题，情感上的困境刺激着他的神经。带着这样的情绪，他走下楼梯。因此如果他的行为举止中带有某种高傲和优越感，惹得那只凶恶的古巴寻血犬卡蒂利内怒从中来，扑上去狠狠咬了自己，那也不足为奇，而他只能哀号着奔上楼，向巴雷特小姐寻求安慰。弗勒希“不是什么英雄”，她总结道。但他为什么不是个英雄呢？难道她不应该对此承担部分责任吗？她为人率直公正，不会意识不到他是为了她才牺牲了自己的勇气，正如他早已为她牺牲了阳光与空气。诚然，这种神经质的敏感也有其缺点—当他扑到被拉铃绳绊倒的凯尼恩先生身上啃咬时，她感到满心歉疚；他整晚可怜的呜咽也令人讨厌，就因为他非要主人来喂，否则不肯进食，因此被罚不准到她床上去睡。然而她愿意承担过错，不嫌麻烦，因为弗勒希终究是爱她的。为了她，他拒绝了空气和阳光。“他值得被爱，不是吗？”她这样问霍恩先生。不论霍恩先生可能给出怎样的回答，巴雷特小姐都对自己的答案确信无疑。她爱弗勒希，弗勒希也值得她爱。

似乎没有任何东西能够摧毁他们之间的纽带—岁月仿佛只是把它打磨得更为坚固、强韧，他们仿佛一生都将如此度过。从一八四二年到一八四三年，一八四三年又到了一八四四年，一八四四年又到了一八四五年。弗勒希已经不再是一条幼犬了，而是一条四五岁的成年犬，处于生命中的巅峰。而巴雷特小姐依旧躺在温波尔街的沙发上，弗勒希也依旧趴在她的脚边。巴雷特小姐过的是“笼中鸟”的生活。她有时会连续数周闭门不出，就算出门，每次顶多一两个小时，通常是乘马车去某家店铺，或是坐在轮椅上由人推去摄政公园。巴雷特一家从不离开伦敦城。巴雷特先生，他家的七兄弟、两姐妹，男管家，威尔逊及女仆们，卡蒂利内、福利，巴雷特小姐还有弗勒希，一直都生活在温波尔街五十号：在餐厅里用餐，在卧室里睡觉，在书房里抽烟，在厨房里烹饪，提热水壶，倒馊水桶—从一月到十二月，从不间断。椅罩稍微变得脏了些，地毯稍微变得旧了些，煤灰、泥巴、油烟、雾气，雪茄、红酒和肉的气味全都积聚在缝隙里、裂口中、布料表面、画框上，以及雕刻物件的旋涡纹饰里。巴雷特小姐卧室窗外的常春藤枝繁叶茂，长成的绿色帷帘也越积越厚。到了夏天，旱金莲和红花菜豆则在窗台上的花盆里竞相疯长。

不过，一八四五年一月初的一天夜里，邮差敲响了大门。信件如往常一样投进了信箱，威尔逊如往常一样下楼去取信。一切都如往常一样—其实邮差每天晚上都会来敲门，威尔逊每天晚上都会去取信，巴雷特小姐每天晚上都会收到一封信。可是今晚送来的信却不太一样，它十分不同寻常。还没等信封拆开，弗勒希就意识到了这点。他从巴雷特小姐取信的模样中看出了端倪，她把信转过来，盯着写下她名字的那刚健有力、龙飞凤舞的字迹。他从她手指难以描述的战栗中，从她撕开信封的迫不及待中，从她读信时聚精会神的表情中，看出了这封信与众不同。他注视着她读信。在她读信时，他听见一个铃声，就像我们常在半睡半醒时从街上传来的喧闹声中辨认出某种为我们而响起的铃声。那声音虽然微弱却充满警惕，仿佛远方有人试图唤醒我们，警告我们发生了火灾或盗窃，或是某种将威胁到我们平静生活的灾难，让我们尚未醒来就感到警觉—同样的，在巴雷特小姐阅读那张沾了墨汁的小纸条时，一声警铃也传到了弗勒希的耳朵里，把他从睡梦中唤醒，警告他某种危险即将降临，他的安全将受到威胁，所以他不能入睡了。巴雷特小姐快速地读完那封信，又慢慢地再读了一遍，然后小心翼翼地把信装回信封。她也一样不能入睡了。

几个夜晚之后，一封类似的信又赫然出现在威尔逊的托盘上。巴雷特小姐又一次快速读完了内容，再慢慢地看，看了一遍又一遍。接着她把信小心翼翼地收起来，没有和米特福德小姐长篇大论的信件一起收在抽屉里，而是单独收好。弗勒希长年累月地趴在巴雷特小姐脚旁的垫子上，他付出了昂贵的代价，才培养出这般敏锐的眼光，能洞悉别人察觉不到的蛛丝马迹。透过巴雷特小姐手指的抚触，他可以察觉到，她现在只等待着一样东西—等邮差敲门，等托盘上出现那封信。起初，她会以规律的节奏轻轻地抚摸他；忽然—敲门声一响—她的手指就会猛地缩紧，把他牢牢钳住，直到威尔逊上楼。然后，她会取过信，把他松开，也彻底把他抛到脑后。

可是，他辩解道，只要巴雷特小姐的生活没有发生任何改变，这有什么可害怕的？确实没有任何改变。没有新的访客出现，凯尼恩先生照常来访，米特福德小姐照常来访，兄弟姐妹们照常出现；傍晚时分巴雷特先生也照常前来。他们什么都没有注意到，也毫不起疑。因此，当那封信连续几晚都没有出现，他便安慰自己，试着去相信敌人已经消失了。他想象那是个罩着长袍的男子，是个穿着斗篷、戴着兜帽的人，如窃贼那样一闪而过，经过时把门弄得咔嗒响，却发现此地禁卫森严，只好灰溜溜地悄悄走掉。弗勒希努力让自己相信危险已经解除，那名男子已经消失不见。结果那封信却再次出现。

随着信封出现得愈加频繁，甚至每晚都有，弗勒希才注意到巴雷特小姐身上有了细微的变化。弗勒希头一回见她如此坐立难安、心浮气躁。她读不进书也写不出东西。她站在窗边向外凝视。她焦虑地询问威尔逊天气如何—外面仍刮着东风吗？公园里是否有开春的迹象？噢，没呢，威尔逊回答，残酷的东风仍在肆虐。弗勒希感到，巴雷特小姐听了既如释重负又深感烦恼。她不停咳嗽，抱怨身体不适—但显然远不像往年刮东风时那么难受。待四下无人，她会把前一夜收到的信重读一遍。这是目前为止最长的一封，页数很多，排列紧凑，墨迹密密麻麻，零零散散地画了些细小突兀的象形文字。弗勒希从她脚边的位置能看到的只有这些，可他完全听不懂巴雷特小姐在轻声自语些什么，只感觉她读到最后一行并大声念出时（尽管他听不懂）—“您看两三个月后我能否与您相见？”—激动万分。

随后她提起笔，迅速又紧张地写了一页又一页。但巴雷特小姐写下的那些小小字符究竟意味着什么呢？“四月将至。倘若我们活得够久，其间还有五月和六月，或许，无论如何，我们可以……待暖和的天气让我恢复一丝生气，我愿意与您相见……但刚开始我会害怕您—尽管我在写下这些话时并不感到害怕。您是帕拉塞尔苏斯[26]，我则是一名隐居者，我的神经早已在肢刑架上绷断了，如今只是软绵绵地悬挂着，只要听到一点儿脚步声、一下呼吸声，便会心悸颤抖。”

弗勒希看不懂她在他头顶上方一两英寸的地方写的什么，却像能读懂每个字的含义一般清楚地知道女主人挥笔时的烦躁是多么反常，也知道矛盾的欲望如何摄住了她的思绪—四月也许会来，也许不会来了；她也许可以立刻见到这个陌生的男人，也有可能永远也见不到他。弗勒希也和她一样，因一丁点儿脚步声和呼吸声而心悸颤抖着。日子冷酷无情地一天天过去。风卷起了遮光帘，阳光染白了半身像，一只鸟儿在笼子里歌唱，有人沿着温波尔街叫卖鲜花。他心里清楚，所有这些声音都意味着四月即将到来，接着五月、六月也会来到—没有任何东西能够阻止那可怕的春天逐步逼近。到底有什么会随着春天一起到来呢？是某种骇人听闻的东西—某种恐怖—某种巴雷特小姐畏惧、弗勒希也同样畏惧的东西。现在他一听见脚步声便悚然惊起，然而那不过是亨丽埃塔。又传来了敲门声，但那只是凯尼恩先生。就这样，四月过去了，五月也过去了二十天。然后，就在五月二十一日那天，弗勒希知道那一天终于来临了。因为在五月二十一日这个星期二，巴雷特小姐对着镜子把自己上上下下打量个遍，仔仔细细地裹好印度披肩，吩咐威尔逊把扶手椅拉近一些，但不要太近。她碰碰这个，又碰碰那个，然后便直挺挺地坐靠在枕头堆里。弗勒希全身紧绷地趴在她脚边。他们单独待在房间里，一起等待着。终于，马里波恩教堂的钟敲了两下；他们继续等待着。接着马里波恩教堂的钟又单独敲了一下—两点半到了—钟声慢慢停歇时，前门响起一声大胆的叩击声。巴雷特小姐顿时血色全无，纹丝不动地躺着。弗勒希也静静趴着。那可怕的、不可阻挡的脚步声上楼了。弗勒希知道，上来的正是那邪恶的午夜暗影—那个戴着兜帽的蒙面人。此刻，他的手正放在门上，门把转动，他就站在门口。

“勃朗宁先生到。”威尔逊通报。

弗勒希盯着巴雷特小姐，只见她突然两颊绯红，双目放光，红唇轻启。

“勃朗宁先生！”她叫道。

勃朗宁先生手里攥着自己的黄手套[3]，眨着眼睛，穿着神气而体面，贸然迈开大步穿过房间。他握住巴雷特小姐的手，往摆在她沙发旁的那张椅子上一坐。两人立刻交谈起来。

令弗勒希难以承受的是，他们谈话时，他深感孤独。曾经，他觉得自己仿佛和巴雷特小姐厮守在一个生了火的洞穴里。如今火已熄灭，洞穴里又黑又潮，而巴雷特小姐已置身洞外。他环顾四周，发觉一切都面目全非。书架、五尊半身像—它们不再是慈眉善目的神祇，满意地高坐其上—变得既陌生又严肃。他在巴雷特小姐的脚旁不停变换姿势，她却浑然不察。他哀哼着，两人却不闻不问。最后，他只好静静地趴着，全身紧绷，默默忍受痛苦。谈话还在继续，但不似其他谈话那般徐徐流动、涟漪荡漾。这谈话横冲直跃、激流猛进，时而戛然而止，时而又跳跃起来。弗勒希之前从没听过巴雷特小姐用那样的语调说话—如此富有活力、激情四射。他从未见过她的脸颊像此刻这般红润发亮，从未见过她的那双大眼睛像此刻这般熠熠生辉。钟响四声，他们两人仍讲个不停。接着四点半的钟声也响了，勃朗宁倏地跳了起来。他的每个动作都昭示着某种令人反感的魄力和令人不快的冒失。一眨眼的工夫，他就把巴雷特小姐的手紧紧握在自己的手里，再拿上自己的帽子和手套，道了再会。他们听见他跑下楼梯的声音。门砰的一声在他身后关上。他就这么消失了。

但巴雷特小姐并没有倒靠在枕头堆里，像凯尼恩先生或米特福德小姐离开后那般萎靡。她依然笔直坐着，双眼依旧炽热，双颊也依旧光彩照人，似乎觉得勃朗宁先生还在身边。弗勒希碰了碰她，她吓了一跳，这才想起他来。她愉快地在他脑袋上轻轻拍了拍，随后面带微笑，用无比怪异的表情看着他—似乎希望他能开口说话—像是指望他也能感同身受。紧接着她又自嘲地笑了，仿佛觉得这个想法实在荒谬—弗勒希，可怜的弗勒希不可能体会她的心情。他也无法参透她所知道的一切。从未有过如此遥远而令人伤感的距离将他们隔开。他趴在那儿，遭人忽视，感觉自己根本就不存在似的。巴雷特小姐不再记得他的存在。

当天晚上，她连鸡骨头都啃得一干二净，连一丁点儿土豆残渣或鸡皮都没有扔给弗勒希。当巴雷特先生像往常一样进来探视时，他的迟钝令弗勒希感到不可思议。他坐在那个男人之前坐过的椅子里，头靠在那个男人靠过的靠垫上，却什么也没察觉。“难道你不知道，”弗勒希惊诧地想，“刚才谁坐在这把椅子上？难道你闻不出来吗？”对弗勒希而言，整个房间仍充斥着勃朗宁先生的气味。这气味从书架旁扫过，围绕着五尊苍白的半身像旋转，掀起一阵旋涡。可这位笨重的男士却坐在女儿身旁，完全沉浸在自己的世界里，对外界浑然不觉，不疑有他。弗勒希惊骇于他的迟钝，偷偷从他身旁溜出了房外。

尽管巴雷特小姐家人的后知后觉令人瞠目结舌，但随着时间一周周过去，他们也渐渐注意到巴雷特小姐身上的变化。她会走出自己的房间，到楼下客厅里坐坐。接着她还做了一件长久不曾做过的事—她竟然靠自己的双腿，和姐妹一起徒步走到了德文郡广场的大门口！她的朋友和家人无不为她的好转惊叹。但唯有弗勒希清楚她的力量源自何方—它来自那位坐在扶手椅里的黝黑男子。他来了一次又一次。起先每周只来访一次，接着是一周两次。他总是下午来下午走。巴雷特小姐总是单独约见他。即使有些日子他本人不现身，他的信也不会缺席。而他人离开之后，他送的花依然留在这儿。每天早晨只身一人时，巴雷特小姐就会给他写信。那个黝黑、整洁、鲁莽又精力充沛的男子，还有他的一头黑发，他红润的面庞，和那双黄手套，简直无处不在。如此一来，巴雷特小姐的身体自然会有起色，她当然可以开始走动了。连弗勒希都觉得自己已经不可能一动不动地趴着了。昔日的渴望再次被激发出来，他陷入了一种新的躁动，甚至入睡后沉浸于种种梦乡。自从离开三英里十字标后，他从未如此梦频—他梦见从高高的草丛里蹿出的野兔，尖叫着跃出的长尾野鸡，还有呼啸一声从麦茬堆中冲出的山鹑。他梦见自己在狩猎，正追着某只身上有斑点的西班牙猎犬，可后者奔跑着逃脱了他的追捕。他一会儿在西班牙，一会儿在威尔士，一会儿在伯克郡，一会儿在手持警棍的摄政公园管理员面前狂奔。然后他睁开眼睛。眼前没有野兔，没有山鹑，没有啪啪作响的皮鞭，也没有高喊“Span！Span！”的黝黑男人，只有坐在扶手椅上的勃朗宁先生，正与躺在沙发上的巴雷特小姐聊天。

那个男人在的时候，睡觉是根本不可能的。弗勒希睁大眼睛趴着，聚精会神地倾听。这些轻言细语总是两点半到四点半之间在他的头顶碰撞交锋，有时甚至一周三次。尽管他对词意一无所知，但他凭借惊人的直觉准确地察觉到，那谈话的语气及声调在不断变化。刚开始，巴雷特小姐的声音显得勉强—具有某种不自然的活力，现在却带着他从未感觉到的温暖和自在。而—每次那个男人来时，总会有一些新的声音掺进他们的说话声中—他们时而发出怪异的吱喳声；时而又似一对疾飞的鸟从他头顶掠过；时而又发出咕咕咯咯的声响，像两只在巢中栖息的鸟儿。然后巴雷特小姐的声音再度响起，在空中翱翔盘旋，接着勃朗宁先生爆发出一连串尖锐刺耳的笑声，再后来只剩下一句嗡嗡絮语，含糊而微弱，仿佛两个声音已融为一体。可随着夏去秋来，弗勒希不胜恐慌地又注意到一种新的声调。那个男人的声音里出现了一种新的急迫感，一种新的压力和能量，弗勒希觉得这似乎让巴雷特小姐受到了惊吓。她的声音焦躁不安、犹豫不决，仿佛在畏缩、躲藏、抗辩，奄奄一息，仿佛在哀求着喘息和暂停，仿佛充满胆怯。然后，那个男人便沉默不语。

他们几乎完全没注意到弗勒希。在勃朗宁先生看来，他跟放在巴雷特小姐脚边的一段木头相差无几。有时在经过他旁边时，勃朗宁先生会突然飞速地挠挠他的头，力气很大，却不带感情。无论那搔头的动作有何意味，弗勒希对勃朗宁先生只感到极端厌恶。看到他那副西装革履、强健紧致、肌肉结实的模样，看到他用力攥紧黄手套的样子，弗勒希就恨得咬牙切齿。噢！这让他想在他的长裤上一口咬下去！然而他却不敢。一言以蔽之，一八四五年到一八四六年间的那个冬季是弗勒希此生最煎熬的时光。

冬去春来，弗勒希看不出这段交往有结束的迹象。然而这一切宛如一条河流，虽倒映着静立的树、吃草的牛群以及归巢的乌鸦，却仍不可避免地奔往瀑布。同样的，弗勒希也明白，这些日子也终将酿成大祸。关于变化的蛛丝马迹在空中萦绕，有时他感觉大规模的迁徙即将发生。家里总有一股莫名的骚动，仿佛是一次远行的前兆，但这真的可能吗？箱盒竟真的被拿出来掸灰，甚至难得一见地被纷纷打开，但立刻又被合上了。不，显然不是全家都要搬走。巴雷特小姐的兄弟姐妹们仍照常进出。每晚，在那个男人离开后，巴雷特先生仍在同一时间进来探视。那么，到底会发生什么事呢？因为随着一八四六年的夏天渐渐收尾，弗勒希相当确定变化就要发生。他可以从那连绵不绝的谈话声中再次分辨出不同的语调。巴雷特小姐那原本像在哀求的、害怕的声音，现在已经不再闪烁其词，而是透露着一种弗勒希从未听到过的决心与胆量。如果巴雷特先生能听到她迎接那位僭越者时的声调，她招呼他时的笑声，还有被他紧握双手时的叹息，那该多好！可惜房间里除了他俩和弗勒希之外再无旁人。对弗勒希来说，这种变化是最令人恼怒的，因为巴雷特小姐不仅对勃朗宁先生的态度变了，对所有人的态度也都变了—尤其是对他自己。现在每当他凑上前亲近，她就颇不耐烦，总是用玩笑阻断他的热情，让他感觉昔日自己表达爱意的方式竟是那般微不足道、愚蠢做作。他的虚荣心遭到重创，妒火中烧。终于，七月来了，他决定强行夺回她的宠爱，甚至驱逐这个新来的家伙。如何一箭双雕他茫然不知，如何筹谋策划他也毫无头绪。但在七月八日那一天，他突然失控，扑向了勃朗宁先生，狠狠地咬了他一口！他的牙齿终于碰到了勃朗宁先生一尘不染的长裤布料！可是裤里的腿却像钢铁一般坚硬—相较之下，凯尼恩先生的腿简直软得像黄油。勃朗宁先生大手一挥，把他推开，继续讲话。无论是他还是巴雷特小姐，似乎都认为这次攻击不值一提。弗勒希矢尽援绝、铩羽而归，气喘吁吁地趴回自己的垫子上，怒不可遏又失望至极。然而，他错估了巴雷特小姐的眼力。待勃朗宁先生离开后，她把他唤到跟前，施以前所未有的最严厉的惩罚。她先是打他的耳朵—那也没什么，说来也怪，他还挺喜欢被打耳朵的，宁愿她再多打几下。但接下来她竟用冷静、确凿的语气说她以后再也不爱他了。一箭穿心。这么多年来，他们住在一起，分享一切，现在，只因为他一时糊涂，她就不再爱他了。随后，似乎为了更完整地展示她的驱逐令，她拿起勃朗宁先生送给她的花，往花瓶里插起来。弗勒希心想：她是故意的，这是个处心积虑、充满恶意的举动，为的是让他彻头彻尾地自惭形秽！“这朵玫瑰是他送的，”她好像在说，“这朵康乃馨也是。让我插一朵红色的在黄色的旁边，再插一朵黄色的在红色的旁边，然后将这枝绿叶放在这里……”待花儿一朵朵插好后，她后退一步，凝望着那一大丛娇艳欲滴的花—仿佛那戴着黄手套的男人就站在她眼前。可即使如此，即使在她插花的时候，她还是无法完全忽视弗勒希凝视她的目光。她不能不理会“他脸上绝望的表情”，也无法不心生同情。“最后我终于说：‘弗勒希，如果你乖乖听话，现在可以过来道歉。’结果他立刻冲过来，全身颤抖地先亲了我的一只手，再亲了另一只，然后举起爪子让我握握，同时用哀求的眼神注视着我。你若看见了，一定也会像我一样原谅他。”她这是在对勃朗宁先生描述。而他当然答道：“噢，可怜的弗勒希。难道你认为我会因为他嫉妒的监视而不爱他、不尊敬他吗？他是因为同你亲近，才不愿再轻易亲近别人了啊！”要勃朗宁先生表现出宽宏大量并非难事，然而这轻易的宽宏大量或许正是扎在弗勒希身上最尖锐的一根芒刺。

几天后又发生了一件事，再次展示了曾经亲密无间的他们俩之间如今产生了多大的隔阂，弗勒希再也指望不上获得巴雷特小姐的怜悯了。那天下午在勃朗宁先生离开后，巴雷特小姐决定和姐妹坐车去摄政公园。她们在公园大门外下车时，四轮马车的车门夹到了弗勒希的爪子，他“可怜兮兮地叫唤”，举起爪子给巴雷特小姐看，乞求同情。若是以前，他即便不这么做，也一定会受到百般呵护。可眼下，她的眼神里满是冷漠、嘲讽和批判。她嘲笑他，认定他在装模作样：“……他一踏上草地，立马拔腿狂奔，忘得一干二净。”她这么写道。她嘲弄地评论说：“弗勒希总喜欢夸大自己的不幸—他是拜伦派的—总爱扮演受害者[27]。”其实，沉浸在自己情感中的巴雷特小姐完全错怪了他。就算他的爪子被压断了，他还是会拔腿狂奔，因为那是对她嘲讽态度的回应—我要与你一刀两断—这便是他往前乱冲的含义。那一瞬间，花儿闻起来是苦的，草地灼烧着他的脚底，尘土充斥着他的鼻孔，令他幻灭。但他仍然继续奔跑—向前飞奔。“狗必须系狗链”—告示牌依旧在那儿，那位公园管理员还是头戴高帽、手持警棍，正执行这项规定。然而现在，“必须”这个词对他而言没有任何意义。爱的锁链已断，他现在想往哪里跑就往哪里跑。他可以去追山鹑，追西班牙猎犬，冲进大丽花丛里，踩烂鲜艳的红玫瑰与黄玫瑰。就让公园管理员挥舞他们的警棍吧—让他们把他打得脑浆四溅，让他肚破肠流地躺在巴雷特小姐的脚旁死掉—他一点儿都不在乎。自然，这些事儿都没发生。没人来追赶他，也没人注意到他。单独出巡的公园管理员忙着和一个保姆聊天。最后，他只好踱回巴雷特小姐身边，让她心不在焉地将狗链套在他的脖子上，带他回家。

经过这样的两次羞辱，不用说一条普通的狗，就连一个普通人，都可能从此一蹶不振。然而温软细腻的弗勒希却目光如炬，胸中的激情不仅能熊熊燃烧，也能默默阴燃。他决心与敌人面对面单挑，进行最后的决战，不容第三者介入，让双方自己分出个胜负。于是，到了七月二十一日，他在这个星期二的下午，溜下楼梯，伺机等在玄关。他没有等太久，很快便听见街上传来熟悉的脚步声，接着听见熟悉的叩门声。有人开门让勃朗宁先生进来。勃朗宁先生早已隐约感受到弗勒希正酝酿攻击，决定以柔克刚，当天带了一盒蛋糕来。见到弗勒希在玄关候着，勃朗宁先生明显是想亲善地抚摸他，或许还想好心地赏他一块蛋糕。真是够了！弗勒希异常凶狠地扑向敌人，牙齿再一次咬上勃朗宁的长裤。可惜在此紧要关头，昏了头的他忘了顶顶重要的一件事—保持安静。他叫了起来，在扑向勃朗宁先生的同时大声吠叫。结果吠声惊动全家，威尔逊闻声冲下楼梯，用力打他，将他制服。他在屈辱中被威尔逊牵走了。那真是莫大的耻辱—袭击勃朗宁先生，却被威尔逊揍了一顿。勃朗宁先生连一根手指头都没抬一下，拎着他的蛋糕，毫发无伤、气定神闲地走上楼梯，单独进入了卧房，弗勒希却被带走了。

他在厨房里被关了两个半小时禁闭，悲惨地和鹦鹉、甲虫、羊齿植物和锅盘共处一室，然后被召回巴雷特小姐房里。她躺在沙发上，姐妹阿拉贝尔坐在旁边。弗勒希自认有理，于是径直走向巴雷特小姐，可是她却不理睬他。他扭头看向阿拉贝尔，她只说了一句：“淘气的弗勒希，走开！”威尔逊也在房里—难缠的、毫不宽容的威尔逊，就是她向巴雷特小姐告的状。她于是揍了他，威尔逊说：“因为他该打！”接着又补充说她只是用手打。就是因为有她做证，弗勒希才成了罪人。巴雷特小姐认定那次袭击没头没脑，认定勃朗宁先生是宽容大度的好人，而弗勒希挨一个仆人的揍（没用鞭子），是因为“他该打”！这事就此定案，不必多费唇舌。巴雷特小姐已认定他有罪。“然后他趴在我脚旁的地板上，”她这样写道，“从眉毛底下抬眼偷瞄我。”但尽管弗勒希一个劲儿盯着巴雷特小姐看，她却怎么也不肯回看他一眼。就这样，她躺在沙发上，他趴在地板上。

被放逐的他趴在地毯上，情绪之纷乱有如身陷汹涌狂暴的漩涡。他的灵魂不是在岩石间冲撞、碎裂，就是好不容易找到一小块立足之地，艰难而缓慢地将自己拉出水面，爬回岸上，最后终于脱离了浩劫后的宇宙，俯瞰一个全然陌生的新世界。问题是，他这番经历到底算是哪个呢—是毁灭，还是新生？这是一个问题。他只能感知这两难困境的大致轮廓，因为他的挣扎是悄无声息的。弗勒希两次都欲倾全力，想要挫败敌人，但均以失败告终。为什么他会失败呢？他问自己。因为他爱巴雷特小姐。他抬眼注视躺在沙发上的她，见她表情严厉、一言不发，心里明白他必须爱她，直到永远。但事情并不简单，而是很复杂。倘若他咬了勃朗宁先生，便等于也咬了她。恨不是恨，恨也是爱。想到这里，弗勒希十分苦恼地甩甩耳朵，浑身不自在地在地板上翻了个身。勃朗宁先生就是巴雷特小姐，巴雷特小姐就是勃朗宁先生；爱即是恨，恨即是爱！他伸了个懒腰，哀鸣一声，从地板上抬起头来。时钟敲了八下，他已经在同一个地方整整趴了三个多小时，始终在痛苦挣扎、进退两难。

这时，就连严厉、冷漠—无情的巴雷特小姐也放下了笔。“弗勒希坏透了！”她刚才在给勃朗宁先生的信中写道，“……如果人们都学弗勒希，像狗一样野蛮行事，那么他们也应该像狗一样为结果受惩罚！而你呢，你却如此和颜悦色地对待他！换作其他任何人，至少也会说几句‘狠话’。”其实真应该考虑买嘴套了，她心想。然后她抬起头，看见了弗勒希。这时，他脸上某种非同寻常的表情势必击中了她。她愣住了，放下笔。曾经，他用一个吻唤醒她，而她则把他想象成牧神潘；曾经，他吃的是鸡肉和浸满奶油的米布丁；曾经，他为了她放弃了阳光。于是，她把他叫到跟前，说自己原谅了他。

然而她因一念之仁原谅他，又将他抱回沙发上，仿佛在地板上忍受那些痛苦之后他并无任何长进，仍是过去的他，她完全没有意识到他已幡然改变。这一切令弗勒希难以接受。不过此时他已精疲力竭，只好屈服。但几天后，他与巴雷特小姐之间发生了一件非比寻常的事，足以显示他感情深邃。那天勃朗宁先生离开之后，只剩下弗勒希与巴雷特小姐单独待在一块儿。平常他都会立刻跳到她脚旁的沙发上，但那天他却一反常态，没有要求钻进她怀里，却走向了那把椅子—现在被称作“勃朗宁先生的扶手椅”。通常那把椅子令他极度厌恶，因为上面仍保留着敌人的身姿留下的形状。可是那一刻，他却打赢了一仗，因为他心中突然充满宽容，不仅正视那把椅子，甚至“忽然陷入了狂喜”。巴雷特小姐全神贯注地观察着他不同寻常的表现。接着，她看见他将视线转向桌上。桌上仍摆放着勃朗宁先生送的那盒蛋糕。他在“提醒我你送的蛋糕仍留在桌上”。此刻蛋糕早就陈腐变质了，绝对不会引起任何食欲。弗勒希的意图非常明显—蛋糕新鲜时他不肯吃，因为那是敌人送的；现在蛋糕坏了，他倒愿意吃了，因为他已与对方化敌为友了，因为那是他将仇恨化成爱意的象征。没错，他表示自己现在愿意吃了。于是巴雷特小姐起身去拿蛋糕，递给他时顺便告诫了他一番。“我解释给他听，说这是你带给他吃的，他应该为过去的恶行感到惭愧，应该下定决心，从今以后好好爱你，不再咬你，这样我才能允许他接受你的好意。”弗勒希一边吞咽着已经受潮泡软的难吃糕饼—这玩意已经发霉发臭，一股酸味，招来苍蝇—一边用自己的语言信誓旦旦地重复她刚才说过的词：他发誓，从今以后会好好爱勃朗宁先生，再也不会咬他了。

他立即受到了奖赏—这奖赏不是走味的蛋糕，不是鸡翅，不是女主人的拥抱爱抚，也不是重新获准趴回巴雷特小姐脚旁的沙发。他的奖赏是精神上的，但奇怪的是，其效果却展现在肉体上。这几个月以来，仇恨一直压着他的灵魂，如同一根铁条，把一切自然的活力都压得腐朽、溃烂、死亡。如今，经过利刃的洗礼，完成了痛苦的手术，铁条被切除了，血液得以再度流通，神经又有了感觉，肌肉又重新长好，仿佛春天到来，万物复苏。弗勒希再次听见鸟鸣，感觉到树在发芽。当他趴在巴雷特小姐脚旁的沙发上，荣耀与欢愉在他的血管里流淌。他现在已站在他们一边，而不是与他们敌对；他们的希望、他们的心愿、他们的渴求，也都是他的了。现在弗勒希可以吠叫着应和勃朗宁先生了。他颈项上的毛会因勃朗宁简洁有力的话语而竖立：“我真希望一周七天全是星期二！”勃朗宁先生呼喊，“然后一个月全是星期二—一年—一辈子都是！”“我，”弗勒希重复他的话，“也想要一个月—一年—一辈子！你们想要的东西，就是我想要的东西！我们是三个同谋者，要追逐最荣耀的使命；我们有同样的怜悯、同样的仇恨，我们反抗同样暗无天日的独裁暴政，也有同样的爱。”简言之，弗勒希将他所有的希望都寄托在同属于他们的光荣胜利上，尽管他对它只有模糊的感觉，却依然深信它必将来临。然而就在此时，弗勒希突如其来地整个跌入黑暗之中，一切来得毫无征兆，而—就发生在文明、安全与友好的中心地带—那是九月一日，一个周二上午，他和巴雷特小姐及其姐妹就在维尔街的一家商店里。地牢的大门在他身后关上。他被偷走了。[4]

[26]帕拉塞尔苏斯（Paracelsus，1493-1541），瑞士医师、炼金师，促进了药物化学的发展。

[27]原文为法语。